<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.wardle.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.wardle.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-12-10T21:56:53+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/</id><title type="html">Health informatics and information technology</title><subtitle>by Dr Mark Wardle, Consultant Neurologist, clinical informatics and software developer. Founder, Eldrix Ltd.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The 5 Os of healthcare IT</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 5 Os of healthcare IT" /><published>2017-12-06T10:39:39+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-06T10:39:39+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html">&lt;p&gt;My writing on &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html&quot;&gt;domain-driven design&lt;/a&gt; arose because of my own experience building an electronic patient record system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A model is an abstraction of the real-world distilling knowledge into core concepts and processes.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;from &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html&quot;&gt;Towards a domain-driven, model-based approach to developing clinical information systems: innovating for the future in NHS Wales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that development, I was fortunate to use technologies developed by NeXT (and continued by Apple - WebObjects), which enforced a strict separation of model, controllers and the view. Importantly, I learned an important principle: the importance of starting with a data model conceived with a deep understanding of the domain in which I worked in my day job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was only later that I read Eric Evans’ “Domain-driven design” which, while not about healthcare, has much to teach us in health information technology about the importance of data modelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“There are many things that make software development complex. But the heart of this complexity is the essential intricacy of the problem domain itself. If you’re trying to add automation to complicated human enterprise, then your software cannot dodge this complexity—all it can do is control it.
The key to controlling complexity is a good domain model, a model that goes beyond a surface vision of a domain by introducing an underlying structure, which gives the software developers the leverage they need. A good domain model can be incredibly valuable, but it’s not something that’s easy to make. Few people can do it well, and it’s very hard to teach.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Martin Fowler&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Excerpt From: Eric Evans. &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/gb/book/domain-driven-design-tackling-complexity-in-heart-software/id502848358?mt=11&quot;&gt;“Domain-Driven Design: Tackling Complexity in the Heart of Software.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-digital-drive&quot;&gt;A digital drive&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to see information technology as a product rather than what it really is - an enabler of transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we deliver transformative change in healthcare using digital technologies?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest that there are five broad principles… my 5 Os of healthcare IT:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-objectives&quot;&gt;1. Objectives&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Define a clear vision. For example, in Wales, the Welsh Government &lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/topics/health/nhswales/about/e-health/?lang=en&quot;&gt;Informed Health and Care strategy&lt;/a&gt; is a very good start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then define tangible definite high-level objectives. This should not be “deploy XXX” where XXX is a product you want to deploy, but instead focus on user need - the requirements, the problems you are solving and the transformation you enable. So, for me, in the next 3 months, NHS Wales should:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ensure laboratory and radiology results and clinical documents are available to all clinical users when they are seeing a patient, irrespective of where those investigations were performed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identify deteriorating patients on the ward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your prioritisation list might be different, but those objectives should support the aims in your overall vision. I have a different list for 6-months, 12-months and onwards (a subject for another post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is sensible to define a list of all objectives, each a stepping stone on the way to delivering your overall vision. You will need to take into account political and business priorities as well so it is about negotiation, discussion and understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate this, we currently have a PACS replacement project ongoing. For me, replacing one PACS (picture archiving and communication systems) with another, in the absence of a well argued need, does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; meet the standard required. In a resource limited environment, wasting resources without good reason is difficult to defend. Always ask for a compelling reason &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; something is important! What value do we gain that cannot be achieved in more prudent manner?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, what is the point in forcing organisations to rip out a patient administrative system to replace with a new “Once for Wales” PAS if each will be configured differently with different information standards? Similarly, if the project to “deploy” the system doesn’t end up providing administrative and clinical staff or indeed the patient, information from across multiple organisations, then what are we trying to achieve?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your objectives define your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-ownership&quot;&gt;2. Ownership&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make information technology and the transformation agenda owned by the users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But who are the users? You need to consider : health professionals, administrators, managers, analysts, the patient, and more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The users must be engaged, must be empowered to own and drive their work. We need to understand the areas in which there is synergy between requirements from different perspectives and design our enterprise to provide the common tools to solve their problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than top-down “You will…”, consider instead “Here are the tools to achieve your goals… do you want help?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all users, ask them what they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, what do our patients want from a healthcare services that recognises that digital is one way of providing a service? Are you sure that we know the answer to this yet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-openness&quot;&gt;3. Openness&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Allow debate. Make your work transparent.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information technology is difficult, so ensure plenty of debate to hear all of the views. There is no right way, but favour solutions to deploy quickly, get software in hands of users early and get feedback, favour an approach that set a foundation for future plans and don’t limit what you don’t know you don’t know. As I have said many times before:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need to build an infrastructure that explicitly recognises that we don’t have all of the answers, and therefore must support innovation. Such innovation may simply be incremental improvement of existing technology, but also must cope with and embrace the introduction of transformative and disruptive technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;Once for Wales debate, March 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should debate and build in the open. There are few situations in which work, particularly funded by the public, should be behind closed doors. Transparency is key; options analyses of the most appropriate way to deliver solutions to our problems. Like everything in medicine, our decisions are rarely black-and-white, but careful  judgements balancing many different options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;4-optimise&quot;&gt;4. Optimise&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Permit failure.  Fail fast. Recognise the relative unchanging components and iterate and prototype the components that change more quickly.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we develop a “can-do” digital culture in healthcare? Should we clone the “Move fast and break things” culture reporting in technological startups? We need to approach information technology in a different way but we can’t “break things”! We work in a safety-critical environment, but we must recognise that the &lt;em&gt;pace of change&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;level of risk&lt;/em&gt; can be different at different levels of our enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rate-of-change-layered.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rate Of Change Layered&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this diagram, we see that our architecture consists of an open platform approach, built using application programming interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The data layer contains longitudinal episodic patient data relating to admissions, appointments, measurements and outcomes. This layer may consist of multiple data repositories for laboratory systems, documents, clinical data and aggregate data from across multiple patient administrative systems from multiple organisations. These complexities are abstracted within our architecture as a set of simple open application programming interfaces (APIs). This layer changes the least. A blood pressure in the right arm will always be a blood pressure recorded in the right arm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The business logic, services and process/workflow layers provides important reusable services that execute business logic.  This ensures that user-facing applications do not make the mistake of embedding important business logic and rules. For example, if access to information needs to be logged, then it is better to perform this at the API level rather than within a user-facing application.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The user-facing components and applications leverage the underlying platform in order to provide value for users. User-facing applications are most likely to need to change frequently given our technological advances. You should consider these to be relatively ephemeral, taking advantage of new mobile devices and other new technology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see this approach in more detail in my &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;plan for an open platform in NHS Wales&lt;/a&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/platform/platform-overall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Platform Overall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a platform, one ends up procuring multiple systems that need to be connected together, rather than to a common enterprise platform. This results in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data silos: most current products store their data in a proprietary format within that product. As a result, we create multiple silos. If one can access that information and connect it to your other deployed products, you hit the complexity of n*(n-1)/2 data interoperability, in which you have to somehow connect that product to everything else (2 systems need one connection, 3 needs 3, 4 needs 6, 5 needs 10, 6 needs 15,7 needs 21!) so one ends up with a combinatorial nightmare. &lt;img src=&quot;/images/cis_design/multiple-interfaces.png&quot; alt=&quot;Multiple Interfaces&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Procurement rules: it is difficult to scale a solution across a wide enterprise as costs hit thresholds for OJEU rules and suddenly, you and your team are committing large sums of money in a high risk deployment in which failure cannot be countenanced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, think “open platform”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;5-organic&quot;&gt;5. Organic&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scale organically, enthusiasts and early adopters, grow horizontally; get people asking “can we have that too?”, until your solutions are the default, that they make process easier and not more difficult.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to support innovation if we cannot tolerate variation. It is easy to assume that all variation across health services is bad, and so it is easy to think you should harmonise people and processes with technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an approach is wrong. Firstly, harmonisation is a people and processes issue, not technological, and secondly, how can you be sure you are harmonising to raise standards? What if you are standardising to the lowest common denominator? Variation allows you, as part of systems continuous improvement, to innovate, appraise and improve. Conversely, unmeasured and unmonitored variation is difficult to justify.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, recognise that information technology is fundamentally an enabler for transformation and that transformation needs to be driven from the bottom-up; imposing a software solution from central diktat rarely results in satisfied users or effective change. Design the health enterprise to instead allow iteration and innovation in a safe way, playing by a well-defined rulebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/DiffusionOfInnovation.png&quot; alt=&quot;DiffusionOfInnovation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(CC BY 2.5, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?curid=11484459&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?curid=11484459&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work with early adopters and enthusiasts and then plan to scale organically, proving benefit using a quality improvement methodology such as DMAIC. Measure!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cis_design/dmaic.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dmaic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects relating to information technology fail frequently and this is seen in many industries, including healthcare. Healthcare enterprises are complex heterogeneous environments with many stakeholders and significant complexity; mistakes may cost lives. It is easy to assume that, faced with such risks, one should centralise and control and drive change from above, but such an approach actually results in a greater risk of failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is an important paradox in many health services, including Wales, is that there is a tendency to centralise the day-to-day management and delivery of individual products and yet high-level strategic and prioritisation decisions are decentralised, haphazard and dependant on capital funding with little or no consideration or control as to how those projects will fit into a wider technical healthcare enterprise architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html&quot;&gt;“A paradox of control”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high-level strategic roadmap to deliver our vision should be centralised across an enterprise. Similarly, the rules of engagement, the the contractual obligations at a human and technical level that permit interaction with the open platform (API and data standards etc.) should defined centrally. Likewise, the day-to-day management and delivery of individual projects should be driven, bottom-up, by the users and for the users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;“Once for Wales debate”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-design/2017/03/23/scope-framing-clinical-design.html&quot;&gt;Scope and framing in clinical information system design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/04/04/test-requesting.html&quot;&gt;Test requesting design: building an open API-based architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data driven healthcare information technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">My writing on domain-driven design arose because of my own experience building an electronic patient record system:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The paradox of ambition</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/paradox-of-ambition.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The paradox of ambition" /><published>2017-12-06T10:39:39+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-06T10:39:39+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/paradox-of-ambition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/paradox-of-ambition.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-paradox-of-ambition&quot;&gt;The paradox of ambition&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have information technology projects in healthcare which are hugely ambitious in their scope - for example, the nursing documentation project in Wales - in which there are many requirements, interactions, dependencies and fundamentally so many issues of change management required across multiple organisations, that it is hugely ambitious as a result of it being really very difficult. That worries me, because ambition to solve something that is extremely difficult is misplaced ambition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.nafw.cloud.vualto.com/Player/Index/f81e649d-044a-40b0-8f42-8d6017d78557?autostart=False&amp;amp;captionsOn=False&quot; name=&quot;NAFW Player&quot; seamless=&quot;seamless&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.senedd.tv/Meeting/Index/f81e649d-044a-40b0-8f42-8d6017d78557&quot;&gt;Welsh Senedd meeting on nursing documentation project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The right kind of ambition is ambition to make a difference and deliver value at pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when we talk about nursing documentation, it is ambitious because I think, the project, as currently designed, will just not work. The approach is just wrong; it needs to be something driven from the bottom-up and not the top-down. What the top-down should be doing is setting the direction of travel, setting the rulebook, giving the users and the people who work on their behalf the tools to solve their problems. You need to get software in the hands of users as soon as possible in order to more fully understand the problems you are trying to solve; a more agile approach is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The right kind of ambition is to deliver. So what I mean by ambition is that I want to have my consultations recorded and my dictation to order blood investigations automatically. Who will be the first to deploy “Amazon Echo” or “Google Home” in the clinic to support my outpatient consultations? How can we enable that innovative future? We do it by creating an appropriate open services-based architecture and allow multiple applications to use those services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So sure, build test requesting into a portal but don’t build the whole stack of functionality into that single codebase so it is inaccessible to any other application. Likewise, don’t build a service that only one application can use. Break it up, make test requesting a service. Make the applications, such as Welsh Clinical Portal, use that service. Don’t make any single application mandating for use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So then if we come along and want to get Amazon or Apple or Google to listen to our speech in clinic, to turn that speech into text and make a range of test requests based on that text, then don’t stop us doing that. Create something that enables that. Enable innovation and don’t suffocate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another paradox here in that I keep repeating in this forum and others, that we don’t know all the stuff we need to solve. We need to look really hard at people who think that they have all of the answers, because they don’t. Getting everyone in a room, and listing the requirements, building a technical specification and building it like it was a bridge, is not the way to build software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be ambitious, be realistic. Have a vision and plan to deliver that vision incrementally at pace.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The paradox of ambition</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The paradox of control: Enabling innovation</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The paradox of control: Enabling innovation" /><published>2017-12-05T08:40:40+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-05T08:40:40+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/docs/dhss/publications/151211reporten.pdf&quot;&gt;Informed Health and Care Strategy, 2015&lt;/a&gt; sets out a clear vision for Wales to use digital technology and online services to support and enable care. The strategy is divided into four workstreams:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information for you&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supporting Professionals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improvement and Innovation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Planned Future&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.003.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.003&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivery of this vision would result in Wales uniquely blending socialised universal prudent healthcare with modern state-of-the-art technology to provide a responsive, fair and quality service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have to question whether we have the current organisational and governance structures within NHS Wales to most effectively implement this strategy? Historically, there has been a lack of pace in the delivery of individual projects that, together, should be incrementally fulfilling important components of the wider vision. Together, those individual projects should be stepping stones on which we deliver that vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wales is a unique place to deliver an effective healthcare information technology strategy given its size and our lack of purchaser-provider split and as a result, technology should be being used to effect broad-based transformational change. It is disappointing that we have not been able to make more progress but with the right changes, Wales can become a global example of a modern, forward-thinking healthcare economy underpinned by data standards, interoperability and an open platform to combine “Once for Wales” solutions with a mixed and thriving economy built on innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-paradox-of-control&quot;&gt;A paradox of control&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transformational change, enabled by technology, must be driven from the bottom-up, from those who deliver healthcare permitting incremental development and innovation while at the same time lowering risk. However, top-down governance must ensure that solutions are standards-compliant, fit-for-purpose and safe as well as checking that developments are not orthogonal to the overall strategic vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an important paradox in many health services, including Wales, is that there is a tendency to centralise the day-to-day management and delivery of individual products and yet high-level strategic and prioritisation decisions are decentralised, haphazard and dependant on capital funding with little or no consideration or control as to how those projects will fit into a wider technical healthcare enterprise architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;performance-management-and-delivery&quot;&gt;Performance management and delivery&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the responsibility of being part of “learning organisations” is to measure our effectiveness and performance, but do we really do that and how can we do that? What formal processes do we have to measure, for example, satisfaction with our clinical applications? Likewise, how is NHS Wales held to account in terms of performance management when delivering transformational change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should be asking the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who is responsible for determining and prioritising the high-level clinical requirements in each of the four workstreams in the strategy?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who is responsible for looking at the common themes between the workstreams and designing a national architecture that will enable delivery of those workstreams as well as giving consideration to future needs?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who is tasked with taking items of user-need and translating these needs into the design of software to meet those needs?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who is responsible for developing an iterative roadmap that delivers incremental benefits at pace and yet can deliver increasing functionality over time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we cannot answer those questions, then we have a duty to change our organisational, governance and technical structures so that we can all be held to account. Unfortunately, it is likely that the different organisations within complex multi-organisation enterprises such as NHS Wales will all attribute the failure of delivery to each other because delivery is dependent on so many interactions between so many levels of multiple, highly hierarchical organisations all with different models of funding and sometimes contradictory opinions on prioritisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear to me that we need to change our approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;collaboration-and-an-appropriate-technical-infrastructure&quot;&gt;Collaboration and an appropriate technical infrastructure&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, we need a new collaborative model in which a national open technical platform, adopting robust industry standards, underpins the development of national and local applications as well as supporting innovation from organisations both within the NHS and from the commercial sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a collaborative model must be underpinned by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the adoption of technical standards and open application programming interfaces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a renewed focus on a health enterprise “platform” for Wales, underpinning by a re-imagining of our software architecture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encouraging the development and evaluation of innovative projects by all&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wales is a unique place to leverage modern information technology in order to deliver transformational change for our clinical services, providing important support for patients, clinicians and managers. With the right technical architecture and organisational structures, Wales can collaborate to safely deliver the Informed Health and Care Strategy and deliver tangible benefit for our citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must start to openly debate the most effective way of delivering that strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Informed Health and Care Strategy, 2015 sets out a clear vision for Wales to use digital technology and online services to support and enable care. The strategy is divided into four workstreams:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Serverless in healthcare</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/04/serverless.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Serverless in healthcare" /><published>2017-12-04T22:22:22+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-04T22:22:22+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/04/serverless</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/04/serverless.html">&lt;p&gt;On serverless:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Serverless computing allows users to run code without provisioning or managing any underlying system or application infrastructure, and they automatically scale to support increasing or decreasing loads. 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.gartner.com/andrew-lerner/2017/07/21/serverless-is-not-networkless/&quot;&gt;https://blogs.gartner.com/andrew-lerner/2017/07/21/serverless-is-not-networkless/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A serverless architecture forces an enterprise architectural design that modularises and isolates code. Rather than creating a full-stack enterprise application containing components for user interactions, business logic, business rules and a persistence layer, one can break-up a solution into its functional constituents isolated from one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A serverless function such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloudacademy.com/blog/microsoft-azure-functions-vs-google-cloud-functions-fight-for-serverless-cloud-domination-continues/&quot;&gt;AWS Lambda, Google Cloud Functions or Microsoft Azure Functions&lt;/a&gt; can be written and deployed virtually instantly, with the hosting provider automatically scaling to manage the load. Ideally, such a function should do one or a few things very well, perhaps offering a set of application programming interfaces for clients to use with clear documentation as to how it can be called and what results might be expected. As such, the function is isolated and can be tested in lots of ways to ensure that it provides the results it is contracted to provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, writing small, well-defined services that provide a limited range of function is a characteristic of any microservice. What makes a serverless approach different is that managing the deployment and scaling of that service is delegated to the hosting provider, such as Amazon, Google or Microsoft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, a rarely used operation may take up no computing resources until it is triggered by an event, such as a HTTP request. Rather than trying to implement all functionality into a single or clustered server, one can break-up that functionality into separate functions. For instance, rather than writing a service to accept uploaded image files, process them, create thumbnails and then serve them as a photo-album, one might write a range of individual separate serverless functions to handle each step of that process so that, the thumbnail generation is automatically executed after a file is uploaded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One then imagines an overall application being simply a range of different independent pieces of functionality stitched together in a declarative manner to solve a specific range of problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This declarative approach then becomes a key driver of architecture. The application speaks the language of the domain and it’s easy to detect and fix force-fits, gaps, misrepresentations and erroneous assumptions in the application each time the implementation is reviewed against the domain. A declarative interface makes it easy to adapt to changes in the domain model.”
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pragatisoftware.com/blog/functional-programming-and-software-architecture&quot;&gt;http://www.pragatisoftware.com/blog/functional-programming-and-software-architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Functional programs are often organized as, sort of, a data flow graph, rather than a dependency structure. There’s declarative orchestration, right,? You just set up a whole bunch of things and you can see how they are related but you don’t have to, sort of, specify the order in which things happen, and you have referential transparency, right? I hand two values to a function, it will always give me the same value as the output because of referential transparency.”
&lt;a href=&quot;https://serverless.com/blog/bobby-calderwood-functional-programming-microservices-emit-2017/&quot;&gt;https://serverless.com/blog/bobby-calderwood-functional-programming-microservices-emit-2017/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, one is forced to focus on two core perspectives: an &lt;em&gt;overall&lt;/em&gt; perspective that takes in the combined architecture in which multiple microservices are stitched together and a &lt;em&gt;granular&lt;/em&gt; perspective at the level of an individual microservice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;healthcare-takes-steps-into-the-cloud&quot;&gt;Healthcare takes steps into the cloud…&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many, if not most, health services still run applications on local servers physically sitting on their premises, running on a private intranet inaccessible to the outside world running the day-to-day organisational processes of the business and usually providing clinical information to clinicians as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But things are changing, many years after most industries have made extensive use of cloud-based services, we are now seeing health organisations move to host servers on commodity cloud providers, resulting in a hybrid approach in which some services run locally and others run elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, rather than buying software and installing it for local users, we are starting to see organisations starting to procure platforms-as-a-service (PAAS) in which cloud-based services are used within the enterprise. For instance, in most modern organisations, a previously private intranet is increasingly having new communication channels laid down in order to enable interaction with patients and their devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, some providers now use PAAS-based patient portals such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patientsknowbest.com/&quot;&gt;Patients Know Best&lt;/a&gt; to enable patients to view their records. Such portals are also committing to opening up their data so that patients can choose to share their information with other providers;  for instance have a look at their &lt;a href=&quot;http://dev.patientsknowbest.com/home/fhir-api&quot;&gt;plans for a FHIR API&lt;/a&gt;). Likewise, other cloud-hosted services such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://drdoctor.co.uk/&quot;&gt;DrDoctor&lt;/a&gt; permit organisations to manage their outpatients by providing a platform on which patients can be contacted ahead of appointments to provide reminders and to collect outcome data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we already see health organisations making use of cloud-based services for hosting their own infrastructure and by using ready made large-scale off-the-shelf services from other providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; have a distributed healthcare platform; it is hosted by our organisations and unfortunately is usually disconnected so that clinical staff in one organisation cannot see health information about their patients from another organisation. Presently, we see healthcare making tentative steps to either move to or adopt cloud hosted services, but these usually remain organisationally-bound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;in-parallel-healthcare-is-changing&quot;&gt;In parallel, healthcare is changing…&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parallel with these technological changes, we see a range of &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;disruptive influences in healthcare&lt;/a&gt; highlighting three core changes enabled by new technology:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changes in models of care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patients as active participants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘Hospitals without walls’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, advances in technology enable a transformation of care. We should look to information technology to re-imagine how citizens interact with their health services. I spoke at a recent &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Digital Health and Care Conference on the benefits of an open platform&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, I highlighted the importance of modelling data &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#data-modelling&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and workflow/process &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#process-modelling&quot;&gt;b&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It has been a source of surprise and frustration that so many efforts to digitise healthcare neglect communication between professionals and with the patient, particularly when information technology has been used so effectively for communication in other domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my phase 1 vision of an appropriate enterprise architecture for NHS Wales:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/platform/platform-overall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Platform Overall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See that little box, “test requesting and results”. This is what is inside it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/platform/platform-lab.png&quot; alt=&quot;Platform Lab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we abstract a new notification service that handles notifications to users such as professionals in response to a result being made available by the laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this phase 1? Because I see the building blocks of our  architecture becoming increasingly distributed and shared among healthcare providers. Why embed a terminology service within an application when one can pick one off the shelf and use on a subscription or pay-as-you-go model?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-could-the-shift-to-a-services-based-economy-mean-for-health&quot;&gt;So what could the shift to a services-based economy mean for health?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A microservice economy means that multiple providers will offer small-scale, well-defined software functionality on a pay-as-you-go basis. We heard an announcement last week from Amazon launching their new &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/aws/aws-serverless-app-repo/&quot;&gt;AWS serverless application repository&lt;/a&gt; to enable a new marketplace of serverless apps that can be consumed by clients in order to solve real-life problems. I expect other providers to do the same, and there is ongoing work to create &lt;a href=&quot;https://serverless.com/&quot;&gt;toolkits&lt;/a&gt; that permit serverless applications to be hosted by any cloud provider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These technological trends mean that we will see large software applications and platforms being broken up into modules and as we progress, we will stitch together functionality from multiple providers to order to create clinical applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we combine these trends with a need to support cross-organisational working, to make patients “active participants in their care” and create “hospitals without walls”, we can see that we are moving to a distributed, decentralised, data-driven and cloud-hosting mixed environment combining functionality from multiple providers in order to create and run our health services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could see core services providing data access and basic workflow models for each organisation but we will increasingly wish to federate across those services, creating a combined view of all data from multiple organisations. For example, an organisation may own or rent a document repository, probably based on IHE-XDS or FHIR document model and because other organisations also converge on standards-based open services then, subject to citizen consent, those repositories can be federated so we see a list of documents across all repositories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, we could quickly see a marketplace of value-added functions that provide functionality layered upon those core services. For example, we might find a market for advanced natural language processing of unstructured text or services that encapsulate the application of machine learning algorithms to existing and new data. For example, why not rent a service that can, given a citizen’s distributed health record data, identify those taking a particular disease modifying treatment such as methotrexate and monitor and arrange the required three-monthly blood tests to check for signs of bone marrow suppression, renal impairment or liver damage? If that service was provided algorithmically as a microservice, given access to the required data and cost a fraction of a pence per patient, it could replace the administrators and specialist nursing staff whose job it currently is to monitor these patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;healthcare-application-sandboxes&quot;&gt;Healthcare application sandboxes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to see how some serverless resources might work. They may simply provide a HL7 FHIR resource endpoint and allow applications to use its application programming interface as if it were hosted locally. Imagine a distributed audit trail functionality, made available via the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/auditevent.html&quot;&gt;HL7 FHIR AuditEvent endpoint&lt;/a&gt;. FHIR servers can support one or many different types of resource and it is not difficult to imagine a single serverless application providing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/capabilitystatement.html&quot;&gt;capability statement&lt;/a&gt; documenting only a single end-point and providing that functionality in an automatically scalable fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a model would be fine for a single organisation, but how can that work in a distributed fashion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we need to create a distributed platform that means that we can plug-and-play these different microservices and make them useful to the wider health economy. To do that, we must design a sandbox environment in which user facing applications running on desktops, web-pages and mobile devices and backend serverless applications can be dropped and expect to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like Apple has “app stores” for mobile and desktop applications and Google has similar for Android, we need to consider what architecture is required for user-facing and serverless applications to be deployed easily and quickly into our distributed healthcare economy. Amazon has introduced the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/about-aws/whats-new/2016/11/introducing-the-aws-serverless-application-model/&quot;&gt;AWS Serverless Application Model&lt;/a&gt; which annotates a serverless application with information about its dependent resource types needed for its proper operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how could this work for our methotrexate monitoring example serverless application? It needs to be provided with a sane runtime environment from which it can safely access the information it needs and to take any actions that are necessary. So what does it need access to?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a test results service to get results including renal profile, full blood count and liver function tests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a test requesting service&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a document or clinical narrative repository&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a audit event logging service&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In software engineering, we frequently use a concept called &lt;em&gt;dependency injection&lt;/em&gt; to pass through dependencies to a subsystem so that we can configure it appropriately and appropriately isolate separate functionality. As such, much like the AWS Serverless application model referenced above, we need to consider how we glue together sensitive health data with different services, perhaps provided by multiple different vendors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that all the functionality our serverless application needs is provided by HL7 FHIR resource endpoints (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/diagnosticreport.html&quot;&gt;diagnostic reports&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/procedurerequest.html&quot;&gt;procedure request&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/fhir/documentreference.html&quot;&gt;documents&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/auditevent.html&quot;&gt;audit&lt;/a&gt;), it might be possible to simply pass in those endpoints as dependencies either when the service is provisioned or even when it is called.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now the logical question becomes, how do we manage looking up and accessing resources across a distributed health enterprise, particularly when we are dealing with sensitive private data?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wrote in the &lt;a href=&quot;[next post](/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html)&quot;&gt;part three of my disruptive influences series&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Applications running on Apple’s iOS provide a useful analogy. In order to gain access to components of the underlying device and its operating system, such as the camera, the photo archive, location services etc, the application must use the appropriate API which forces explicit user consent. This “sandbox” environment means that an application is prevented from accessing resources to which consent has not been provided and presumably can log each and every attempt should that be required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Can we do the same for health applications and services? It seems to me that we can create tremendous value from healthcare data - for patients, for health professionals and for society - but the foundation must be to allow that information to be organised in such a way that we can make it “universally accessible and useful” &lt;em&gt;subject to individual consent&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to our distributed future, built declaratively to glue together distributed data and services, is underpinned by a robust model of citizen consent that itself is hardwired into the systems to manage resource lookup and access. We now need to start thinking about how this will work, and how a “healthcare application model” might operate so that we can make use of new technology to improve the care of our patients. We need to start talking about how an “API gateway” might work for healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;data-modelling&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;: Data modelling ensures that we create semantically interoperable data coded in such a way as to make it meaningful to multiple disparate units of software. Such data may represent all types of clinical information, such as a blood pressure measured with a traditional sphygmomanometer on the right arm or the result of a laboratory test. As such, a focus on data standards is important so that there is agreement as to how individual items are coded and contextual information can be understood, such as who performed the measurement, how it was done and when.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;process-modelling&quot;&gt;b&lt;/a&gt;: While a prospective clinical record of structured and unstructured information forms our medical record, the medical record does much more than simply record a narrative of events. Our medical records &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; our clinical practice, enabling processes and workflow. Paper medical records have important properties in enabling workflow; &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/hazards-of-paper.html&quot;&gt;their presence on my desk with a post-it note tells to do something vital&lt;/a&gt;. It is therefore important to conceptualise not only a model of healthcare data but also model the workflow, processes and communications that enable care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information.html&quot;&gt;Organise healthcare information and make it universally accessible and useful&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;Disruptive influences in healthcare information technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/hazards-of-paper.html&quot;&gt;The hazards of paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">On serverless:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Data-driven healthcare: integration</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data-driven healthcare: integration" /><published>2017-10-19T23:22:22+01:00</published><updated>2017-10-19T23:22:22+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html">&lt;p&gt;This post is from a talk I gave at the inaugural Digital Health and Care Conference at the Principality Stadium in Cardiff, Wales on the 19th October 2017&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.001.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Introduction&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to talk about being data-driven in healthcare - how we need to create an architecture that enables us to capture and use data to improve patient care and our clinical services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want us to develop an open platform for healthcare in Wales built on a foundation of standards and interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to remember three things, the three “P”s - platform, patient and preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.002.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Platform, Patient, Preparation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By “platform”, I mean a collection of interoperating computing services built using industry standards a) on which we can build multiple applications for clinicians, patients and managers and b) provides a single consistent and logical patient record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By “patient”, I mean that we need to re-focus our work on our patients : and avoid simply digitising our old ways of working but instead make use of digital tools to support all citizens to interact with and contribute to their records and importantly, help them manage their own healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, by “preparation”, I mean that we need to create systems now that support solving our current problems but does not limit future development and innovation. We need to develop an infrastructure that fosters innovation in a safe way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/topics/health/nhswales/about/e-health/?lang=en&quot;&gt;Informed Health and Care strategy&lt;/a&gt;, as you all know, is split into four key themes, focused on the patient, the professional, our services and our future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.003.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.001&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially for patients, the requirements boil down to enabling patients to monitor and manage their own health, accessing, contributing to and controlling their own data. This patient focus is important and is essentially a disruptive influence on how our clinical services should develop in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For professionals, we essentially want access to the right information at the right time, information that reduces uncertainty about the decisions we make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, we are responsible for multiple cohorts of patients across our clinical services and need to ensure that we configure those services appropriately and permit innovation in service design and research and development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, we need to build systems - and I use that word in as loose fashion as possible - that support working in partnership - in collaboration to drive up quality and performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would argue that the solution to these requirements is not to jump to developing multiple software applications  but instead to develop a widespread recognition that DATA is at the heart of those aims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.004.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.001&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is DATA that tells us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what happened,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what is happening now&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;why it happened and even, if we get it right…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and what will happen…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is DATA that drives our work and digitisation of that data - historically on paper - means that we can do it at scale and in real-time -  it is analysis of renal function blood tests that should prompt a real-time notification that our patient is deteriorating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the question is how to successfully digitise healthcare?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time thinking about what “the medical record” actually means and I can’t express it better than the late Larry Weed, the founder of the problem-based medical record, who said, in his Internal medicine grand rounds:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You’re a victim of it or a triumph because of it. The human mind simply cannot carry all the information without error so the record becomes part of your practice”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.005.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.001&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course by medical record, I am not talking about an application running on a desktop computer, on an app on a mobile device: I’m talking about the logical medical record comprising all of the information that supports our decision making. It’s the data - the medical record that counts, and not the applications that we use to access that record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;joined-up-thinking&quot;&gt;Joined-up thinking&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think our biggest failure in healthcare IT is to create artificial boundaries between data : for example, in 2001, The Bristol Heart Enquiry highlighted the consequences of separating administrative and clinical data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The various clinical systems, many of them paper based, 
differed from one another and had no relationship with the administrative hospital-wide systems. The funding made available in the late 1980s and early 1990s for medical and later clinical audit helped to reinforce this separation by making available to groups of clinicians money for small local computer systems. The lack of any connection between these different systems, one administrative, the others clinical, for collecting data cannot be explained solely on the basis of some technical or technological reason. It was just as strongly a reflection of a mindset that clinical matters were the sole domain of clinicians and non-clinical matters, to do with the management of resources and with the movement of patients into and through the hospital, were the preserve of managers and administrators.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.006.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.001&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must stop thinking about administrative systems, clinical systems and research systems, and instead, focus on data - on the patient and the varying types of longitudinal data that are collected - by the patient, their devices and the professionals involved in their care. Of course, different people have need to see those data in different ways - different perspectives - different prisms, but the data - the  patient record - that is key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;start-with-problems&quot;&gt;Start with problems&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I recommend starting with PROBLEMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.007.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.001&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problems define your requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Show me all of my upcoming appointments. I have multiple chronic conditions and need to organise my life.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Should I say ‘yes’ to this high risk treatment?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Show me how a patient with multiple sclerosis is doing compared to their peers. Do I need to give more aggressive treatment?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I know how many patients are seen in outpatients, but I don’t know why or indeed, how they fare.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Which of our patients are suitable for this trial? Find me patients with drug-refractory epilepsy who have not tried lamotrigine and are keen on research?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“How can we work together collaboratively?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, what are the informatics challenges facing us in solving “show me all of my upcoming appointments”, particularly if we need to solve that across multiple organisations? We need to integrate data from across multiple PAS - and provide a unified view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should prioritise our requirements and consider the data requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how can we help patients come to decisions about a high-risk treatment? How can we understand our outpatient services without setting in motion systems to track clinical problems and diagnoses in a structured way rather than free text?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we make Wales the best place for IT, for collaboration?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thesis is: we think about the data required to solve those problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So given our problems, what kinds of data must we capture and link together to make them meaningful? I feel strongly that understanding  cohorts of patients - grouped by disease or clinical problem or intervention or contact with a specific service - these underpin the interpretation of all other data. For example, how can we interpret patient reported outcomes without understanding all of those issues? Information has to be linked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.008.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.008&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so essentially, we stop thinking about applications and think instead about the patient record, combining administrative, clinical records - including GP and hospital records, laboratory and other sources of information - into a logical longitudinal record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when we start thinking about a patient record, we must consider how we link disparate pieces of information together to solve our problems. We must stop creating data silos with information unusable outside of where it is collected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an abstraction of a logical longitudinal record:
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.009.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Logical longitudinal record&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps an example would be useful. Here is a screenshot from my own clinical information system that is currently used to look after over 25,000 patients in Wales and records 4,500 clinical encounters every month for a range of neurological and non-neurological diseases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.010.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;EDSS graph for patient plotted over time compared to peers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chart shows the progress of a single patient  marked with a red line against the progression of the disease in all patients with multiple sclerosis in South East Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did we do this? The chart is generated in real-time using analysis of all patient data taking to into account diagnosis and disease progression recorded by patients and clinicians. In clinic we find it useful to also see charted the  medications received by the patient - you can see that they have had alemtuzumab and methylprednisolone and also their exacerbations in their disease - marked with an “R” - for relapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now have years of longitudinal data for a wide range of cohorts of patients such as multiple sclerosis, motor neurone disease and Parkinson’s disease and real-time analytics and clinically-useful dashboards form an important part of making it &lt;em&gt;worth&lt;/em&gt; entering information. It is no good having either professionals or patients enter data or use devices to collect data unless we use that data for decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;snomed-ct&quot;&gt;SNOMED-CT&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important aspects of our work must be to support the collection of data by clinicians for clinicians in the day-to-day work. One important technology is SNOMED-CT a comprehensive terminology that supports the entry of structured clinical information coded in a computer-readable format. This is a KEY enabler of data-driven clinical systems and analytics. Using this, we can record a patient has multiple sclerosis and firstly expect that other software will understand this diagnosis and secondly understand what type of disease that this is. SNOMED-CT is an ontology - it not only includes concepts but the relationships between them, so I can potentially find all patients with a demyelinating disease and it will support me finding patients with multiple sclerosis but also related conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cppjedy-hMo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entering codes can be as simple as typing free text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With such a data-driven foundation, it becomes straightforward to build useful dashboards that take data from multiple systems and multiple sources and presents them in a useful fashion for end-users. Here we have a dashboard bringing together important information about a patient with motor neurone disease:
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.012.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.011&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we must ensure our patients can engage fully…. in the Parkinson’s disease clinic we have successfully trialled the use of iPads to connect to the EPR and allow them to contribute to their medical record via adaptive questionnaires. Here is a view of all patient data from a single clinic visit that is used to generate our clinic letter automatically. Each of these outcomes can be graphed to show changes over time.
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.013.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.011&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;scaling&quot;&gt;Scaling&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how can we take what we’ve done and scale it to every other clinical encounter in Wales? The problem is that “We don’t realise how much we don’t know”. I am sure that there are some clever people who can take my Parkinson’s disease medication and disease progression data and turn it into something even more useful, who can then link it to home monitoring technology and falls detection and send our team alerts when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we design or implement software that solves our problems today and adopts a sufficiently flexible approach that we can innovate and adapt to solve the problems of our future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.014.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;We don't realise how much we don't know&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t read it, I recommend Domain-driven design by Eric Evans - a focus on data modelling to support complex systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start with a model of our data; this model will change but slowly over time — a blood pressure measured in the right arm will always be a blood pressure measured in the right arm. On top of this information model, we build conceptual models of workflow and process, a platform made up of core services providing access to those models and finally lightweight applications. Process and workflow models will change much more frequently that our data model and likely need dynamic customisation via rules engines for different contexts. Applications should be the most ephemeral component of our designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;an-open-innovation-platform&quot;&gt;An open innovation platform&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.015.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Open innovation platform&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, we create an &lt;em&gt;open innovation platform&lt;/em&gt; built on a secure foundation of structured, semantically meaningful data. We provide a range of core application programming interfaces or APIs - providing access to a range of useful services such as identity, access and consent. Together, these form a platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must stop thinking about applications and instead think about how our platform can interact with our work streams - our patients, our professionals, our partners and the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.016.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.016&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most businesses have already realised that information technology forms an inherent part of their operations; in essence, they have realised IT &lt;em&gt;IS&lt;/em&gt; their way of doing business. It is about time healthcare did the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the model becomes a data-centric core, open platforms exposing those data and multiple lightweight applications solving specific process and workflow problems for patients and professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.017.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.017&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, we create a single patient record : and ensure that we can see all of the relevant information for a patient while not getting lost in an excess of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is how it could look in Wales:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.018.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.018&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We open up our core services, create a platform leveraging new technologies such as HL7 FHIR to expose application programming interfaces that can be used by multiple applications providing different views and different perspectives on a single patient record or collections of those records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[ explain diagram ]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must focus on data standards and interoperability, creating lightweight applications at pace and design useful real-time analytics services for clinicians and managers. Critically, we build a platform that can provide the building blocks for future innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.019.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.019&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in summary, I remind you to remember three “P”s : we need to build an open platform, ensure we focus on our patients and… prepare for and permit future innovation by understanding that we don’t have all of the answers… at least - not yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information.html&quot;&gt;Organise healthcare information and make it universally accessible and useful&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;Disruptive influences in healthcare information technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/hazards-of-paper.html&quot;&gt;The hazards of paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This post is from a talk I gave at the inaugural Digital Health and Care Conference at the Principality Stadium in Cardiff, Wales on the 19th October 2017</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The ‘fractal’ medical record</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/medical-records/2017/10/08/the-broken-medical-record.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 'fractal' medical record" /><published>2017-10-08T04:14:15+01:00</published><updated>2017-10-08T04:14:15+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/medical-records/2017/10/08/the-broken-medical-record</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/medical-records/2017/10/08/the-broken-medical-record.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fractal/mandelbrot.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Mandelbrot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical data are complex and heterogeneous with individual patient records combining multiple disparate sources of information including :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;administrative data, scheduling and context (e.g. outpatient neurology clinic - movement disorders)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;patient reported outcome and experience measures  (e.g. “I can walk”, “he was rude”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clinical diagnostic, procedural and outcome measures    (e.g. “multiple sclerosis”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;diagnostic synthesis and management plans  (e.g. “offer a new high-risk disease modifying treatment”)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between those categories, it is possible that we can answer the what, who, how and possibly the why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What many people don’t realise is that the interpretation of medical data, irrespective of its form, depends, to a variable degree on everything else. The most important dependency, in my view, is the context in which those data were acquired. This need for interpretation is why the phrase, “the single source of truth”, when used in building health record software, is only a partially useful mantra; it hopefully encourages a data-focused, clinical modelling approach but it inappropriately suggests that there is a “single truth”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you need to re-appraise how you consider, for example, “problem lists” - and understand that the meaning of “angina”, whether encoded as a consecutive array of letters of the alphabet (e.g. in English: “a-n-g-i-n-a” as free text) or encoded using a code from a medical terminology or classification system (e.g. in SNOMED-CT: Angina (disorder) SCTID: 194828000 with synonyms: Angina, Cardiac angina, Angina pectoris, Stenocardia,  Anginal syndrome, AP - Angina pectoris, Ischemic heart disease - angina, Ischaemic heart disease - angina,   Angina (disorder)) cannot be understood without contextual information, including the series of logical inferences that resulted in that diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, you should regard a diagnosis of “angina” with skepticism if it was given by me, a consultant neurologist but you might trust my diagnosis of “myasthenia gravis” even if the antibody test for that condition is negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even data sourced from an accredited laboratory requires careful interpretation. A single test might be a false-negative result unless there is 100% sensitivity. Likewise, a positive test may be false-positive unless there is 100% specificity; either scenario would be extremely unusual indeed. In addition, tests, such as laboratory tests may be combined to improve their predictive power. It becomes even more complex as sensitivity and specificity depends on the &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; probability of that test in that population. As a result the interpretation of a test or combination of tests depends on the context in which those tests were performed. A positive test result performed as the result of screening a whole unselected population has less importance than a test performed in a patient suspected of having the disease in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if a laboratory test does not perfectly predict a disease, we can easily see how more subjective, opinion-based tests and diagnostic processes such as radiology or getting a clinical opinion in an outpatient clinic, will suffer from the same issues. In particular, if a report changes (and they do) or clinical opinions vary (fairly common) then “truth” becomes a poor conceptual foundation for our electronic health systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logical conclusion  is that there is no single “truth”, but instead a deeply hierarchical, nested inter-dependent, frequently correlated set of multi-dimensional data. Does it matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;data-for-decision-making&quot;&gt;Data for decision-making&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve written about measurement &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/machine-learning-2.html&quot;&gt;previously&lt;/a&gt; concluding that medical data, whether a measurement of a physiological parameter, a laboratory test result or report from a radiological investigation, is useful only in &lt;em&gt;reducing the uncertainty around a decision&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we perform measurements, of whatever type, to support decision making and conceptually, those decisions may be grouped into three broad categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the direct care of that patient&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the care of groups of patients within our clinical service(s) and organisations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clinical research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we have measurements that don’t influence current or future decisions in any of these domains, then we must ask ourselves why are we performing and recording those measurements at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if we have imperfect measurements that are not 100% sensitive or 100% specific, then we have to ask, sensitive and specific to &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt;? Realising this provides an important insight: when applied, say to clinical diagnosis, is that almost all of our measurements in medicine are as if we are looking at the truth out of the corner of our eye. We cannot see the &lt;em&gt;hidden truth&lt;/em&gt; but a combination of our measurements are, together, governed by a few simpler variables or concepts that are actually the cause of the results of the measurements that we can measure. As a result, we hope that our measurements can be used to understand the &lt;em&gt;latent&lt;/em&gt; variable(s) that are actually the hidden cause of those measurements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, sometimes we get an elevated C-reactive protein (CRP) result. It is usually raised in certain types of inflammatory or infectious disorders. It is like the smoke from a fire in a forest, we see the smoke from our helicopter but do not necessarily the cause of the fire. If the patient has had a cough for three days and has a fever, and when we listen to the chest there are crepitations in the right lower zone and the CRP is raised, the diagnosis is likely to be a community-acquired pneumonia. We have to take into account the &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; probability as well, which means that we consider common causes more frequently than rare causes. Likewise, if the patient has had a cough for three months then we might reach a different conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, when we consider clinical diagnosis, our combination of multi-dimensional &lt;em&gt;measurements&lt;/em&gt; is providing us with a probabilistic determination of a specific considered diagnosis. Over time and with experience, most clinicians build up a set of heuristics that imperfectly approximate this diagnostic process and learn a range of practical short-cuts in order to cope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has always been a surprise to me that we have not yet developed tools to support this fundamentally complex and difficult problem; while we teach “red flags” to aid the identification of the unusual patient (e.g. a headache that is the worst ever headache), such decision-support aids remain crude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;nested-data&quot;&gt;Nested data&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we know a patient has a history of angina and presents with chest pain, understanding how and why that &lt;em&gt;label&lt;/em&gt; of “angina” was given is important. In fact, what does that label actually mean? Is it the diagnosis given by a consultant cardiologist or, inappropriately by a rather over-enthusiastic neurologist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re actually using the term “angina” to represent an approximate and subjective clinical concept as an abbreviation rather than endlessly writing down the multiple logical inferences made in order to determine that the patient suffered, for example, chest pain on exertion and had a stent placed for stenosis in her coronary circulation. It is a placeholder that actually hides a lot of potential complexity and permits professionals and patients to communicate and make decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fractal/angina-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Angina 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see that a constellation of information (our measurements, binary choices or continuous variables) allows us to apply a pragmatic diagnostic label, “angina”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except is that right? What is the point of that label unless it too is useful for future decision making? If I visit the catheter laboratory and ask my cardiology colleague for a coronary angiogram because a patient has “angina”, they’ll want to interrogate that diagnostic label in much greater detail to make a decision about whether a patient should have a specific intervention. They will want to know more than simply “angina”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our measurements and our labels are therefore interpretable and usable only in a specific context and for a specific set of circumstances in order to make a decision to effect care. Indeed, for future care, perhaps the diagnosis of “angina” is less useful than an understanding of pathology : ie whether the patient has significant arteriosclerotic vascular disease or not; after all, perhaps that is the biggest predictor of future cardiac events?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fractal/angina-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Angina 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; we use information when a patient presents to the emergency department with new crushing chest pain. Clinical decisions at the front door can simply use our placeholder diagnostic lists in order to action safe care and combine that historic information (that the patient has proven coronary artery disease) together with new information to make a diagnosis of acute myocardial infarction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;fractal-data&quot;&gt;Fractal data&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fractal/angina-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Angina 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now we see a repeated pattern in our data used for clinical decision making. Not only is our information nested, but we see that there are similarities in our data at different levels of detail. This repeating pattern of data at different levels of our decision making hierarchy is similar to that seen in &lt;em&gt;fractal data&lt;/em&gt;. In essence, a combination of measurements (data) are used to identify a hidden (latent) trait that itself is difficult to measure to inform a clinical reasoning process. The end-result of that clinical reasoning may be itself used in future clinical reasoning. This highlights the naturally &lt;em&gt;recursive&lt;/em&gt; nature of medical information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, an understanding of the hierarchical nature of clinical decision making allows us to consider the considerable redundancy and correlations seen between different covariates; for instance both having a drug-eluting coronary stent placed in 2014 and a diagnosis of unstable angina both flag an underlying (more difficult to measure) latent trait, namely that of arteriosclerotic coronary artery disease. Those characteristics are therefore highly correlated and may be redundant in a single patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;decision-making---by-humans-and-by-machines&quot;&gt;Decision making - by humans and by machines&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Redundancy and latent traits are important when we consider what information needs to be made available at the time of a clinical decision. How do we make sense of large volumes of hierarchical, highly correlated fractal-type data and decide what needs to be seen by a clinician in a particular clinical scenario, or indeed what needs to be used by a machine to learn to appropriately make a diagnosis or decide on a treatment plan? We cannot show or indeed use all information, and not all information is in fact useful at any particular clinical context. As such, we should be considering techniques to reduce the redundant dimensions that exist within healthcare data. For data mining and “big data” processing, we should be exploring dimensionality reduction techniques in order to make sense of an overload of redundant medical information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, we need clinical systems to appropriately model the clinical decision making process and understand that there is no single “truth” but a chain of clinical reasoning at a given point in time that should take into account any and all variables that influence the results of a clinical decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, this is where machine learning and more general purpose artificial intelligence can most help us in our day-to-day clinical work. We need tools to help us understand what our measurements, our data, actually mean and how, in combination, they hide latent variables that should truly determine our next clinical decision. Our knowledge of this fractal-type pattern of clinical decision making should inform how we can generate training data for machine learning and apply those algorithms in the real-world. We should be aiming to replace our informal human heuristics, those short-cuts we use to permit decision-making at a time of significant uncertainty and instead build a data-driven approach to clinical reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now have access to sufficient computing power to allow machine supported clinical decision making but those algorithms need to be trained. As such, we must study and understand clinical decision making, adequately model both clinical data and clinical reasoning and make those data available for machine learning so we can build the next generation of tools to improve medical care for all of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The term “fractal” was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fractal&quot;&gt;coined by Mandelbrot&lt;/a&gt; who “based it on the Latin frāctus meaning ‘broken’ or ‘fractured’, and used it to extend the concept of theoretical fractional dimensions to geometric patterns in nature.” I’ve therefore titled this blog post “the broken medical record” for two different reasons: 1) medical records are broken and fragmented in the truest sense of those words, 2) they have similarities to fractal data as they are deeply hierarchical and nested with clinical reasoning built upon chains of previous reasoning (e.g. a process of clinical reasoning takes place in order to order an investigation, the radiologist reporting the scan performs her own reasoning based on the referral and the actual imaging, a receiving clinician repeats the process now integrating all of those chains of reasoning).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Mandelbrot generated by &lt;a href=&quot;//commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?title=User:Mjdean&amp;amp;action=edit&amp;amp;redlink=1&quot; class=&quot;new&quot; title=&quot;User:Mjdean (page does not exist)&quot;&gt;Michael James Dean&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;span class=&quot;int-own-work&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;Own work&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0&quot; title=&quot;Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=17070006&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Information at the right time…</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/analytics/2017/09/29/information-at-the-right-time.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Information at the right time..." /><published>2017-09-29T20:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-09-29T20:18:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/analytics/2017/09/29/information-at-the-right-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/analytics/2017/09/29/information-at-the-right-time.html">&lt;p&gt;It is surprising how my interests have converged and supported one another over time: computing, technology and programming; data analysis, clinical medicine, neuroscience, clinical neurology and genetics; undergraduate assessments and psychometrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I want to discuss the fundamental importance of data in clinical medicine and the overlap between direct care, service management and improvement and clinical research. The overlap and relationships between these three are shown in this schematic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cis_design/data_pipelines.png&quot; alt=&quot;Data Pipelines&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In clinical research, we have relatively small numbers of individuals with highly detailed information (“high level phenotypic data”). In day-to-day clinical practice, we have large numbers of patients with patchy or low level clinical data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common theme that runs through this blog is, I hope, that the &lt;a href=&quot;/cis-design/2017/05/01/medical-record.html&quot;&gt;medical record defines our clinical practice&lt;/a&gt;, and the foundation of that medical record is usable data… usable &lt;em&gt;information&lt;/em&gt;.  We use that information for direct care of individual patients, organising our services to support the care of groups of patients and to perform clinical research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;creating-a-data-driven-culture&quot;&gt;Creating a data-driven culture&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2005 I started using R (The R Project for Statistical Computing) for my statistical analysis during my doctorate. I’d been disappointed with SPSS and its point and click user interface and crude scripting language. As a researcher, I realised that I would need to run and re-run many different analyses and remembering how to transform and clean-up in preparation for configuring and then running different types of statistical test was going to be difficult and time-consuming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote about R on my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.medicalnerds.com/10-pieces-of-free-software-every-doctor-should-havean-introduction-to-r/&quot;&gt;old blog in 2007&lt;/a&gt; and since then, I have managed to convince many colleagues to adopt it for their own research. In 2005, I didn’t know anyone else using R (except the R-help mailing list) but it was immediately appealing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is a programming language, an environment for statistical computing and not simply an application to run statistical tests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it results in reproducibility. I can run the same analyses over and over again, for example when my data are updated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is open-source&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own research involved clinical epidemiology, phenotype-genotype correlations, clinical genetics and psychometrics and, if you are very keen (and want to know a bit more about ataxia), you can &lt;a href=&quot;/images/wardle-2009-thesis.pdf&quot;&gt;read my thesis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;deep-phenotyping&quot;&gt;Deep phenotyping&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a junior researcher, I quickly learnt the value of “deep phenotyping”, the importance of systematically recording the longitudinal morphology of disease for individual patients, aggregating those data for groups of similar patients and understanding the cohort by the use of those data. To do this, one needs to consider the hypotheses and ensure that the appropriate clinical data is captured and recorded in a format that allows those hypotheses to be tested. My project looked at clinical progression, rating scales, the use of wearables and genetics with the combination of different sources of data to make logical inferences about these patient groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clinical research requires compromise, intuition and judgement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much data should be collected?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what will be important?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what can be collected in the timeframe?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how many patients do I need to assess in order to reach a valid conclusion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how will I record that data and in what format so that it is practical for storage, retrieval and analysis?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early on, we generated lots of ideas. For example, I gave up on the wearables project when we realised that patients were recording 0 steps in 24 hours, that the devices were too cumbersome and so were being left on the shelf rather than being worn. In those days, the technology was such that the wearable wasn’t actually very wearable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might have already concluded, none of these questions are unique to the specific neurological conditions I was interested in at the same and in fact are generic and widely applicable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;building-analytics&quot;&gt;Building analytics&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built an analytics pipeline in which clinical and genetic data were extracted, cleaned up and transformed and analysed. This combined a database and used R to do the rest, generating analyses and charts based on those data. With Sweave, I combined those results into reports, clinical papers and eventually my thesis by linking R and LaTeX:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;We identified \Sexpr{nrow(subset(cl, excluded==F))} patients with a reported history of 
cerebellar ataxia between 1999 and 2007 in South East Wales.
Applying inclusion and exclusion criteria as described above resulted in a subset of 
\Sexpr{cf.loca$total} with chronic progressive \ac{loca} with no identified aetiology 
as a denominator population for study. There were \Sexpr{cf.loca$num.familial} 
(\Sexpr{nrow(subset(loca, fh==T &amp;amp; sex=='Male'))} male, 
\Sexpr{nrow(subset(loca, fh==T &amp;amp; sex=='Female'))} female)
familial cases segregating in \Sexpr{cf.loca$num.families} kindreds 
and \Sexpr{cf.loca$num.sporadic} 
(\Sexpr{nrow(subset(loca, fh==F &amp;amp; sex=='Male'))} male, 
\Sexpr{nrow(subset(loca, fh==F &amp;amp; sex=='Female'))} female)
sporadic patients.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When run, this would output the following text:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;We identified 401 patients with a reported history of cerebellar ataxia between 1999 
and 2007 in South East Wales. Applying inclusion and exclusion criteria as described 
above resulted in a subset of 178 with chronic progressive LOCA with no identified 
aetiology as a denominator population for study. There were 55 (26 male, 29 female) 
familial cases segregating in 38 kindreds and 123 (79 male, 44 female) sporadic patients.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course, much more sophisticated analyses were possible, including the dynamic generation of charts, maps and statistics. For example, this chart is dynamically generated from our data source&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/data-driven/sca-prevalence.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sca Prevalence&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;generated using the following code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;\begin{figure}[!tb]
% This is the same as the ACNR graph, but using the (NEW) new SCA prevalence functions
&amp;lt;&amp;lt;sca-prev-adca, echo=FALSE, quiet=T, fig=T,width=6,height=4&amp;gt;&amp;gt;=
sp = sp.sca.prev(subset=patient.type=='ADCA' &amp;amp; total&amp;gt;10 &amp;amp; (region=='Asia' | region=='Europe' ), by=region, FUN=sp.percentage)
barplot(as.matrix(sp[,c(2:7,12)]), beside=T,
		xlab='Disease', ylab='Percentage of families', 
        main=&quot;&quot;, 		#  Ethnic differences in SCA subtype frequency&quot;,
        legend.text=c(
		    paste('Asia   (n=',sp[sp$region=='Asia',]$total,')',sep=&quot;&quot;),
		    paste('Europe (n=',sp[sp$region=='Europe',]$total,')',sep=&quot;&quot;)))
@
\caption[Aggregated data showing ethnic differences in SCA subtype frequency among families with ADCA.]{Aggregated data showing ethnic differences in SCA subtype frequency among families with ADCA. Data from Table~\ref{tab:sca.prev.adca}.}
% \cite{\Sexpr{print.citations(sp$cite)}}
\label{fig:sca.prev}
\end{figure}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sp.sca.prev() function source code is &lt;a href=&quot;/images/data-driven/sp-sca-prev.R&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, all of my papers and my thesis were built automatically whenever I wanted, simply by running &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; that would run a series of steps in a &lt;a href=&quot;/images/data-driven/Makefile&quot;&gt;Makefile&lt;/a&gt;. Consequently, I could identify any obvious errors in data entry quickly and ensure they were fixed as well as build analyses based on interim data with the confidence that they could be run again and again as data were added. I did all the work in LaTeX, R and used subversion as a version control system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-different-lenses-same-data&quot;&gt;So what? Different lenses, same data&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been discussing data warehouses, data lakes and analytic pipelines within NHS Wales. Some of us are pushing for an “open platform” based on a foundation of structured data recorded in using open standards and integrating a range of new and legacy services and systems via an API-approach (API - application programming interface) while others think we should be getting on with developing applications and thinking about interoperability later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My clinical colleagues want the right information about the patient in front of them, irrespective of organisational boundaries, so that clinical information recorded by other teams in different organisations, or even in different countries, is available at the point-of-care. We are overloaded by information, and this will increase (particularly given recent and ongoing &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;disruptive influences&lt;/a&gt;) so we need the right tools to make sense of that information. Presently, much of the administrative data is computerised but most clinical data exists only on paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My more senior clinical and managerial colleagues want to understand more about how our services perform and how can they be improved. They want to aggregate individual patient data and prepare data to inform decisions across our organisations and need to feed much of that information to other authorities as part of central returns. As only administrative data are routinely digitised, most analytics are focused on administrative matters, so we might &lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/06/using-data-patient-safety.html&quot;&gt;know how many people were seen, but not really have an idea as to why&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My academic colleagues want to recruit patients into clinical research and capture data in a much more systematic and structured way and use that information to study and publish and inform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to all three requirements is, of course, &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we may need to include much more detail for our research projects, I cannot stress the importance of the systematic and routine collection of outcome data in normal clinical practice for direct clinical care and management of our services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;adopting-a-data-driven-clinical-practice&quot;&gt;Adopting a data-driven clinical practice&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/22/health-data.html&quot;&gt;I wrote previously&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We should be focusing on &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; first, as &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; as the solution to a &lt;em&gt;problem&lt;/em&gt;. Data, structured, understandable, semantically interoperable data are the foundation on which clinical applications and our analytics can run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what was wrong with my research analytics pipeline? Although at the end of it I could run and re-run it and get almost immediate results, my data were not stored in a standardised format and my code can’t easily be picked up and used by others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be done differently: storing structured, informative and useful clinical data recorded by patients and health professionals; combining data from multiple sources to add value to information and creating learning adaptive systems that support our work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example I have used before, in which I present a dashboard on which the important information for a patient with motor neurone disease is aggregated in a single view. The determination as to whether the patient has a gastrostomy (or other kinds nutritional support) is a sequential look at the record of procedures performed (insertions and removal of gastrostomy tubes):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mnd-dashboard.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mnd Dashboard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That dashboard took me about 10 minutes of work to write as all of the important information was already being collected in a sequence of clinical encounters by my colleagues from palliative care, speech and language, dietetics, specialist nurses and neurologists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-power-of-aggregation&quot;&gt;The power of aggregation…&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EDSS is the expanded disability scale score, a relatively easy-to-use scale running from 0 to 10 that is used as a clinical indicator of disability. Health professionals can record it but we can also derive the score directly from patients using my iPad application:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/N3PQ2EEQNt4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following dynamically generated chart shows a single patient’s disease course over time compared to every single other patient we know with multiple sclerosis or a type of that disease:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/edss-graph.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Edss Graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The single patient’s course is shown by the red line, with relapses (acute deteriorations) marked with an “R”. The dotted lines are like the centile lines on a baby’s growth chart: from disease onset, the median disability for the whole cohort is shown. At a glance, we can then see whether an individual patient is deteriorating more quickly than expected or is more disabled that their peers and helps us to tailor their treatments appropriately. In patients with aggressive disease, we might choose to use more aggressive treatments with a greater risk of side-effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SQL code that identifies all patients with any type of multiple sclerosis, tracks their progress and aggregates the disability data is &lt;a href=&quot;/images/data-driven/msss-edss.sql&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;iteration&quot;&gt;Iteration&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we don’t stop there. We continue to build statistical models to track disease progression, combining different outcome measures and their proxies to try to understand the disease. As a result, our work will never be done; we can generate new models of disease progression that better predict deterioration and must embed that work into our day-to-day clinical practice. As such, we should aim for a virtuous cycle of continuous improvement, embedding clinical research into our day-to-day clinical practice in a similar way to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.isixsigma.com/dictionary/dmaic/&quot;&gt;Six Sigma quality initiative&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cis_design/dmaic.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dmaic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning is a useful addition to our analytics platform. We can already use standard survival analysis to identify the factors that are important in predicting survival and subsequently build a heuristic to help us in our clinical decision making. New technology offers us hope to improve those models and to speed up the iterative cycle to build continuously adaptive and learning systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a schematic representing how I think we need to create an open platform for healthcare in Wales:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/platform/platform-overall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Platform Overall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this schematic, the platform represents a range of APIs providing access to a unified aggregated view of a single patient record, but the other definition of a “platform” is of a multisided market:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Interestingly, another definition of a “platform” is a set of services that bring together users and providers to form a multisided market. Is it possible then to take our “open platform” and start to think of a future in which we have products and services that actually do enable a re-imagining of healthcare provision to bring together patients, carers, health professionals, commissioners, analytics, researchers and all other stakeholders in a safe and secure manner?  (see &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html&quot;&gt;a previous blog post&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment, our health platforms, if they exist, are lopsided asymmetric systems in which patients play little or no role. We must start thinking about creating a data-driven architecture that corrects this asymmetry in power and control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all cases, the foundation of that work is data. Technology is the enabler; it can release the value from our data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It is surprising how my interests have converged and supported one another over time: computing, technology and programming; data analysis, clinical medicine, neuroscience, clinical neurology and genetics; undergraduate assessments and psychometrics.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Privacy and Artificial intelligence</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/09/06/privacy-ai.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Privacy and Artificial intelligence" /><published>2017-09-06T20:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-09-06T20:18:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/09/06/privacy-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/09/06/privacy-ai.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently contributed to a &lt;a href=&quot;wired uk ai privacy&quot;&gt;Wired UK article on privacy and healthcare&lt;/a&gt;. Here is my full response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;should-we-worry-about-big-dataaimachine-learning-in-healthcare&quot;&gt;Should we worry about ‘Big Data’/AI/machine learning in healthcare?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, the two main concerns relate to privacy and value: fundamentally, privacy simply relates to the risk to individuals of sharing information about those individuals and value relates to the intrinsic worth of that data as well as the value of any algorithms or software produced as a result of analysis of that data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to explore the privacy concerns without clarifying what we mean by data and how it is already used, particularly as privacy depends fundamentally on the purpose to which the data is processed and by whom. For example, in medical settings, you might expect me as your neurologist to have access to your relevant medical information from other healthcare professionals, such as reports, documents and the results of investigations such as scans and laboratory investigations. Currently, most such data is held by NHS organisations or commercial companies operated for and behalf of those healthcare providers. There are, therefore, already many current situations in which selected data is shared externally with healthcare, social care and commercial entities. Such data are used for direct care of individual patients and for managing our clinical services. Likewise, there are already many situations in which routine NHS data is combined and de-identified in some way and made available for research such as the CPRD (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cprd.com/home/&quot;&gt;https://www.cprd.com/home/&lt;/a&gt;) and SAIL (&lt;a href=&quot;https://saildatabank.com&quot;&gt;https://saildatabank.com&lt;/a&gt;). Such systems usually try to remove obviously identifiable information such as name and date of birth and instead generate categorical variables (e.g. year of birth) to try to obfuscate the identify of individuals. Have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://understandingpatientdata.org.uk/what-does-anonymised-mean&quot;&gt;https://understandingpatientdata.org.uk/what-does-anonymised-mean&lt;/a&gt; in relation to de-identified, anonymous and pseudonymous data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there is not a discontinuity between identifiable and non-identifiable information but instead a spectrum running from low to high risk of re-identification. This risk increases as more and more data are made available and this is where the concept of “big data” results in privacy concerns. You may not be able to identify me from only knowing I’m a neurologist, but if you know I work in Wales and have an interest in information technology then you’re likely to know it’s me. As a result, “big data” in which large amounts of different types of data are made available and aggregated can undermine techniques to de-identify that data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next question is, does sharing identifiable or re-identifiable data matter? In general, the answer depends on who is doing the processing and the consequences, benefits and risks from that processing. People naturally have different expectations for the usage of data depending on whether it is for direct care, for clinical research, for a perceived “greater-good” or for commercial means. The care.data fiasco demonstrated the strong public concern relating to the release of information to commercial such as the insurance industry (e.g. see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/feb/28/care-data-is-in-chaos&quot;&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/feb/28/care-data-is-in-chaos&lt;/a&gt;). Fundamentally therefore, this means that we need strong and appropriate legal and regulatory frameworks to ensure that we take advantage of the enormous opportunities inherent in combining these sources of data with modern technology to improve patient care and clinical research. The new GDPR legislation extends the rights of individuals to control the purposes to which their information is used, and we in healthcare must take these changes into account when considering “big data” and machine learning. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/data-protection-reform/overview-of-the-gdpr/&quot;&gt;https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/data-protection-reform/overview-of-the-gdpr/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the issue of “value” depends on who gains that value. If an algorithm is developed that can, for example, screen a chest x-ray to determine whether it is normal or abnormal, with only the latter images needing formal radiologist review, then there would a huge interest across the world in commercialising that technology and free up valuable time for radiologists. Who should own that technology? The services providing the data or the technology companies who have built the systems to learn from that data? For me, this should be a partnership between health and technology as both need each other in order to make progress to potentially improve patient care. As a result, I’d always expect explicit clauses relating to intellectual property rights to be included in data sharing agreements in which software and algorithms may be of commercial value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-other-privacy-protectingenhancing-technologies-are-there&quot;&gt;What other privacy-protecting/enhancing technologies are there?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like “Understanding patient data” : see &lt;a href=&quot;https://understandingpatientdata.org.uk/how-data-kept-safe&quot;&gt;https://understandingpatientdata.org.uk/how-data-kept-safe&lt;/a&gt; and its explanations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, it is necessary to have a mixed set of strategies as there is no single “magic bullet” that magically preserves or enhances privacy.  Instead, we need a combination of appropriate legal and regulatory frameworks (as I mentioned above), independent review and audit, formal software specifications and methodologies and, most importantly, a conversation with everyone about the benefits and risks of the use of patient data to improve care, now and in the future. As part of that national debate, we must determine the scenarios in which different levels of consent are required, such as an explicit opt-in for clinical research or an opt-out for other uses. At the same time, we must increase general public awareness about the benefits and risks of the wider use of health information. Ideally, data should be de-identified as much as possible for the specific use-case in question so that we instead start to talk about “risk of re-identification” and it is likely that different levels of risk will be acceptable for different use-cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are additional technologies to add into the mix such as “differential privacy” (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Differential_privacy&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Differential_privacy&lt;/a&gt; for more information) which introduce randomness into aggregated data in order to reduce the risk of re-identification and yet preserve conclusions made from the use of that data. Another interesting research development has been homomorphic encryption allows information such as private medical data to be encrypted and subsequently processed without needing decryption. Have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homomorphic_encryption&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homomorphic_encryption&lt;/a&gt; but such technology is, as far as I am aware, at a very early stage as it is extremely computationally-intensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;are-we-considering-privacy-enough&quot;&gt;Are we considering privacy enough?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably not!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health data becomes even more complex when one considers the ever increasing use of new technologies in healthcare. I have written about these in my “disruptive technologies” blog post (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&lt;/a&gt;) and in particular, how we deal with data from multiple sources such as devices carried by the patient or installed in the home. As a result, there will be an increasing number of &lt;em&gt;“attack surfaces”&lt;/em&gt; in which confidential medical information may be leaked. For instance, how will we deal with the data sent from a device designed to monitor an elderly patient and check for falls, or whether they have left their home, or their activity? How will we ensure that only the right people receive that information?   The same issues apply to medical and health applications aimed at consumers which may leak confidential medical information. There are many examples unfortunately - see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4419898/&quot;&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4419898/&lt;/a&gt;  for just some of the examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A useful resource is the “privacy-by-design” page from the ICO: see &lt;a href=&quot;https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-data-protection/privacy-by-design/&quot;&gt;https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-data-protection/privacy-by-design/&lt;/a&gt; in which organisations undertake a privacy impact assessment to reduce potential harm to patients. Such tools are only useful when they are used, so the concept of sandboxes is also important, particularly for mobile device “apps”. For example, on most mobile devices, an application must request permission to access contacts, the camera or onboard health data and checks of those permissions are not a function of the application to implement (or not) but a function instead of the sandbox in which the application runs and all data access can be logged. So I think device manufacturers have a role in checking and verifying applications in their app stores and programmes like NHS digital’s app store (see https://apps.beta.nhs.uk) add an additional layer of inspection and curation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t add much more to what Dame Fiona Caldicott said : &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/national-data-guardian-ndg-statement-on-government-response-to-the-ndg-review&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/national-data-guardian-ndg-statement-on-government-response-to-the-ndg-review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main conclusion is that there is no single answer but a combination of solutions :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;give people choice,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;engender public trust by
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;appropriate regulatory and legislative frameworks,&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;adopting appropriate technical safeguards and de-identify information at a level that minimises re-identification risk and satisfies the specific requirements for analytics on that occasion,&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;using verifiable logs to ensure access to confidential information is logged and capable of inspection.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical data is terrifically valuable, powerful and offers tremendous scope to do good, but we also have a great responsibility to protect those data and ensure access is safe, secure and transparent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best wishes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently contributed to a Wired UK article on privacy and healthcare. Here is my full response.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Health data - start with a problem</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/08/22/health-data.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Health data - start with a problem" /><published>2017-08-22T22:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-08-22T22:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/08/22/health-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/08/22/health-data.html">&lt;p&gt;Walk about on the wards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chat with nursing, medical or pharmacy staff. Chat with physiotherapists, occupational therapists, managers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They all have problems that need to be solved, problems that make carrying out their day-to-day work more difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask them:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“What would make your job easier?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“What would enable you to provide &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; care?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At their most fundamental, their problems and the solutions to those problems relate to data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may scoff. Oh here he is again, going on about data as the answer to everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why clinical research, such as a clinical trial, used to answer questions such as “Does this treatment work?”, is built on data; carefully acquired, carefully managed and carefully analysed data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a nursing staffing crisis! We should be solving it, with data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to run an audit to see whether our service is performing well. Solve it, with data (and in a computer on not on paper).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to identify that patient not responding to conventional treatments; we want to show them their progress compared to their peers, because we need to have a discussion about more aggressive treatments. Solve it, with data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many nursing staff do we need on &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; ward, with &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; patients, for &lt;em&gt;this&lt;/em&gt; shift? How can we identify the deteriorating patient? Show the admitting team looking after the patient with muscular weakness that the GP had already checked the acetyl-choline receptor antibodies two weeks ago and the result is already available tonight. How do patients &lt;em&gt;like me&lt;/em&gt; fare after that procedure?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;think-big-with-data&quot;&gt;THINK BIG WITH DATA&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now have virtually unlimited computer resources at our disposal, both in terms of storage and computational power. We need to think big and have grand aims. It’s then our job to develop strategies to carefully take advantage of that technology to envisage better ways of working and to iterate our way to achieve those aims. As I mentioned in my &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html&quot;&gt;disruptive influences blog post&lt;/a&gt;, we may change the detail, but not necessarily our direction of travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;we-dont-have-all-of-the-answers-but-we-dont-have-all-of-the-questions-either&quot;&gt;We don’t have all of the answers…. but we don’t have all of the questions either&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key message, and I cannot say this too many times, is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need to build an infrastructure that explicitly recognises that we don’t have all of the answers, and therefore must support innovation. Such innovation may simply be incremental improvement of existing technology, but also must cope with and embrace the introduction of transformative and disruptive technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote that during &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;debates within NHS Wales&lt;/a&gt; about the best way to formulate an information technology strategy. I’m reviewing a “functional requirements” list for a project currently which will end up with a procurement. It is hard work and it brings into sharp focus an important question: how can I know what will happen when our systems finally meet their users?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, we should be focusing on &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; first, as &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; as the solution to a &lt;em&gt;problem&lt;/em&gt;. Data, structured, understandable, semantically interoperable data are the foundation on which clinical applications and our analytics can run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why you should be learning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;openEHR : &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openehr.org&quot;&gt;www.openehr.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HL7 FHIR &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/overview.html&quot;&gt;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/overview.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SNOMED-CT &lt;a href=&quot;/cis-design/2017/05/02/data-standards.html&quot;&gt;see my introduction&lt;/a&gt; or a paper relating to how I &lt;a href=&quot;http://m.futurehospital.rcpjournal.org/content/4/2/126.full.pdf&quot;&gt;implemented SNOMED-CT in a clinical system in the Future Hospital Journal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And start thinking about immutable, structured and understandable data stored in vendor-neutral archives or exposed using an open application programming interface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for homework, start thinking about how you might create an infrastructure for real-time analytics… for example, show me some simple survival curves in real-time for patients having emergency surgery for any type of pancreatic surgery in the last 30 days stratified by age, gender and co-morbidities… Or, for that matter, the data that might be needed to solve the nursing staffing allocation problem…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we’re going to make “health information universally accessible and useful”, then let’s get the right information in the first place. After all, there are two words in “information technology”…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading:&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disruptive influences in healthcare information technology: &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/11/disruptive-influences-current.html&quot;&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html&quot;&gt;part 3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Walk about on the wards.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Disruptive influences in healthcare: the future</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Disruptive influences in healthcare: the future" /><published>2017-08-20T10:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-08-20T10:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html">&lt;p&gt;I previously discussed &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;three disruptive influences in healthcare in my previous blog post&lt;/a&gt; that, over the next five years, will disrupt both the provision of healthcare and the technological solutions currently used to support that care:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changes in the models of care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patients as active participants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘Hospitals without walls’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And subsequently, I tried to &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/11/disruptive-influences-current.html&quot;&gt;give an overview of how current strategies used by health services and commercial companies will struggle to meet those disruptions&lt;/a&gt;, principally as a result of a focus on single organisations and enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to draw these strands together in one place and hopefully provide some important context for some of my other blog posts. In my view, the two planks of work to form the foundation of our work are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An “open decentralised platform” for healthcare made up of multiple standards-based interoperable services and data repositories.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A single distributed logical patient record made up of multiple shards connected with multiple pseudo-identities wrapped in a consent model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, we need the right structures in place to allow us &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information.html&quot;&gt;“to organise healthcare and patient information and make it universally accessible and useful.”&lt;/a&gt; We need to be much more ambitious and yet plan to iterate to get to that future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-open-platforms-in-health&quot;&gt;1. Open platforms in health&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, administrative and clinical information relating to patients must be made more widely available outside of closed networks and across disciplines, services, organisations and sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, we must discuss the “open platform” approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Internet is one example of an “open platform”, in which open standards result in an open network in which many different software applications and devices can be connected and exchange information. One important consequence of an “open platform” is its use for applications not originally considered by its designers. For example, TCP/IP, the networking protocol that underpins the Internet handles, in a generic way, the low-level handling of bundles of data (messages) between computer systems. This open technical architecture was used as the foundation of the HTTP protocol, although other protocols such as Gopher were also built using TCP/IP as a foundation. This is an example of a &lt;em&gt;layered architecture&lt;/em&gt; in which an open platform, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://technet.microsoft.com/en-gb/library/cc958821.aspx&quot;&gt;“Open Systems Interconnection (OSI) model”&lt;/a&gt; is made up of multiple layers in which scope and function are well defined. Importantly, each subsequent layer usually provides a higher-level of abstraction from the detail. Low-levels of the OSI platform handle the physical connectivity and nitty-gritty details of networking such as data exchange and acknowledgements of transfer. Higher-levels allow software to ignore these low levels of networking management and simply exchange information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Internet has made information of all types universally accessible, useful and searchable and most of us now do this on mobile devices we carry with us all of the time. We now carry around practically unlimited computing resources in our pockets, so why can we not do that in healthcare?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;why-an-open-platform&quot;&gt;Why an open platform?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does the “open platform” matter in healthcare? I have &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/11/disruptive-influences-current.html&quot;&gt;touched on the problems previously&lt;/a&gt;. Essentially, healthcare informatics has been dominated by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a focus on administrative functionality rather than prioritising clinical care and the patient.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;large commercial vendors with closed systems and little or no interoperability.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a focus on the procurement of “products” based on &lt;em&gt;features&lt;/em&gt; on a capital expenditure basis with old-fashioned project plans built using a waterfall methodology with start and completion dates and little or no concept of iterative improvement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;organisations that are hierarchical and autocratic, designed to funnel information upwards and decisions made by those at the top flowing downwards. In essence, such structures have arisen as a result of trying to manage risk; when one considers large multi-million pound procurements, one must attempt to slow down decision making and reduce the risk of a bad decision&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;organisations that are risk-averse and fail slowly like a car crash in slow motion, rather than failing fast and learning from those failures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, how do we create the right structures that lower risk and allow more rapid iterative development?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer that, we must ask… what is our goal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open platform is simply the foundation for a longer and much more ambitious journey in healthcare information technology. It is so important to have a vision for a future in 5 or 10 years; we are certain to be wrong, but having ambitious goals &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; understanding that we’re going to have to change some of our plans; probably the details of some of the steps used to get there; but we won’t be changing the the direction of travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… shouldn’t our goal be to provide the right structures and technology to create high-quality, valuable user-centric applications that can help solve clinical problems, with the “user” being a patient or a professional or other worker involved in care. Don’t we want those applications running &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt; so that we can start work on the next generation of clinical applications. We want to understand our patients and have ready access to tools that support our teams in providing care for patients. Iteration is the key; we will never be finished and there will always be more to do. How can we enable that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve previously described user-facing applications as ideally being “almost throwaway” in our team meetings here in Wales and such statements have sometimes resulted in looks of incredulity. However, describing applications as “throwaway” simply reflects the following logical chain of reasoning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You say I can write clinical applications are “almost throwaway”?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Therefore, the engineering work must be quite straightforward, because I’m a lazy engineer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But surely there is a tonne of clever engineering work needed in healthcare, such as managing users, managing access, looking at patients, managing consent, access logs, getting and storing complex medical information and understanding the status of a variety of healthcare resources?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ah! The clever stuff must be already be provided elsewhere!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So, can you show me the API endpoints and documentation?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logical conclusion is therefore that we strive for an open platform in which applications coordinate and leverage multiple services provided within the platform; applications are the conductors for our orchestra of services. I expect some core services that are initially, mainly enterprise-bound, provided by individual organisations so that a single application can be deployed with little change between and across multiple those organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, with time, I’d expect to see a marketplace of increasingly sophisticated “services” that are provided outside of the scope of individual organisations, many provided by commercial vendors, in which sophisticated additional functionality can be made available on a cost per-use basis. Over time, the functionality of “the platform” extends upwards into &lt;em&gt;the cloud&lt;/em&gt; increasingly combining traditional data from organisations with new forms of patient-reported, patient-recorded real-life data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are already seeing the commercialisation of services like that in other sectors, with Google Cloud Functions and Amazon AWS lambda services providing serverless and maintenance free deployment and scaling of discrete pieces of logic. When are we going to do this for healthcare? Who’ll be first to offer a natural language processing API that takes a legacy clinical document and turns it into a structured document together with mapping to SNOMED-CT for £0.0001 per document? &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#snomed&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, I see an “open platform” as stage one of a larger plan, but how do we get started?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-is-an-open-platform&quot;&gt;What is an open platform?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been discussing strategy at length within NHS Wales and continue to have a fierce debate about the best way of using limited resources in the most valuable way. Perhaps reasonably, there are some who think we should be concentrating our limited resources on a single all-Wales application, the Welsh Clinical  Portal (WCP). I will not cover that debate here, but I feel strongly that a focus on an application is a &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;poor way of meeting both present and future challenges&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hope, instead, to influence the national strategy in favour of a platform approach.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#getting-sacked&quot;&gt;b&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For example, at the moment, laboratory and radiology investigation results are available only through the WCP application. We currently tightly bind WCP into our commercially procured laboratory management system and make WCP the only way of viewing those data, allowing other applications to open a separate frame in a web browser “stapling” functionality together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my schematic of the architecture of a more “open”  test requesting and results service:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/platform/platform-lab.png&quot; alt=&quot;Platform Lab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here WCP is but one view on the &lt;em&gt;same data&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;same services&lt;/em&gt;. Unfortunately, there are some people that think that embedding different parts of an application within another at the user-interface level, using technology such as frames is a better approach. Importantly, such an approach does not expose the underlying data and so fails to support the use of those underlying data in any innovative manner and thus fails to appreciate the importance of data analytics for supporting clinical decision making for an individual patient, managing our clinical services for groups of patients or for research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The laboratory information management system (LIMS) is provided by Intersystems (Trakcare) and we should replicate that data source in a vendor-neutral archive (VNA) that is exposed to client software via a standardised application programming interface (API). This abstraction is an important tool in making commercial systems a &lt;em&gt;commodity&lt;/em&gt;. Commoditisation of components of an open platform is a vital step in reducing vendor lock-in and focusing on what is important; our data and its intrinsic value rather than a product. In this schematic, the VNA is represented by the “results archival service”. Now if TrakCare exposed a standardised API, for example using HL7 FHIR, then it may be that API could be used by the service layer. But the important lesson is that &lt;em&gt;it doesn’t matter&lt;/em&gt;, because we’ve abstracted the service. Indeed, the same approach would work if we were trying to provide a unified set of results across multiple laboratories all using different laboratory systems, so long as we built a VNA and carefully managed patient identity between different instances. Indeed, our laboratory colleagues could completely change their systems and our application software &lt;em&gt;does not even need to be aware&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our business logic is codified at the &lt;em&gt;service level&lt;/em&gt; and not the application level and, to manage changes in business processes and clinical need, many of the rules that underpin that business logic should be delegated to a rules engine, which allows business rules to be recorded dynamically in a declarative and not procedural fashion in the language of the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve previously discussed the importance of &lt;em&gt;scope&lt;/em&gt;; starting with our problem and broadening the scope to create generic solutions. However, that doesn’t mean that we have to build everything in one step. Instead, if we get the architecture right at the beginning, we can offer a laboratory test requesting and results service and then extend the platform to also support radiology requesting and reported as well. The schematic shows this evolution, with a FHIR test requesting service acting as a &lt;em&gt;concierge&lt;/em&gt;-type service, taking a request and delegating that request to the appropriate, now private, test service depending on the details of that request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The test requesting / results service would fit into the wider architecture like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/platform/platform-overall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Platform Overall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, a pipeline in which data is extracted, transformed and modelled ready for analytics is critical in ensuring that clinical information is made available at the right time to the right people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This “platform” shows the important components required by clinical applications, such as patient demography, user management (a user directory which for NHS Wales is a large Active Directory), logging and security, laboratory and radiology test requesting and results, clinical documents, structured clinical information including patient outcomes, electronic prescribing and reference data. HL7 FHIR supports presenting all of these types of data and services as a RESTful API already. As a result, legacy services would require either a FHIR facade to wrap and map that existing service or a method to replicate information to a VNA that exposed that information in a standardised way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An application written for such a platform, using FHIR end-points to make use of data and services provided by that platform, can potentially be deployed in any environment which provides similar services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-balancing-availability-and-privacy--consent&quot;&gt;2. Balancing availability and privacy = consent!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not difficult to imagine scaling an open platform across multiple organisations and enterprises much like the Internet has scaled so dramatically since its inception with patient data stored encrypted at rest and in transit by those organisations or their proxies and made available to others. The next logical step is to take that information and &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information.html&quot;&gt;“make it universally accessible and useful.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is an important paradox here: we want to increase information sharing and yet preserving privacy and confidentiality for that health information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, healthcare information technology must consider the use of privacy-enhancing technologies in order to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allow safe and secure information sharing between multiple organisations, professionals, sectors and the patient&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;give patients the tools required in order to control when and how their information is shared&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provide a distributed, verifiable infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support a range of mobile devices used by patients and staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;maintain the privacy of both patients and staff when mobile devices are ubiquitous.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patients must have trust that their private and confidential information is secure and yet want that same information available when it is required. As a result, information systems and the way that they are connected must be &lt;em&gt;secure-by-design&lt;/em&gt;, with security and transparency built-in as a result of the architecture and networking protocols. Layered upon this infrastructure must be mechanisms to capture patient consent. A &lt;em&gt;private-by-design&lt;/em&gt; networking layer would need to implement and support a range of services including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cross-organisational identity, for both patient and professionals as well as other parties such as carers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;multiple pseudo-identities, in which identity may be obfuscated for a particular use to prevent linkage beyond what is permitted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;commoditising semantic interoperability and data standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;decoupling of logical systems, including `patient portals’ so that patients not only can choose a provider themselves but then use that portal to communicate and interact with multiple decentralised services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;networking that does not leak information as a result of analysis of the traffic within it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support for innovation, trust and verifiability with `sandboxing’ for health applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my final assertion is that HL7 FHIR is only a component of a wider health informatics strategy. We must consider how to create a &lt;em&gt;single patient record&lt;/em&gt;, with information about a single individual made available at the right time and right place when approved by that individual. Fundamentally, this is predicated upon systems to manage &lt;em&gt;identity and patient consent&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we rely on applications and third-party services to double-check that they have consent or is it possible to build that consent into the architecture itself as part of how applications and services locate and use resources about that patient? I think the best way of handling this is the use of multiple pseudo-identities which can be linked or unlinked into an aggregated view of a &lt;em&gt;single patient record&lt;/em&gt;. In essence, we don’t want to rely on software to have to check whether it can access patient data but instead not even know that data exists or where to find it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, another definition of a “platform” is a set of services that bring together users and providers to form a multisided market. Is it possible then to take our “open platform” and start to think of a future in which we have products and services that actually do enable a re-imagining of healthcare provision to bring together patients, carers, health professionals, commissioners, analytics, researchers and all other stakeholders in a safe and secure manner?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;secure-by-design-sandboxing-services-and-applications&quot;&gt;Secure-by-design: sandboxing services and applications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One practical way of considering the problem is to consider how to permit innovation in a safe and secure way and have successful work quickly scaled out across and between organisations. For example, if a new startup company can create tools to automatically identify and monitor patients on drugs such as methotrexate and ensure that they have the required blood tests, how could such tools be deployed safely with certainty as to how, when and why that information was processed with support for an opt-out should a patient not agree to their information being used for that purpose? Can an infrastructure be created that means such applications can be installed in essentially a `sandbox’ in which its interactions with patient data are controlled and monitored automatically? Could that paradigm scale to support access to health data in a generic fashion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applications running on Apple’s iOS provide a useful analogy. In order to gain access to components of the underlying device and its operating system, such as the camera, the photo archive, location services etc, the application must use the appropriate API which forces explicit user consent. This “sandbox” environment means that an application is prevented from accessing resources to which consent has not been provided and presumably can log each and every attempt should that be required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can we do the same for health applications and services? It seems to me that we can create tremendous value from healthcare data - for patients, for health professionals and for society - but the foundation must be to allow that information to be organised in such a way that we can make it “universally accessible and useful” &lt;em&gt;subject to individual consent&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started writing a version of this post back in June, Estonia had just announced its plans for its EU presidency to include the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eu2017.ee/sites/default/files/2017-06/EU2017EE\%20Programme_0.pdf&quot;&gt;cross-border movement of health data for the purposes of treatment, research and innovation and to promote data-based innovation in healthcare&lt;/a&gt;. Creating secure platforms on which such communications can operate would be a pre-requisite for those aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-next&quot;&gt;So what next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that there are several important strands of work, most of which require health organisations and technology companies to work together to use technology as an enabler for the transformation of healthcare:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;work together on joint data standards and both technical and semantic interoperability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;build open platforms to bring together meaningful structured clinical information with data from legacy applications, adopting open standards such as HL7 FHIR and openEHR.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transform healthcare IT procurement moving away from capital “product”-based procurements to recurring expenditure models based on services ensuring that such procurements are measured against interoperability standards. Procure “products” only when truly contributing to or enabling a larger platform within and potentially between organisations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;break-down hierarchical autocratic organisations, and instead create highly functionally integrated teams combining skills from multiple disciplines who can take responsibility for achieving their goals; similarly, with such teams we should not be afraid of in-house development work when appropriate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;explore ways of turning unstructured information into usable and valuable data to explore clinical phenotypes, identify cohorts and use real-life outcome data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;look to improve the routine real-time use of analytics in healthcare for patient care and service improvement; if we can’t do simple survival curves in real-time for patients having emergency surgery in the last 30 days stratified by age, gender and co-morbidities, then we won’t be able to adopt more sophisticated analytics based on deep learning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consider picking niche specialist “vertical” markets such as long-term health conditions, in order to innovate and iterate before taking the lessons learnt to a wider audience.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take a 5-year (long-term) view and work on applying innovative technology (that probably exists today but just needs combining in interesting ways) into healthcare to support a secure, privacy-enhancing distributed patient record that engenders public and agency trust. I think it has something to do with a high-level abstraction of a distributed patient record, with multiple pseudo-identities bound together by consent with verifiable audit logs and service discovery based on that consent security model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why should a technology company be interested in building such an open platform? Because, like the Internet, it will be an enabler and create value for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html&quot;&gt;Domain-driven design in clinical informatics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information.html&quot;&gt;Organise healthcare information and make it universally accessible and useful&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/hazards-of-paper.html&quot;&gt;The hazards of paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;snomed&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;: Actually, don’t do that, as I’m already working on this using my SNOMED-CT service  (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.github.com/wardle/rsterminology&quot;&gt;rsterminology&lt;/a&gt;) and using Google Cloud’s NLP API to identify entities within the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;getting-sacked&quot;&gt;b&lt;/a&gt;: And hopefully without being sacked in the process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I previously discussed three disruptive influences in healthcare in my previous blog post that, over the next five years, will disrupt both the provision of healthcare and the technological solutions currently used to support that care:</summary></entry></feed>