<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.wardle.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.wardle.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-08-20T22:42:52+02:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/</id><title type="html">Health informatics and information technology</title><subtitle>by Dr Mark Wardle, Consultant Neurologist, clinical informatics and software developer. Founder, Eldrix Ltd.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Disruptive influences in healthcare: the future</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Disruptive influences in healthcare: the future" /><published>2017-08-20T11:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-08-20T11:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html">&lt;p&gt;I previously discussed &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;three disruptive influences in healthcare in my previous blog post&lt;/a&gt; that, over the next five years, will disrupt both the provision of healthcare and the technological solutions currently used to support that care:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changes in the models of care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patients as active participants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘Hospitals without walls’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And subsequently, I tried to &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/11/disruptive-influences-current.html&quot;&gt;give an overview of how current strategies used by health services and commercial companies will struggle to meet those disruptions&lt;/a&gt;, principally as a result of a focus on single organisations and enterprises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to draw these strands together in one place and hopefully provide some important context for some of my other blog posts. In my view, the two planks of work to form the foundation of our work are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An “open decentralised platform” for healthcare made up of multiple standards-based interoperable services and data repositories.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A single distributed logical patient record made up of multiple shards connected with multiple pseudo-identities wrapped in a consent model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, we need the right structures in place to allow us &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information.html&quot;&gt;“to organise healthcare and patient information and make it universally accessible and useful.”&lt;/a&gt; We need to be much more ambitious and yet plan to iterate to get to that future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-open-platforms-in-health&quot;&gt;1. Open platforms in health&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, administrative and clinical information relating to patients must be made more widely available outside of closed networks and across disciplines, services, organisations and sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, we must discuss the “open platform” approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Internet is one example of an “open platform”, in which open standards result in an open network in which many different software applications and devices can be connected and exchange information. One important consequence of an “open platform” is its use for applications not originally considered by its designers. For example, TCP/IP, the networking protocol that underpins the Internet handles, in a generic way, the low-level handling of bundles of data (messages) between computer systems. This open technical architecture was used as the foundation of the HTTP protocol, although other protocols such as Gopher were also built using TCP/IP as a foundation. This is an example of a &lt;em&gt;layered architecture&lt;/em&gt; in which an open platform, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://technet.microsoft.com/en-gb/library/cc958821.aspx&quot;&gt;“Open Systems Interconnection (OSI) model”&lt;/a&gt; is made up of multiple layers in which scope and function are well defined. Importantly, each subsequent layer usually provides a higher-level of abstraction from the detail. Low-levels of the OSI platform handle the physical connectivity and nitty-gritty details of networking such as data exchange and acknowledgements of transfer. Higher-levels allow software to ignore these low levels of networking management and simply exchange information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Internet has made information of all types universally accessible, useful and searchable and most of us now do this on mobile devices we carry with us all of the time. We now carry around practically unlimited computing resources in our pockets, so why can we not do that in healthcare?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;why-an-open-platform&quot;&gt;Why an open platform?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does the “open platform” matter in healthcare? I have &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/11/disruptive-influences-current.html&quot;&gt;touched on the problems previously&lt;/a&gt;. Essentially, healthcare informatics has been dominated by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a focus on administrative functionality rather than prioritising clinical care and the patient.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;large commercial vendors with closed systems and little or no interoperability.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a focus on the procurement of “products” based on &lt;em&gt;features&lt;/em&gt; on a capital expenditure basis with old-fashioned project plans built using a waterfall methodology with start and completion dates and little or no concept of iterative improvement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;organisations that are hierarchical and autocratic, designed to funnel information upwards and decisions made by those at the top flowing downwards. In essence, such structures have arisen as a result of trying to manage risk; when one considers large multi-million pound procurements, one must attempt to slow down decision making and reduce the risk of a bad decision&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;organisations that are risk-averse and fail slowly like a car crash in slow motion, rather than failing fast and learning from those failures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, how do we create the right structures that lower risk and allow more rapid iterative development?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer that, we must ask… what is our goal?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open platform is simply the foundation for a longer and much more ambitious journey in healthcare information technology. It is so important to have a vision for a future in 5 or 10 years; we are certain to be wrong, but having ambitious goals &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; understanding that we’re going to have to change some of our plans; probably the details of some of the steps used to get there; but we won’t be changing the the direction of travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So… shouldn’t our goal be to provide the right structures and technology to create high-quality, valuable user-centric applications that can help solve clinical problems, with the “user” being a patient or a professional or other worker involved in care. Don’t we want those applications running &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt; so that we can start work on the next generation of clinical applications. We want to understand our patients and have ready access to tools that support our teams in providing care for patients. Iteration is the key; we will never be finished and there will always be more to do. How can we enable that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve previously described user-facing applications as ideally being “almost throwaway” in our team meetings here in Wales and such statements have sometimes resulted in looks of incredulity. However, describing applications as “throwaway” simply reflects the following logical chain of reasoning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You say I can write clinical applications are “almost throwaway”?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Therefore, the engineering work must be quite straightforward, because I’m a lazy engineer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;But surely there is a tonne of clever engineering work needed in healthcare, such as managing users, managing access, looking at patients, managing consent, access logs, getting and storing complex medical information and understanding the status of a variety of healthcare resources?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ah! The clever stuff must be already be provided elsewhere!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;So, can you show me the API endpoints and documentation?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logical conclusion is therefore that we strive for an open platform in which applications coordinate and leverage multiple services provided within the platform; applications are the conductors for our orchestra of services. I expect some core services that are initially, mainly enterprise-bound, provided by individual organisations so that a single application can be deployed with little change between and across multiple those organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, with time, I’d expect to see a marketplace of increasingly sophisticated “services” that are provided outside of the scope of individual organisations, many provided by commercial vendors, in which sophisticated additional functionality can be made available on a cost per-use basis. Over time, the functionality of “the platform” extends upwards into &lt;em&gt;the cloud&lt;/em&gt; increasingly combining traditional data from organisations with new forms of patient-reported, patient-recorded real-life data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are already seeing the commercialisation of services like that in other sectors, with Google Cloud Functions and Amazon AWS lambda services providing serverless and maintenance free deployment and scaling of discrete pieces of logic. When are we going to do this for healthcare? Who’ll be first to offer a natural language processing API that takes a legacy clinical document and turns it into a structured document together with mapping to SNOMED-CT for £0.0001 per document? &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#snomed&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, I see an “open platform” as stage one of a larger plan, but how do we get started?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-is-an-open-platform&quot;&gt;What is an open platform?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been discussing strategy at length within NHS Wales and continue to have a fierce debate about the best way of using limited resources in the most valuable way. Perhaps reasonably, there are some who think we should be concentrating our limited resources on a single all-Wales application, the Welsh Clinical  Portal (WCP). I will not cover that debate here, but I feel strongly that a focus on an application is a &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;poor way of meeting both present and future challenges&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I hope, instead, to influence the national strategy in favour of a platform approach.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#getting-sacked&quot;&gt;b&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; For example, at the moment, laboratory and radiology investigation results are available only through the WCP application. We currently tightly bind WCP into our commercially procured laboratory management system and make WCP the only way of viewing those data, allowing other applications to open a separate frame in a web browser “stapling” functionality together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my schematic of the architecture of a more “open”  test requesting and results service:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/platform/platform-lab.png&quot; alt=&quot;Platform Lab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here WCP is but one view on the &lt;em&gt;same data&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;same services&lt;/em&gt;. Unfortunately, there are some people that think that embedding different parts of an application within another at the user-interface level, using technology such as frames is a better approach. Importantly, such an approach does not expose the underlying data and so fails to support the use of those underlying data in any innovative manner and thus fails to appreciate the importance of data analytics for supporting clinical decision making for an individual patient, managing our clinical services for groups of patients or for research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The laboratory information management system (LIMS) is provided by Intersystems (Trakcare) and we should replicate that data source in a vendor-neutral archive (VNA) that is exposed to client software via a standardised application programming interface (API). This abstraction is an important tool in making commercial systems a &lt;em&gt;commodity&lt;/em&gt;. Commoditisation of components of an open platform is a vital step in reducing vendor lock-in and focusing on what is important; our data and its intrinsic value rather than a product. In this schematic, the VNA is represented by the “results archival service”. Now if TrakCare exposed a standardised API, for example using HL7 FHIR, then it may be that API could be used by the service layer. But the important lesson is that &lt;em&gt;it doesn’t matter&lt;/em&gt;, because we’ve abstracted the service. Indeed, the same approach would work if we were trying to provide a unified set of results across multiple laboratories all using different laboratory systems, so long as we built a VNA and carefully managed patient identity between different instances. Indeed, our laboratory colleagues could completely change their systems and our application software &lt;em&gt;does not even need to be aware&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our business logic is codified at the &lt;em&gt;service level&lt;/em&gt; and not the application level and, to manage changes in business processes and clinical need, many of the rules that underpin that business logic should be delegated to a rules engine, which allows business rules to be recorded dynamically in a declarative and not procedural fashion in the language of the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve previously discussed the importance of &lt;em&gt;scope&lt;/em&gt;; starting with our problem and broadening the scope to create generic solutions. However, that doesn’t mean that we have to build everything in one step. Instead, if we get the architecture right at the beginning, we can offer a laboratory test requesting and results service and then extend the platform to also support radiology requesting and reported as well. The schematic shows this evolution, with a FHIR test requesting service acting as a &lt;em&gt;concierge&lt;/em&gt;-type service, taking a request and delegating that request to the appropriate, now private, test service depending on the details of that request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The test requesting / results service would fit into the wider architecture like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/platform/platform-overall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Platform Overall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, a pipeline in which data is extracted, transformed and modelled ready for analytics is critical in ensuring that clinical information is made available at the right time to the right people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This “platform” shows the important components required by clinical applications, such as patient demography, user management (a user directory which for NHS Wales is a large Active Directory), logging and security, laboratory and radiology test requesting and results, clinical documents, structured clinical information including patient outcomes, electronic prescribing and reference data. HL7 FHIR supports presenting all of these types of data and services as a RESTful API already. As a result, legacy services would require either a FHIR facade to wrap and map that existing service or a method to replicate information to a VNA that exposed that information in a standardised way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An application written for such a platform, using FHIR end-points to make use of data and services provided by that platform, can potentially be deployed in any environment which provides similar services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-balancing-availability-and-privacy--consent&quot;&gt;2. Balancing availability and privacy = consent!&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not difficult to imagine scaling an open platform across multiple organisations and enterprises much like the Internet has scaled so dramatically since its inception with patient data stored encrypted at rest and in transit by those organisations or their proxies and made available to others. The next logical step is to take that information and &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information.html&quot;&gt;“make it universally accessible and useful.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is an important paradox here: we want to increase information sharing and yet preserving privacy and confidentiality for that health information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, healthcare information technology must consider the use of privacy-enhancing technologies in order to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;allow safe and secure information sharing between multiple organisations, professionals, sectors and the patient&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;give patients the tools required in order to control when and how their information is shared&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;provide a distributed, verifiable infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support a range of mobile devices used by patients and staff&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;maintain the privacy of both patients and staff when mobile devices are ubiquitous.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patients must have trust that their private and confidential information is secure and yet want that same information available when it is required. As a result, information systems and the way that they are connected must be &lt;em&gt;secure-by-design&lt;/em&gt;, with security and transparency built-in as a result of the architecture and networking protocols. Layered upon this infrastructure must be mechanisms to capture patient consent. A &lt;em&gt;private-by-design&lt;/em&gt; networking layer would need to implement and support a range of services including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cross-organisational identity, for both patient and professionals as well as other parties such as carers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;multiple pseudo-identities, in which identity may be obfuscated for a particular use to prevent linkage beyond what is permitted.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;commoditising semantic interoperability and data standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;decoupling of logical systems, including `patient portals’ so that patients not only can choose a provider themselves but then use that portal to communicate and interact with multiple decentralised services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;networking that does not leak information as a result of analysis of the traffic within it.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support for innovation, trust and verifiability with `sandboxing’ for health applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So my final assertion is that HL7 FHIR is only a component of a wider health informatics strategy. We must consider how to create a &lt;em&gt;single patient record&lt;/em&gt;, with information about a single individual made available at the right time and right place when approved by that individual. Fundamentally, this is predicated upon systems to manage &lt;em&gt;identity and patient consent&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do we rely on applications and third-party services to double-check that they have consent or is it possible to build that consent into the architecture itself as part of how applications and services locate and use resources about that patient? I think the best way of handling this is the use of multiple pseudo-identities which can be linked or unlinked into an aggregated view of a &lt;em&gt;single patient record&lt;/em&gt;. In essence, we don’t want to rely on software to have to check whether it can access patient data but instead not even know that data exists or where to find it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, another definition of a “platform” is a set of services that bring together users and providers to form a multisided market. Is it possible then to take our “open platform” and start to think of a future in which we have products and services that actually do enable a re-imagining of healthcare provision to bring together patients, carers, health professionals, commissioners, analytics, researchers and all other stakeholders in a safe and secure manner?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;secure-by-design-sandboxing-services-and-applications&quot;&gt;Secure-by-design: sandboxing services and applications&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One practical way of considering the problem is to consider how to permit innovation in a safe and secure way and have successful work quickly scaled out across and between organisations. For example, if a new startup company can create tools to automatically identify and monitor patients on drugs such as methotrexate and ensure that they have the required blood tests, how could such tools be deployed safely with certainty as to how, when and why that information was processed with support for an opt-out should a patient not agree to their information being used for that purpose? Can an infrastructure be created that means such applications can be installed in essentially a `sandbox’ in which its interactions with patient data are controlled and monitored automatically? Could that paradigm scale to support access to health data in a generic fashion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applications running on Apple’s iOS provide a useful analogy. In order to gain access to components of the underlying device and its operating system, such as the camera, the photo archive, location services etc, the application must use the appropriate API which forces explicit user consent. This “sandbox” environment means that an application is prevented from accessing resources to which consent has not been provided and presumably can log each and every attempt should that be required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can we do the same for health applications and services? It seems to me that we can create tremendous value from healthcare data - for patients, for health professionals and for society - but the foundation must be to allow that information to be organised in such a way that we can make it “universally accessible and useful” &lt;em&gt;subject to individual consent&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I started writing a version of this post back in June, Estonia had just announced its plans for its EU presidency to include the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eu2017.ee/sites/default/files/2017-06/EU2017EE\%20Programme_0.pdf&quot;&gt;cross-border movement of health data for the purposes of treatment, research and innovation and to promote data-based innovation in healthcare&lt;/a&gt;. Creating secure platforms on which such communications can operate would be a pre-requisite for those aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-next&quot;&gt;So what next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that there are several important strands of work, most of which require health organisations and technology companies to work together to use technology as an enabler for the transformation of healthcare:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;work together on joint data standards and both technical and semantic interoperability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;build open platforms to bring together meaningful structured clinical information with data from legacy applications, adopting open standards such as HL7 FHIR and openEHR.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;transform healthcare IT procurement moving away from capital “product”-based procurements to recurring expenditure models based on services ensuring that such procurements are measured against interoperability standards. Procure “products” only when truly contributing to or enabling a larger platform within and potentially between organisations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;break-down hierarchical autocratic organisations, and instead create highly functionally integrated teams combining skills from multiple disciplines who can take responsibility for achieving their goals; similarly, with such teams we should not be afraid of in-house development work when appropriate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;explore ways of turning unstructured information into usable and valuable data to explore clinical phenotypes, identify cohorts and use real-life outcome data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;look to improve the routine real-time use of analytics in healthcare for patient care and service improvement; if we can’t do simple survival curves in real-time for patients having emergency surgery in the last 30 days stratified by age, gender and co-morbidities, then we won’t be able to adopt more sophisticated analytics based on deep learning.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;consider picking niche specialist “vertical” markets such as long-term health conditions, in order to innovate and iterate before taking the lessons learnt to a wider audience.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take a 5-year (long-term) view and work on applying innovative technology (that probably exists today but just needs combining in interesting ways) into healthcare to support a secure, privacy-enhancing distributed patient record that engenders public and agency trust. I think it has something to do with a high-level abstraction of a distributed patient record, with multiple pseudo-identities bound together by consent with verifiable audit logs and service discovery based on that consent security model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why should a technology company be interested in building such an open platform? Because, like the Internet, it will be an enabler and create value for years to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html&quot;&gt;Domain-driven design in clinical informatics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information.html&quot;&gt;Organise healthcare information and make it universally accessible and useful&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/hazards-of-paper.html&quot;&gt;The hazards of paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;snomed&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;: Actually, don’t do that, as I’m already working on this using my SNOMED-CT service  (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.github.com/wardle/rsterminology&quot;&gt;rsterminology&lt;/a&gt;) and using Google Cloud’s NLP API to identify entities within the text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;getting-sacked&quot;&gt;b&lt;/a&gt;: And hopefully without being sacked in the process.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I previously discussed three disruptive influences in healthcare in my previous blog post that, over the next five years, will disrupt both the provision of healthcare and the technological solutions currently used to support that care:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Disruptive influences in healthcare: current solutions</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/07/11/disruptive-influences-current.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Disruptive influences in healthcare: current solutions" /><published>2017-07-11T22:59:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-11T22:59:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/07/11/disruptive-influences-current</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/07/11/disruptive-influences-current.html">&lt;p&gt;In my previous blog post, I discussed &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;three core disruptive influences&lt;/a&gt; that must be considered when designing the architecture of clinical information systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three disruptive influences are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changes in the models of care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patients as active participants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘Hospitals without walls’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I discuss the current landscape with healthcare information technology and how current products have evolved to deal with these disruptions as well as their deficiencies. My &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html&quot;&gt;third post discusses an open future&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;current-solutions-and-their-problems&quot;&gt;Current solutions and their problems&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A number of strategies have already been adopted to deal with these disruptive influences:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enterprise-wide clinical information systems hosted by organisations to provide clinical record keeping as well as administrative functionality.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Research portals and registries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patient portals to allow patients to view and contribute to their record -  “personal health records”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patient-facing mobile device applications to allow recruitment into research.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Organisation-by-organisation procurement and data sharing agreements with commercial entities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;monolithic-organisation-specific-systems&quot;&gt;Monolithic organisation-specific systems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computer software deployed within healthcare has traditionally been procured and hosted by the organisation in which it is used. Many health organisations in the United Kingdom (UK) have closed networks in which desktop computers are wired into the network and run a mixture of different types of software with file-based network storage. More recent deployments of electronic patient record (EPR) systems such as Cerner’s Millenium and Epic within the UK have repeated this historic approach centred on an organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an architecture benefits that organisation in meeting its statutory duty to care for patients, combining administrative and clinical data. In the United States, where these products were designed, that combination permits item-level billing and as a result they are integral to business operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this type of architecture is less suitable for cross-organisational working in which multiple disparate teams of health professionals and the patient collaborate. Such an architecture means that community teams, for example, might need to be registered directly as users on any systems in which data on their may reside to permit interaction with other professionals involved in a patient’s care. As a result, professionals may need to switch between applications in order to view a complete record. Similarly, single organisation-bound systems do not easily support sharing information between organisations so that information relating to a patient presenting as an emergency when on holiday to a different facility may not be readily available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, solutions to cross-organisational working adopt a health-information exchange (HIE) model in which information from multiple organisations, typically within a defined geographical region, exchange information. Commercial companies are now increasingly adopting data standards to try to provide semantic interoperability, and it is likely that their products will transform to a ``platform’’ on which other applications can run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several important initiatives encouraging and supporting semantic and technical interoperability:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apperta foundation: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apperta.org&quot;&gt;http://www.apperta.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;INTEROPen &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.interopen.org&quot;&gt;http://www.interopen.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HL7 FHIR: CareConnect profiles (UK): &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/HL7-UK/CareConnect-profiles&quot;&gt;https://github.com/HL7-UK/CareConnect-profiles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;openEHR: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openehr.org&quot;&gt;http://www.openehr.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;SNOMED-CT: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.snomed.org/snomed-ct&quot;&gt;http://www.snomed.org/snomed-ct&lt;/a&gt;, browser: &lt;a href=&quot;http://browser.ihtsdotools.org&quot;&gt;http://browser.ihtsdotools.org&lt;/a&gt;, my blog posts: &lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org&quot;&gt;http://wardle.org&lt;/a&gt; such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/02/future-hospital-snomed-ct.html&quot;&gt;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/02/future-hospital-snomed-ct.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current focus is therefore on increasing interoperability at an organisation level, or between organisations within a defined geographic region (such as the Great North Care Record).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;patient-portals&quot;&gt;Patient portals&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current solution to giving patients access to their records is a secure `patient portal’, or multiple portals providing different functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While `patient portals’ may  allow patients to communicate with their teams, see their results and contribute data to their records, such portals are frequently tied a single organisation or service. For example, Cerner offer a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cerner.com/solutions/hospitals_and_health_systems/patient_portal/?langtype=2057&quot;&gt;proprietary patient portal&lt;/a&gt; which is linked with its own EPR. Even when patient portals are not tied to a single health organisation such as with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patientsknowbest.com&quot;&gt;‘Patients Know Best’ (PKB)&lt;/a&gt; an organisation must have signed up to use that provider in order to allow a patient to interact with them via that portal. In Wales, there is a patient portal available for certain GP surgeries providing functionality for booking appointments but this is not universal and there is a separate portal for the recording of patient reported outcome measures, the results of which are not made available in clinicians. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthwisewales.gov.wales/homepage/&quot;&gt;Healthwise Wales&lt;/a&gt; programme is a separate portal that allows the population of Wales to register for a research project on wellbeing and health, but it does not integrate with or support the enrolment into any other research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, the choice of patient portals is by the organisation and not the patient, who may wish to interact with multiple providers of healthcare and flag their interest in multiple research projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, how can a patient interact with all of their disparate health services across multiple organisations? Do we expect our patients to use multiple portals depending on whether they are visiting the Royal Free or the Royal London Hospital?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, patients with specific needs, such as those who do not have a fixed address, or those requiring communication via braille or spoken text, must hope that a single provider supports those needs. What if a patient cannot manage appointments themselves, but has a proxy who needs to be involved in their care, such as a nursing home resident?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;research-portals-and-registries&quot;&gt;Research portals and registries&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clinical research has traditionally focused on recording longitudinal patient outcomes in well-defined cohorts of patients recruited as part of observation or interventional trials. As a result, there are now many different research registries which are usually disease or specialty-specific. I have written about the &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/06/using-data-patient-safety.html&quot;&gt;disadvantages of registries before&lt;/a&gt;, but essentially they don’t really support clinical practice. The main problems are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there are lots of them, so potentially lots of disparate systems (they are not joined up)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they are not embedded in day-to-day workflow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is sometimes little feedback, result or reward, particularly in any timely manner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;patient-consent&quot;&gt;Patient consent&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current mainstream solution for clinical research is direct recruitment by clinicians in their clinical practice or via advertising in newsletters of third-party charitable organisations. However, technology such as Apple’s ResearchKit provides a simple framework for research teams to build trivial mobile device applications to allow patients to sign up themselves, consent and then take part in any necessary data capture for clinical research. As a result, patients can be recruited in large numbers for a single project. As an example, see the mPower study on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/articles/sdata201611&quot;&gt;Parkinson’s disease published in Nature&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A limitation of these approaches is that research data are typically collected separately from routinely collected clinical data. Historically, this has not had any significant drawback due to a lack of routinely collected clinical data that would actually be usable for clinical research. However, given the other disruptive changes in healthcare, it is likely that structured longitudinal data will be increasingly available from systematic collection in clinical practice. Much like the failed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/speeches/review-of-health-and-care-data-security-and-consent&quot;&gt;‘care.data’ project&lt;/a&gt;, such data would need to be combined with multiple other disparate sources of information and as a result, patients must be given appropriate tools to understand and control the use of their information. Importantly however, a record of consent must take care to not divulge personal information as a result of its existence. Just as in email communications, if information relating to a withdrawal of consent of a patient from a HIV project is made available, then confidential information is leaked. Thus, a patient’s current and historic opt-in or opt-out choices must be made available so those choices can be enforced and yet remain private.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;organisation-by-organisation-procurement-and-data-sharing-agreements&quot;&gt;Organisation-by-organisation procurement and data sharing agreements&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most innovative healthcare information technology solutions must still be procured by organisations and then deployed. As a result, a commercial entity acts on behalf of that health organisation and, if data are transferred, formal data sharing agreements signed. For small and medium sized enterprises, procurement processes are long, complex and expensive and traditionally have favoured larger, more established companies over smaller companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, procuring an established, ‘proven’ solution is perceived as lower in risk than collaborating with a small or medium-sized enterprise in a development partnership. Procurement rules frequently require levels of insurance, financial and regulatory backing that make it more difficult for new enterprises to deploy and scale innovation with the health system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How then to balance innovation and governance? Unfortunately, there are many examples of innovative projects that are closed down as a result of a loss of trust in the governance of private and confidential medical information. For example, the `care.data’ project aimed to combine multiple large scale datasets together across multiple organisations in order to support population health research within England, but controversy resulted in its closure. Similarly, Google DeepMind’s project to provide a smartphone clinical application (Streams) to clinicians at the Royal Free has been mired in controversy with negative press reports and a referral from the National Data Guardian to the Information Commissioner’s Office (ICO) and a formal ruling pending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such debacles result in a perception of wrongdoing even if no information was shared inappropriately and risk the deployment of innovative technologies in the future Unfortunately, few commentators note the consequences of &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; deploying modern technology in order to support healthcare or indeed note the gap between where we should be and where we current stand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, existing technology focuses on an organisation, a specialty or a specific project. In essence, the digitisation has followed existing paper-based processes instead of using technology to underpin transforming our healthcare services around the patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have read my other blog posts, you will already know the answers to the problems posed in this and the previous post; we need to focus on a data-driven standards-based “platform” consisting of multiple well-defined services working together to create vendor-neutral archives of immutable clinical information in structured formats. My &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html&quot;&gt;next post&lt;/a&gt; covers the components of this platform in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In my previous blog post, I discussed three core disruptive influences that must be considered when designing the architecture of clinical information systems.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Disruptive influences in healthcare</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Disruptive influences in healthcare" /><published>2017-07-07T22:59:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-07-07T22:59:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html">&lt;p&gt;Healthcare has traditionally been conservative in its adoption of new technologies. Many clinicians still routinely use pen and paper to record medical information during a face-to-face encounter with a patient on the ward or in the clinic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information technology was first adopted in order to manage the administrative running of hospitals such as appointment scheduling and tracking the location of paper records. Traditionally, there has been a separation of these patient administrative systems (PAS) from clinical systems used by health professionals, even if such systems were available.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#patient-safety&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are a number of transformative and disruptive influences in health that, together with new technology, are driving and will continue to drive new ways of working. I’ve grouped these influences into three broad related categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changes in the models of care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patients as active participants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘Hospitals without walls’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;changes-in-the-models-of-care&quot;&gt;Changes in the models of care&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first group of transformative influences relate to the changing way in which healthcare is provided, primarily as a result of changing working practices, a need for safe and secure channels of communication between the patient and multi-disciplinary teams from different organisations and different sectors and a focus on measures of outcome and not process. Such changes are particularly relevant to an ageing population with individuals living longer with multiple long-term health conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;changes-in-how-patients-experience-their-care&quot;&gt;Changes in how patients experience their care&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The traditional approach to healthcare is based on face-to-face consultations with a primary care physician in a community-based facility, an outpatient clinic with a specialist in a hospital or an unscheduled or scheduled stay within that hospital for a medical emergency or an elective procedure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a consequence of this model, patients with diabetes mellitus used to be called for specialist outpatient review every 3-months and care would be provided by a fragmented patchwork with little or no overall coordination between services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A modern approach to healthcare requires support for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Management of multiple long-term health conditions requiring multi-disciplinary teamwork, cross-organisation care coordination as well as involvement of non-health partners such as social care and the third-sector when appropriate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shared care between teams with remote monitoring using modern technology.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Avoidance of ‘information silos’ that would usually result in information not being available at the right time or place for clinical decision making. Information should follow the patient and not be fixed in the organisation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, a patient with diabetes mellitus should now be able to monitor their disease themselves with support from community teams including the general practitioner who can call upon a range of specialist services for specific complications or surveillance. Rather than a patient being screened for retinopathy (a complication of diabetes mellitus) in a clinic by an inexperienced junior doctor, they are called to a dedicated diabetic retinopathy screening programme with retinal photography and the results made available to all others in the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;changes-in-how-we-measure-care&quot;&gt;Changes in how we measure care&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important parallel change has been a focus on health outcomes rather than assessing services according to simply how many patients are seen or how many have a procedure. A focus on outcomes permits services to judge whether an intervention such as a knee replacement, actually improves outcomes in groups of patients with similar characteristics to yours. By analysing aggregated outcomes for groups of patients, we can modify our services to achieve the best outcome for patients and benchmark local services with those from elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changing our practice to consider outcomes requires an infrastructure that allows the routine and systematic capture of structured clinical data before and after by both clinicians and patients. Outcomes may be based on questionnaires but can just as easily be other outcomes such as return to work, number of steps walked per day, ability to exercise or managing to live independently in one’s home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;big-data&quot;&gt;“Big data”&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, we face a future in which we have ever increasing amounts of data on patients. Information sourced from multiple organisations, increasingly structured outcome data and information from technology worn by the patient or used in the home to monitor progress and health status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genomics is an important additional potential source of “big data”. Genomics provides genotype data which, when linked with phenotypic data (what the patient looks like), allows us to assess genotype-phenotype correlations. Such analysis allows us to understand the causes of disease and the modifiers that affect progression of disease or predict responsiveness to treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All such data is sensitive and it is in the &lt;em&gt;linkage&lt;/em&gt; of these datasets that is most important. While all medical information is confidential, it is &lt;em&gt;linkage&lt;/em&gt; that those of us who are interested in protected privacy should focus.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#linkage&quot;&gt;b&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;patients-as-active-participants&quot;&gt;Patients as active participants&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second group of transformative influences relate to a repositioning of a patient from a person unto which &lt;em&gt;care is performed&lt;/em&gt; to an &lt;em&gt;active and involved participant&lt;/em&gt; in their care, controlling their interactions and deciding how and with whom their information should be shared. Such a repositioning is necessary given the changes in models care care outlined above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of this paradigm shift, it becomes necessary to design our information systems around the patient and not our organisations. Instead of fragmented services being run using fragmented software, information technology is needed to support an approach in which the patient is at the centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, patients must be able to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;View and contribute to their own records.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Record their aims and objectives as well as their own outcomes for use in monitoring their problems and assessing the efficacy of any intervention.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Communicate with members of their healthcare teams as well as other professionals and volunteers who are involved in their care with those communications forming part of a longitudinal record.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Control how and what information is shared about them, including choosing to share their information for clinical research.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;communication-between-patients-and-their-services&quot;&gt;Communication between patients and their services&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Government Procurement Service (GPS) has estimated that the NHS in England spends £79 million each year on postal costs. While many patients do try to communicate with their healthcare teams via email, there are several problems that restrict its wider use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Current email is insecure with both content and metadata unencrypted with no way of proving identity. While cryptographic technologies are available, tools for signing and encrypting communications, such as ‘PGP’, are too difficult for most users to use routinely.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Email communications are not usually filed into medical records and so the record is not available to the wider team, unless printed and placed into paper records.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Even encrypted email communications leak confidential information by virtue of the metadata required to appropriately route those communications. For example, one can infer a relationship between a patient and the HIV clinic if they regularly communicate with hiv-clinic-cardiff@wales.nhs.uk even if the content of that communication is encrypted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Communication may be appointment letters, cancellations, clinical communications but also data from devices such as a video recorded of an epileptic seizure, a step-count from an ambulatory step-monitor or an implantable device monitoring heart rhythm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;consent&quot;&gt;Consent&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patient consent for information sharing may be implicit, in which, consent is assumed until a patient opts out, or explicit, in which a specific opt-in is required before information retrieval or processing can begin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, an opt-in model is required for patients to participate in clinical research. It is recognised that patients are keen to be involved in research but wish to be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/192572/2900774_InfoGovernance_accv2.pdf&quot;&gt;asked for their consent before their identifiable information is shared&lt;/a&gt;. However, that report also notes that “more could be done to increase awareness of the benefits of research”. As a result, intermediary brokering services are needed to allow patients to signify their interest in clinical research and permit them to subsequently be informed of &lt;em&gt;relevant&lt;/em&gt; research projects without divulging their private information. ‘Research brokers’ should match patients to projects and aim to maximise participation. To enable such functionality, private information such as diagnosis and treatments must be processed but via mechanisms that prevent the inappropriate use of that information for other purposes. A patient who opts-in to receive information about research suitable for them must (i) expect to have their information not used for any other purpose except brokering, and (ii) not be shown projects that are obviously unsuitable for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like Google connects users to advertisers, there is value in brokering connections between patients and researchers. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/05/20/using-snomed-ct.html&quot;&gt;use of SNOMED-CT as an ontology&lt;/a&gt; (algorithmically I can understand that ‘multiple sclerosis’ IS-A type of ‘demyelinating disease’ for example) can help to support such connections based on diagnosis, procedure or other facets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While simple brokering requires little more than matching on SNOMED-CT, how can more complex requirements be assessed such as, “patients with JME who have not yet had lamotrigine” -  how can allow a broker permit a third-party to check suitability without divulging identity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;hospitals-without-walls&quot;&gt;Hospitals without walls&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third group of transformative influences relate to the decentralisation and democratisation of healthcare enabled by new technologies. These technologies comprise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increasing availability of personal mobile devices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Increasing capability for smart home monitoring with an ‘internet of things’ in which multiple devices are connected together and combine to provide a unified view of a patient&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New commercial models of care, including advanced analytics, supported clinical decision making with applied machine learning for ‘artificial intelligence’.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;mobile-devices-home-monitoring-and-the-internet-of-things&quot;&gt;Mobile devices, home monitoring and the ‘internet of things’&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New technology means that patients can now increasingly receive their care and monitoring in their home using a range of medical grade devices. For example, implantable loop recorders can be inserted under the skin and, in the event of a cardiac event, the results sent wirelessly to the healthcare team. In addition, there is increasing acceptance of commodity consumer-grade devices, frequently marketed as fitness devices, in order to gain objective data on health outcomes in order to monitor a disease or to assess the effect of an intervention.  There are parallels with the technology used for video-conferencing in which professional, enterprise-grade devices installed in business are increasingly replaced with consumer-grade devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, there is now consumer-grade technology available to allow patients to obtain ongoing advice and care from a range of professionals from a range of organisations via electronic communication channels such as electronic mail or voice or video calls rather than attending for routine outpatient clinic appointments. Such communications need to be safe and secure, with guarantees about identity at both sides of the communication, with guarantees of non-repudiation and verifiability with an appropriate entry recorded contemporaneously in the medical record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, just as outlined above, data transfers from a patient and their devices to clinical services must be encrypted and be kept private with avoidance of information leakage. As a result, not only must the content of those transfers be encrypted but the metadata needed to describe and route those transfers must be kept private. For example, network traffic analysis may be able to identify all elderly frail patients living alone with dementia in a region simply by looking for specific types of electronic monitoring data streams in a similar way to being able to identify when a person leaves their house by eavesdropping on smart meter data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;innovation-data-sharing-and-analytics&quot;&gt;Innovation, data sharing and analytics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is significant potential benefit to the use of software within healthcare in order to improve outcomes, safety and efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such software might provide functionality to improve the care of a single patient, or might work across groups of patients to provide analysis of services and outcomes providing a view for clinicians and managers that combines data from multiple sources. In parallel, clinical users are now expecting to be able to use their own or the organisation’s mobile devices in order to work effectively when on the ward. Such applications support team-working, communication and alerts regarding patients under their care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The traditional approach has been to bring innovation ‘within the walls’ of health organisations which can work when procuring specific products from vendors in order to perform a specific task. However, this model is less suitable for products which provide services via ‘cloud computing’ in which large-scale computing power may be provided across the network. For example, if a commercial entity provided automated or computer-assisted interpretation of histological slides or radiology imaging to multiple organisations using the results of deep learning, that functionality may be better provided across a network rather than being installed within the server rooms of a health organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, the “hospitals-without-walls” trend requires a focus on the network with a mixed economy of core functionality upon which innovative applications can operate in secure sandboxes, in which data access and interactions can be monitored and controlled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/11/disruptive-influences-current.html&quot;&gt;next post discusses the current solutions&lt;/a&gt; already created in response to these disruptive influences. The &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html&quot;&gt;third post discusses how an open platform might better deal with these disrupting influences in the future&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;patient-safety&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;: For more information on the separation of administrative and clinical systems, see my &lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/06/using-data-patient-safety.html&quot;&gt;blog post on patient safety&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;linkage&quot;&gt;b&lt;/a&gt;: I’m not sure that everyone realises this.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Healthcare has traditionally been conservative in its adoption of new technologies. Many clinicians still routinely use pen and paper to record medical information during a face-to-face encounter with a patient on the ward or in the clinic.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Safely deploying machine learning in healthcare 2/2</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/machine-learning-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Safely deploying machine learning in healthcare 2/2" /><published>2017-06-20T13:48:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-20T13:48:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/machine-learning-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/machine-learning-2.html">&lt;p&gt;I have previously discussed the value of information technology in supporting clinical care, unashamedly stealing and modifying Google’s original mantra:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“to organise the world’s information and make it universally accessible and useful”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and adapted it to healthcare information:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information.html&quot;&gt;to organise healthcare information and make it universally accessible and useful&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and argued that we should be making healthcare safer by &lt;a href=&quot;/information-governance/2017/03/19/information-governance.html&quot;&gt;running it on rails&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to talk about artificial intelligence and healthcare in relation to measurement, data and decision making. I outlined the &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/05/10/machine-learning.html&quot;&gt;regulatory issues according to the MHRA of the application of AI in healthcare in a prior blog post.&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;decision-making&quot;&gt;Decision making&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is information important? At its most fundamental, healthcare is about decision making. As such, I would argue that making the right information available at the right time is critical in reducing the uncertainty around any decision in healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.howtomeasureanything.com&quot;&gt;“How to measure anything” by Douglas Hubbard&lt;/a&gt;. It is not primarily written for healthcare, but instead focuses on how to use measurement to reduce the uncertainty around business decisions with a particular emphasis on the importance of &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; is measured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decision-making in healthcare may be relating to the diagnosis or treatment of an individual patient but just as importantly relates to decision-making for groups of patients when we are making decisions about the design of our healthcare services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Douglas Hubbard:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In business cases, most of the variables have an “information value” at or near zero. But usually at least some variables have an information value that is so high that some deliberate measurement effort is easily justified.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In medicine, many of our “measurements” (facts gleaned about how a symptom developed, results of investigations) have very high “information values”. Others have very little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I have regularly argued that we should be routinely recording structured information about our patients including information relating to problems, diagnoses and outcomes. Such data then allows us to make appropriate inferences about our patients such as, how is this patient doing compared to other patients with this condition? In many clinical situations, identifying the patient not behaving as expected is important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, many of our current “measurements” in healthcare relate to information easily acquired, rather than measurements of &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt;. Before deciding on measurement, he opines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What is the decision this measurement is supposed to support?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What is the definition of the thing being measured in terms of observable consequences?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How, exactly, does this thing matter to the decision being asked?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How much do you know about it now (i.e., what is your current level of uncertainty)?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What is the value of additional information?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are recording information (making measurements) that do not support decision making and that information has no intrinsic worth itself, then why are we asking/examining/performing/assaying/recording it at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;reducing-uncertainty&quot;&gt;Reducing uncertainty&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if we decide that a measurement is worth doing, do we need to perform that measurement on all patients in order to make appropriate conclusions? The answer of course is no. We saw this in the recent UK general election in which an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/sci/statistics/staff/academic-research/firth/exit-poll-explainer/&quot;&gt;exit poll&lt;/a&gt; correctly predicted the outcome based on sampling a small number of voters (100-200) at each polling station.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accordingly, decision-making relating to groups of patients, particularly in relation to how we configure services or apply limited resources to populations of patients, does not need measurement of all people within those populations in order to reduce the uncertainty relating to those decisions. Instead, it is reasonable to perform those measurements on a random sample. A random sample is, however, not a sample based on a subgroup of patients who have volunteered to take part. Such a sampling methodology will introduce bias in your results. Instead, sampling should, ideally, be a random sample of individuals&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now these three propositions are outlined in the book (I have reworded them slightly to suit medicine):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We care about measurements because measurements inform uncertain decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;For any decision or set of decisions, there are a large combination of things to measure and ways to measure them—but perfect certainty is rarely a realistic option.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Therefore, we need a method to analyse options for reducing uncertainty about decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;using-ai-to-reduce-uncertainty&quot;&gt;Using AI to reduce uncertainty&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In healthcare, we have a problem with information overload. I must manually scroll through laboratory results looking for something relevant, and in the current (nationally-provided) software I have to use, one has to actually click to open each individual result to check what it showed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we can refine our needs to include the importance of displaying the &lt;em&gt;right information at the right time&lt;/em&gt;. In other words, which “measurements” to show at a given time point that will most reduce the uncertainty relating to a decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While machine learning holds the promise for creating tools that can make clinical decisions inferences independently or semi-independently, I would argue that information technology should focus on valuably supporting care by organising and presenting information about patients to patients and clinicians and providing intuitive adaptive tools that allow the systematic recording of clinical information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is considerable hype relating to AI in healthcare, but this risks overlooking concrete and tangible benefits in the short-term to &lt;em&gt;augment&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;support&lt;/em&gt; humans, whether patient or clinician, in healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such goals may sound mundane compared to the future possibilities of machine learning in healthcare, but to clinicians and patients who have spent many years being “information-poor”, the power of having all relevant information available on hand as well as adaptive tools to record that information quickly and efficiently should not be under-estimated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a patient admitted with weakness as an emergency. An acetyl-choline receptor antibody test was requested by the general practitioner four weeks ago before the patient deteriorated quickly. Do you think the admitting team will notice that result sitting in the laboratory? At the moment, it will be left to luck. How can that be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, adaptive, learning, intelligent systems should be able to curate medical information (our “measurements”) in order to reduce uncertainty (in this case, our diagnosis of myasthenia gravis).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could try to manually curate the rules behind adaptive information displays with complex if…then statements, but ML offers scope to learn from clinicians. For example, real-time adaptive systems could learn what clinicians click on in different circumstances, “see” that patients are having repeated blood tests after a surgical procedure and then subsequently “understand” that it is useful to graph them. Like Amazon can suggest other things for you to buy, adaptive displays of information can “learn” to present the right information at the right time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, you have multiple sclerosis? Here are your outcomes over time compared to patients like you of the same age:
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/edss-graph.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Edss Graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have built that manually, but why can’t machines curate the information for us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;bayesian-logic&quot;&gt;Bayesian logic&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthcare professionals regularly use tacit rules to arrive at clinical decisions based on a set heuristics which will include ‘a priori’ knowledge applied to individual patients. For example, if I know Wilson’s disease is rare but treatable, I will attempt to diagnose it more frequently that something rare but untreatable. Likewise, if a condition is common, then I will test for it more frequently. Likewise, no investigation or diagnostic test is foolproof, with false positive and false negative results. &lt;em&gt;Bayesian inference&lt;/em&gt; is a way of adjusting the probability of a hypothesis (eg. my patient has Wilson’s disease) based on a combination of `a priori’ knowledge (e.g. its prevalence) combined with new information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in clinical practice it is difficult to truly understand the significance of new information. Just as we need to make information available, we also need help in deciding whether new information (“measurements”) are relevant to the clinical decision we face. As a result, we need technology to identify ‘a priori’ knowledge and support us in interpreting how new data influences our clinical decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion therefore, AI can valuably support healthcare by making the right information available at the right time, and learning how to present that information in the appropriate way to reduce the uncertainty relating to clinical decisions. In addition, adaptive systems can usefully identify the “measurements” (data) required to further reduce uncertainty, leveraging ‘a priori’ knowledge and appropriately adjusting to an individual scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we need clinical information systems that enable health professionals and patients to make inferences and support clinical decision making, and AI can and must play a useful role in supporting those systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information.html&quot;&gt;Organise healthcare information and make it universally accessible and useful&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/information-governance/2017/03/19/information-governance.html&quot;&gt;Making healthcare “run on rails” - the importance of technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/05/10/machine-learning.html&quot;&gt;Regulatory issues of the application of AI in healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.howtomeasureanything.com&quot;&gt;“How to measure anything” by Douglas Hubbard&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I have previously discussed the value of information technology in supporting clinical care, unashamedly stealing and modifying Google’s original mantra:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The hazards of paper?</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/hazards-of-paper.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The hazards of paper?" /><published>2017-06-20T13:48:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-20T13:48:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/hazards-of-paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/hazards-of-paper.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Paper is one of the most hazardous substances in a hospital.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Keeping paper over EHR is like keeping horse and cart for fear of theft of cars.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Software is eating the world.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first two are informal quips from colleagues on Twitter, but as I am going to argue that they are wrong, they shall remain nameless!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of you will recognise the last quote from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424053111903480904576512250915629460&quot;&gt;Marc Andreeson&lt;/a&gt;. I truly believe that software is critical to the future of healthcare, in supporting both patients and health professionals in their respective roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a professional, I want information systems that support me in my work and facilitate changes in working practices that mean that I can do &lt;em&gt;my job&lt;/em&gt; more effectively and to the greater benefit of my patients. If I have electronic records wherever I am, I can have a consultation at any time, perhaps in person but perhaps not. With paper records, such responsiveness is not possible; who is going to fetch the notes from the archives?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a patient, I want information systems that support me and facilitate changes in working practices that mean that I can do &lt;em&gt;my job&lt;/em&gt; more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;paper-isnt-all-bad-it-has-workflow-built-in&quot;&gt;Paper isn’t all bad… it has workflow built-in&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Dear Doctors, Can we stop printing out the electronic discharge summaries from the neurology day unit now that they are available in &lt;em&gt;Welsh Clinical Portal&lt;/em&gt;?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“No. Please keep sending them, as otherwise we won’t know when the patient has been admitted and has had their investigations.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very easy to design clinical information systems thinking about how the system will look and work and build a product that will solve the &lt;em&gt;perceived&lt;/em&gt; problem. I have written before about how we need to be careful on &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-design/2017/03/23/scope-framing-clinical-design.html&quot;&gt;framing our problem and scoping the solution to that problem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many hospitals now generate discharge documents electronically. They solve a problem: namely transcribing medications and then creating a discharge document. When a patient is discharged from hospital, a communication should be sent to ensure that the patient’s general practitioner is aware of the admission and what happened. Just like a referral to hospital, it is a handover of care from one team to another made up of a diagnostic synthesis and chain of reasoning supporting those diagnoses including results of relevant investigations together with any procedures or interventions and their complications. We used to hand-write these and then the fourth (illegible) copy would be sent to the general practitioner. Later, and sometimes months later, a team member might dictate a more formal summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But my colleague above, in asking for the electronic notifications to be printed, has identified a missing need that the new electronic discharge system fails to solve: a notification to support his workflow in his ongoing care of the patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;digitisation&quot;&gt;Digitisation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paper is not the most hazardous substance in the hospital; it is a key enabler of many processes and workflows with its use and subsequent benefits not necessarily explicitly understood by outsiders. A benefit of paper is that it allows end-users to rapid prototype a system that support a business workflow when an alternative is either not provided or impedes productivity. In essence, workflows built upon paper were the original “feral” systems until such time that they were replaced with a more formal system or became that system by virtue of its ongoing use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have these “systems”. My secretary places notes in my in-tray and I process them. It is a workflow, albeit a rudimentary one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pile-of-notes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pile Of Notes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that these “feral systems” may not be acknowledged explicitly during information technology deployments - the workflow may be understood by all who work there but never explicitly expressed - it is tacit knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;software-should-be-eating-healthcare&quot;&gt;Software &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be “eating healthcare”&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have previously written about the &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information.html&quot;&gt;importance of software in healthcare&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital transformation is more than simply replacing a single paper-based process with an electronic one. Instead, one needs to understand the workflows and processes that are dependent on the process you are examining and ensure that these are included in your design for a clinical information system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start with data and the structures that will be used to hold that data. Data, particularly in health, will be immutable as it reflects what was done at that timepoint and changes in data should be modelled accordingly. Prefer open standards, adopt published information models and bind appropriate terminologies and data dictionaries so that you can provide semantic interoperability with partner software.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Examine the workflow and processes that are dependent and create explicit process models; there may be many such processes for different services with different perspectives on the same data. Different professionals need different views of the same data. Consider how such models can be flexibly configured at runtime using rule-based engines written in the language of the business, rather than hard-coding processes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acknowledge that, at its most fundamental, healthcare is about communication. Software that ignores human factors will be doomed in the pit of &lt;a href=&quot;/cis-design/2017/05/02/clinical-modelling.html&quot;&gt;real-life/model mismatch.&lt;/a&gt; Build systems that improve communication between and among the healthcare team. Create shared records but understand there is a difference between notifications and alerts and reading a medical record.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use the design of user-interfaces as a useful part of an exploratory process to understand data and workflow, but build a layered architecture with separation of data persistence, business/application logic and user interface. Consider user-facing applications to be minimal, thin-wrappers around more substantial services forming a “platform”, providing different perspectives for different users of the same data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plan user-facing applications for multiple devices, even if you don’t intend to create different versions now so that no-one inadvertently loses separation between business logic and the user interface. Make user interfaces “smart” in the way that they help the user but “stupid” in that they delegate their logic to underlying business services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“Paper is one of the most hazardous substances in a hospital.”</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Embedding data in routine clinical practice</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/15/embedding-data.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Embedding data in routine clinical practice" /><published>2017-06-15T21:22:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-15T21:22:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/15/embedding-data</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/15/embedding-data.html">&lt;p&gt;I spent today at a medical conference relating to motor neurone disease. Today’s conference reinforced my previously held beliefs about the best strategy for healthcare information technology improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the conference, we had a mixture of health professionals and academics, all struggling to do what they need to do. The nursing and care coordinators desperately need tools to support their day-to-day work, managing patients and recording their interactions and communicating with one another. The Motor Neurone Disease Association (MNDA)  want them to use Excel spreadsheets to audit their services for benchmarking and assessment against the NICE guidance. The researchers in the room want a population-based registry in which patient data are recorded to support national history modelling, epidemiological students and subsequently act as a platform for subsequent interventional studies. We heard about researchers collecting patient reported data using paper and pen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This pattern recurs again and again and I’ve referenced the three core needs of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting day-to-day clinical care,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;audit and quality improvement and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;in my blog posts repeatedly: (eg see my post on &lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/06/using-data-patient-safety.html&quot;&gt;patient safety&lt;/a&gt;). This approach is not specific to motor neurone disease and is widely applicable. The critical issue is to embed the three processes within the same system so that, for example, a clinician recording research-level detailed phenotypic information about a patient for their area of interest uses the same system as the one that he or she uses to simply record a register of diagnoses. I think of a nested approach in one has small numbers of very well phenotyped patients and large numbers of less well phenotyped patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pyramid-of-data.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pyramid Of Data&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important component of this approach is increasing patient involvement in research. Patients want it but there are impediments such as the time needed to obtain patient consent and the resources needed to perform more detailed clinical evaluations. As such, using technology to support enrolment into clinical research is vital; that is, we must provide tools to obtain consent from large numbers of patients in a way that satisfies the regulatory frameworks in which we work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, we are increasingly using patient-reported outcomes and adaptive questionnaires to not only understand how our patients fare but even to shape subsequent clinical consultations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it becomes straightforward to imagine an architecture that will support these needs. Indeed, if built correctly with a generic core, a standardised terminology and bolt-on specialist modules, one could imagine it being a disruptive product, creating a commodity platform. I want to see a future in which the platform becomes an interchangeable commodity with innovation and differentiation occurring at a higher conceptual level of support for medical practice. Rather than simple data collection, our mission must be to imagine a future in which medical practice, which at its most fundamental is about clinical decision making, is supported by the most sophisticated tools possible to improve patient care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mission’s greatest risk is in the continued creation of data silos in which health information is locked away in proprietary systems. The answer is to create an open, extensible platform on which innovation can thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would draw a parallel to the evolution of the Internet. In the early days of computer networking, there were many proprietary networking protocols. The advent of TCP/IP and the creation of an interoperable but layered architecture in which at the highest conceptual layer, lower level details of networking were abstracted has resulted in the thriving interconnected Internet as we know it. Similarly, we need create abstractions of our high level clinical requirements but take into account the complexities and paradoxes required in order to share private confidential medical information safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;minimally-viable-products&quot;&gt;Minimally viable products&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have always liked the concept of minimally viable products (MVP) in which one works to prove a methodology or design by creating a minimal proof-of-concept and running it in the real world&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/minimal-viable-product.png&quot; alt=&quot;Minimal Viable Product&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have built my own electronic patient record system and think it is essentially an MVP for healthcare information technology, although perhaps it has now better regarded as an actual product given it is in-use in live clinical environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, clinicians need solutions that solve their problems, and that will vary depending on their role, their speciality and their particular interests. While clinical practice and research are separate processes, having a single system that supports the collection of clinical and research data in different contexts but as part of the same record has been a powerful and valuable tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is an NHS-hosted web-based electronic patient record system already in use for 8 years&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it now records 3000 clinical encounters every month by a wide variety of multidisciplinary teams, recording structured clinical information and embedding SNOMED-CT into clinical practice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it links to multiple PAS within different hospitals and sends clinical documents into a document repository&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it allows flexible data collection configured at runtime to support multiple cohorts of patients and the generic and disease-specific outcome measures. As such, it is used widely for multiple sclerosis, Parkinson’s disease, metabolic disease, neuromuscular disease, motor neurone disease. It is about to be used for adult cystic fibrosis services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it uses SNOMED-CT as a lingua franca to allow loose-coupling between components and switch functionality on and off in different clinical circumstances.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it provides an Internet-hosted portal for patient reported outcomes and mobile device management&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it has client iPad applications to collect patient reported outcome measures and obtain patient consent using Apple’s ResearchKit software.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it can send alerts if patients lose weight or are admitted to hospital, based on an understanding of defined cohorts for long-term health conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it can generate clinical correspondence automatically from data entered during the day-to-day processes of clinical care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it acts as a communication hub between different members of the team, with messages linked to the patient record&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m now working on scaling out this suite of products and the underlying data-driven principles of the architecture more generally. My goal is to create an open, semantically interoperable architecture for healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I spent today at a medical conference relating to motor neurone disease. Today’s conference reinforced my previously held beliefs about the best strategy for healthcare information technology improvement.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Using data for patient safety</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/06/using-data-patient-safety.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using data for patient safety" /><published>2017-06-06T17:42:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-06T17:42:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/06/using-data-patient-safety</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/06/using-data-patient-safety.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This blog post is from a talk I gave to the RCPE in December 2016.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In healthcare, we use data for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the day-to-day care of individual patients&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the management and governance of our clinical services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to support clinical research and innovation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, the effective use of data is critical for patient safety, both now and in the future. So, you might expect healthcare services to have highly developed systems to allow the recording of structured longitudinal observational data?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pile-of-notes-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pile Of Notes 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, no we don’t. Instead, we largely have expensive paper records, poorly accessible with no support for team working. Paper records frequently end up poorly structured containing lots of data but in a format difficult to use in any systematic, safe or indeed automated way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;supporting-your-practice&quot;&gt;Supporting your practice&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/qMsPXSMTpFI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You’re a victim of it or a triumph because of it. The human mind simply cannot carry all the information without error so the record becomes part of your practice”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“if you can’t audit a thing for quality, it means you do not have the means to produce quality”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dr Larry Weed, Internal Medicine Grand Rounds, 1971&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The information in the medical record isn’t something separate to the day-to-day care of an individual patient or indeed a group of patients, but instead is part of that care. However, we clinicians have historically been neglected and the information we need to run our services is not available in a routine and systematic way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should not capture information unless it is useful and, as its most fundamental, data are only useful if they influence a decision or reduce uncertainty in relation to that decision, whether it is a decision for a single patient sitting in front of you or a whole group of patients sharing some defined characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-is-already-collected&quot;&gt;What is already collected?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Korner report was published in 1982, there has been a commitment to routinely collect a national set of data for the management of the NHS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result the health service &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; collect lots of data, such as the hospital episode statistics (HES):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/hes-data.png&quot; alt=&quot;Hes Data&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is illuminating to read contemporary criticism of that report such as that from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bmj.com/content/285/6350/1227&quot;&gt;Sir Douglas Black&lt;/a&gt;, then RCP president who noted:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“the focus of the inquiry seems to have been on the use of information in management, not in any way as a criticism (improvement in management is both possible and desirable) but to underline that the report must be judged in that context and not in relation to other uses of information in clinical medicine or clinical epidemiology.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The recommendation that diagnostic data should be collected on all patients covered by the system is to be welcomed; its omission would make these scheme &lt;em&gt;even more obviously&lt;/em&gt; a management exercise, thereby lessening its appeal to the active clinician” (my emphasis added)&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Sir Douglas Black, 1982.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is reasonable to say that the majority of clinicians have not engaged with these data, nor have they used those data to support their own practice or indeed plan their own service developments. In addition, while there are clinical coders recording diagnostic and procedural codes for inpatient episodes of care, no such information is recorded for outpatient clinics. As a result, we know how many patients are seen in our outpatient clinics, but have little idea why they are seen or how they fare. Importantly, most hospital patient administrative systems do not record information relating to any other type of patient encounter, such as telephone calls&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#telephone&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, home visits or electronic communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The limitations of HES data have been widely known; perhaps the most important limitation is that it is incomplete. As a result, those data bear little resemblance to what happens in real-life, do not recognise team-working and are not recorded by health professionals. Consequently, health professionals rarely see the data, and when they do, they scoff at its inaccuracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this isn’t of only academic interest; this is serious and important to our health services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please read this extract from the Bristol children’s heart surgery report 16 years ago (2001). Are you confident that we have addressed this within the NHS in 2017?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The various clinical systems, many of them paper based, differed from one another and had no relationship with the administrative hospital-wide systems. The funding made available in the late 1980s and early 1990s for medical and later clinical audit helped to reinforce this separation by making available to groups of clinicians money for small local computer systems. The lack of any connection between these different systems, one administrative, the others clinical, for collecting data cannot be explained solely on the basis of some technical or technological reason. It was just as strongly a reflection of a mindset that clinical matters were the sole domain of clinicians and non-clinical matters, to do with the management of resources and with the movement of patients into and through the hospital, were the preserve of managers and administrators.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://webarchive.nationalarchives.gov.uk/20090811143745/http:/www.bristol-inquiry.org.uk/final_report/the_report.pdf&quot;&gt;Bristol Heart Enquiry, 2001&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-is-the-answer-another-registry&quot;&gt;So, is the answer another registry?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer for many clinical services appears to have been the creation of bespoke, specialty or disease-specific registries. Such registries are often created by a particular medical or surgical specialty, a disease-specific organisation such as a charity or an academic centre looking to build a cohort of patients for clinical research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/plurality-of-registries.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Plurality Of Registries&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problems with dedicated disease or speciality-specific registries are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there are lots of them, so potentially lots of disparate systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;not embedded in day-to-day workflow&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;sometimes little feedback, result or reward, particularly in any timely manner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/one-way-registry.png&quot; alt=&quot;One Way Registry&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I am in clinic, I might see consecutive patients with epilepsy, chronic fatigue syndrome, headache, and then multiple sclerosis. How can I possibly use a different clinical system for each individual patient, and what should I do if a patient has more than one problem!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important disadvantage is the lack of timely feedback for users. All clinical systems must provide value to the users of that system, with the value of a system arithmetically divided by the length of time it takes to return that value back to the user. If I am going to spend time entering information, that information must create value immediately so that we create a virtuous cycle of continuous data improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in stroke medicine, we have the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.strokeaudit.org&quot;&gt;Sentinal Stroke National Audit Programme (SSNAP)&lt;/a&gt;. This is a large-scale national audit project in which teams of health professionals perform notes review, completing data collection forms answering questions to derive data on outcomes such as “Median number of minutes per day on which physiotherapy is received”. The aggregated results for a region and comparison of these indicators with other regions are then disseminated months later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, we need systems in place that can answer that question for our current inpatients today so that, for this example, our physiotherapy colleagues can identify those patients who need to receive physiotherapy. To achieve real-time dashboards of these clinical indicators, we must provide appropriate information technology systems so that we can embed the routine and systematic collection of data into our day-to-day processes to capture data as a side-effect of our direct care, and not as an afterthought once care has been provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-is-the-answer&quot;&gt;So what is the answer?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to be ambitious and demand systems that enable intelligent and prudent healthcare. We need to start with &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-1.html&quot;&gt;understanding our problems&lt;/a&gt;, and design our clinical information systems to solve those problems. As clinicians, we need to take ownership of the data on our patients and make data collection routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, taking a domain-driven approach to solving clinical information system design results in boiling down most of our data problems into two broad categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cohorts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Outcomes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cohort is a group of patients who share a defining characteristic, such as the same diagnosis, symptom, clinical finding, or receipt of the same procedure or treatment. I have written about the &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/04/28/importance-of-cohorts.html&quot;&gt;importance of defining cohorts previously&lt;/a&gt; and will not duplicate that post here except to say that SNOMED-CT, a comprehensive and modern terminology provides a hierarchical ontology. As a result, we can record that a patient has “Addison’s disease” (concept identifier 363732003) and determine algorithmically, by virtue of the ontology, that the patient has a type of “hypoadrenalism” (concept identifier 111563005). As such, we can then potentially identify all patients with hypoadrenalism even if they have been recorded as having “Addison’s disease”.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#snomed-understand&quot;&gt;b&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Value-based healthcare is predicated upon understanding and improving our patients’ health outcomes. As such, the systematic and routine collection of outcomes must underpin everything we do; what point in doing a hip replacement if we do not assess how our patient fares? Outcome data may be recorded by health professionals, but the most important outcomes are those that address the needs of our patients and as a result, patient-reported outcomes are critical in understanding how to configure and how to monitor our clinical services. In addition, there are other techniques that provide compelling real-world measures of outcome such as return to employment, need for care, long-term dependency and frequency of complications which should be combined with our other data in order to build well-rounded, comprehensive longitudinal measures of outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, these two broad categories are mutually dependent. How can we interpret quality of life information without an understanding of the patient characteristics?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, SNOMED-CT permits us to understand our cohorts and partially allows us to record patient outcomes, but we must supplement SNOMED-CT with the routine collection of outcome data by professionals and by patients using a variety of disease/procedure and generic outcome tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;routine-collection-of-data&quot;&gt;Routine collection of data&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how can we build the right tools for health professionals and patients to allow the routine and systematic collection of data to support our cohorts and monitor our outcomes? Well, I’ve been trying to do this since 2009….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of recording diagnoses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cppjedy-hMo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we routinely record the toxin, dose and site of injections for our botulinum toxin clinic. It saves time for the clinician, because we can then generate the letter to the general practitioner automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/tgw4FRAiRVs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behind the scenes, each click records data as a SNOMED-CT coded procedure and site and drug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here, my iPad application collects patient reported outcome measures in the clinic and makes them immediately available to the clinician:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/GTo0fGHgoIA&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pd-data.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pd Data&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pd-data-letter.png&quot; alt=&quot;Pd Data Letter&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-can-do-this-at-scale&quot;&gt;How can do this at scale?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, my software records highly structured data using SNOMED-CT and an open information model. As such, documents created using the system consist of a binary blob of data representing a PDF representation as well as a computer-readable data structure recording diagnoses, problems, procedures and interventions in a standardised way. The problem is that, presently, while I expose these data, there are no other applications running in the live clinical environment that are able to interact, yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to collect these data across all of our organisations and services:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/care-plans/patient-data-cohorts.png&quot; alt=&quot;Patient Data Cohorts&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we must stop thinking at the scale of individual services, diseases and organisations and instead recognise that we must support interoperability between multiple disparate clinical information systems across enterprises. This requires action to define appropriate data standards and data exchange, with the adoption of terminology such as SNOMED-CT and LOINC, the use of defined information models such as HL7 FHIR and openEHR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such standards must be mandated for new developments to avoid vendor lock-in, and ideally we should be building vendor-neutral archives of data that other applications, whether in-house or from third-parties, can use for data persistence and retrieval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design of clinical systems must begin with the patient and support the provision of their care irrespective of whether they begin their journey in one organisation and continue it in another. Similarly, we need to train a cadre of experts in health informatics in order to ensure that the routine use of open, standards-backed interoperable information for healthcare is given priority in system development instead of a traditional focus on information for the &lt;em&gt;management&lt;/em&gt; of an individual organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly, if you are a health professional, you must start to demand more information technology in order to support your day-to-day work looking after patients. You need systems to allow the rapid and routine collection of structured data and to be given the required tools in order to make sense of those data for your patient and your services with data linkage and realtime clinical dashboards for your services, your cohorts and your outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;telephone&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;: The telephone was patented in 1876.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;snomed-understand&quot;&gt;b&lt;/a&gt;: I have turned the usual use of SNOMED-CT upside-down as a simple demonstration of using the ontology to derive semantic understanding in a &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/05/20/using-snomed-ct.html&quot;&gt;recent blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This blog post is from a talk I gave to the RCPE in December 2016.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Designing the future 3/3: the patient</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designing the future 3/3: the patient" /><published>2017-06-03T17:10:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-03T17:10:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-3.html">&lt;p&gt;This is part three of a 3-part series on designing future clinical information systems. Part 1 covers the &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-1.html&quot;&gt;importance of data models&lt;/a&gt;. Part 2 covers &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-2.html&quot;&gt;clinical modelling in relation to process and workflow&lt;/a&gt;. This part covers patient portals and the internet-of-things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we need to take several steps back from sitting in our clinics and understand what we do and where we are likely to be going in healthcare. Can we model this in an abstract and future-proof way? Can we do what we did when we &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-2.html&quot;&gt;model a blood pressure&lt;/a&gt;, but for something more complex?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is useful to imagine a patient with several long-term health conditions. These are problems that a patient will have for the rest of their life and most such conditions need ongoing monitoring. This monitoring will be usually managed by a primary care physician or a specialist and their respective teams. As such, several different professionals will be involved, including a range of administrative staff, nurses, physiotherapists, occupational therapists, third-sector providers, social services and doctors. These professionals may all work in the same organisation, but it is much more likely that they will work across organisational boundaries and yet need to collaborate and share information in supporting their patient together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, a patient is not and cannot be a passive recipient of healthcare. Instead, patients should be active members and leaders of the team, setting achievable goals and defining priorities of care. As such, patients need to be able to interact and collaborate with their teams and not only see the information relating to their care but contribute to it as well. Why do we either not measure outcomes or use surrogate proxy markers of outcomes when a patient can tell us, either directly or indirectly by virtue of their activity data, their prospectively recorded log of seizures or their home monitoring equipment?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the model of care in which a patient comes for a 6-monthly outpatient clinic is outdated, inefficient and does not respect the patient - placing them in a subservient, passive role in order to receive healthcare. They arrive, sit in a waiting room, have their pulse and blood pressure measured and are weighed and then, as any who has experienced an outpatient clinic will testify, feel their autonomy fade away. We give them an appointment for six months which doesn’t fit with their schedule and will probably be cancelled. Our administrative systems track patients waiting for a new patient appointment, but patients wait for months for another follow-up slot. Information technology alone is not going to solve this, but can we step back and re-imagine our care processes and &lt;em&gt;use&lt;/em&gt; information technology to enable that change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example overview of how longitudinal prospectively collected information about a patient can be combined from disparate sources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cis_design/data_pipelines.png&quot; alt=&quot;Data Pipelines&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we make sense of step-count data without an understanding that the patient had a hip replacement in May 2017? Likewise, how can we looks at biomarkers on a serum sample taken in April 2017 without understanding the patient had a seizure the day before? We need to integrate, summarise and make available information from multiple disparate sources to the patient and those that support that patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a patient has a clinic appointment in three weeks time, it is possible to have a medical records department that fetches a set of paper notes from the archive and ensures (mostly) that I have them on my desk in clinic at the right time. This model does not scale to support a patient calling us to discuss their care or to support multiple teams looking after patients across multiple disciplines and organisations - who has got the notes? As such, we can use information technology to support a change in the way that we work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;monolithic-architectures&quot;&gt;Monolithic architectures&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early days of the Internet, we had Compuserve and later AOL. As I recall, every computer magazine had a floppy disk or later a CD-ROM with their software on it. Both were proprietary, locked-down portals accessible using a dial-up modem that offered everything from email to bulletin boards to news. As the internet took over, built on open-standards and interoperability, these systems faded into irrelevance and obsolescence. Both tried to react to the more open ‘World Wide Web’ by allowing some degree of information exchange such as permitting emails to be sent and received from the internet, but such limited interoperability was insufficient to prevent the irresistible march of progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthcare information technology is at a similar level of development to those systems from the 1980s and early 1990s with monolithic systems and single portals pitched as the solution to all healthcare problems. Large-scale enterprise applications (such as Epic and Cerner’s Millenium) are now installed in many hospitals and these have started offering limited interoperability in order to make their data available to other systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, those systems can offer a patient portal in which patients themselves can login and interact with that organisation and its teams. In addition, there are now increasing numbers of more consumer-focused patient portals acting as “personal health records” (PHRs) such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patientsknowbest.com&quot;&gt;Patients Know Best&lt;/a&gt;, Microsoft’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthvault.com/en-gb/&quot;&gt;HealthVault&lt;/a&gt; and Google’s (now closed) &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Google_Health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/a&gt; PHR. An overview of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rcplondon.ac.uk/file/3738/download?token=lPb9TkQE&quot;&gt;use of PHRs was written by the Royal College of Physicians’ Health Informatics Unit in 2016&lt;/a&gt; with a focus on PHRs provided by healthcare organisations themselves. In all cases, these products create portals to which patients may interact, and their use is principally communication between the patient and their healthcare team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advantage of a monolithic system is that the patient portal can encrypt all communications between itself and the patient or their device(s) and appropriately manage the secure transmission of clinical information to and from other clinical systems within a wider healthcare enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disadvantage of a monolithic system is similar to the problems experienced by users of closed systems like Compuserve and AOL; they are locked into using that system and potentially innovative smaller enterprises become excluded from the market. If a particular provider does not support data from a particular device, such as a new product to detect seizures occurring in a patient as they sleep, then that patient cannot share that data with their healthcare team. Finally, which system should be used? Should the patient choose? Should the organisation choose? And what about patients who are looked after by multiple organisations?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;can-we-do-better&quot;&gt;Can we do better?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with healthcare data is that it is private and sensitive. So how can we make healthcare data more open and more accessible and yet keep that data safe and confidential? How can we connect the patient and their devices and everyone else involved, whatever their organisation? And if we want to make healthcare data more available, won’t we exacerbate our existing explosion of data and will need tools to make sense of that information. I don’t want to have to read through all of the day-to-day nursing notes recorded when a patient was an inpatient to find that critical piece of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need systems that can make health information more widely available within our NHS network between NHS organisations, but that is insufficient. We also need to extend our reach to the patient, to other care providers such as social services and the third-sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what do we need?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A secure but open distributed infrastructure:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Solve the seemingly mutually exclusive goals of security and availability. I think the answer will have to come in a future blog post, but we need to consider how to make a secure, distributed, decentralised infrastructure on which open standards permit semantic interoperability between disparate systems. We think that there are some clever ways that this might be achieved.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Can such a system adopt both a messaging function, in which electronic communication can be sent securely from one end-point to another, but also a publish-subscribe (multicast) model in which different services contribute and receive information about their patients?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Support data standards and semantic interoperability with clinical modelling for data and process:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Build tools to capture structured data at the point-of-care, and make entering structured data easier to do than entering unstructured free text.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Build tools to turn unstructured data into structured information by advances in natural language processing.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Build tools to support making sense of large amounts of unstructured and structured information in a variety of different clinical, professional and personal contexts.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Understand what we mean by a clinical service and a team, not defined by an organisation but how they &lt;em&gt;work together&lt;/em&gt; for a patient.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Essentially, we need an “information superhighway” for healthcare, in which we can exchange communications securely and yet privately between multiple end-points&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the problems with the secure exchange of information is that, while we can encrypt the contents of my message, the metadata (data about data) leaks confidential information:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/communication/msg-leaking-metadata.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Msg Leaking Metadata&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this rather contrived example, you can see that I sent some information to the genito-urinary clinic and then received some information back. You can guess that a result was included as the laboratory has also been involved. You don’t need to see the contents to make some inferences about what is happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaking information via your metadata is even more problematic for electronic communications. If my patient sends and receives electronic communication to a HIV helpline address, that information tells me something important and leaks private information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any distributed system connecting patients and their devices to our healthcare enterprises needs to solve this privacy concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/05/27/patientcare-epr.html&quot;&gt;Overview of my PatientCare EPR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;{$ link _posts/2017-02-03-domain-drive-design.markdown %}&quot;&gt;Domain-driven design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is part three of a 3-part series on designing future clinical information systems. Part 1 covers the importance of data models. Part 2 covers clinical modelling in relation to process and workflow. This part covers patient portals and the internet-of-things.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Designing the future 2/3: modelling process</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designing the future 2/3: modelling process" /><published>2017-06-03T17:09:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-03T17:09:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-2.html">&lt;p&gt;This is part two of a 3-part series on designing future clinical information systems. Part 1 covers the &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-1.html&quot;&gt;importance of data models&lt;/a&gt;. This part covers clinical modelling in relation to process and workflow. Part 3 covers &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-3.html&quot;&gt;patient portals and the internet-of-things&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/post-it-note.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Post It Note&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I want to talk about how we model clinical information systems and how communication between patients, professionals and services underpins all that we do in healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, my arguments are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It is easy to see information technology (IT) as a product to be deployed: “drop it in and all will be well”. This isn’t true. Instead, IT should be used to support existing workflow and planned changes in that workflow to improve patient care. You need to therefore understand workflow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This boils down to understanding how we work in teams and how those relationships between people need to be modelled within any computer system designed to support healthcare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthcare is all about communication: between patient and the team and between team members and the services that we use. The communication may be a patient phoning us, but it is much more that that. For example, the communication from the laboratory to us on the ward relating to the results of a blood investigation such as a renal function test or a full blood count, the discussion I have with a colleague about the most appropriate next step or my request for that MRI scan of the brain sent from my clinic this morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is easy to forget and instead see technology as an answer itself. As such, we end up with a read-only portal to which I login to see a list of patients on the ward, a list of pending outpatient referrals and a chronological list of investigations for that patient. Such software has been created in response to a requirement such as “allow the professionals to see all of the results”, which seems like an entirely reasonable statement of the requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But has that requirement been correctly scoped?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;poor-scoping-and-the-mismatched-model&quot;&gt;Poor scoping and the mismatched model&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to step back and consider all of the information flows that exist, and particularly note the difference between “push” and “pull” communications. A “push” communication is a message that you receive as an active process : a letter is posted through your letterbox, a result is placed on your desk, the laboratory phones you because the haemoglobin is very low. A “pull” communication is something you fetch yourself : you go and read the noticeboard, you look through a list of results on the computer, you look through the notes to find a filed letter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, information technology in healthcare has adopted a “pull” model for end-users because there was no practical way of offering “push” notifications. This is an interesting paradox because at a technological level, most health enterprises have used “push” messaging (HL7) to integrate different systems within their architecture. There are many reasons why end-users have missed out:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How could a system stand any chance of sending a blood result to the right person when, as designed, no computer could work out to whom to send the result? The request was made on paper, with an illegible name for the consultant, and no way of knowing which professionals worked in which team.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do push notifications work when ward computers are used by multiple users, many of whom move around every few months? Users did not carry personal devices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yet so many processes are predicated upon a “push” model, in which the receipt of a communication (a request or a result of a test), is an integral part of the workflow of a service. The team need to know the result of the blood test in order to send the patient home; a delay in getting that blood test results in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://qir.bmj.com/content/5/1/u209098.w3772.full&quot;&gt;late discharge and a consequent effect on hospital bed efficiencies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, I still get a lot of “push” notifications: my office is cluttered with paper records, post-it notes and a paper inbox. Similarly, I have NHS email with an electronic inbox that fills up with alarming rapidity with stuff for me to do but none of those emails end up linked into the patient record and are not visible to anyone else in the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/pile-of-notes.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Pile Of Notes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as email is not designed as a system to manage workflow, these different systems are not joined up and do not support me in my care for patients. Most of us set-up workaround systems that mean that when we sign off typed letters, we get the notes and can check the results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The systems I have to use don’t support the clinical processes I need in order to provide safe, good care. I have solutions that have been poorly scoped, poorly thought through and a mismatch between reality and the implicit or explicit model underlying those solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need help!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;modelling-process&quot;&gt;Modelling process&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the examples above demonstrate, I now receive a variety of healthcare information via paper, traditional email, and existing organisation-provided and national all-Wales portals. I also receive messages within my own homegrown electronic patient record system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paper post-it notes and my in-tray on my shelf do not support modern ways of working and timely collaboration of patient care, but at least there is no mismatch in the process. I request something, the result is posted back, an administrator bundles the result with the notes and I can deal with it. It is a workflow that is generally safe, if not rather old-fashioned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My health board turned off paper reports for laboratory investigations. I currently receive no notifications about results, whether normal or abnormal. It is left to chance, unless I make a habit of always checking results whenever I sign off letters. This is a process model mismatch. I have to login and manually check results for patients under my care and there is currently no way of knowing that someone has dealt with a result. Now we’re starting to fix this as part of the Welsh Clinical Portal project within NHS Wales but there is more work to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the PatientCare EPR, I built a model for rapid team-based, patient-linked electronic communication. While not perfect, it builds in a task-manager so that users can track what they have and have not dealt with. At the time of writing, users have sent 57,412 messages between each other with 45,743 explicitly linked to a patient record. Users now send over 1,000 messages per month to one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/patientcare-messages.png&quot; alt=&quot;Patientcare Messages&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the graph shows, the vast majority of messages are sent by administrators and by specialist nurses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many different ways of supporting team communication and it is important for users to be able to send messages from lots of different contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first context is the software’s encounter wizard, which can be used to record clinic encounters, ward reviews or telephone calls (or any other user-defined service-specific type of encounter):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/communication/msg-encounter-wizard.png&quot; alt=&quot;Msg Encounter Wizard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here you see an administrator recording encounters against two patients. Those encounters will be recorded in the longitudinal record for that patient automatically. For each encounter, a user has the option of sending a message to a colleague. As such, in one click, the user records both an encounter with the patient and informs someone else of the need to do something. Once created, at any time a user can see a list of encounter. Users are able to filter the list depending on a range of different characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/communication/msg-encounter-list.png&quot; alt=&quot;Msg Encounter List&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, we can also see a pure list of the messages for that patient, irrespective of whether an encounter exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/communication/msg-message-view.png&quot; alt=&quot;Msg Message View&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we can create a message directly from the patient’s record:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/communication/msg-simple.png&quot; alt=&quot;Msg Simple&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users can choose whether to receive an email notification about secure messages received. If all our users had their own personal handheld devices, a push notification would work similarly. In addition, within the PatientCare EPR, they have a simple inbox functionality to see their unread messages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/communication/msg-inbox.png&quot; alt=&quot;Msg Inbox&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And to facilitate task management, messages can be flagged as complete:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/communication/msg-completed.png&quot; alt=&quot;Msg Completed&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important feature is that the contents of the communications are available to all members of the team looking after that patient, because it is recorded within the patient record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-model-for-the-future&quot;&gt;A model for the future&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, patients and users are explicitly linked to one another via the concept of “episodes of care” and “user registration”. As such, the system supports a finely-grained security model in which we can vouch that a particular health professional has a direct-care relationship with a specific patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/care-plans/patient-project-membership.png&quot; alt=&quot;Patient Project Membership&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our services for long-term health conditions, the episode is lifelong as you would expect. For more acute services, such as our liaison neurology service, the system closes episodes after a custom defined period (e.g. 3 months). At any point, users with the correct permissions can themselves can register patients to a service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of this information and process model, the software is a fine abstraction of the real-world, making it more likely that it can be repurposed for future needs. This approach creates systems that have longevity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given this modelling of real-life processes and communication, it is easy to see how dealing with communications from patients could work. Rather than communications being sent to an individual health professional, who conceivably may be on leave or unable to respond, building a process and information model that mimics real-life offers the potential to build true team/patient communication. Likewise, the same model works for data from the patient’s own devices, whether they be home-monitors or wearables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part 3 of this series covers &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-3.html&quot;&gt;patient portals and the internet-of-things&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is part two of a 3-part series on designing future clinical information systems. Part 1 covers the importance of data models. This part covers clinical modelling in relation to process and workflow. Part 3 covers patient portals and the internet-of-things.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Designing the future 1/3: modelling data</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Designing the future 1/3: modelling data" /><published>2017-06-03T17:08:00+02:00</published><updated>2017-06-03T17:08:00+02:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-1.html">&lt;p&gt;This is part one of a 3-part series on designing future clinical information systems. This post covers the importance of data models. Part 2 covers &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-2.html&quot;&gt;clinical modelling in relation to process and workflow&lt;/a&gt;. Part 3 covers &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-3.html&quot;&gt;patient portals and the internet-of-things&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two fundamental principles that we must consider when designing clinical information systems for the future:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We can’t build perfect systems straightaway; if we wait until everything is perfect, we’ll never get anything done.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We shouldn’t give up on creating perfect systems. We’ll never achieve perfection of course, because they will always be something even &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; to implement, so we need a roadmap for stuff we need to solve now, solve tomorrow and solve in the future.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusion is, therefore, we must get technology in the hands of users, but plan to iterate and try to design systems that are future-proof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, information technology (IT) is not something that one can buy, deploy and then sit back and bask in the glory of improved efficiency and streamlined processes. Instead, we need to consider how our clinical processes work now, how they might, could or should work in the future and build systems that support those processes. At the very least, our designs should not unnecessarily limit our ability to adapt to new ways of working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of us have all of the answers at this point in time, so what can we do to create future-proof systems that solve problems now that don’t unnecessarily limit our future scope and prevent future innovation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is to develop clinical models of data and the processes and workflows relating to those data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start with our data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;clinical-modelling&quot;&gt;Clinical modelling&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps I can draw a parallel between software engineering and a famous Danish interlocking brick toy company?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that toy company creates a model with blocks that are specific to that model, only usable in the construction of that car or boat or train, then it might be possible to try to re-purpose those blocks to build an aeroplane, but it is much less likely. Conversely, creating a wide-range of general purpose blocks means that those blocks can be re-used in hundreds of different applications right now and in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I opined in my &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html&quot;&gt;Domain-driven clinical design document&lt;/a&gt;, the same is true in software. The best way of creating systems that solve problems right now and support our future iterative development efforts is to start with open and standard data structures with a core focus on interoperability. I cannot overstate the importance of supporting interoperability, even in the unlikely event that you think you don’t need to interoperate with any other system right now. Baking in interoperability forces you and your team to make the right decisions when it comes to designing an architecture to support your software. I have heard people argue that interoperability is something “nice to have” but we’ve “got to get something done” as if designing systems properly will somehow slow or impede development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the designers of the interlocking brick systems have a problem. They can’t know what bricks to make until they start thinking about the toys they want to be able to build with those bricks, but they can’t design the toys until they know which bricks they have available. So they need to ensure their teams work iteratively, bringing people together with different skills, using some common basic bricks and adding more specialised bricks for certain use-cases. Likewise, in software, modelling data and process requires an understanding of both and how they might be used now and changed in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we can make it easier for ourselves. We can begin with modelling the easy things: won’t a blood pressure recorded in millimetres of mercury will always be a blood pressure recorded in millimetres of mercury? Well yes, but don’t we also need to codify who took it, when they took it, how they took it, and what the patient was doing at the time? How can we create a representation in a computer that is re-usable and understandable by multiple systems? So now we need something to represent “120/70 mmHg taken in the right arm by Dr Wardle in the sitting position at rest using a manual sphygmomanometer”. But what about a blood pressure taken using a transducer from an arterial line in the intensive care unit?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So suddenly we need to start thinking not just about representing a numeric value in specified units but all of the additional metadata. We are building an information model to represent a real-life concept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, someone has done most of the work for us already. Read Dr Heather Leslie’s (@omowizard) blog post about blood pressure to see how openEHR provides a rich model of the concept of blood pressure. Similarly, the HL7 FHIR observation resource provides a simpler but similar representation with metadata represented either as a choice of options in openEHR or using a standardised terminology such as SNOMED-CT for FHIR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, there are already a large number of archetypes defined within openEHR representing a wide-range of clinical concepts. Similarly, HL7 FHIR already supports exposing a great variety of (similar) clinical concepts as part of an API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;openEHR clinical knowledge manager: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openehr.org/ckm/&quot;&gt;http://www.openehr.org/ckm/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;HL7 FHIR 3.0.1 resources: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/resourcelist.html&quot;&gt;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/resourcelist.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future of healthcare systems is based on open-standards and semantic interoperability in which multiple systems can share information about patients. We can use vendor-neutral archives for data persistence of openEHR archetypes or expose proprietary legacy information to other systems using a standardised HL7 FHIR API. Whatever the case, starting with our data allows us to solve our immediate problems and permits ongoing iterative development to use that information in new and innovative ways in order to support the care of patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part 2 of this series covers &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/03/designing-future-2.html&quot;&gt;clinical modelling in relation to process and workflow&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is part one of a 3-part series on designing future clinical information systems. This post covers the importance of data models. Part 2 covers clinical modelling in relation to process and workflow. Part 3 covers patient portals and the internet-of-things.</summary></entry></feed>