<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.wardle.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.wardle.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-01-19T16:02:30+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/</id><title type="html">Health informatics and information technology</title><subtitle>by Dr Mark Wardle, Consultant Neurologist, clinical informatics and software developer. Founder, Eldrix Ltd.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Focus focus focus</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Focus focus focus" /><published>2018-01-19T14:44:44+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-19T14:44:44+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html">&lt;p&gt;“Informed health and care – A digital health and social care strategy for Wales” (http://gov.wales/topics/health/nhswales/about/e-health/?lang=en) sets out a clear vision for the use of information technology to support the provision of healthcare for citizens within Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This vision is split into four key themes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Information for You”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Supporting professionals”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Improvement and innovation”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“A Planned future”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We want a future where staff, service users, patients and carers are empowered and better informed, where organisational boundaries are not a barrier to effective care, as information is available electronically and joined-up, and where innovation and improvement can flourish built on a solid technical infrastructure and a safe environment for those who work in or are served by health and care services in Wales.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key question for us to answer is, what are the key challenges that must be overcome to deliver this vision? As part of that process, we must be frank and honest about both current and future impediments to delivery. It is easy to fall into a trap of thinking of the “Informed Health and Care” strategy as an finished product instead of what it is, a set of high level goals which requires us to build a tangible and specific roadmap bringing together multiple strands of work into a truly cohesive vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, we must be honest about the economical and political environment in which we work, acknowledging the limitations in resources. We face a multitude of potentially conflicting demands and interests; as such, delivering the “Informed Health and Care Strategy” requires us to not only understand what we must do to achieve those goals but critically to understand what we must stop doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is our strategy to deliver the vision?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;difficult-choices--we-cannot-do-it-all&quot;&gt;Difficult choices : we cannot do it all&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NHS Wales must face some difficult choices.  For too long, external factors have resulted in incoherent and inconsistent delivery or projects, frequency orthogonal to delivery of the wider vision; in many cases it has been driven by the budgeting process and the availability of funds in any single financial year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A coherent strategy needs more than a list of disconnected and incompatible goals but instead a clear understanding of what needs to be done and what doesn’t need to be done; we must know when to say “no”. Instead, we focus our limited resources on specific tangible actions and make some difficult decisions to prune areas of work that do not support delivery of the wider vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… you should have a very short list of the most important things for the company to do. Then you will have a basis for moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Good-Strategy-Bad-Difference-Matters/dp/1846684811&quot;&gt;“Good Strategy Bad Strategy”, 2011 by Richard Rumelt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we need a coordinated all-Wales approach that permits all stakeholders to work cooperatively and collaboratively with clear lines of responsibility and governance. We need to re-organise our approach to healthcare information technology that takes into account the steps needed to deliver the vision, the principles of enterprise architectural design, modern information standards and interoperability, modern quality improvement methodology and user-centred design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that the only logical response to the Welsh Audit Office report is to re-imagine the relationship between the NHS Wales Informatics Service (NWIS) and the health boards. Such a re-imagining requires us to stop ignoring the, in my view, currently incoherent set of responsibilities and divisions of labour that exist within Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, is NWIS a standards and governance body, a consultancy, a software development house, a provider of a computing platform, a user experience and design shop, a procurement specialist, a business intelligence and analytics service or a provider of information technology infrastructure? Who is responsible? Who takes the credit and who takes the blame when something is not delivered? If we cannot answer such questions, we have to question our governance and organisational structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, while it makes sense that the “Informed Health and Care” strategy is divided into four workstreams, I believe it is incorrect to assume that the safe and efficient delivery of those objectives is necessarily delineated into separate workstreams in which it is assumed that work may continue semi-independently without consideration to other projects. There are, in my opinion, too many common goals and solutions to solve those goals that cross-cut those workstreams to consider them independently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, we must consider a “target architecture”, an enterprise master-plan which lays out an overall set of systems and functions that will support delivery of our shared vision. For example, understanding the similarities and differences between providing information for patients or professionals provides important insight into the shared data and software components that must serve both sets of requirements. Patients and health professionals need to see past and prior appointments and entries on waiting lists; there are shared needs that cut across those workstreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, transformational change, enabled by technology, must be driven from the bottom-up, from those who deliver healthcare permitting incremental development and innovation while at the same time lowering risk? Likewise, don’t we all know that we must have top-down governance to ensure that solutions are standards-compliant, fit-for-purpose and safe as well as checking that developments are not orthogonal to the overall strategic vision so eloquently described in four workstreams of the Informed Health and Care Strategy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paradox, put simply, is that we, in NHS Wales, have centralised the day-to-day management and delivery of individual projects and yet high-level strategic and prioritisation decisions are decentralised, haphazard and dependant on capital funding with little or no consideration or control as to how those projects will fit into a wider technical all-Wales architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-are-the-challenges-we-face&quot;&gt;What are the challenges we face?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are our challenges in delivering the vision today?  The recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wao.gov.uk/publication/informatics-systems-nhs-wales&quot;&gt;Welsh Audit Office report&lt;/a&gt;  raised important concerns about healthcare information technology in Wales including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Highlighting the inherent complexity of deploying information technology across a large complex system, spread across multiple organisations, with staff operating out of hospitals, GP practices and in the community.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Significant delays in delivery of projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lack of strategic prioritisation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Disagreements between some NHS bodies and NWIS in relation to delivery and the meaning of “Once for Wales”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A need to strengthen leadership&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weakness in governance arrangements, lack of independent scrutiny and unbalanced reporting of progress&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inadequate funding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inconsistent planning with a need to aligning plans across organisations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Issues of information technology staff capacity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Issues of clinical engagement and dissatisfaction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Concerns about the quality and functionality of many national systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unclear lines of responsibility in relation to delivering and monitoring the benefits of projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, we must also consider what challenges our services will face in the future. Healthcare is ever-changing and there are a number of transformative and disruptive influences in health that, together with new technology, are driving and will continue to drive new ways of working. I wrote about these in my &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;disruptive challenges series of blog posts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changes in model of care:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Management of multiple long-term health conditions, cross-disciplinary teamwork, non-health partnerships including social care and third-sector&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shared care and shared records&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Remote monitoring using modern technology including wearables and the “Internet of things”.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Focus on health outcomes and prudent healthcare, a need to support big data and real-time analytics and embed artificial intelligence into management and clinical practice.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patients as active participants:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;View and contribute to their own records, recording their own aims and objectives and target outcomes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Communication with the healthcare team&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Control the sharing of their information for direct care, for service evaluation and for research via consent and robust citizen identity services&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hospitals without walls:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Increasing availability of personal mobile devices, wearables and smart home monitoring&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New commercial models of care and software provision&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/docs/dhss/publications/180116reviewen.pdf&quot;&gt;Parliamentary Review of Health and Social Care report&lt;/a&gt;, published in January 2018 highlights the need for a seamless health and care system in Wales, centred around the citizen irrespective of where they live with the avoidance of creating artificial barriers between services and organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It quite appropriately highlights that such service redesign can be enabled by the appropriate use of digital technology. In addition, it highlights how frontline innovation across different parts of Wales has already emerged and the importance of being able to disseminate good practice once proven as well as adopting continuous quality improvement methodologies to create a learning health and care system. Similarly, it recognises that different localities across Wales do not need to operate in the same way or that services must be identical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that report, similar concerns to that from the WAO were raised :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Simply put, activity is just too dispersed and stretched, and lacks overall commitment around a unified vision and set of priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the report draws out the seemingly conflicting goals between local variation and harmonisation and standardisation. How can we support innovation, variation in services and the delivery of a thriving digital ecosystem supporting local industry and innovation with centralised reduction in needless variation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I do not, for example, want patients to be disadvantaged because the technology used in one health board is different to another and the information available is incomplete and the pathway of care disrupted. This is why Wales has committed to working together to adopt common information services and I expect all parts of the NHS in Wales, supported by the Informatics Service, to adopt them&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dr Andrew Goodall,  Chief Executive, NHS Wales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we deliver these two seemingly mutually exclusive goals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer, of course, is to understand that coordination and central control can be applied differently depending on what is being discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thus we should seek coordinated policies only when the gains are very large. There will be costs to demanding coordination, because it will ride roughshod over economies of specialization and more nuanced local responses. The brilliance of good organization is not in making sure that everything is connected to everything else. How that road lies a frozen maladaptive stasis. Good strategy and good organization lie in specializing on the right activities and imposing only the essential amount of coordination.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;from “Good Strategy Bad Strategy”, 2011 by Richard Rumelt&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our strategy must therefore take into account coordination for some areas of our work and yet enable innovation and variation in others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-do-we-meet-those-challenges&quot;&gt;How do we meet those challenges?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WAO rightly recommends deep clinical and managerial engagement and so suggests that NWIS and NHS bodies should work together to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“strengthen the relationship between developers and clinicians, particularly in designing and testing new systems and functions, so that there is a better collective understanding of what is wanted and what is possible; and [..] engage with managers to identify their information needs as well as the needs of clinicians.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I do not believe that this recommendation, or any of their other recommendations, to be sufficiently far-reaching to effect substantial change for NHS Wales IT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is helpful to review the UK &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/guidance/government-design-principles&quot;&gt;“Government Digital Service” design principles&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start with user needs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do less&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design with data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do the hard work to make it simple&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iterate, then iterate again&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is for everyone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand context&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build digital services, not websites&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be consistent, not uniform&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make things open: it makes things better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital transformation is complex and needs deep involvement of the whole service and not simply an “information technology project”. Indeed, to make the most effective use of information technology, that technology can be used hand-in-hand as an enabler of service transformation. Few would argue that organisational change is rather more difficult to execute that deploying software and yet why is it that we expect a third-party organisation to parachute into another organisation and deliver change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is therefore evident that successful healthcare information technology requires partnerships and collaboration. However, another major obstacle within NHS Wales is the existing current and legacy information technology solutions in place across different organisations and as a result, their varying priorities in relation to digital transformation. Such an structure risks placing any national strategy, or indeed any organisation tasked with delivering that strategy such as NWIS, into an impossible situation trying to meet disparate or even opposing priorities or accommodating compromise in design or functionality. Such conflicting priorities result only in user dissatisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, at a clinical design meeting on Friday, the implementation of an “outpatient administrative outcome form” was discussed. For background, we were shown the advanced end-to-end service transformation work at Abertawe Bro Morgannwg involving linking up multiple disparate systems to digitise the outpatient department. This work combined a commercial patient-call system with access to clinical documents, investigation results and tracking the workflow from patient arrival to their attendance for investigations or procedures. The striking conclusion must be that service transformation must be driven by local NHS organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would not matter if there were three or three-hundred clinicians in the room to design an “outpatient administrative outcome form”, if the scope of the challenge is limited to the design of a form and not the end-to-end service change for which it is but one component; clinical engagement does not fix the inherent design flaw or failure of limited project scope that does not factor into the end-to-end process re-design required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge then is to ensure that innovation of design, of process and of information technology in one part of Wales can be rapidly spread to other areas. Rapidly scaling out good practice requires information technology that is scalable and can work in different environments with minimal change. If software is developed interfacing to bespoke or proprietary local systems, then it is necessarily much more difficult to deploy it in other environments. We cannot, for example, take the clinician portal (CWS) used in Aneurin Bevan Health Board and deploy it into Cardiff and Vale, despite the fact that it offers valuable clinical functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;delivering-an-open-standards-based-digital-health-platform-for-wales&quot;&gt;Delivering an open, standards-based digital health platform for Wales&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a technical architecture that can support all of this complexity, allow innovation and parallel working at pace and yet provide assurance and governance. Many of you heard my talk on Data-driven Healthcare at the inaugural Digital Health and Care Conference in August 2017.  In it, I advocate for a standards-based, open computing platform built on data and services. From McKinsey:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Consider an open innovation platform that holds healthcare data, and provides data access that is enabled for application programming interfaces as well as common technical IT services such as identity, access, or consent management.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;McKinsey, January 2016&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, Gartner, 2016, developed the theme of a computing platform onto which digital businesses can be built, exposing services to customers (patients), employees (professionals), things (devices such as home monitors, wearables, mobile device applications etc) and partners (a digital ecosystem).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.016.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.016&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, “Once for Wales” should mean we focus on delivering a suite of data and software services that support a suite of lightweight user-facing applications. The whole system must be designed to be interconnected and consists of lots of small pieces each one “channel agnostic” and each re-usable, perhaps in ways hitherto not considered in order to innovate in the future. Data flows between these components via application programming interfaces (APIs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my illustrative schematic in which we open up our core services, create a platform leveraging new technologies (such as HL7 FHIR) to expose application programming interfaces that can be used by multiple applications providing different views and different perspectives on a single patient record or collections of those records.  We must focus on data standards and interoperability, creating lightweight applications at pace and design useful real-time analytics services for clinicians and managers. Critically, we build a platform that can provide the building blocks for future innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.018.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.018&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Interestingly, another definition of a “platform” is a set of services that bring together users and providers to form a multisided market. Is it possible then to take our “open platform” and start to think of a future in which we have products and services that actually do enable a re-imagining of healthcare provision to bring together patients, carers, health professionals, commissioners, analytics, researchers and all other stakeholders in a safe and secure manner?  (see &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html&quot;&gt;a previous blog post&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment, our health platforms, if they exist at all, are lopsided asymmetric systems in which patients play little or no role. We must start thinking about creating a data-driven architecture that corrects this asymmetry in power and control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/docs/dhss/publications/180116reviewen.pdf&quot;&gt;Parliamentary Review of Health and Social Care report&lt;/a&gt;, there is explicit recognition of needing to balance enabling nuanced local response and specialisation with a centrally dictated state unable to adequately adapt to need at pace. It suggests a need for a set of agreed national broad principles with appropriate central governance and local involvement. Those broad principles should be focused on data standards and software services with a clear set of application programming interfaces using which, we can build the next generation of innovative user-facing applications, whether for professionals or patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must recognise that cooperation and standardisation must be mandated for our core platform of national services, with data structures and application programming interfaces defined clearly to the benefit of all. Likewise, creating a layered architecture in which data persistence, business rules and logic and presentation layers are separate and linked by well-defined human and technological contracts, defining the interactions and the results that are to be expected, permits us to have different governance structures. As I wrote in the &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html&quot;&gt;5 O’s of healthcare IT&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Recognise the relative unchanging components and iterate and prototype the components that change more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;How can we develop a “can-do” digital culture in healthcare? Should we clone the “Move fast and break things” culture reported in technological startups? Not really! We need to approach information technology in a different way but we can’t “break things”! We work in a safety-critical environment, but we must recognise that the pace of change and the level of risk can be different at different levels of our enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html&quot;&gt;The 5 O’s of healthcare IT&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;re-organising-healthcare-it-in-wales&quot;&gt;Re-organising healthcare IT in Wales&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A basic challenge we face is to match our clinical and administrative problems with technological opportunities including new ways of working that new technologies make possible. This challenge is particularly difficult because some of our day-to-day problems still have no straightforward technical solutions and many new technologies may impact on our provision of healthcare in ways that we cannot yet clearly articulate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To counter this challenge, we must accept that we do not have all of the answers and must build systems and software that can meet both current and future demands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, NWIS should be broken-up into functional units with clear lines of governance and focused responsibilities, with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A platform group, responsible for core components of the “Once for Wales” health platform, providing data and services to professionals, the patient and third-parties with strong analytics support.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An applications group, providing lightweight building blocks of user-interface components which can be used by health organisations in conjunction with their existing resources.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A data standards and governance group, to oversee the platform and its design as well as provide governance and sign-off of permission to connect by both internal and external systems.   This group would contain WISB and WTSB and govern the performance of both the platform and applications group.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An infrastructure group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current “strategy” focused on delivering a portal is not fit-for-purpose and must be vigorously challenged. A portal approach, in which one plans a national portal through which all functionality is provided, risks creating a brittle top-down centralised design, needlessly limits innovation and does not take full advantage of the use of information technology to re-imagine and transform our clinical services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, NWIS should become a provider of a platform and a toolbox of components useful for building clinical applications that use open industry-standards such as HL7 FHIR and SNOMED-CT. The services and modules provided by the groups would be mandated by an all-Wales governance group on behalf of NHS Wales representing all stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we need to carefully balance decentralisation and ensure that no organisation is left behind. As such, centralised teams containing expertise in technology, user-experience and design should be made available to organisations to support their transformation programmes, leveraging our open platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;priorities---what-is-our-focus&quot;&gt;Priorities - what is our focus?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be surprised to hear that we still do not have access to clinical documents and investigation results across Wales. These two priorities must be delivered before any new projects are started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The platform team should focus, in the first year, on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exposing the Welsh Results Reporting Service (WRRS) as a national open service, ensuring all results are available across Wales irrespective of organisation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exposing the document service as a national open service.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building a national demographic service wrapping the existing eMPI and WDS/NSTS.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating a national pathway service, providing administrative support for tracking pathways across organisations and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making the National Intelligent Integrated Audit Service (NIIAS) available as a service and at the service layer rather than only via specific applications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building a national test requesting concierge service handling investigation requests, whether laboratory or radiology, seamlessly by encapsulated lower-level systems such as RADIS and LIMS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should develop a range of key performance indicators for each core national service to include functionality and performance. For example, demographic services providing a unified wrap of the enterprise master patient index using a modern FHIR-based API might be expected to return results matching on &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; demographic identifiers within &lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt; microseconds. Breaking up an architecture into modular independent microservices permits automatic scaling and monitoring and simplifies testing which can be performed in isolation and automatically when software code is changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new website should be created, &lt;strong&gt;https://api.wales.nhs.uk&lt;/strong&gt; providing service documentation, code examples and governance procedures for each service as well as way for internal and external organisations to register user-facing applications and submit requests for connection to the wider platform. Our design and service work should be public, open and transparent. National services and the organisation running them should be the servant of users, including health and care organisations in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The applications group should focus on breaking-up WCP into modular re-usable components, identifying and removing important business logic which should be implemented at the service-layer. The results viewing component should simply leverage the underlying services and be a lightweight wrapper that can be used to support multiple workflows dependent on the clinical context. Applications should be ephemeral and lightweight; designed for customisation and integration into the myriad of complex healthcare workflows that exist across our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The infrastructure group must begin an options analysis of the costs and security implications of running server infrastructure on existing hardware or commodity UK-based cloud providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must be honest about what we can and cannot do in Wales. There are existing commercial solutions for a range of user-facing applications and it makes little sense to duplicate that functionality. Similarly, why should NWIS develop software for outpatient outcome recording to fix a problem that ABM, ABHB and CAV have already solved? Instead, NWIS should be focused on delivering what no-one else can, an open, standards-based, consent-driven digital health platform. No health board or commercial entity can build that; let’s focus on creating an enabling technology platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an approach will allow health boards to adopt new functionality at their own pace and develop solutions themselves leveraging the same shared platform. One current failing across Wales is that local developments are orthogonal to the national shared interest because, in the absence of a truly open standards-based platform, software is developed tightly bound to local systems. As such, those new developments are not easily scaled across the wider economy. As such, we should mandate that local developments leverage the national platform and that those developments are made available to other NHS organisations when complete via a shared open-source code repository. It would then be possible for new developments developed elsewhere to be scaled rapidly across all of our services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separately, the standards and governance team should provide an interoperability toolkit to be used for scoring both internal and external applications on a range of interoperability factors including the use of existing national services, adoption of approved data standards and plans for the future. Such a toolkit would be used to drive the adoption of standards over time and improve compatibility with the national platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we should be working in the open. My blog is one example of this; we should foster debate of the difficult issues, acknowledging that there is no easy or straightforward solution, but only compromise, collaboration and cooperation to do the right thing for patients in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“Informed health and care – A digital health and social care strategy for Wales” (http://gov.wales/topics/health/nhswales/about/e-health/?lang=en) sets out a clear vision for the use of information technology to support the provision of healthcare for citizens within Wales.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Applying artificial intelligence in healthcare</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/machine-learning/2017/12/17/diagnostic-inference.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Applying artificial intelligence in healthcare" /><published>2017-12-17T14:32:32+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-17T14:32:32+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/machine-learning/2017/12/17/diagnostic-inference</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/machine-learning/2017/12/17/diagnostic-inference.html">&lt;p&gt;In this post, I discuss machine learning and computer-aided decision support in healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I discuss the importance of understanding the process of clinical decision making and how we use information to support that process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I discuss how software can valuably support our clinical decision making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I would like to convince you of the need for an computable data structure which I have termed OCMR, the &lt;em&gt;“open computable medical record”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, as a community, must collaborate to define the structure of the OCMR. This structure must allow us to create large amounts of publicly-available training data to provide to machine learning algorithms. Likewise, when it comes to evaluation and use of that trained algorithm, we need a computable data structure that can be populated from the real records of an individual patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;applying-artificial-intelligence-in-healthcare&quot;&gt;Applying artificial intelligence in healthcare&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial intelligence is a term used to describe intelligent machines that makes inferences or decisions based on data with little or no human interaction. Such decisions might be simple and rule-based (“Does this patient have anaemia?”) or more complex inferences based on multiple variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistical modelling, in which we study an outcome and the covariates that contribute to that outcome is, in itself, not that different to machine learning, at least conceptually; they are akin to two sides of the same coin. The advent of powerful computing power in every desktop and even in your pocket has meant that computationally-intensive methods, such as machine learning, are a useful tool in any statistician’s armamentarium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, we could create a tool, such as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chadsvasc.org/&quot;&gt;“CHADSVASC”&lt;/a&gt;, that could calculate the risk of a patient having a stroke if they had atrial fibrillation. That tool was generated from a conventional statistical approach looking at thousands of patients, their outcomes and the possible determinants of that outcome; the statistical model would identify the important factors that influence the outcome and provide a coefficient for each factor giving an indication as to its influence. The tool, created based on an understanding of those factors and their influence, can then be evaluated in clinical practice to ensure it is safe and accurate; such analyses might include estimates of sensitivity and specificity in specific populations of patients. For example, a tool generated from data from a non-representative sample of patients is unlikely to be generalisable to other populations. If such a tool is proven valid for a population of patients, then it could be used in clinical practice to support clinical decision making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning approaches the problem from a different perspective using a computationally-intensive approach, often from data with many more variables than one could plan to use in a more conventional statistical approach such as logistic regression, to predict results from data. However, the end result is that machine learning can be used to understand data in a broadly similar way to more conventional statistical approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep learning is a type of machine learning that has seen rapid advances in the last decade; it is a technology that has been used in computer vision applications to recognise handwriting or categorise images based on the objects or things they contain. However, there are increasing applications outside of this field such as voice recognition, natural language processing and playing common computer and board games to a standard greater than that possible by humans, sooner than expected simply by virtue of advances in raw computing power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep learning uses multiple layers of neural networks to extract, transform and process information in multiple steps, with each layer using the output from the previous layer as input and training performed by backpropagation using a type of gradient descent. This backpropagation is akin to maximum likelihood estimation (MLE) in statistical regression in which estimates of parameters are generated; backpropagation works to train the network to give the outputs as labelled in the training data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chains-of-inference&quot;&gt;Chains of inference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already use multiple structured models in clinical practice - such as CHADSVASC or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.england.nhs.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/psa-aki-alg.pdf&quot;&gt;identifying acute kidney injury&lt;/a&gt; - as part of the wider care of patients to support a range of purposes such as clinical decision support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such models can be considered, generically, as a black-box that when provided with inputs is expected to give an answer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ai/generic-model.png&quot; alt=&quot;Generic Model&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, such a model does not only apply to proven tools or computer-based decision making but is also applicable to human decision-makers. In the &lt;a href=&quot;/medical-records/2017/10/08/the-broken-medical-record.html&quot;&gt;“Fractal medical record”&lt;/a&gt;, I discussed the concept of nested hierarchical data being used to make inferences which themselves are used as inputs to support further inferences:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fractal/angina-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Angina 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the patient reports a crushing tight chest pain when they exert themselves walking up a hill, investigations show a normal resting electrocardiogram (ECG) and a history of smoking, together with some other findings. A diagnosis of angina is made; a useful diagnostic label to aid communication and, importantly, to aid clinical decision making and pattern recognition. When the patient presents in the future with new chest pain and ST segment elevation in the anterior leads of an ECG, old and new factors are combined implicitly to derive two conceptual diagnoses: &lt;a href=&quot;/medical-records/2017/10/08/the-broken-medical-record.html&quot;&gt;one is the latent trait of arteriosclerotic disease, perhaps never recorded but concluded implicitly, and one is a new acute anterior myocardial infarction&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, a consultant radiologist will be given a brief summary of a patient’s clinical problems (“shortness of breath”, “wheeze”), the contextual clues (inpatient vs. outpatient, name of the referrer) and the imaging itself to provide a diagnostic opinion. A respiratory physician may take those same clinical problems, the radiology report and additional investigation results to provide a further diagnostic opinion. The diagnostic inferences become nested:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fractal/angina-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Angina 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end result? A chain of multiple abstract black-boxes representing models accepting input data and providing an output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do all of these models need in order to provider inferences?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Models, whether human or algorithms built using software, need &lt;strong&gt;information&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make best use of that information we need, to paraphrase a well known commercial motto:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“to organise clinical information and make it universally accessible and useful”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-record-becomes-part-of-your-practice&quot;&gt;“The record becomes part of your practice”&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In relation to the medical record:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You’re a victim of it or a triumph because of it. The human mind simply cannot carry all the information without error so the record becomes part of your practice.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dr Larry Weed, Internal Medicine Grand Rounds, 1971&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how we structure and use our medical records, whether on paper or digitally, is critical in supporting good clinical care. So how do we use our records to come to a diagnosis?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-one-look-at-raw-information&quot;&gt;Step one: look at raw information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see a list of investigation results from an individual patient in a tabular view sorted by descending date:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ai/flat-results.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flat Results&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A view like this is seen in many different electronic health record systems and it is usable. As clinicians, we can click on one of the rows and see the result. Most systems allow the graphical display of various results over time permitting us to assess trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, we will have gathered additional raw information directly from the patient or carers about current and past symptoms, established previous medical problems such as chronic obstructive airways disease, an allergy to penicillin or previous cholecystectomy. In addition, we can corroborate and supplement that information from a review of the previous medical records. Such records may be on paper, in which case it is unlikely that they will be available in the emergency department, or electronic, either as a summary problem list or from piecing together information from multiple pieces of correspondence from multiple specialties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most health professionals will have sympathy with the analogy that we work as hunter-gatherers; our job is to find the right information at the right time and most of us will readily admit that this is usually time-consuming and error-prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, imagine a patient presents with drooping of the eyelids to their general practitioner, and that doctor checks for acetyl-choline receptor antibodies. This is an investigation that will take two weeks to be processed.  Imagine the patient deteriorates after the test result is back but before it is seen by the general practitioner. Imagine then that the patient presents to the emergency unit, do you have confidence that your current clinical systems will make that result available to the admitting team or, even if it is available, that the team will specifically look for that test result?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we have a problem: we must trawl through the medical record in order to manually organise information and make it useful. We take a problem with thousands of dimensions - our raw results - and reduce them to some high-level concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-two-summarise-and-synthesise&quot;&gt;Step two: summarise and synthesise&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, to make sense of an excess of information in the medical record, most clinicians will attempt to create a summary to aid decision making. This is, in machine learning terms, a process of dimensionality reduction to identify the latent traits that are giving rise to the measurements that we can see. For example, one might write:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;2-hours central chest pain&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Sweating&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Breathless&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;ECG: ST elevation anterior leads&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Known: 
angina
acute coronary syndrome 1997 -&amp;gt; stent in circumflex - angioplasty 1997
hypertension
smoker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We conceive of the important information and apply that information to arrive at a clinical diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;3-months of headache&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;subacute encephalopathy&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;deteriorating renal function&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;chronic lymphocytic meningitis&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;leptomeningeal enhancement on MRI brain&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;bilateral facial nerve palsies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each, just as in Dr Larry Weed’s problem orientated medical records (POMR), we summarise at the most specific conceptual level that is defensible. If only a single lumbar puncture had been performed, we’d probably conceive of “lymphocytic meningitis” only, unless we could make an inference that the pathological process was chronic because of other factors, such as chronic headache and a long history of multiple cranial neuropathies. We might conclude chronicity based on repeated lumbar punctures or from synthesising the temporal pattern of clinical symptoms and signs over time. We populate our problem list based on the synthesis of multiple inferences from multiple sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first example, we have summarised the salient facts and have enough information to suggest “anterior myocardial infarction” as a most likely diagnosis. Indeed, we could use our anatomical knowledge to opine that the patient most likely has an occlusion in the left anterior descending coronary artery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second example, we do not have sufficient information to arrive at a single most likely diagnosis, but we can arrive at a sensible differential diagnosis, a list of possible diagnoses such as “malignant meningitis”, “neurosarcoidosis” or “tuberculous meningitis”. The cause of the deteriorating renal function is unclear; we need more information to solve that problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have defined the &lt;em&gt;essence&lt;/em&gt; of the clinical scenario in order to help us make clinical decisions; we reduce the uncertainty about those decisions to a level which permits rational decision making. As I have &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/machine-learning-2.html&quot;&gt;previously quoted&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;We care about measurements because measurements inform uncertain decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;For any decision or set of decisions, there are a large combination of things to measure and ways to measure them—but perfect certainty is rarely a realistic option.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Therefore, we need a method to analyse options for reducing uncertainty about decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-three-iterate&quot;&gt;Step three: iterate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generating a differential diagnostic list is important; it allows us to consider the &lt;em&gt;next steps&lt;/em&gt; of the diagnostic pathway: what questions to ask previously omitted and what tests to arrange. Such a methodology re-affirms the nested hierarchical nature of diagnostic inference and the importance of understanding &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; probabilities and the &lt;em&gt;a posteriori&lt;/em&gt; probability after our measurement, test or indeed any other method of obtaining more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A test can only be interpreted in a wider clinical context. Acetyl-choline receptor antibodies, tested in a patient with a pattern of symptoms (what the patient says) and signs (what we find on examination) suggestive of myasthenia gravis, are highly, but not perfectly sensitive to a diagnosis of myasthenia gravis. As I have &lt;a href=&quot;/medical-records/2017/10/08/the-broken-medical-record.html&quot;&gt;written before&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Similarly, if we have imperfect measurements that are not 100% sensitive or 100% specific, then we have to ask, sensitive and specific to &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt;? Realising this provides an important insight: when applied, say to clinical diagnosis, is that almost all of our measurements in medicine are as if we are looking at the truth out of the corner of our eye. We cannot see the &lt;em&gt;hidden truth&lt;/em&gt; but a combination of our measurements are, together, governed by a few simpler variables or concepts that are actually the cause of the results of the measurements that we can measure. As a result, we hope that our measurements can be used to understand the &lt;em&gt;latent&lt;/em&gt; variable(s) that are actually the hidden cause of those measurements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A latent variable is a variable that cannot be measured directly but we can infer its value from measurement of other observable measurements. In essence, we might conceptualise a latent trait as the real process to which our tests and assessments, combined together, provide an imperfect measurement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-four--reduce-dimensionality-reduction&quot;&gt;Step four : reduce (dimensionality reduction)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, our highly complex, multi-dimensional medical record, combining symptoms, signs and investigation results, can potentially be simplified in terms of latent traits. Such a process is termed &lt;em&gt;dimensionality reduction&lt;/em&gt; and humans perform this task implicitly to simplify both the process of decision making and the communication required around that decision-making between professionals and the patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, a 72-year-old patient with a long history of smoking cigarettes and a prior myocardial infarction is likely to have atherosclerotic vascular disease. When that patient presents with new right sided arm and face weakness, we are likely to assume that their stroke has been caused by emboli from atherosclerosis rather than a dissection, even if both causes are possible. The same clinical event occurring in a 32-year-old patient during high-intensity exercise is likely to have had a stroke due to arterial dissection. Humans perform such inferences without necessarily being explicit in documenting their chain of inference; over years we build a set of heuristics, rough and ready rules of thumb, that mean we make reasonable conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-five--avoid-biases&quot;&gt;Step five : avoid biases&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, humans are subject to a range of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_bias&quot;&gt;cognitive biases&lt;/a&gt; (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Thinking-Fast-Slow-Daniel-Kahneman/dp/0141033576/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1513438649&amp;amp;sr=8-2&amp;amp;keywords=cognitive+biases&quot;&gt;“Thinking fast and slow” by Prof. Daniel Kahneman&lt;/a&gt;) which results in a failure of our heuristics. For example, in confirmation bias, we may place greater emphasis on new information if it confirms a pre-existing belief or conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;By Jm3 (Own work) [CC BY-SA 4.0 (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0)], via Wikimedia Commons&quot; href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3AThe_Cognitive_Bias_Codex_-_180%2B_biases%2C_designed_by_John_Manoogian_III_(jm3).png&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;512&quot; alt=&quot;The Cognitive Bias Codex - 180+ biases, designed by John Manoogian III (jm3)&quot; src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a4/The_Cognitive_Bias_Codex_-_180%2B_biases%2C_designed_by_John_Manoogian_III_%28jm3%29.png/512px-The_Cognitive_Bias_Codex_-_180%2B_biases%2C_designed_by_John_Manoogian_III_%28jm3%29.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, the structure of our medical records, whether on paper or electronic, can inadvertently exaggerate our own biases. Conversely, properly organised and well structured records may help us to spot our biases and support their avoidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, it is easy to fall into the trap of “anchoring”, in which the first piece of information acquired skews all subsequent inference as it is prioritised ahead of subsequent information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;computer-assisted-care&quot;&gt;Computer-assisted care&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information technology can and should valuably support caring for patients. Unfortunately, healthcare has not adopted information technology as quickly or effectively as other industries. For others, information technology is now &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; way that those businesses operate. Healthcare could immediately benefit from better scheduling, planning and communication using off-the-shelf technologies widely used in other domains. In addition, we should be adopting other technologies as soon as possible : identity management, delegation and consent, evaluating &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privacy-enhancing_technologies&quot;&gt;privacy-enhancing technologies (PETs)&lt;/a&gt; with focus on re-imagining our services around patients and enabling that transformation with technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in this essay, I want to focus on discussing computer-aided decision support and the value of applying machine learning in supporting the care of patients. With the right tools, we could do much to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support presenting the right information at the right time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;suggest “measurements” (to obtain new information such as symptoms, signs or investigation results) that will add valuably to the decision-making process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;suggest differential diagnoses or treatment plans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take steps to avoid common human cognitive biases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;machine-learning-and-healthcare&quot;&gt;Machine learning and healthcare&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason that machine learning has been used so effectively for image interpretation was the creation of large amounts of training data. Training data, for machine learning, needs to provide the input parameters and the labelled expected output. For an image, you might have a human label an image of a cat as a “cat” and then, together with hundreds of thousands of other images, a machine learning model can be trained and tested. There are now many publicly available training datasets &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_datasets_for_machine_learning_research&quot;&gt;available&lt;/a&gt; from multiple sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how can we achieve superhuman performance for clinical decision making?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to start thinking now about how to structure medical information so that it is possible to create large-scale publicly available training datasets and to understand how to transform clinical data from electronic patient records into the same format to permit testing and application in real-life clinical scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, we need a &lt;em&gt;“open computable medical record”&lt;/em&gt;, the OCMR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;open-computable-medical-record-ocmr&quot;&gt;Open Computable Medical Record (OCMR)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OCMR is a simple intermediary data structure that can be used to be build datasets representing clinical knowledge. Initially for version 1, its focus is on diagnostic inference, mapping a combination of clinical findings to a most likely diagnosis. We use SNOMED-CT, an international terminology to represent the concepts in our clinical knowledge model; they are the primitives around which we build our knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the simplest structure might be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[acute kidney injury:&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=14669001&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;14669001&lt;/a&gt;] + [naproxen:&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=11847009&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;11847009&lt;/a&gt;] = [Analgesic nephropathy:&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=59400006&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;59400006&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each link will take you to the NHS digital SNOMED CT browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why should we use SNOMED CT?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SNOMED CT is a human-curated ontology tracking clinical and non-clinical concepts and the relationships between them. For instance, SNOMED CT will tell you that [acute kidney injury] is a type of [kidney disease:&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=90708001&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;90708001&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own SNOMED CT REST API provides this information in a computationally-useful manner : &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/concepts/14669001?include=recursiveParentConcepts&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;acute kidney injury&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/concepts/11847009?include=recursiveParentConcepts&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;naproxen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this means is that an algorithm can potentially learn generic knowledge from specific examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is conceivable that a model, knowing that naproxen can cause acute kidney injury, can also learn that the broad class of analgesics can cause acute kidney injury and so, when faced with a patient on ibuprofen, can suggest a correct judgement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While SNOMED CT contains many types of relationships permitting us to infer that “acute kidney injury” is a type of kidney disease, it does not contain any data providing support for diagnostic inference. As such, we need to embed SNOMED CT concepts within a wider OCMR information model in order to express potential diagnostic inferential relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not difficult to conceptualise the OCMR as a 2-dimensional image with each pixel representing a clinical finding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ai/mi.png&quot; alt=&quot;Conceptualising the OCMR as an image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the source “image”, a set of factors representing “chest pain”, “shortness of breath” and “ECG ST elevation” are analysed and the most likely diagnosis given: “acute MI” (myocardial infarction).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not difficult to envisage making an OCMR more structured and more refined to provide additional contextual information relating to clinical context, baseline characteristics of the patient such as age and sex as well as the severity and nature of each clinical finding; we might categorise these as acute, sub-acute, chronic or episodic for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have included an example OCMR record for a diagnosis of myocardial infarction. It is available as a JSON-formatted file including the clinical problems (and for each the higher-order more generic concepts) and the final diagnosis. The example file is available &lt;a href=&quot;/images/ai/question.json&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I would envisage converting this to a flat vector for ease of processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;meta-learning-and-dimensionality-reduction&quot;&gt;Meta-learning and dimensionality reduction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rationale behind defining an OCMR is to provide machine learning models with a set of deep underlying (latent) traits that act as as the core principles supporting diagnostic inference, just as used by humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not simply want a model that, given free text, outputs possible diagnoses, even though that might be an eventual result. Instead we want models that support building a more thorough foundation for clinical inference, that might even allow us, with the right right tools, to identify and understand inferential relationships and latent traits that we currently do not recognise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we might use the models to take new input from a patient’s medical record and support their direct care. In a patient with chest pain, a trained algorithm should be able to make diagnostic inferences and suggest information that is required such as “we need an ECG for this patient presenting with chest pain”. The model has learnt the relationship between chest pain and an ECG and even troponin results; with the right integration of decision support into our electronic health records, the algorithm could help us by highlighting the important information rather than simply showing all results in chronological order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sources-of-training-data&quot;&gt;Sources of training data&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ai/model-generation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Model Generation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we build a corpus of medical knowledge containing diagnostic inferential relationships as well as codifying choice of next diagnostic steps, interventions and treatments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would argue that we need to consider multiple sources of medical knowledge and make them usable by converting them into the OCMR format; the OCMR data model is essentially an intermediary data structure for medical information in the same way as images can be represented as a bitmap image file and readily analysed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential sources of information are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;core epidemiological data - providing information on incidence and prevalence for a range of disease&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;free-text monographs about diseases, such as those from rare disease databases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;free-text monographs about drugs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;textbooks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;exam questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;epidemiological-data&quot;&gt;Epidemiological data&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Epidemiological data relating to the incidence and prevalence of different diseases are usually well-described in the literature. Such data can provide important &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; probabilities of different diagnoses in different clinical contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such data could be supplemented by real-life data taken from known patients - for example, the GP research database (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.herc.ox.ac.uk/downloads/health_datasets/browse-data-sets/general-practice-research-database-gprd&quot;&gt;GPRD&lt;/a&gt;) or hospital episode statistics (HES) for hospital admission and discharges. Such data will be recorded either as Read codes or ICD-10, but these are readily convertible to SNOMED-CT and could contribute to an publicly-accessible OCMR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;free-text-monographs-literature-and-textbooks&quot;&gt;Free-text monographs, literature and textbooks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many rare diseases, there are excellent semi-structured and authoritative descriptions of clinical features and types of presentation. It is not difficult to see how natural language processing could be used to extract the important phenotypic features of a range of rare diseases in order to support the identification of patients usually only possible by specialists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the OMIM (Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man) resource on &lt;a href=&quot;http://omim.org/entry/125370?search=drpla&amp;amp;highlight=drpla&quot;&gt;DRPLA&lt;/a&gt;, a rare neurodegenerative disorder is detailed and includes the important symptoms and signs. OMIM make their dataset available on the Internet in both human-readable and machine-readable formats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, adverse-effects of different pharmaceutical compounds could be imputed from monographs in standard pharmacopeiae and so potentially highlight to non-specialists where a drug might be contributing to a patient’s problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;exam-questions&quot;&gt;Exam questions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been building up large numbers of semi-structured questions in medical schools across the UK and have a collaborative national question bank run by the Medical Schools Council Assessment Alliance (MSC-AA). We also have similar banks of questions for the postgraduate examinations managed by our Royal Colleges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could these question banks be useful as a corpus of knowledge for machine learning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my prior role in the School of Medicine at Cardiff University, we used to encourage students to use assessments to drive their learning by sitting as many exam questions as possible. As part of that work, we implemented a “progress test” in which students sat 3-4 exams per year with detailed feedback to identify areas for which they needed more help. We now have thousands of questions in our bank alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can questions drive learning for machines?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, this is from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usmle.org/pdfs/step-
1/2015samples_step1.pdf&quot;&gt;USMLE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A 52-year- old woman comes to the physician because of a 1-month history of headache, weakness, tingling of her extremities, muscle cramping, and fatigue. Her blood pressure is 170/110 mm Hg. Physical examination shows no other abnormalities. Laboratory studies show a decreased serum potassium concentration, metabolic alkalosis, and decreased plasma renin activity; serum sodium concentration is within the reference range. Urine catecholamine concentrations are within the reference range.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?
A. Adrenal adenoma
B. Focal segmental glomerulosclerosis
C. Hypothalamic tumor
D. Juxtaglomerular cell tumor
E. Renal artery stenosis&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Answer : A&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The important characteristics of exam questions are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they are a succinct distillation of important clinical concepts with a labelled answer; they usually do not contain extraneous information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they contain sufficient information information to identify a single best answer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is a single best answer, although the distractors should be reasonable to someone who doesn’t know the answer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they are semi-structured - with a stem (the clinical scenario), a lead-in (the question), the possible answers and the correct keyed answer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;medical schools and colleges &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; write questions on the most important and common clinical scenarios; they should represent a representative corpus of medical knowledge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential problems with exam questions are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is it possible to obtain sufficient questions in order to contribute to the learning of a model?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is it possible to use natural language processing to extract the terms from the lead-in and to map the possible answers into a structured format suitable for our OCMR?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these issues can be overcome, then the SNOMED-CT ontology tells us “headache” is a type of “pain” in the “head” so that any learning system can learn on the broad generic concepts and not only the concept used at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we can map each entity within that free text to a SNOMED-CT concept. Here I use my relatively rudimentary free-text mapping service:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/search?s=plasma%20renin%20activity&quot;&gt;Plasma renin activity&lt;/a&gt;
maps to to &lt;a href=&quot;http://browser.ihtsdotools.org/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=8883510000001
02&amp;amp;edition=uk-edition&amp;amp;release=v20170401&amp;amp;server=https://prod- browser-
exten.ihtsdotools.org/api/snomed&amp;amp;langRefset=900000000000508004&quot;&gt;8883510000001&lt;/a&gt;
or in JSON:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/concepts/888351000000102/recursiveP
arents&quot;&gt;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/concepts/888351000000102/recursiveP
arents&lt;/a&gt;
which tells us we’re measuring “renin”…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, we match on &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/search?s=headache&quot;&gt;“headache”&lt;/a&gt; and understand that this is a type of &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/concepts/25064002/recursiveParents&quot;&gt;“pain”…. in the “head”…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the right answer is (A)… Adrenal adenoma, so, we can look that up too…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/search?s=adrenal adenoma&quot;&gt;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/search?s=adrenal adenoma&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/concepts/255036008/recursiveParents&quot;&gt;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/concepts/255036008/recursiveParents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and then understand that this is a type of benign neoplasm of the adrenal gland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, for any single question, it might be possible to &lt;em&gt;impute&lt;/em&gt; a range of different data based on more generic high-level broad concepts. Likewise, if there is insufficient training data for creating a high-dimensional map at a high level of granularity, we can use techniques to reduce dimensionality and create a low-dimensional model. Indeed, it is likely that identifying the core principles and trends from high-dimensional datasets will permit better predictive models to be created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, this question not only links a diagnosis of adrenal adenoma with fatigue, hypertension, a low serum potassium concentration and metabolic alkalosis, but it is conceivable that the training data could be used to identify patients with similar symptoms and signs and suggest that renal profile should be checked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, the resultant model may be able to generate additional questions for subsequent training, by humans and algorithms alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information technology has the potential to revolutionise healthcare and augment our clinical decisions by helping us understand patient information in ways to directly improve care. Clinical decision making is complex and we need to consider ways to both understand and support our decision-making. We don’t want to abdicate responsibility for 
decision-making; indeed, decision-making is a partnership between professional and patient. However, for too long, human professionals have had to spend time gathering the right information instead of focussing on where our skills are needed most : high-level thinking and communication. We should be working towards building tools that support us in the care of our patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have started work on the first version of the OCMR and I am going to try to build some publicly-available datasets to kickstart the application of machine learning in healthcare. As an experiment, I have built a fake dataset generator (&lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/wardle/go-snomed&quot;&gt;go-snomed&lt;/a&gt;) which builds a fake OCMR JSON structure to try to understand the pitfalls of this approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the next steps are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build natural language processing tools to extract clinical terms from different sources of clinical knowledge such as monographs and questions from exam banks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work with universities and colleges to obtain questions for machine learning. In the interim, generate fake questions for testing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generate dimensionality reduction techniques to genericise highly granular concepts and their relationships identifying the broad underlying principles at play.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work on collecting incidence and prevalence data from a variety of different clinical contexts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would love to hear from you if you would like to be involved or indeed, help support this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In this post, I discuss machine learning and computer-aided decision support in healthcare.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The 5 Os of healthcare IT</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 5 Os of healthcare IT" /><published>2017-12-06T10:39:39+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-06T10:39:39+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html">&lt;p&gt;My writing on &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html&quot;&gt;domain-driven design&lt;/a&gt; arose because of my own experience building an electronic patient record system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A model is an abstraction of the real-world distilling knowledge into core concepts and processes.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;from &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html&quot;&gt;Towards a domain-driven, model-based approach to developing clinical information systems: innovating for the future in NHS Wales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that development, I was fortunate to use technologies developed by NeXT (and continued by Apple - WebObjects), which enforced a strict separation of model, controllers and the view. Importantly, I learned an important principle: the importance of starting with a data model conceived with a deep understanding of the domain in which I worked in my day job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was only later that I read Eric Evans’ “Domain-driven design” which, while not about healthcare, has much to teach us in health information technology about the importance of data modelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“There are many things that make software development complex. But the heart of this complexity is the essential intricacy of the problem domain itself. If you’re trying to add automation to complicated human enterprise, then your software cannot dodge this complexity—all it can do is control it.
The key to controlling complexity is a good domain model, a model that goes beyond a surface vision of a domain by introducing an underlying structure, which gives the software developers the leverage they need. A good domain model can be incredibly valuable, but it’s not something that’s easy to make. Few people can do it well, and it’s very hard to teach.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Martin Fowler&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Excerpt From: Eric Evans. &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/gb/book/domain-driven-design-tackling-complexity-in-heart-software/id502848358?mt=11&quot;&gt;“Domain-Driven Design: Tackling Complexity in the Heart of Software.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-digital-drive&quot;&gt;A digital drive&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to see information technology as a product rather than what it really is - an enabler of transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we deliver transformative change in healthcare using digital technologies? Why does a domain-driven design approach help us? Why and how should we start with domain models?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest that there are five broad principles… my 5 Os of healthcare IT:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-objectives&quot;&gt;1. Objectives&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Define a clear vision. For example, in Wales, the Welsh Government &lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/topics/health/nhswales/about/e-health/?lang=en&quot;&gt;Informed Health and Care strategy&lt;/a&gt; is a very good start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then define tangible definite high-level objectives. This should not be “deploy XXX” where XXX is a product you want to deploy, but instead focus on user need - the requirements, the problems you are solving and the transformation you enable. So, for me, in the next 3 months, NHS Wales should:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ensure laboratory and radiology results and clinical documents are available to all clinical users when they are seeing a patient, irrespective of where those investigations were performed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identify deteriorating patients on the ward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your prioritisation list might be different, but those objectives should support the aims in your overall vision. I have a different list for 6-months, 12-months and onwards (a subject for another post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is sensible to define a list of all objectives, each a stepping stone on the way to delivering your overall vision. You will need to take into account political and business priorities as well so it is about negotiation, discussion and understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate this, we currently have a PACS replacement project ongoing. For me, replacing one PACS (picture archiving and communication systems) with another, in the absence of a well argued need, does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; meet the standard required. In a resource limited environment, wasting resources without good reason is difficult to defend. Always ask for a compelling reason &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; something is important! What value do we gain that cannot be achieved in more prudent manner?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, what is the point in forcing organisations to rip out a patient administrative system to replace with a new “Once for Wales” PAS if each will be configured differently with different information standards? Similarly, if the project to “deploy” the system doesn’t end up providing administrative and clinical staff or indeed the patient, information from across multiple organisations, then what are we trying to achieve?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your objectives define your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-ownership&quot;&gt;2. Ownership&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make information technology and the transformation agenda owned by the users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But who are the users? You need to consider : health professionals, administrators, managers, analysts, the patient, and more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The users must be engaged, must be empowered to own and drive their work. We need to understand the areas in which there is synergy between requirements from different perspectives and design our enterprise to provide the common tools to solve their problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than top-down “You will…”, consider instead “Here are the tools to achieve your goals… do you want help?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all users, ask them what they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, what do our patients want from a healthcare services that recognises that digital is one way of providing a service? Are you sure that we know the answer to this yet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-openness&quot;&gt;3. Openness&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Allow debate. Make your work transparent.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information technology is difficult, so ensure plenty of debate to hear all of the views. There is no right way, but favour solutions to deploy quickly, get software in hands of users early and get feedback, favour an approach that set a foundation for future plans and don’t limit what you don’t know you don’t know. As I have said many times before:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need to build an infrastructure that explicitly recognises that we don’t have all of the answers, and therefore must support innovation. Such innovation may simply be incremental improvement of existing technology, but also must cope with and embrace the introduction of transformative and disruptive technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;Once for Wales debate, March 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should debate and build in the open. There are few situations in which work, particularly funded by the public, should be behind closed doors. Transparency is key; options analyses of the most appropriate way to deliver solutions to our problems. Like everything in medicine, our decisions are rarely black-and-white, but careful  judgements balancing many different options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;4-optimise&quot;&gt;4. Optimise&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Permit failure.  Fail fast. Recognise the relative unchanging components and iterate and prototype the components that change more quickly.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we develop a “can-do” digital culture in healthcare? Should we clone the “Move fast and break things” culture reporting in technological startups? We need to approach information technology in a different way but we can’t “break things”! We work in a safety-critical environment, but we must recognise that the &lt;em&gt;pace of change&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;level of risk&lt;/em&gt; can be different at different levels of our enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rate-of-change-layered.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rate Of Change Layered&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this diagram, we see that our architecture consists of an open platform approach, built using application programming interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The data layer contains longitudinal episodic patient data relating to admissions, appointments, measurements and outcomes. This layer may consist of multiple data repositories for laboratory systems, documents, clinical data and aggregate data from across multiple patient administrative systems from multiple organisations. These complexities are abstracted within our architecture as a set of simple open application programming interfaces (APIs). This layer changes the least. A blood pressure in the right arm will always be a blood pressure recorded in the right arm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The business logic, services and process/workflow layers provides important reusable services that execute business logic.  This ensures that user-facing applications do not make the mistake of embedding important business logic and rules. For example, if access to information needs to be logged, then it is better to perform this at the API level rather than within a user-facing application.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The user-facing components and applications leverage the underlying platform in order to provide value for users. User-facing applications are most likely to need to change frequently given our technological advances. You should consider these to be relatively ephemeral, taking advantage of new mobile devices and other new technology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see this approach in more detail in my &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;plan for an open platform in NHS Wales&lt;/a&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/platform/platform-overall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Platform Overall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a platform, one ends up procuring multiple systems that need to be connected together, rather than to a common enterprise platform. This results in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data silos: most current products store their data in a proprietary format within that product. As a result, we create multiple silos. If one can access that information and connect it to your other deployed products, you hit the complexity of n*(n-1)/2 data interoperability, in which you have to somehow connect that product to everything else (2 systems need one connection, 3 needs 3, 4 needs 6, 5 needs 10, 6 needs 15,7 needs 21!) so one ends up with a combinatorial nightmare. &lt;img src=&quot;/images/cis_design/multiple-interfaces.png&quot; alt=&quot;Multiple Interfaces&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Procurement rules: it is difficult to scale a solution across a wide enterprise as costs hit thresholds for OJEU rules and suddenly, you and your team are committing large sums of money in a high risk deployment in which failure cannot be countenanced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, think “open platform”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;5-organic&quot;&gt;5. Organic&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scale organically, enthusiasts and early adopters, grow horizontally; get people asking “can we have that too?”, until your solutions are the default, that they make process easier and not more difficult.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to support innovation if we cannot tolerate variation. It is easy to assume that all variation across health services is bad, and so it is easy to think you should harmonise people and processes with technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an approach is wrong. Firstly, harmonisation is a people and processes issue, not technological, and secondly, how can you be sure you are harmonising to raise standards? What if you are standardising to the lowest common denominator? Variation allows you, as part of systems continuous improvement, to innovate, appraise and improve. Conversely, unmeasured and unmonitored variation is difficult to justify.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, recognise that information technology is fundamentally an enabler for transformation and that transformation needs to be driven from the bottom-up; imposing a software solution from central diktat rarely results in satisfied users or effective change. Design the health enterprise to instead allow iteration and innovation in a safe way, playing by a well-defined rulebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/DiffusionOfInnovation.png&quot; alt=&quot;DiffusionOfInnovation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(CC BY 2.5, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?curid=11484459&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?curid=11484459&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work with early adopters and enthusiasts and then plan to scale organically, proving benefit using a quality improvement methodology such as DMAIC. Measure!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cis_design/dmaic.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dmaic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects relating to information technology fail frequently and this is seen in many industries, including healthcare. Healthcare enterprises are complex heterogeneous environments with many stakeholders and significant complexity; mistakes may cost lives. It is easy to assume that, faced with such risks, one should centralise and control and drive change from above, but such an approach actually results in a greater risk of failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is an important paradox in many health services, including Wales, is that there is a tendency to centralise the day-to-day management and delivery of individual products and yet high-level strategic and prioritisation decisions are decentralised, haphazard and dependant on capital funding with little or no consideration or control as to how those projects will fit into a wider technical healthcare enterprise architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html&quot;&gt;“A paradox of control”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high-level strategic roadmap to deliver our shared vision should be centralised across an enterprise. Similarly, the rules of engagement, the the contractual obligations at a human and technical level that permit interaction with the open platform (API and data standards etc.) should be defined centrally. Conversely, the day-to-day management and delivery of individual projects should be driven, bottom-up, by the users and for the users and scaled out when appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;“Once for Wales debate”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-design/2017/03/23/scope-framing-clinical-design.html&quot;&gt;Scope and framing in clinical information system design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/04/04/test-requesting.html&quot;&gt;Test requesting design: building an open API-based architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data driven healthcare information technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">My writing on domain-driven design arose because of my own experience building an electronic patient record system:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The paradox of ambition</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/paradox-of-ambition.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The paradox of ambition" /><published>2017-12-06T10:39:39+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-06T10:39:39+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/paradox-of-ambition</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/paradox-of-ambition.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-paradox-of-ambition&quot;&gt;The paradox of ambition&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have information technology projects in healthcare which are hugely ambitious in their scope - for example, the nursing documentation project in Wales - in which there are many requirements, interactions, dependencies and fundamentally so many issues of change management required across multiple organisations, that it is hugely ambitious as a result of it being really very difficult. That worries me, because ambition to solve something that is extremely difficult is misplaced ambition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe src=&quot;http://player.nafw.cloud.vualto.com/Player/Index/f81e649d-044a-40b0-8f42-8d6017d78557?autostart=False&amp;amp;captionsOn=False&quot; name=&quot;NAFW Player&quot; seamless=&quot;seamless&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;360&quot;&gt;
&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.senedd.tv/Meeting/Index/f81e649d-044a-40b0-8f42-8d6017d78557&quot;&gt;Welsh Senedd meeting on nursing documentation project&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The right kind of ambition is ambition to make a difference and deliver value at pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when we talk about nursing documentation, it is ambitious because I think, the project, as currently designed, will just not work. The approach is just wrong; it needs to be something driven from the bottom-up and not the top-down. What the top-down should be doing is setting the direction of travel, setting the rulebook, giving the users and the people who work on their behalf the tools to solve their problems. You need to get software in the hands of users as soon as possible in order to more fully understand the problems you are trying to solve; a more agile approach is required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The right kind of ambition is to deliver. So what I mean by ambition is that I want to have my consultations recorded and my dictation to order blood investigations automatically. Who will be the first to deploy “Amazon Echo” or “Google Home” in the clinic to support my outpatient consultations? How can we enable that innovative future? We do it by creating an appropriate open services-based architecture and allow multiple applications to use those services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So sure, build test requesting into a portal but don’t build the whole stack of functionality into that single codebase so it is inaccessible to any other application. Likewise, don’t build a service that only one application can use. Break it up, make test requesting a service. Make the applications, such as Welsh Clinical Portal, use that service. Don’t make any single application mandating for use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So then if we come along and want to get Amazon or Apple or Google to listen to our speech in clinic, to turn that speech into text and make a range of test requests based on that text, then don’t stop us doing that. Create something that enables that. Enable innovation and don’t suffocate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is another paradox here in that I keep repeating in this forum and others, that we don’t know all the stuff we need to solve. We need to look really hard at people who think that they have all of the answers, because they don’t. Getting everyone in a room, and listing the requirements, building a technical specification and building it like it was a bridge, is not the way to build software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be ambitious, be realistic. Have a vision and plan to deliver that vision incrementally at pace.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The paradox of ambition</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The paradox of control: Enabling innovation</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The paradox of control: Enabling innovation" /><published>2017-12-05T08:40:40+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-05T08:40:40+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/docs/dhss/publications/151211reporten.pdf&quot;&gt;Informed Health and Care Strategy, 2015&lt;/a&gt; sets out a clear vision for Wales to use digital technology and online services to support and enable care. The strategy is divided into four workstreams:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information for you&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supporting Professionals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improvement and Innovation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Planned Future&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.003.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.003&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivery of this vision would result in Wales uniquely blending socialised universal prudent healthcare with modern state-of-the-art technology to provide a responsive, fair and quality service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have to question whether we have the current organisational and governance structures within NHS Wales to most effectively implement this strategy? Historically, there has been a lack of pace in the delivery of individual projects that, together, should be incrementally fulfilling important components of the wider vision. Together, those individual projects should be stepping stones on which we deliver that vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wales is a unique place to deliver an effective healthcare information technology strategy given its size and our lack of purchaser-provider split and as a result, technology should be being used to effect broad-based transformational change. It is disappointing that we have not been able to make more progress but with the right changes, Wales can become a global example of a modern, forward-thinking healthcare economy underpinned by data standards, interoperability and an open platform to combine “Once for Wales” solutions with a mixed and thriving economy built on innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-paradox-of-control&quot;&gt;A paradox of control&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transformational change, enabled by technology, must be driven from the bottom-up, from those who deliver healthcare permitting incremental development and innovation while at the same time lowering risk. However, top-down governance must ensure that solutions are standards-compliant, fit-for-purpose and safe as well as checking that developments are not orthogonal to the overall strategic vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an important paradox in many health services, including Wales, is that there is a tendency to centralise the day-to-day management and delivery of individual products and yet high-level strategic and prioritisation decisions are decentralised, haphazard and dependant on capital funding with little or no consideration or control as to how those projects will fit into a wider technical healthcare enterprise architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;performance-management-and-delivery&quot;&gt;Performance management and delivery&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the responsibility of being part of “learning organisations” is to measure our effectiveness and performance, but do we really do that and how can we do that? What formal processes do we have to measure, for example, satisfaction with our clinical applications? Likewise, how is NHS Wales held to account in terms of performance management when delivering transformational change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should be asking the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who is responsible for determining and prioritising the high-level clinical requirements in each of the four workstreams in the strategy?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who is responsible for looking at the common themes between the workstreams and designing a national architecture that will enable delivery of those workstreams as well as giving consideration to future needs?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who is tasked with taking items of user-need and translating these needs into the design of software to meet those needs?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;who is responsible for developing an iterative roadmap that delivers incremental benefits at pace and yet can deliver increasing functionality over time?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we cannot answer those questions, then we have a duty to change our organisational, governance and technical structures so that we can all be held to account. Unfortunately, it is likely that the different organisations within complex multi-organisation enterprises such as NHS Wales will all attribute the failure of delivery to each other because delivery is dependent on so many interactions between so many levels of multiple, highly hierarchical organisations all with different models of funding and sometimes contradictory opinions on prioritisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear to me that we need to change our approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;collaboration-and-an-appropriate-technical-infrastructure&quot;&gt;Collaboration and an appropriate technical infrastructure&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, we need a new collaborative model in which a national open technical platform, adopting robust industry standards, underpins the development of national and local applications as well as supporting innovation from organisations both within the NHS and from the commercial sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a collaborative model must be underpinned by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the adoption of technical standards and open application programming interfaces&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a renewed focus on a health enterprise “platform” for Wales, underpinning by a re-imagining of our software architecture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encouraging the development and evaluation of innovative projects by all&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wales is a unique place to leverage modern information technology in order to deliver transformational change for our clinical services, providing important support for patients, clinicians and managers. With the right technical architecture and organisational structures, Wales can collaborate to safely deliver the Informed Health and Care Strategy and deliver tangible benefit for our citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must start to openly debate the most effective way of delivering that strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Informed Health and Care Strategy, 2015 sets out a clear vision for Wales to use digital technology and online services to support and enable care. The strategy is divided into four workstreams:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Serverless in healthcare</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/04/serverless.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Serverless in healthcare" /><published>2017-12-04T22:22:22+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-04T22:22:22+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/04/serverless</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/04/serverless.html">&lt;p&gt;On serverless:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Serverless computing allows users to run code without provisioning or managing any underlying system or application infrastructure, and they automatically scale to support increasing or decreasing loads. 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.gartner.com/andrew-lerner/2017/07/21/serverless-is-not-networkless/&quot;&gt;https://blogs.gartner.com/andrew-lerner/2017/07/21/serverless-is-not-networkless/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A serverless architecture forces an enterprise architectural design that modularises and isolates code. Rather than creating a full-stack enterprise application containing components for user interactions, business logic, business rules and a persistence layer, one can break-up a solution into its functional constituents isolated from one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A serverless function such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloudacademy.com/blog/microsoft-azure-functions-vs-google-cloud-functions-fight-for-serverless-cloud-domination-continues/&quot;&gt;AWS Lambda, Google Cloud Functions or Microsoft Azure Functions&lt;/a&gt; can be written and deployed virtually instantly, with the hosting provider automatically scaling to manage the load. Ideally, such a function should do one or a few things very well, perhaps offering a set of application programming interfaces for clients to use with clear documentation as to how it can be called and what results might be expected. As such, the function is isolated and can be tested in lots of ways to ensure that it provides the results it is contracted to provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, writing small, well-defined services that provide a limited range of function is a characteristic of any microservice. What makes a serverless approach different is that managing the deployment and scaling of that service is delegated to the hosting provider, such as Amazon, Google or Microsoft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, a rarely used operation may take up no computing resources until it is triggered by an event, such as a HTTP request. Rather than trying to implement all functionality into a single or clustered server, one can break-up that functionality into separate functions. For instance, rather than writing a service to accept uploaded image files, process them, create thumbnails and then serve them as a photo-album, one might write a range of individual separate serverless functions to handle each step of that process so that, the thumbnail generation is automatically executed after a file is uploaded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One then imagines an overall application being simply a range of different independent pieces of functionality stitched together in a declarative manner to solve a specific range of problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“This declarative approach then becomes a key driver of architecture. The application speaks the language of the domain and it’s easy to detect and fix force-fits, gaps, misrepresentations and erroneous assumptions in the application each time the implementation is reviewed against the domain. A declarative interface makes it easy to adapt to changes in the domain model.”
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pragatisoftware.com/blog/functional-programming-and-software-architecture&quot;&gt;http://www.pragatisoftware.com/blog/functional-programming-and-software-architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Functional programs are often organized as, sort of, a data flow graph, rather than a dependency structure. There’s declarative orchestration, right,? You just set up a whole bunch of things and you can see how they are related but you don’t have to, sort of, specify the order in which things happen, and you have referential transparency, right? I hand two values to a function, it will always give me the same value as the output because of referential transparency.”
&lt;a href=&quot;https://serverless.com/blog/bobby-calderwood-functional-programming-microservices-emit-2017/&quot;&gt;https://serverless.com/blog/bobby-calderwood-functional-programming-microservices-emit-2017/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, one is forced to focus on two core perspectives: an &lt;em&gt;overall&lt;/em&gt; perspective that takes in the combined architecture in which multiple microservices are stitched together and a &lt;em&gt;granular&lt;/em&gt; perspective at the level of an individual microservice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;healthcare-takes-steps-into-the-cloud&quot;&gt;Healthcare takes steps into the cloud…&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many, if not most, health services still run applications on local servers physically sitting on their premises, running on a private intranet inaccessible to the outside world running the day-to-day organisational processes of the business and usually providing clinical information to clinicians as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But things are changing, many years after most industries have made extensive use of cloud-based services, we are now seeing health organisations move to host servers on commodity cloud providers, resulting in a hybrid approach in which some services run locally and others run elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, rather than buying software and installing it for local users, we are starting to see organisations starting to procure platforms-as-a-service (PAAS) in which cloud-based services are used within the enterprise. For instance, in most modern organisations, a previously private intranet is increasingly having new communication channels laid down in order to enable interaction with patients and their devices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, some providers now use PAAS-based patient portals such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patientsknowbest.com/&quot;&gt;Patients Know Best&lt;/a&gt; to enable patients to view their records. Such portals are also committing to opening up their data so that patients can choose to share their information with other providers;  for instance have a look at their &lt;a href=&quot;http://dev.patientsknowbest.com/home/fhir-api&quot;&gt;plans for a FHIR API&lt;/a&gt;). Likewise, other cloud-hosted services such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://drdoctor.co.uk/&quot;&gt;DrDoctor&lt;/a&gt; permit organisations to manage their outpatients by providing a platform on which patients can be contacted ahead of appointments to provide reminders and to collect outcome data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we already see health organisations making use of cloud-based services for hosting their own infrastructure and by using ready made large-scale off-the-shelf services from other providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; have a distributed healthcare platform; it is hosted by our organisations and unfortunately is usually disconnected so that clinical staff in one organisation cannot see health information about their patients from another organisation. Presently, we see healthcare making tentative steps to either move to or adopt cloud hosted services, but these usually remain organisationally-bound.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;in-parallel-healthcare-is-changing&quot;&gt;In parallel, healthcare is changing…&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parallel with these technological changes, we see a range of &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;disruptive influences in healthcare&lt;/a&gt; highlighting three core changes enabled by new technology:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changes in models of care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patients as active participants&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;‘Hospitals without walls’&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, advances in technology enable a transformation of care. We should look to information technology to re-imagine how citizens interact with their health services. I spoke at a recent &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Digital Health and Care Conference on the benefits of an open platform&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, I highlighted the importance of modelling data &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#data-modelling&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and workflow/process &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#process-modelling&quot;&gt;b&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. It has been a source of surprise and frustration that so many efforts to digitise healthcare neglect communication between professionals and with the patient, particularly when information technology has been used so effectively for communication in other domains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my phase 1 vision of an appropriate enterprise architecture for NHS Wales:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/platform/platform-overall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Platform Overall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See that little box, “test requesting and results”. This is what is inside it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/platform/platform-lab.png&quot; alt=&quot;Platform Lab&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we abstract a new notification service that handles notifications to users such as professionals in response to a result being made available by the laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is this phase 1? Because I see the building blocks of our  architecture becoming increasingly distributed and shared among healthcare providers. Why embed a terminology service within an application when one can pick one off the shelf and use on a subscription or pay-as-you-go model?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-could-the-shift-to-a-services-based-economy-mean-for-health&quot;&gt;So what could the shift to a services-based economy mean for health?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A microservice economy means that multiple providers will offer small-scale, well-defined software functionality on a pay-as-you-go basis. We heard an announcement last week from Amazon launching their new &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/aws/aws-serverless-app-repo/&quot;&gt;AWS serverless application repository&lt;/a&gt; to enable a new marketplace of serverless apps that can be consumed by clients in order to solve real-life problems. I expect other providers to do the same, and there is ongoing work to create &lt;a href=&quot;https://serverless.com/&quot;&gt;toolkits&lt;/a&gt; that permit serverless applications to be hosted by any cloud provider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These technological trends mean that we will see large software applications and platforms being broken up into modules and as we progress, we will stitch together functionality from multiple providers to order to create clinical applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we combine these trends with a need to support cross-organisational working, to make patients “active participants in their care” and create “hospitals without walls”, we can see that we are moving to a distributed, decentralised, data-driven and cloud-hosting mixed environment combining functionality from multiple providers in order to create and run our health services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could see core services providing data access and basic workflow models for each organisation but we will increasingly wish to federate across those services, creating a combined view of all data from multiple organisations. For example, an organisation may own or rent a document repository, probably based on IHE-XDS or FHIR document model and because other organisations also converge on standards-based open services then, subject to citizen consent, those repositories can be federated so we see a list of documents across all repositories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, we could quickly see a marketplace of value-added functions that provide functionality layered upon those core services. For example, we might find a market for advanced natural language processing of unstructured text or services that encapsulate the application of machine learning algorithms to existing and new data. For example, why not rent a service that can, given a citizen’s distributed health record data, identify those taking a particular disease modifying treatment such as methotrexate and monitor and arrange the required three-monthly blood tests to check for signs of bone marrow suppression, renal impairment or liver damage? If that service was provided algorithmically as a microservice, given access to the required data and cost a fraction of a pence per patient, it could replace the administrators and specialist nursing staff whose job it currently is to monitor these patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;healthcare-application-sandboxes&quot;&gt;Healthcare application sandboxes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to see how some serverless resources might work. They may simply provide a HL7 FHIR resource endpoint and allow applications to use its application programming interface as if it were hosted locally. Imagine a distributed audit trail functionality, made available via the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/auditevent.html&quot;&gt;HL7 FHIR AuditEvent endpoint&lt;/a&gt;. FHIR servers can support one or many different types of resource and it is not difficult to imagine a single serverless application providing a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/capabilitystatement.html&quot;&gt;capability statement&lt;/a&gt; documenting only a single end-point and providing that functionality in an automatically scalable fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a model would be fine for a single organisation, but how can that work in a distributed fashion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we need to create a distributed platform that means that we can plug-and-play these different microservices and make them useful to the wider health economy. To do that, we must design a sandbox environment in which user facing applications running on desktops, web-pages and mobile devices and backend serverless applications can be dropped and expect to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much like Apple has “app stores” for mobile and desktop applications and Google has similar for Android, we need to consider what architecture is required for user-facing and serverless applications to be deployed easily and quickly into our distributed healthcare economy. Amazon has introduced the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/about-aws/whats-new/2016/11/introducing-the-aws-serverless-application-model/&quot;&gt;AWS Serverless Application Model&lt;/a&gt; which annotates a serverless application with information about its dependent resource types needed for its proper operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how could this work for our methotrexate monitoring example serverless application? It needs to be provided with a sane runtime environment from which it can safely access the information it needs and to take any actions that are necessary. So what does it need access to?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a test results service to get results including renal profile, full blood count and liver function tests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a test requesting service&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a document or clinical narrative repository&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a audit event logging service&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In software engineering, we frequently use a concept called &lt;em&gt;dependency injection&lt;/em&gt; to pass through dependencies to a subsystem so that we can configure it appropriately and appropriately isolate separate functionality. As such, much like the AWS Serverless application model referenced above, we need to consider how we glue together sensitive health data with different services, perhaps provided by multiple different vendors?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that all the functionality our serverless application needs is provided by HL7 FHIR resource endpoints (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/diagnosticreport.html&quot;&gt;diagnostic reports&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/procedurerequest.html&quot;&gt;procedure request&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/fhir/documentreference.html&quot;&gt;documents&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/auditevent.html&quot;&gt;audit&lt;/a&gt;), it might be possible to simply pass in those endpoints as dependencies either when the service is provisioned or even when it is called.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now the logical question becomes, how do we manage looking up and accessing resources across a distributed health enterprise, particularly when we are dealing with sensitive private data?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wrote in the &lt;a href=&quot;[next post](/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html)&quot;&gt;part three of my disruptive influences series&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Applications running on Apple’s iOS provide a useful analogy. In order to gain access to components of the underlying device and its operating system, such as the camera, the photo archive, location services etc, the application must use the appropriate API which forces explicit user consent. This “sandbox” environment means that an application is prevented from accessing resources to which consent has not been provided and presumably can log each and every attempt should that be required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Can we do the same for health applications and services? It seems to me that we can create tremendous value from healthcare data - for patients, for health professionals and for society - but the foundation must be to allow that information to be organised in such a way that we can make it “universally accessible and useful” &lt;em&gt;subject to individual consent&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to our distributed future, built declaratively to glue together distributed data and services, is underpinned by a robust model of citizen consent that itself is hardwired into the systems to manage resource lookup and access. We now need to start thinking about how this will work, and how a “healthcare application model” might operate so that we can make use of new technology to improve the care of our patients. We need to start talking about how an “API gateway” might work for healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;data-modelling&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;: Data modelling ensures that we create semantically interoperable data coded in such a way as to make it meaningful to multiple disparate units of software. Such data may represent all types of clinical information, such as a blood pressure measured with a traditional sphygmomanometer on the right arm or the result of a laboratory test. As such, a focus on data standards is important so that there is agreement as to how individual items are coded and contextual information can be understood, such as who performed the measurement, how it was done and when.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;process-modelling&quot;&gt;b&lt;/a&gt;: While a prospective clinical record of structured and unstructured information forms our medical record, the medical record does much more than simply record a narrative of events. Our medical records &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; our clinical practice, enabling processes and workflow. Paper medical records have important properties in enabling workflow; &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/hazards-of-paper.html&quot;&gt;their presence on my desk with a post-it note tells to do something vital&lt;/a&gt;. It is therefore important to conceptualise not only a model of healthcare data but also model the workflow, processes and communications that enable care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information.html&quot;&gt;Organise healthcare information and make it universally accessible and useful&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;Disruptive influences in healthcare information technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/hazards-of-paper.html&quot;&gt;The hazards of paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">On serverless:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Data-driven healthcare: integration</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Data-driven healthcare: integration" /><published>2017-10-19T23:22:22+01:00</published><updated>2017-10-19T23:22:22+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html">&lt;p&gt;This post is from a talk I gave at the inaugural Digital Health and Care Conference at the Principality Stadium in Cardiff, Wales on the 19th October 2017&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.001.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Introduction&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am going to talk about being data-driven in healthcare - how we need to create an architecture that enables us to capture and use data to improve patient care and our clinical services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want us to develop an open platform for healthcare in Wales built on a foundation of standards and interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to remember three things, the three “P”s - platform, patient and preparation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.002.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Platform, Patient, Preparation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By “platform”, I mean a collection of interoperating computing services built using industry standards a) on which we can build multiple applications for clinicians, patients and managers and b) provides a single consistent and logical patient record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By “patient”, I mean that we need to re-focus our work on our patients : and avoid simply digitising our old ways of working but instead make use of digital tools to support all citizens to interact with and contribute to their records and importantly, help them manage their own healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And finally, by “preparation”, I mean that we need to create systems now that support solving our current problems but does not limit future development and innovation. We need to develop an infrastructure that fosters innovation in a safe way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/topics/health/nhswales/about/e-health/?lang=en&quot;&gt;Informed Health and Care strategy&lt;/a&gt;, as you all know, is split into four key themes, focused on the patient, the professional, our services and our future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.003.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.001&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially for patients, the requirements boil down to enabling patients to monitor and manage their own health, accessing, contributing to and controlling their own data. This patient focus is important and is essentially a disruptive influence on how our clinical services should develop in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For professionals, we essentially want access to the right information at the right time, information that reduces uncertainty about the decisions we make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, we are responsible for multiple cohorts of patients across our clinical services and need to ensure that we configure those services appropriately and permit innovation in service design and research and development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, we need to build systems - and I use that word in as loose fashion as possible - that support working in partnership - in collaboration to drive up quality and performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would argue that the solution to these requirements is not to jump to developing multiple software applications  but instead to develop a widespread recognition that DATA is at the heart of those aims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.004.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.001&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is DATA that tells us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what happened,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what is happening now&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;why it happened and even, if we get it right…&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and what will happen…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is DATA that drives our work and digitisation of that data - historically on paper - means that we can do it at scale and in real-time -  it is analysis of renal function blood tests that should prompt a real-time notification that our patient is deteriorating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the question is how to successfully digitise healthcare?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time thinking about what “the medical record” actually means and I can’t express it better than the late Larry Weed, the founder of the problem-based medical record, who said, in his Internal medicine grand rounds:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You’re a victim of it or a triumph because of it. The human mind simply cannot carry all the information without error so the record becomes part of your practice”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.005.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.001&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course by medical record, I am not talking about an application running on a desktop computer, on an app on a mobile device: I’m talking about the logical medical record comprising all of the information that supports our decision making. It’s the data - the medical record that counts, and not the applications that we use to access that record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;joined-up-thinking&quot;&gt;Joined-up thinking&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think our biggest failure in healthcare IT is to create artificial boundaries between data : for example, in 2001, The Bristol Heart Enquiry highlighted the consequences of separating administrative and clinical data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The various clinical systems, many of them paper based, 
differed from one another and had no relationship with the administrative hospital-wide systems. The funding made available in the late 1980s and early 1990s for medical and later clinical audit helped to reinforce this separation by making available to groups of clinicians money for small local computer systems. The lack of any connection between these different systems, one administrative, the others clinical, for collecting data cannot be explained solely on the basis of some technical or technological reason. It was just as strongly a reflection of a mindset that clinical matters were the sole domain of clinicians and non-clinical matters, to do with the management of resources and with the movement of patients into and through the hospital, were the preserve of managers and administrators.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.006.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.001&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must stop thinking about administrative systems, clinical systems and research systems, and instead, focus on data - on the patient and the varying types of longitudinal data that are collected - by the patient, their devices and the professionals involved in their care. Of course, different people have need to see those data in different ways - different perspectives - different prisms, but the data - the  patient record - that is key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;start-with-problems&quot;&gt;Start with problems&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I recommend starting with PROBLEMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.007.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.001&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problems define your requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Show me all of my upcoming appointments. I have multiple chronic conditions and need to organise my life.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Should I say ‘yes’ to this high risk treatment?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Show me how a patient with multiple sclerosis is doing compared to their peers. Do I need to give more aggressive treatment?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“I know how many patients are seen in outpatients, but I don’t know why or indeed, how they fare.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Which of our patients are suitable for this trial? Find me patients with drug-refractory epilepsy who have not tried lamotrigine and are keen on research?”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“How can we work together collaboratively?”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, what are the informatics challenges facing us in solving “show me all of my upcoming appointments”, particularly if we need to solve that across multiple organisations? We need to integrate data from across multiple PAS - and provide a unified view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should prioritise our requirements and consider the data requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how can we help patients come to decisions about a high-risk treatment? How can we understand our outpatient services without setting in motion systems to track clinical problems and diagnoses in a structured way rather than free text?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we make Wales the best place for IT, for collaboration?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My thesis is: we think about the data required to solve those problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So given our problems, what kinds of data must we capture and link together to make them meaningful? I feel strongly that understanding  cohorts of patients - grouped by disease or clinical problem or intervention or contact with a specific service - these underpin the interpretation of all other data. For example, how can we interpret patient reported outcomes without understanding all of those issues? Information has to be linked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.008.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.008&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so essentially, we stop thinking about applications and think instead about the patient record, combining administrative, clinical records - including GP and hospital records, laboratory and other sources of information - into a logical longitudinal record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And when we start thinking about a patient record, we must consider how we link disparate pieces of information together to solve our problems. We must stop creating data silos with information unusable outside of where it is collected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an abstraction of a logical longitudinal record:
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.009.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Logical longitudinal record&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps an example would be useful. Here is a screenshot from my own clinical information system that is currently used to look after over 25,000 patients in Wales and records 4,500 clinical encounters every month for a range of neurological and non-neurological diseases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.010.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;EDSS graph for patient plotted over time compared to peers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This chart shows the progress of a single patient  marked with a red line against the progression of the disease in all patients with multiple sclerosis in South East Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How did we do this? The chart is generated in real-time using analysis of all patient data taking to into account diagnosis and disease progression recorded by patients and clinicians. In clinic we find it useful to also see charted the  medications received by the patient - you can see that they have had alemtuzumab and methylprednisolone and also their exacerbations in their disease - marked with an “R” - for relapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now have years of longitudinal data for a wide range of cohorts of patients such as multiple sclerosis, motor neurone disease and Parkinson’s disease and real-time analytics and clinically-useful dashboards form an important part of making it &lt;em&gt;worth&lt;/em&gt; entering information. It is no good having either professionals or patients enter data or use devices to collect data unless we use that data for decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;snomed-ct&quot;&gt;SNOMED-CT&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important aspects of our work must be to support the collection of data by clinicians for clinicians in the day-to-day work. One important technology is SNOMED-CT a comprehensive terminology that supports the entry of structured clinical information coded in a computer-readable format. This is a KEY enabler of data-driven clinical systems and analytics. Using this, we can record a patient has multiple sclerosis and firstly expect that other software will understand this diagnosis and secondly understand what type of disease that this is. SNOMED-CT is an ontology - it not only includes concepts but the relationships between them, so I can potentially find all patients with a demyelinating disease and it will support me finding patients with multiple sclerosis but also related conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cppjedy-hMo&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entering codes can be as simple as typing free text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With such a data-driven foundation, it becomes straightforward to build useful dashboards that take data from multiple systems and multiple sources and presents them in a useful fashion for end-users. Here we have a dashboard bringing together important information about a patient with motor neurone disease:
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.012.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.011&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we must ensure our patients can engage fully…. in the Parkinson’s disease clinic we have successfully trialled the use of iPads to connect to the EPR and allow them to contribute to their medical record via adaptive questionnaires. Here is a view of all patient data from a single clinic visit that is used to generate our clinic letter automatically. Each of these outcomes can be graphed to show changes over time.
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.013.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.011&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;scaling&quot;&gt;Scaling&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how can we take what we’ve done and scale it to every other clinical encounter in Wales? The problem is that “We don’t realise how much we don’t know”. I am sure that there are some clever people who can take my Parkinson’s disease medication and disease progression data and turn it into something even more useful, who can then link it to home monitoring technology and falls detection and send our team alerts when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we design or implement software that solves our problems today and adopts a sufficiently flexible approach that we can innovate and adapt to solve the problems of our future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.014.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;We don't realise how much we don't know&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you haven’t read it, I recommend Domain-driven design by Eric Evans - a focus on data modelling to support complex systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We start with a model of our data; this model will change but slowly over time — a blood pressure measured in the right arm will always be a blood pressure measured in the right arm. On top of this information model, we build conceptual models of workflow and process, a platform made up of core services providing access to those models and finally lightweight applications. Process and workflow models will change much more frequently that our data model and likely need dynamic customisation via rules engines for different contexts. Applications should be the most ephemeral component of our designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;an-open-innovation-platform&quot;&gt;An open innovation platform&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.015.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Open innovation platform&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, we create an &lt;em&gt;open innovation platform&lt;/em&gt; built on a secure foundation of structured, semantically meaningful data. We provide a range of core application programming interfaces or APIs - providing access to a range of useful services such as identity, access and consent. Together, these form a platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must stop thinking about applications and instead think about how our platform can interact with our work streams - our patients, our professionals, our partners and the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.016.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.016&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most businesses have already realised that information technology forms an inherent part of their operations; in essence, they have realised IT &lt;em&gt;IS&lt;/em&gt; their way of doing business. It is about time healthcare did the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the model becomes a data-centric core, open platforms exposing those data and multiple lightweight applications solving specific process and workflow problems for patients and professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.017.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.017&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, we create a single patient record : and ensure that we can see all of the relevant information for a patient while not getting lost in an excess of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is how it could look in Wales:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.018.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.018&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We open up our core services, create a platform leveraging new technologies such as HL7 FHIR to expose application programming interfaces that can be used by multiple applications providing different views and different perspectives on a single patient record or collections of those records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[ explain diagram ]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must focus on data standards and interoperability, creating lightweight applications at pace and design useful real-time analytics services for clinicians and managers. Critically, we build a platform that can provide the building blocks for future innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.019.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.019&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in summary, I remind you to remember three “P”s : we need to build an open platform, ensure we focus on our patients and… prepare for and permit future innovation by understanding that we don’t have all of the answers… at least - not yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information.html&quot;&gt;Organise healthcare information and make it universally accessible and useful&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;Disruptive influences in healthcare information technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/hazards-of-paper.html&quot;&gt;The hazards of paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This post is from a talk I gave at the inaugural Digital Health and Care Conference at the Principality Stadium in Cardiff, Wales on the 19th October 2017</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The ‘fractal’ medical record</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/medical-records/2017/10/08/the-broken-medical-record.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 'fractal' medical record" /><published>2017-10-08T04:14:15+01:00</published><updated>2017-10-08T04:14:15+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/medical-records/2017/10/08/the-broken-medical-record</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/medical-records/2017/10/08/the-broken-medical-record.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fractal/mandelbrot.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Mandelbrot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical data are complex and heterogeneous with individual patient records combining multiple disparate sources of information including :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;administrative data, scheduling and context (e.g. outpatient neurology clinic - movement disorders)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;patient reported outcome and experience measures  (e.g. “I can walk”, “he was rude”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clinical diagnostic, procedural and outcome measures    (e.g. “multiple sclerosis”)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;diagnostic synthesis and management plans  (e.g. “offer a new high-risk disease modifying treatment”)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between those categories, it is possible that we can answer the what, who, how and possibly the why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What many people don’t realise is that the interpretation of medical data, irrespective of its form, depends, to a variable degree on everything else. The most important dependency, in my view, is the context in which those data were acquired. This need for interpretation is why the phrase, “the single source of truth”, when used in building health record software, is only a partially useful mantra; it hopefully encourages a data-focused, clinical modelling approach but it inappropriately suggests that there is a “single truth”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you need to re-appraise how you consider, for example, “problem lists” - and understand that the meaning of “angina”, whether encoded as a consecutive array of letters of the alphabet (e.g. in English: “a-n-g-i-n-a” as free text) or encoded using a code from a medical terminology or classification system (e.g. in SNOMED-CT: Angina (disorder) SCTID: 194828000 with synonyms: Angina, Cardiac angina, Angina pectoris, Stenocardia,  Anginal syndrome, AP - Angina pectoris, Ischemic heart disease - angina, Ischaemic heart disease - angina,   Angina (disorder)) cannot be understood without contextual information, including the series of logical inferences that resulted in that diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, you should regard a diagnosis of “angina” with skepticism if it was given by me, a consultant neurologist but you might trust my diagnosis of “myasthenia gravis” even if the antibody test for that condition is negative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even data sourced from an accredited laboratory requires careful interpretation. A single test might be a false-negative result unless there is 100% sensitivity. Likewise, a positive test may be false-positive unless there is 100% specificity; either scenario would be extremely unusual indeed. In addition, tests, such as laboratory tests may be combined to improve their predictive power. It becomes even more complex as sensitivity and specificity depends on the &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; probability of that test in that population. As a result the interpretation of a test or combination of tests depends on the context in which those tests were performed. A positive test result performed as the result of screening a whole unselected population has less importance than a test performed in a patient suspected of having the disease in question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if a laboratory test does not perfectly predict a disease, we can easily see how more subjective, opinion-based tests and diagnostic processes such as radiology or getting a clinical opinion in an outpatient clinic, will suffer from the same issues. In particular, if a report changes (and they do) or clinical opinions vary (fairly common) then “truth” becomes a poor conceptual foundation for our electronic health systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logical conclusion  is that there is no single “truth”, but instead a deeply hierarchical, nested inter-dependent, frequently correlated set of multi-dimensional data. Does it matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;data-for-decision-making&quot;&gt;Data for decision-making&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve written about measurement &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/machine-learning-2.html&quot;&gt;previously&lt;/a&gt; concluding that medical data, whether a measurement of a physiological parameter, a laboratory test result or report from a radiological investigation, is useful only in &lt;em&gt;reducing the uncertainty around a decision&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we perform measurements, of whatever type, to support decision making and conceptually, those decisions may be grouped into three broad categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the direct care of that patient&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the care of groups of patients within our clinical service(s) and organisations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clinical research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we have measurements that don’t influence current or future decisions in any of these domains, then we must ask ourselves why are we performing and recording those measurements at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if we have imperfect measurements that are not 100% sensitive or 100% specific, then we have to ask, sensitive and specific to &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt;? Realising this provides an important insight: when applied, say to clinical diagnosis, is that almost all of our measurements in medicine are as if we are looking at the truth out of the corner of our eye. We cannot see the &lt;em&gt;hidden truth&lt;/em&gt; but a combination of our measurements are, together, governed by a few simpler variables or concepts that are actually the cause of the results of the measurements that we can measure. As a result, we hope that our measurements can be used to understand the &lt;em&gt;latent&lt;/em&gt; variable(s) that are actually the hidden cause of those measurements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, sometimes we get an elevated C-reactive protein (CRP) result. It is usually raised in certain types of inflammatory or infectious disorders. It is like the smoke from a fire in a forest, we see the smoke from our helicopter but do not necessarily the cause of the fire. If the patient has had a cough for three days and has a fever, and when we listen to the chest there are crepitations in the right lower zone and the CRP is raised, the diagnosis is likely to be a community-acquired pneumonia. We have to take into account the &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; probability as well, which means that we consider common causes more frequently than rare causes. Likewise, if the patient has had a cough for three months then we might reach a different conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, when we consider clinical diagnosis, our combination of multi-dimensional &lt;em&gt;measurements&lt;/em&gt; is providing us with a probabilistic determination of a specific considered diagnosis. Over time and with experience, most clinicians build up a set of heuristics that imperfectly approximate this diagnostic process and learn a range of practical short-cuts in order to cope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has always been a surprise to me that we have not yet developed tools to support this fundamentally complex and difficult problem; while we teach “red flags” to aid the identification of the unusual patient (e.g. a headache that is the worst ever headache), such decision-support aids remain crude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;nested-data&quot;&gt;Nested data&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we know a patient has a history of angina and presents with chest pain, understanding how and why that &lt;em&gt;label&lt;/em&gt; of “angina” was given is important. In fact, what does that label actually mean? Is it the diagnosis given by a consultant cardiologist or, inappropriately by a rather over-enthusiastic neurologist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re actually using the term “angina” to represent an approximate and subjective clinical concept as an abbreviation rather than endlessly writing down the multiple logical inferences made in order to determine that the patient suffered, for example, chest pain on exertion and had a stent placed for stenosis in her coronary circulation. It is a placeholder that actually hides a lot of potential complexity and permits professionals and patients to communicate and make decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fractal/angina-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Angina 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see that a constellation of information (our measurements, binary choices or continuous variables) allows us to apply a pragmatic diagnostic label, “angina”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except is that right? What is the point of that label unless it too is useful for future decision making? If I visit the catheter laboratory and ask my cardiology colleague for a coronary angiogram because a patient has “angina”, they’ll want to interrogate that diagnostic label in much greater detail to make a decision about whether a patient should have a specific intervention. They will want to know more than simply “angina”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our measurements and our labels are therefore interpretable and usable only in a specific context and for a specific set of circumstances in order to make a decision to effect care. Indeed, for future care, perhaps the diagnosis of “angina” is less useful than an understanding of pathology : ie whether the patient has significant arteriosclerotic vascular disease or not; after all, perhaps that is the biggest predictor of future cardiac events?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fractal/angina-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Angina 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; we use information when a patient presents to the emergency department with new crushing chest pain. Clinical decisions at the front door can simply use our placeholder diagnostic lists in order to action safe care and combine that historic information (that the patient has proven coronary artery disease) together with new information to make a diagnosis of acute myocardial infarction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;fractal-data&quot;&gt;Fractal data&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fractal/angina-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Angina 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now we see a repeated pattern in our data used for clinical decision making. Not only is our information nested, but we see that there are similarities in our data at different levels of detail. This repeating pattern of data at different levels of our decision making hierarchy is similar to that seen in &lt;em&gt;fractal data&lt;/em&gt;. In essence, a combination of measurements (data) are used to identify a hidden (latent) trait that itself is difficult to measure to inform a clinical reasoning process. The end-result of that clinical reasoning may be itself used in future clinical reasoning. This highlights the naturally &lt;em&gt;recursive&lt;/em&gt; nature of medical information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, an understanding of the hierarchical nature of clinical decision making allows us to consider the considerable redundancy and correlations seen between different covariates; for instance both having a drug-eluting coronary stent placed in 2014 and a diagnosis of unstable angina both flag an underlying (more difficult to measure) latent trait, namely that of arteriosclerotic coronary artery disease. Those characteristics are therefore highly correlated and may be redundant in a single patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;decision-making---by-humans-and-by-machines&quot;&gt;Decision making - by humans and by machines&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Redundancy and latent traits are important when we consider what information needs to be made available at the time of a clinical decision. How do we make sense of large volumes of hierarchical, highly correlated fractal-type data and decide what needs to be seen by a clinician in a particular clinical scenario, or indeed what needs to be used by a machine to learn to appropriately make a diagnosis or decide on a treatment plan? We cannot show or indeed use all information, and not all information is in fact useful at any particular clinical context. As such, we should be considering techniques to reduce the redundant dimensions that exist within healthcare data. For data mining and “big data” processing, we should be exploring dimensionality reduction techniques in order to make sense of an overload of redundant medical information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, we need clinical systems to appropriately model the clinical decision making process and understand that there is no single “truth” but a chain of clinical reasoning at a given point in time that should take into account any and all variables that influence the results of a clinical decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, this is where machine learning and more general purpose artificial intelligence can most help us in our day-to-day clinical work. We need tools to help us understand what our measurements, our data, actually mean and how, in combination, they hide latent variables that should truly determine our next clinical decision. Our knowledge of this fractal-type pattern of clinical decision making should inform how we can generate training data for machine learning and apply those algorithms in the real-world. We should be aiming to replace our informal human heuristics, those short-cuts we use to permit decision-making at a time of significant uncertainty and instead build a data-driven approach to clinical reasoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now have access to sufficient computing power to allow machine supported clinical decision making but those algorithms need to be trained. As such, we must study and understand clinical decision making, adequately model both clinical data and clinical reasoning and make those data available for machine learning so we can build the next generation of tools to improve medical care for all of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The term “fractal” was &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fractal&quot;&gt;coined by Mandelbrot&lt;/a&gt; who “based it on the Latin frāctus meaning ‘broken’ or ‘fractured’, and used it to extend the concept of theoretical fractional dimensions to geometric patterns in nature.” I’ve therefore titled this blog post “the broken medical record” for two different reasons: 1) medical records are broken and fragmented in the truest sense of those words, 2) they have similarities to fractal data as they are deeply hierarchical and nested with clinical reasoning built upon chains of previous reasoning (e.g. a process of clinical reasoning takes place in order to order an investigation, the radiologist reporting the scan performs her own reasoning based on the referral and the actual imaging, a receiving clinician repeats the process now integrating all of those chains of reasoning).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;(Mandelbrot generated by &lt;a href=&quot;//commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?title=User:Mjdean&amp;amp;action=edit&amp;amp;redlink=1&quot; class=&quot;new&quot; title=&quot;User:Mjdean (page does not exist)&quot;&gt;Michael James Dean&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;span class=&quot;int-own-work&quot; lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;Own work&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0&quot; title=&quot;Creative Commons Attribution-Share Alike 3.0&quot;&gt;CC BY-SA 3.0&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=17070006&quot;&gt;Link&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Information at the right time…</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/analytics/2017/09/29/information-at-the-right-time.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Information at the right time..." /><published>2017-09-29T20:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-09-29T20:18:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/analytics/2017/09/29/information-at-the-right-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/analytics/2017/09/29/information-at-the-right-time.html">&lt;p&gt;It is surprising how my interests have converged and supported one another over time: computing, technology and programming; data analysis, clinical medicine, neuroscience, clinical neurology and genetics; undergraduate assessments and psychometrics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I want to discuss the fundamental importance of data in clinical medicine and the overlap between direct care, service management and improvement and clinical research. The overlap and relationships between these three are shown in this schematic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cis_design/data_pipelines.png&quot; alt=&quot;Data Pipelines&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In clinical research, we have relatively small numbers of individuals with highly detailed information (“high level phenotypic data”). In day-to-day clinical practice, we have large numbers of patients with patchy or low level clinical data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common theme that runs through this blog is, I hope, that the &lt;a href=&quot;/cis-design/2017/05/01/medical-record.html&quot;&gt;medical record defines our clinical practice&lt;/a&gt;, and the foundation of that medical record is usable data… usable &lt;em&gt;information&lt;/em&gt;.  We use that information for direct care of individual patients, organising our services to support the care of groups of patients and to perform clinical research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;creating-a-data-driven-culture&quot;&gt;Creating a data-driven culture&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2005 I started using R (The R Project for Statistical Computing) for my statistical analysis during my doctorate. I’d been disappointed with SPSS and its point and click user interface and crude scripting language. As a researcher, I realised that I would need to run and re-run many different analyses and remembering how to transform and clean-up in preparation for configuring and then running different types of statistical test was going to be difficult and time-consuming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote about R on my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.medicalnerds.com/10-pieces-of-free-software-every-doctor-should-havean-introduction-to-r/&quot;&gt;old blog in 2007&lt;/a&gt; and since then, I have managed to convince many colleagues to adopt it for their own research. In 2005, I didn’t know anyone else using R (except the R-help mailing list) but it was immediately appealing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is a programming language, an environment for statistical computing and not simply an application to run statistical tests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it results in reproducibility. I can run the same analyses over and over again, for example when my data are updated&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is open-source&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own research involved clinical epidemiology, phenotype-genotype correlations, clinical genetics and psychometrics and, if you are very keen (and want to know a bit more about ataxia), you can &lt;a href=&quot;/images/wardle-2009-thesis.pdf&quot;&gt;read my thesis&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;deep-phenotyping&quot;&gt;Deep phenotyping&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a junior researcher, I quickly learnt the value of “deep phenotyping”, the importance of systematically recording the longitudinal morphology of disease for individual patients, aggregating those data for groups of similar patients and understanding the cohort by the use of those data. To do this, one needs to consider the hypotheses and ensure that the appropriate clinical data is captured and recorded in a format that allows those hypotheses to be tested. My project looked at clinical progression, rating scales, the use of wearables and genetics with the combination of different sources of data to make logical inferences about these patient groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clinical research requires compromise, intuition and judgement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how much data should be collected?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what will be important?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what can be collected in the timeframe?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how many patients do I need to assess in order to reach a valid conclusion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how will I record that data and in what format so that it is practical for storage, retrieval and analysis?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early on, we generated lots of ideas. For example, I gave up on the wearables project when we realised that patients were recording 0 steps in 24 hours, that the devices were too cumbersome and so were being left on the shelf rather than being worn. In those days, the technology was such that the wearable wasn’t actually very wearable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might have already concluded, none of these questions are unique to the specific neurological conditions I was interested in at the same and in fact are generic and widely applicable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;building-analytics&quot;&gt;Building analytics&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I built an analytics pipeline in which clinical and genetic data were extracted, cleaned up and transformed and analysed. This combined a database and used R to do the rest, generating analyses and charts based on those data. With Sweave, I combined those results into reports, clinical papers and eventually my thesis by linking R and LaTeX:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;We identified \Sexpr{nrow(subset(cl, excluded==F))} patients with a reported history of 
cerebellar ataxia between 1999 and 2007 in South East Wales.
Applying inclusion and exclusion criteria as described above resulted in a subset of 
\Sexpr{cf.loca$total} with chronic progressive \ac{loca} with no identified aetiology 
as a denominator population for study. There were \Sexpr{cf.loca$num.familial} 
(\Sexpr{nrow(subset(loca, fh==T &amp;amp; sex=='Male'))} male, 
\Sexpr{nrow(subset(loca, fh==T &amp;amp; sex=='Female'))} female)
familial cases segregating in \Sexpr{cf.loca$num.families} kindreds 
and \Sexpr{cf.loca$num.sporadic} 
(\Sexpr{nrow(subset(loca, fh==F &amp;amp; sex=='Male'))} male, 
\Sexpr{nrow(subset(loca, fh==F &amp;amp; sex=='Female'))} female)
sporadic patients.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When run, this would output the following text:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;We identified 401 patients with a reported history of cerebellar ataxia between 1999 
and 2007 in South East Wales. Applying inclusion and exclusion criteria as described 
above resulted in a subset of 178 with chronic progressive LOCA with no identified 
aetiology as a denominator population for study. There were 55 (26 male, 29 female) 
familial cases segregating in 38 kindreds and 123 (79 male, 44 female) sporadic patients.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But of course, much more sophisticated analyses were possible, including the dynamic generation of charts, maps and statistics. For example, this chart is dynamically generated from our data source&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/data-driven/sca-prevalence.png&quot; alt=&quot;Sca Prevalence&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;generated using the following code:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;\begin{figure}[!tb]
% This is the same as the ACNR graph, but using the (NEW) new SCA prevalence functions
&amp;lt;&amp;lt;sca-prev-adca, echo=FALSE, quiet=T, fig=T,width=6,height=4&amp;gt;&amp;gt;=
sp = sp.sca.prev(subset=patient.type=='ADCA' &amp;amp; total&amp;gt;10 &amp;amp; (region=='Asia' | region=='Europe' ), by=region, FUN=sp.percentage)
barplot(as.matrix(sp[,c(2:7,12)]), beside=T,
		xlab='Disease', ylab='Percentage of families', 
        main=&quot;&quot;, 		#  Ethnic differences in SCA subtype frequency&quot;,
        legend.text=c(
		    paste('Asia   (n=',sp[sp$region=='Asia',]$total,')',sep=&quot;&quot;),
		    paste('Europe (n=',sp[sp$region=='Europe',]$total,')',sep=&quot;&quot;)))
@
\caption[Aggregated data showing ethnic differences in SCA subtype frequency among families with ADCA.]{Aggregated data showing ethnic differences in SCA subtype frequency among families with ADCA. Data from Table~\ref{tab:sca.prev.adca}.}
% \cite{\Sexpr{print.citations(sp$cite)}}
\label{fig:sca.prev}
\end{figure}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sp.sca.prev() function source code is &lt;a href=&quot;/images/data-driven/sp-sca-prev.R&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, all of my papers and my thesis were built automatically whenever I wanted, simply by running &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;make&lt;/code&gt; that would run a series of steps in a &lt;a href=&quot;/images/data-driven/Makefile&quot;&gt;Makefile&lt;/a&gt;. Consequently, I could identify any obvious errors in data entry quickly and ensure they were fixed as well as build analyses based on interim data with the confidence that they could be run again and again as data were added. I did all the work in LaTeX, R and used subversion as a version control system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-different-lenses-same-data&quot;&gt;So what? Different lenses, same data&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve been discussing data warehouses, data lakes and analytic pipelines within NHS Wales. Some of us are pushing for an “open platform” based on a foundation of structured data recorded in using open standards and integrating a range of new and legacy services and systems via an API-approach (API - application programming interface) while others think we should be getting on with developing applications and thinking about interoperability later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My clinical colleagues want the right information about the patient in front of them, irrespective of organisational boundaries, so that clinical information recorded by other teams in different organisations, or even in different countries, is available at the point-of-care. We are overloaded by information, and this will increase (particularly given recent and ongoing &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;disruptive influences&lt;/a&gt;) so we need the right tools to make sense of that information. Presently, much of the administrative data is computerised but most clinical data exists only on paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My more senior clinical and managerial colleagues want to understand more about how our services perform and how can they be improved. They want to aggregate individual patient data and prepare data to inform decisions across our organisations and need to feed much of that information to other authorities as part of central returns. As only administrative data are routinely digitised, most analytics are focused on administrative matters, so we might &lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/06/06/using-data-patient-safety.html&quot;&gt;know how many people were seen, but not really have an idea as to why&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My academic colleagues want to recruit patients into clinical research and capture data in a much more systematic and structured way and use that information to study and publish and inform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer to all three requirements is, of course, &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we may need to include much more detail for our research projects, I cannot stress the importance of the systematic and routine collection of outcome data in normal clinical practice for direct clinical care and management of our services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;adopting-a-data-driven-clinical-practice&quot;&gt;Adopting a data-driven clinical practice&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/22/health-data.html&quot;&gt;I wrote previously&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We should be focusing on &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; first, as &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; as the solution to a &lt;em&gt;problem&lt;/em&gt;. Data, structured, understandable, semantically interoperable data are the foundation on which clinical applications and our analytics can run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what was wrong with my research analytics pipeline? Although at the end of it I could run and re-run it and get almost immediate results, my data were not stored in a standardised format and my code can’t easily be picked up and used by others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be done differently: storing structured, informative and useful clinical data recorded by patients and health professionals; combining data from multiple sources to add value to information and creating learning adaptive systems that support our work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example I have used before, in which I present a dashboard on which the important information for a patient with motor neurone disease is aggregated in a single view. The determination as to whether the patient has a gastrostomy (or other kinds nutritional support) is a sequential look at the record of procedures performed (insertions and removal of gastrostomy tubes):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mnd-dashboard.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mnd Dashboard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That dashboard took me about 10 minutes of work to write as all of the important information was already being collected in a sequence of clinical encounters by my colleagues from palliative care, speech and language, dietetics, specialist nurses and neurologists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-power-of-aggregation&quot;&gt;The power of aggregation…&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EDSS is the expanded disability scale score, a relatively easy-to-use scale running from 0 to 10 that is used as a clinical indicator of disability. Health professionals can record it but we can also derive the score directly from patients using my iPad application:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/N3PQ2EEQNt4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following dynamically generated chart shows a single patient’s disease course over time compared to every single other patient we know with multiple sclerosis or a type of that disease:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/edss-graph.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Edss Graph&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The single patient’s course is shown by the red line, with relapses (acute deteriorations) marked with an “R”. The dotted lines are like the centile lines on a baby’s growth chart: from disease onset, the median disability for the whole cohort is shown. At a glance, we can then see whether an individual patient is deteriorating more quickly than expected or is more disabled that their peers and helps us to tailor their treatments appropriately. In patients with aggressive disease, we might choose to use more aggressive treatments with a greater risk of side-effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SQL code that identifies all patients with any type of multiple sclerosis, tracks their progress and aggregates the disability data is &lt;a href=&quot;/images/data-driven/msss-edss.sql&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;iteration&quot;&gt;Iteration&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we don’t stop there. We continue to build statistical models to track disease progression, combining different outcome measures and their proxies to try to understand the disease. As a result, our work will never be done; we can generate new models of disease progression that better predict deterioration and must embed that work into our day-to-day clinical practice. As such, we should aim for a virtuous cycle of continuous improvement, embedding clinical research into our day-to-day clinical practice in a similar way to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.isixsigma.com/dictionary/dmaic/&quot;&gt;Six Sigma quality initiative&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cis_design/dmaic.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dmaic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning is a useful addition to our analytics platform. We can already use standard survival analysis to identify the factors that are important in predicting survival and subsequently build a heuristic to help us in our clinical decision making. New technology offers us hope to improve those models and to speed up the iterative cycle to build continuously adaptive and learning systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a schematic representing how I think we need to create an open platform for healthcare in Wales:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/platform/platform-overall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Platform Overall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this schematic, the platform represents a range of APIs providing access to a unified aggregated view of a single patient record, but the other definition of a “platform” is of a multisided market:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Interestingly, another definition of a “platform” is a set of services that bring together users and providers to form a multisided market. Is it possible then to take our “open platform” and start to think of a future in which we have products and services that actually do enable a re-imagining of healthcare provision to bring together patients, carers, health professionals, commissioners, analytics, researchers and all other stakeholders in a safe and secure manner?  (see &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html&quot;&gt;a previous blog post&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment, our health platforms, if they exist, are lopsided asymmetric systems in which patients play little or no role. We must start thinking about creating a data-driven architecture that corrects this asymmetry in power and control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all cases, the foundation of that work is data. Technology is the enabler; it can release the value from our data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">It is surprising how my interests have converged and supported one another over time: computing, technology and programming; data analysis, clinical medicine, neuroscience, clinical neurology and genetics; undergraduate assessments and psychometrics.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Privacy and Artificial intelligence</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/09/06/privacy-ai.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Privacy and Artificial intelligence" /><published>2017-09-06T20:18:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-09-06T20:18:00+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/09/06/privacy-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/09/06/privacy-ai.html">&lt;p&gt;I recently contributed to a &lt;a href=&quot;wired uk ai privacy&quot;&gt;Wired UK article on privacy and healthcare&lt;/a&gt;. Here is my full response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;should-we-worry-about-big-dataaimachine-learning-in-healthcare&quot;&gt;Should we worry about ‘Big Data’/AI/machine learning in healthcare?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, the two main concerns relate to privacy and value: fundamentally, privacy simply relates to the risk to individuals of sharing information about those individuals and value relates to the intrinsic worth of that data as well as the value of any algorithms or software produced as a result of analysis of that data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to explore the privacy concerns without clarifying what we mean by data and how it is already used, particularly as privacy depends fundamentally on the purpose to which the data is processed and by whom. For example, in medical settings, you might expect me as your neurologist to have access to your relevant medical information from other healthcare professionals, such as reports, documents and the results of investigations such as scans and laboratory investigations. Currently, most such data is held by NHS organisations or commercial companies operated for and behalf of those healthcare providers. There are, therefore, already many current situations in which selected data is shared externally with healthcare, social care and commercial entities. Such data are used for direct care of individual patients and for managing our clinical services. Likewise, there are already many situations in which routine NHS data is combined and de-identified in some way and made available for research such as the CPRD (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cprd.com/home/&quot;&gt;https://www.cprd.com/home/&lt;/a&gt;) and SAIL (&lt;a href=&quot;https://saildatabank.com&quot;&gt;https://saildatabank.com&lt;/a&gt;). Such systems usually try to remove obviously identifiable information such as name and date of birth and instead generate categorical variables (e.g. year of birth) to try to obfuscate the identify of individuals. Have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://understandingpatientdata.org.uk/what-does-anonymised-mean&quot;&gt;https://understandingpatientdata.org.uk/what-does-anonymised-mean&lt;/a&gt; in relation to de-identified, anonymous and pseudonymous data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there is not a discontinuity between identifiable and non-identifiable information but instead a spectrum running from low to high risk of re-identification. This risk increases as more and more data are made available and this is where the concept of “big data” results in privacy concerns. You may not be able to identify me from only knowing I’m a neurologist, but if you know I work in Wales and have an interest in information technology then you’re likely to know it’s me. As a result, “big data” in which large amounts of different types of data are made available and aggregated can undermine techniques to de-identify that data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next question is, does sharing identifiable or re-identifiable data matter? In general, the answer depends on who is doing the processing and the consequences, benefits and risks from that processing. People naturally have different expectations for the usage of data depending on whether it is for direct care, for clinical research, for a perceived “greater-good” or for commercial means. The care.data fiasco demonstrated the strong public concern relating to the release of information to commercial such as the insurance industry (e.g. see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/feb/28/care-data-is-in-chaos&quot;&gt;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2014/feb/28/care-data-is-in-chaos&lt;/a&gt;). Fundamentally therefore, this means that we need strong and appropriate legal and regulatory frameworks to ensure that we take advantage of the enormous opportunities inherent in combining these sources of data with modern technology to improve patient care and clinical research. The new GDPR legislation extends the rights of individuals to control the purposes to which their information is used, and we in healthcare must take these changes into account when considering “big data” and machine learning. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/data-protection-reform/overview-of-the-gdpr/&quot;&gt;https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/data-protection-reform/overview-of-the-gdpr/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the issue of “value” depends on who gains that value. If an algorithm is developed that can, for example, screen a chest x-ray to determine whether it is normal or abnormal, with only the latter images needing formal radiologist review, then there would a huge interest across the world in commercialising that technology and free up valuable time for radiologists. Who should own that technology? The services providing the data or the technology companies who have built the systems to learn from that data? For me, this should be a partnership between health and technology as both need each other in order to make progress to potentially improve patient care. As a result, I’d always expect explicit clauses relating to intellectual property rights to be included in data sharing agreements in which software and algorithms may be of commercial value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-other-privacy-protectingenhancing-technologies-are-there&quot;&gt;What other privacy-protecting/enhancing technologies are there?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like “Understanding patient data” : see &lt;a href=&quot;https://understandingpatientdata.org.uk/how-data-kept-safe&quot;&gt;https://understandingpatientdata.org.uk/how-data-kept-safe&lt;/a&gt; and its explanations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, it is necessary to have a mixed set of strategies as there is no single “magic bullet” that magically preserves or enhances privacy.  Instead, we need a combination of appropriate legal and regulatory frameworks (as I mentioned above), independent review and audit, formal software specifications and methodologies and, most importantly, a conversation with everyone about the benefits and risks of the use of patient data to improve care, now and in the future. As part of that national debate, we must determine the scenarios in which different levels of consent are required, such as an explicit opt-in for clinical research or an opt-out for other uses. At the same time, we must increase general public awareness about the benefits and risks of the wider use of health information. Ideally, data should be de-identified as much as possible for the specific use-case in question so that we instead start to talk about “risk of re-identification” and it is likely that different levels of risk will be acceptable for different use-cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are additional technologies to add into the mix such as “differential privacy” (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Differential_privacy&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Differential_privacy&lt;/a&gt; for more information) which introduce randomness into aggregated data in order to reduce the risk of re-identification and yet preserve conclusions made from the use of that data. Another interesting research development has been homomorphic encryption allows information such as private medical data to be encrypted and subsequently processed without needing decryption. Have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homomorphic_encryption&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homomorphic_encryption&lt;/a&gt; but such technology is, as far as I am aware, at a very early stage as it is extremely computationally-intensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;are-we-considering-privacy-enough&quot;&gt;Are we considering privacy enough?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Probably not!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health data becomes even more complex when one considers the ever increasing use of new technologies in healthcare. I have written about these in my “disruptive technologies” blog post (see &lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&lt;/a&gt;) and in particular, how we deal with data from multiple sources such as devices carried by the patient or installed in the home. As a result, there will be an increasing number of &lt;em&gt;“attack surfaces”&lt;/em&gt; in which confidential medical information may be leaked. For instance, how will we deal with the data sent from a device designed to monitor an elderly patient and check for falls, or whether they have left their home, or their activity? How will we ensure that only the right people receive that information?   The same issues apply to medical and health applications aimed at consumers which may leak confidential medical information. There are many examples unfortunately - see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4419898/&quot;&gt;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4419898/&lt;/a&gt;  for just some of the examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A useful resource is the “privacy-by-design” page from the ICO: see &lt;a href=&quot;https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-data-protection/privacy-by-design/&quot;&gt;https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/guide-to-data-protection/privacy-by-design/&lt;/a&gt; in which organisations undertake a privacy impact assessment to reduce potential harm to patients. Such tools are only useful when they are used, so the concept of sandboxes is also important, particularly for mobile device “apps”. For example, on most mobile devices, an application must request permission to access contacts, the camera or onboard health data and checks of those permissions are not a function of the application to implement (or not) but a function instead of the sandbox in which the application runs and all data access can be logged. So I think device manufacturers have a role in checking and verifying applications in their app stores and programmes like NHS digital’s app store (see https://apps.beta.nhs.uk) add an additional layer of inspection and curation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t add much more to what Dame Fiona Caldicott said : &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/national-data-guardian-ndg-statement-on-government-response-to-the-ndg-review&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/government/news/national-data-guardian-ndg-statement-on-government-response-to-the-ndg-review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main conclusion is that there is no single answer but a combination of solutions :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;give people choice,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;engender public trust by
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;appropriate regulatory and legislative frameworks,&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;adopting appropriate technical safeguards and de-identify information at a level that minimises re-identification risk and satisfies the specific requirements for analytics on that occasion,&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;using verifiable logs to ensure access to confidential information is logged and capable of inspection.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical data is terrifically valuable, powerful and offers tremendous scope to do good, but we also have a great responsibility to protect those data and ensure access is safe, secure and transparent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best wishes,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I recently contributed to a Wired UK article on privacy and healthcare. Here is my full response.</summary></entry></feed>