<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.wardle.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.wardle.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-03-30T22:56:15+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/</id><title type="html">Health informatics and information technology</title><subtitle>by Dr Mark Wardle, Consultant Neurologist, clinical informatics and software developer. Founder, Eldrix Ltd.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Where is the value?</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/30/where-is-the-value.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Where is the value?" /><published>2018-03-30T13:12:12+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-30T13:12:12+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/30/where-is-the-value</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/30/where-is-the-value.html">&lt;p&gt;Why is digital technology so important for the future of our healthcare services?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we consider how we can most effectively use digital technology in healthcare, It is easy to fall into a trap and simply support existing models and processes of care. Instead, we must raise our ambitions and look to digital technology to enable new ways to transform our health services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we mustn’t only limit our transformation agenda to only using digital channels to enable new ways of delivering care either. Fundamentally, we should be looking to digital tools to improve healthcare to provide &lt;em&gt;better outcomes for the populations that we serve&lt;/em&gt;. It is easy to lose sight of this ultimate aim: &lt;em&gt;outcomes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, we need to embed &lt;em&gt;digital thinking&lt;/em&gt; across all facets of our health services; digital is more than simply using technology but broad-based fundamental change which, at its core, means we focus on the data to become &lt;em&gt;data-driven&lt;/em&gt;, and what are we driven to do? We must be driven to improve outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means we need to create structured, meaningful data that will provide the foundation on which we create added value. Meaningful data means data that can be used for making decisions, reducing the uncertainty inherent in any decision. That decision may be whether to recommend a particular treatment for a specific patient, it might decide where your emergency medical team needs to intervene with a deteriorating patient on a ward in a hospital but it might also be used to inform us how and why we need to reconfigure or restructure our health services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, our healthcare digital transformation agenda must, like many other enterprises, invest in data analytical capability and, consequently, in computing power to help us store, retrieve and make sense of burgeoning amounts of data. We must make data the bedrock of our health enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, healthcare has always used data to inform practice. This is the basis of evidence-based medicine, but the cycle of clinical research from data collection, analysis, intervention and assessment can be too slow and usually, data collection has been designed specifically for that trial in a carefully selected population of patients. We use a similar approach with service transformation and quality improvement but fully embracing digital should mean that we improve the efficiency and effectiveness of our quality improvement interventions and embed those process in day-to-day care; the important difference is the use of systematically and routinely collected real-life data on process and outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cis_design/dmaic.png&quot; alt=&quot;Quality improvement lifecycle - define, measure, analyse, improve, control&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, such analytics should run in real-time, providing us continuously updated information about the patients and services for whom we care. The logical conclusion is that we will see a convergence of ‘business analytics’ with our electronic health records built on a single source of “truth”: meaningful data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do we enable data-driven digital transformation? In my view, it is with open data standards, open application programming interfaces and citizen engagement with transparency and control over the use of data. Together, those pieces fit together to form a ‘platform’ onto which other valuable services and applications can be built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open data standards, open protocols and open application programming interfaces are powerful disruptive technological advances which cause creative disruptive and commodification in an industry. We are about to see the result of this in healthcare. But what is creative destruction?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;creative-destruction&quot;&gt;Creative destruction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is useful to examine how ‘value’ in technological terms evolves over the years as it helps to understand and perhaps predict what might happen in the coming years. To do so, we must look at how new technology has evolved and disrupted the technological advances of the previous generation as part of a continuous cycle of &lt;em&gt;creative destruction&lt;/em&gt; and commodification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A commodity refers to goods or services which have value but are &lt;em&gt;fungible&lt;/em&gt;; that is, it doesn’t really matter who produces or provides that commodity, essentially they are interchangeable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In software, the creative destruction cycle can result in the commodification of technology. For example, historically, computing networking protocols were proprietary resulting in networking that was both expensive and incompatible with other proprietary network systems. The open networking protocol (TCP/IP) has disrupted the marketplace for proprietary networking; we now regard networking as a commodity on which most of our modern information technology solutions are built. Networking itself has permitted worldwide communication and collaboration permitting new ways of working, new approaches to distributed software development and ‘open source’ technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the world’s most valuable companies have arisen due to near ubiquitous personal networking; commoditisation can create a new market far larger than that achieved than when the same technology was proprietary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current software technology such as cloud computing, in which applications and services can be provisioned and scaled on demand by a hosting provider, are the end result of this continuous cycle of innovation and commoditisation. Indeed, with container and serverless technology, we see the hosting providers becoming increasingly fungible. But what do these providers gain from making their services a commodity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-where-is-the-value&quot;&gt;So where is the ‘value’?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; in creative destruction and commoditisation derives from building valuable innovative products in the new markets created by those processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As cloud computing becomes more ubiquitous, healthcare enterprises will increasingly switch away from purchasing and installed software locally and instead make use of software-as-a-service. We can see the beginnings of this in non-health markets already with the advent of marketplaces like &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/serverless/serverlessrepo/&quot;&gt;Amazon’s Serverless Application Repository&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/compute/monetize-your-apis-in-aws-marketplace-using-api-gateway/&quot;&gt;AWS Marketplace / API gateway&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this mean for healthcare information technology? What will happen if as we build open systems, open standards and open application programming interfaces creating an &lt;em&gt;open platform&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will see a commodification of that platform and we will enable an ecosystem of innovation products that can use that platform to add value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Interestingly, another definition of a “platform” is a set of services that bring together users and providers to form a multisided market. Is it possible then to take our “open platform” and start to think of a future in which we have products and services that actually do enable a re-imagining of healthcare provision to bring together patients, carers, health professionals, commissioners, analytics, researchers and all other stakeholders in a safe and secure manner?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html&quot;&gt;Disruptive influences, the future.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it likely that the technology giants, such as Amazon, Apple, Google and Microsoft, already recognise the value in creating a new multi-sided marketplace for healthcare by the use of open standards and commodification of a platform. We already see how Apple has worked to permit patient access to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2018/03/doctors-put-patients-in-charge-with-apples-health-records-feature/&quot;&gt;medical records via the use of HL7 FHIR&lt;/a&gt;, Google has &lt;a href=&quot;https://healthitanalytics.com/news/google-using-fhir-deep-learning-for-healthcare-predictive-analytics&quot;&gt;embraced HL7 FHIR for predictive analytics and machine learning&lt;/a&gt; and launched a new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalhealth.net/2018/03/google-launches-cloud-healthcare-api/&quot;&gt;cloud application programming interface to manage DICOM and HL7 FHIR data&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Google Cloud’s goal for healthcare is very much a reflection of Google’s overall mission: to organize the world’s information and make it universally accessible and useful. Applying this mission to healthcare means using open standards to help enable data sharing and interactive collaboration, while also providing a secure platform. Just imagine if all healthcare providers could easily, securely and instantaneously collaborate while caring for you. Ultimately, we hope that better flow of data will inspire new discoveries with artificial intelligence (AI) and machine learning (ML), leading to insights that improve patient outcomes.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Google Cloud blog, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.google/topics/google-cloud/google-cloud-healthcare-new-apis-customers-partners-and-security-updates/&quot;&gt;https://blog.google/topics/google-cloud/google-cloud-healthcare-new-apis-customers-partners-and-security-updates/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must recognise that unlocking healthcare data opens up extraordinary potential advances and that, the use of open standards will enable a new generation of value-added data-driven services and applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal goal is to create the next generation of electronic patient record systems with the aim to improve outcomes, but I recognise that to do that, we must strive for a open, dynamic data-driven healthcare environment onto which we can build innovation and build value. And that doesn’t yet exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With ubiquitous computing power available on demand, we should be planning now on how we will build and evaluate and then deploy automated tools to triage, risk assess, interpret investigation, and support diagnosis and management as well as making use of new technology to aid redesigning our healthcare systems around patients and not organisations to, most importantly, improve outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to see a future in which the platform becomes an interchangeable commodity with innovation and differentiation occurring at a higher conceptual level of support for medical practice. Rather than simple data collection, our mission must be to imagine a future in which medical practice, which at its most fundamental is about clinical decision making, is supported by the most sophisticated tools possible to improve patient care.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This mission’s greatest risk is in the continued creation of data silos in which health information is locked away in proprietary systems. The answer is to create an open, extensible platform on which innovation can thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/15/embedding-data.html&quot;&gt;Embedding data in routine clinical practice, June 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Why is digital technology so important for the future of our healthcare services?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An open digital health platform: what we need to do next</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An open digital health platform: what we need to do next" /><published>2018-03-03T03:03:03+00:00</published><updated>2018-03-03T03:03:03+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is part three of a three-part series on why and how we should be building an open digital health platform in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-1.html&quot;&gt;Part one&lt;/a&gt; was a high-level overview of how standards and interoperability are critical in building a digital ecosystem. &lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-1.html&quot;&gt;Part two&lt;/a&gt; assessed our current messaging-based architecture and highlighted the benefits of an API-first enterprise architecture together with the new technologies that have facilitated the move to cloud computing in other industries. This part ties together these strands into a manifesto for phase 1 of building our open platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to change what we are doing in Wales. We have two important reports that have criticised how healthcare information technology has been delivered - the Welsh Audit Office report and the Parliamentary Review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must ask hard questions about what we should do about the issues raised in the audit report including defects in governance and leadership, lack of delivery and concerns about the quality of information technology systems that are delivered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I believe that the only logical response to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wao.gov.uk/publication/informatics-systems-nhs-wales&quot;&gt;Welsh Audit Office report&lt;/a&gt; is to re-imagine the relationship between the NHS Wales Informatics Service (NWIS) and the health boards. Such a re-imagining requires us to stop ignoring the, in my view, currently incoherent set of responsibilities and divisions of labour that exist within Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;from my blog post, &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html&quot;&gt;“Focus focus focus”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, we need to focus our energy on creating an open platform onto which the next generation of applications, created internally and externally, can run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/docs/dhss/publications/180116reviewen.pdf&quot;&gt;Parliamentary Review of Health and Social Care report&lt;/a&gt;, published in January 2018 highlights the need for a seamless health and care system in Wales, centred around the citizen irrespective of where they live with the avoidance of creating artificial barriers between services and organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;from my blog post, &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges.html&quot;&gt;The challenges we face in delivering the vision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, our services must re-focus on our citizens to transform healthcare with digital tools enabling that transformation. As I have written before, &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html&quot;&gt;we need to enable innovation and invert the current paradox we have in command and control of our software systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to recognise the obstacles in our way, some of them non-technical:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Strategies focus resources, energy, and attention on some objectives rather than others. Unless
collective ruin is imminent, a change in strategy will make some people worse off. Hence there will be powerful 
forces opposed to almost any change in strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When organisations are unable to make new strategies - when people evade the work of choosing among different paths into the future - then you get vague mom-and-apple-pie goals that everyone can agree on. Such goals are direct evidence of leadership’s insufficient will or political power to make or enforce hard choices. Put differently, universal buy-in usually signals the absence of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Good Strategy, Bad strategy” by Richard Rumelt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to make use of our existing good work and build on that. We cannot afford to rip-and-replace, but plan, pragmatically and carefully, taking advantage of the new digital technologies available to us, to transform our health system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;we-must-build-an-evolutionary-architecture&quot;&gt;We must build an evolutionary architecture&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An evolutionary architecture is one that supports change, recognising we need, both figuratively and literally, platform on which we can build solutions to meet our current &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; future needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The principles to consider are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Plan for change at the outset&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build a cohesive vision&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create modular services cared for by cross-functional teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-plan-for-change-at-the-outset&quot;&gt;1. Plan for change at the outset&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most appropriate way to build an evolutionary architecture is to ensure that support for evolutionary change is built-in to your designs at the outset. This means recognising the components that are likely to change and those that are not. On many occasions, I have stressed the need for clinical modelling in which we think carefully about &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to create model data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A model is an abstraction of the real-world distilling knowledge into core concepts and processes. A model is a careful balance between complexity and over-simplification with models that are too complex model providing brittle abstractions which are poorly generalisable and models that are too simple model not supporting all of the demands placed upon it in real-life clinical scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;by me, &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html&quot;&gt;Towards a domain-driven, model-based approach to developing clinical information systems: innovating for the future in NHS Wales&lt;/a&gt;, November 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, essentially, underpins a data-driven approach in we consider data and the computing services that operate on those data as our platform onto which ephemeral and lightweight applications can be built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means that we leverage what we have already built in Wales and plan to build increasingly sophisticated functionality over time. As a result, we turn the existing ESB-based architecture into a more modern, API-based architecture in which data and services are made available to both internal and external users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-build-a-cohesive-vision&quot;&gt;2. Build a cohesive vision&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, the components which underpin our platform must be &lt;em&gt;cohesive&lt;/em&gt;. Cohesion means that the plan and the components that make up delivery of that plan form a cohesive and integrated plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A coherent plan to deliver the [Informed Health and Care strategy] needs more than a list of disconnected and incompatible goals but instead a clear understanding of what needs to be done and what doesn’t need to be done; we must know when to say “no”. Instead, we focus our limited resources on specific tangible actions and make some difficult decisions to prune areas of work that do not support delivery of the wider vision.
[…]
As such, we need a coordinated all-Wales approach that permits all stakeholders to work cooperatively and collaboratively with clear lines of responsibility and governance. We need to re-organise our approach to healthcare information technology taking into account the steps needed to deliver the vision, the principles of enterprise architectural design, modern information standards and interoperability, modern quality improvement methodology and user-centred design.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;by me, &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html&quot;&gt;Focus focus focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to build consensus around a cohesive plan to deliver the vision in the Informed Health and Care Strategy. This doesn’t mean getting everyone to agree, but requires political drive to make difficult decisions about what we can do with limited resources, taking into account our own strengths and weaknesses as public sector organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-create-modular-services-cared-for-by-cross-functional-teams&quot;&gt;3. Create modular services cared for by cross-functional teams&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest that you read the very helpful &lt;a href=&quot;https://apperta.org/_attachment/DefiningOpenPlatform/Apperta_Defining_an_Open_Platform_SP.pdf&quot;&gt;Apperta documents on “open platforms”&lt;/a&gt;. In it, they give a high-level overview of the typical ‘services’ which are required from an open platform. They suggest:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identity assurance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data repositories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Record location&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Resource discovery and scheduling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Knowledge sources&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Legacy connectors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are a useful starting point, but the most helpful chapters are 3 and 4 on why an open platform is a good idea for healthcare and their proposed definition of an open platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Wales, I would argue that we need a phased approach to make the best use of the good work already done. This could include in phase 1:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;User identity services
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wrap existing “NADEX” Windows (Kerberos) domain controllers into an &lt;a href=&quot;https://oauth.net/2/&quot;&gt;OAUTH2&lt;/a&gt; service that be used to authenticate and authorise healthcare users. Later phases should include federation of other authentication providers in non-health domains such as social care.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Citizen identity and delegation. We need to evaluate different options including &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/introducing-govuk-verify/introducing-govuk-verify&quot;&gt;GOV.UK VERIFY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Electronic staff record integration that, together with the user directory from NADEX, is exposed as a FHIR &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/practitioner.html&quot;&gt;Practitioner resource&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patient identity services
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wrap existing patient administration systems across Wales, the enterprise master patient index and the Welsh Demographic Service into a simple HL7 FHIR &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/patient.html&quot;&gt;Patient resource&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Results reporting and requesting services
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Wrap existing vendor neutral archive of results from the national laboratory information management system as a FHIR &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/diagnosticreport.html&quot;&gt;Diagnostic report resource&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/imagingstudy.html&quot;&gt;Imaging study resource&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Create new requesting service based on HL7 FHIR &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/procedurerequest.html&quot;&gt;ProcedureRequest resource&lt;/a&gt; which acts as a concierge handling and delegating multiple different types of request to our existing underlying laboratory and radiology systems.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;New e-Obs repository to include HL7 FHIR &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/observation.html&quot;&gt;Observation&lt;/a&gt; resource permitting storage and retrieval of observations such as pulse, blood pressure, temperature and weight and height.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Appointments and scheduling including providing federated read-only views initially across our multiple PAS and radiology services to provide &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/episodeofcare.html&quot;&gt;Episode of care resources&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/encounter.html&quot;&gt;Clinical encounters&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/appointment.html&quot;&gt;Appointments&lt;/a&gt;. Such a service could be used by professionals and citizens alike to see upcoming appointments for example.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A document repository, wrapping our existing national document repository (WCRS) but adding a more sophisticated metadata model to expose data as a HL7 FHIR &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/documents.html&quot;&gt;Document resource&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reference data services including the UK-wide organisational data services (ODS) to create FHIR endpoints including &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/organization.html&quot;&gt;Organisation&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/healthcareservice.html&quot;&gt;Service&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/location.html&quot;&gt;Location&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Centralised logging and audit services, exposing our existing national audit service as a FHIR &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/auditevent.html&quot;&gt;Audit event resource&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These services are shown in schematic form here, from my &lt;a href=&quot;(/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html)&quot;&gt;data-driven presentation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.018.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.018&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These would form a bare-bones set of services that could be used by a new generation of applications providing the right information for users at the right time, whether professional, citizen or their delegate. In line with an evolutionary approach, we need to recognise the challenges ahead including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A robust approach to citizen consent in order to control how and why their health data is shared.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need to start thinking about how &lt;a href=&quot;http://microservices.io/patterns/apigateway.html&quot;&gt;“API gateways”&lt;/a&gt; could be used across our health enterprise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To work with industry on how we can enable an ecosystem of healthcare software and real-time analytics that permit the safe use of independent software modules within the wider ecosystem. We probably need something much like the Amazon AWS Serverless Application Model I have referenced previously when discussing &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/04/serverless.html&quot;&gt;“Serverless in healthcare”&lt;/a&gt;.  For example, how can we safely make use of a cloud-hosted service that is the result of machine learning that can tell us whether a chest x-ray is normal or abnormal? How can we make use of a new acute kidney injury algorithm? What are the technical and legal requirements we must solve to do that?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To work to change our governance and funding models.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the latter point, we must recognise Conway’s Law:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“organizations which design systems … are constrained to produce designs which are copies of the communication structures of these organizations”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Conway, Melvin E. (April 1968), &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.melconway.com/Home/Conways_Law.html&quot;&gt;“How do Committees Invent?”&lt;/a&gt;, Datamation, 14 (5): 28–31&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must, therefore, change our governance structures in tandem with changing our software architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data driven healthcare information technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Strategy - focus, focus focus!&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html&quot;&gt;Part 1 : The importance of strategy : focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges.html&quot;&gt;Part 2 : The challenges we face in delivering the vision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-solutions.html&quot;&gt;Part 3 : Pragmatic solutions to those challenges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is part three of a three-part series on why and how we should be building an open digital health platform in Wales. Part one was a high-level overview of how standards and interoperability are critical in building a digital ecosystem. Part two assessed our current messaging-based architecture and highlighted the benefits of an API-first enterprise architecture together with the new technologies that have facilitated the move to cloud computing in other industries. This part ties together these strands into a manifesto for phase 1 of building our open platform.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An open digital health platform: an API-first approach</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An open digital health platform: an API-first approach" /><published>2018-03-03T03:03:03+00:00</published><updated>2018-03-03T03:03:03+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-2.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is part two of a three-part series on why and how we should be building an open digital health platform in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-1.html&quot;&gt;Part one&lt;/a&gt; was a high-level overview of how standards and interoperability are critical in building a digital ecosystem. This part assesses our current messaging-based architecture and highlights the benefits of an API-first enterprise architecture together with the new technologies that have facilitated the move to cloud computing in other industries. &lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3.html&quot;&gt;Part three&lt;/a&gt; ties together these strands into a manifesto for phase 1 of building our open platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what is the most effective overall enterprise architecture that facilitates modern interoperability and an ecosystem, as described in &lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-1.html&quot;&gt;part one&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any answer to that question must consider legacy systems already supporting clinical care within and between our organisations. There are many such services, such as patient administrative systems (eg HL7v2), laboratory information management systems, user identity and authentication and in Wales, we have an enterprise service bus (ESB)-based messaging architecture linking them together. In addition, there are sometimes explicit, often implicit reference data and rules and heuristics built into each application and service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first consideration is whether those services and applications currently deployed can support both robust interoperability and our ecosystem project. The second consideration is, if they cannot, how can we most effectively use what we have to do so?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;can-our-current-architecture-support-interoperability-and-an-ecosystem&quot;&gt;Can our current architecture support interoperability and an ecosystem?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ESB-architecture is one example of an event-driven architecture connecting disparate software without tight-coupling. An ESB is the typical technology used in Service Orientated Architectures (SOA) most popular several years ago. For example, there are a set of services and applications already in Wales supporting the care of patients on dialysis units across Wales. These take a live real-time feed of messages of laboratory results and persisting those data into a repository for the care of those patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ESB has supported integration, but it has required work &lt;em&gt;for all parties&lt;/em&gt;, internal and external, to perform that integration. Normally, an ESB will adopt a standards-based messaging protocol and so data are sent within a data “envelope”, usually SOAP, reflecting the technology of the time. This solves interoperability from a technical standpoint, but semantic and legal interoperability are out-of-scope. The ESB is therefore a component of an event-driven SOA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an event-driven architecture, it can be difficult to handle long-running business processes and orchestrate workflow across services. In addition, while applications and services are disconnected, separated by the ESB, the overall architecture is much like a monolith, but with the added complexity of a distributed system with every component part of a larger stream of messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This makes testing individual components difficult with changes in one system resulting in difficult to predict consequences on other systems. A test environment might need to replicate the entire ecosystem making it more difficult to automate and have confidence that any component or the whole ‘system’ is deterministic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, an ESB is an &lt;em&gt;internal&lt;/em&gt; solution to enterprise architecture integration. It is poorly suited to creating a truly open platform, although of course, can remain an important constituent part. We need to look elsewhere to see how technological trends could transform the way we build healthcare platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-can-we-learn-from-cloud-computing-and-modern-architectural-design&quot;&gt;What can we learn from cloud computing and modern architectural design?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen a revolution in both how data can be stored and how we can write software that operates on those data; we have &lt;em&gt;cloud computing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cloud computing brings together on-demand scalability and efficiency allowing organisations to consume storage and computing power to meet demand. Instead of running your own database in your own data centre, you can delegate its operation, backup and replication to a commercial supplier, normally on a pay-as-you-go basis. Example providers include Amazon AWS, Microsoft Azure and Google Cloud.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move to a cloud-based architecture has been predicated upon technological advances and new approaches to the design, creation, testing and deployment of modern applications. However, these advances are not necessarily limited to deployment to the cloud. Technologies such as “containers” can be used in local data centres as well. As such, software code can be built as lightweight portable services deployed in-house or to an external hosting provider anywhere. Indeed, this vendor-neutrality means that in essence we are moving to a future in which hosting data and software services is a commodity. As a result of this flexibility, many enterprises adopt a hybrid approach in which their existing infrastructure continues to run on private networks hosted in private data centres but these are supplemented with new services provided using containers, deployed either in-house or by a cloud provider or in combination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern application development and operations (such as testing and deployment into live environments) are called “DevOps” and support greater degrees of agility in all steps of the software lifecycle so that development becomes more modular, modules become more isolated and independently test-able, and changes to those modules can be committed, tested and even deployed with little or no manual intervention. We know that modern technology companies like Google deploy billions of containers per week across their cloud infrastructure; to do so requires automation in deployment and scaling to meet their ever-increasing demands for computing power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new type of cloud-based architecture - Serverless - is increasingly popular, recognising that application developers wish to focus on their core business of creating value via writing software and not be concerned about the infrastructure that is needed to run that software. Serverless allows developers to write a function, which could perform any imagined well-defined computing task, and deploy it easily. Such a function can be used by other software components but the provider is responsible for automatically scaling the service to meet demand, expanding or contracting the resources required to computing power responsive to user need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now seeing a new market for software code, in which re-usable independent modules of code, deployed as containers as “microservices” or as “serverless” functions, can be knitted together to create functionality for end-users.  These modules might look simple on the surface but hide (abstract) a great deal of complexity to deliver their results. Have a look at the speech recognition services now available from &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/transcribe/?hp=tile&amp;amp;so-exp=below&quot;&gt;Amazon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/speech/&quot;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;. Developers using those services simply send an audio file and receive back a text file containing the transcribed text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to see that such an architecture permits vendor-neutrality, in which we could substitute one service for another based on quality and price, with our changes limited to changing how we locate the resources used to knit together an end-to-end solution for our users. Substitutability is an important architectural principle for future-proofing and requires us to adopt standardised and open application programming interfaces (APIs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am convinced that we will see an increasingly sophisticated marketplace providing on-demand computing services in the next five years; for example, see the new &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/serverless/serverlessrepo/&quot;&gt;Amazon Serverless Application Repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we should recognise that cloud computing should inform our architectural designs for healthcare:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Virtually unlimited computing power on an as-required, scalable basis&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Openness, modularisation and abstraction of software to appropriately ‘decouple’ software and thus facilitating evolutionary change.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sophisticated support for “DevOps” in the develop-test-deploy software lifecycle with a focus on automation and rapid ‘agile’ development.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;an-api-first-approach-for-an-open-architecture&quot;&gt;An API-first approach for an open architecture&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not difficult to see how healthcare has lagged behind other industries in adopting a more “open” approach to information technology. Most healthcare software has traditionally been dominated by vendors who supply whole-organisation scale software products that are usually ‘closed’ systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open systems provide interoperability so that different components from different vendors can communicate and exchange meaningful information. In addition, open systems support &lt;em&gt;portability&lt;/em&gt; of applications and services. Portability means that software can be written once and deployed without change irrespective of the environment in which it is deployed. Portability requires standardisation and usually some form of runtime configuration and resource location. For example, to use a health example, if an application expects to use HL7 FHIR to fetch blood results and perform analytics, it should be possible to deploy that application within any ecosystem that provides those HL7 FHIR endpoints. These endpoints are what we mean by an standard “API”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is an “API”? An API is an &lt;em&gt;application programming interface&lt;/em&gt;. Crudely, it is a set of usually related software functions that, for our purposes, can be called by one system to execute software functionality in another. Essentially, an API is an abstraction, a way of decoupling how a software service is used from its implementation. In the example above, you do not need to know how Amazon or Google have implemented their speech transcription service, you send the text file and get back text. For all you know, they have thousands of transcriptionists sitting at computers listening with headphones and typing! In addition, you do not really care whether they change how they implement the transcription service, so long as you get back the results you expect. They could switch over to a new implementation and you wouldn’t know. The use of APIs has meant you have isolated different modules of software from each other and permitted work to continue independently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we might expect to be able to make use of a module to identify acute kidney injury (AKI). Currently, this could simply implement the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.england.nhs.uk/akiprogramme/aki-algorithm/&quot;&gt;national AKI algorithm&lt;/a&gt; but, could &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; be used to inform and develop the next-generation of algorithm that could perhaps identify patients &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; there is kidney injury and be &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; replaced with more sophisticated algorithms with different and hopefully improved receiver-operator curves for the patient group at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all APIs are “standard”. Proprietary APIs might allow interoperability but at the expense of new work, perhaps on both sides, to perform integration. Similarly, proprietary interfaces usually expose implementation details so that rather than being appropriately decoupled, the two separate software systems become entwined and dependent -  much like a limpet clinging to a rock than flexible and interchangeable plugs and sockets we all use for our electrical devices in the home!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A focus on open and standard APIs is key to creating a powerful ecosystem so that both internal and external developers can contribute and work independently. Our ecosystem project in Wales must not simply cater to external users but &lt;em&gt;be&lt;/em&gt; the platform on which new innovation can occur both internally and in partnership with others. This is a paradigm shift from the closed approach we have seen in healthcare in the past and treats external developers as first-class citizens in our digital health ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our efforts in Wales on standards, interoperability and the digital ecosystem must therefore build a ‘connected business platform’ usable by developers, internal and external, on behalf of users, across health and care and most importantly the patient and their delegates, to support a transformation in how we deliver healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;privacy-and-trust&quot;&gt;Privacy and trust&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important not to confuse “openness” with a lack of data security. Openness, at a principle in software architecture, relates to interoperability.  For example, TCP/IP, the technical underpinnings of the Internet, is an open protocol but that does not stop it being used by your bank to offer online banking to authorise and execute financial transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An open architecture does not mean that confidential patient information is made accessible to all. Any design for a target architecture for Wales must take into account the need for authentication (‘you are you say are’), authorisation (‘you are allowed to do what you are asking to do’) and verifiable logging (‘we are watching what you do’) as well as need to handle different levels of sensitive information. For example, it would be expected that sexual health, genomic, mental health and social care data might be treated differently to general health data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, not only might accessibility depend on the type of data, but the intended use of those data. For example, so that data made available for direct patient care might depend on the direct care relationship between citizen and professional while aggregated data for a clinical service or organisation used for planning and performance management and data made available to researchers would be handled quite differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to ensure privacy and trust when one uses as ‘push’ based messaging fabric like an ESB because data are sent to services who consume or decide to discard those messages. An API-based approach is usually a ‘pull’ service, in which a client requests something from a service and so a service can decide whether to satisfy that request by virtue of authentication and authorisation and can log such access via a logging service. Of course, an API-based approach can adapt to a ‘push’ model usually via ‘publish-and-subscribe’ in which interested clients subscribe to notifications from a service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-next&quot;&gt;So what next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next question to ask is, what are the next steps that we need to take to build an open platform in Wales using these architectural design principles? I have tried to answer this in my &lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3.html&quot;&gt;next post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3.html&quot;&gt;Part three&lt;/a&gt; ties together these strands into a manifesto for phase 1 of building our open platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is part two of a three-part series on why and how we should be building an open digital health platform in Wales. Part one was a high-level overview of how standards and interoperability are critical in building a digital ecosystem. This part assesses our current messaging-based architecture and highlights the benefits of an API-first enterprise architecture together with the new technologies that have facilitated the move to cloud computing in other industries. Part three ties together these strands into a manifesto for phase 1 of building our open platform.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An open digital health platform: standards and interoperability</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An open digital health platform: standards and interoperability" /><published>2018-03-03T03:03:03+00:00</published><updated>2018-03-03T03:03:03+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-1.html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;This is part one of a three-part series on why and how we should be building an open digital health platform in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This part is a high-level overview of how standards and interoperability are critical in building a digital ecosystem. &lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-2.html&quot;&gt;Part two&lt;/a&gt; assesses our current messaging-based architecture and highlights the benefits of an API-first enterprise architecture together with the new technologies that have facilitated the move to cloud computing in other industries. &lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3.html&quot;&gt;Part three&lt;/a&gt; ties together these strands into a manifesto for phase 1 of building our open platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I firmly believe that Wales has potential to be the best place in the World for digitally-enabled healthcare and innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we need to change what we have been doing. We need to move away from the single portal approach advocated by some and move to building an open platform, as I have &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;previously discussed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;standards-and-interoperability&quot;&gt;Standards and interoperability&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our “Once-for-Wales” task and finish group has finished its work and we have recommended a new Welsh Technical Standards Board (WTSB) be set up to define and mandate the technical and semantic standards for interoperability across our principality. We have recognised that there are many services and system functions, such as patient demographics and identity, that should be provided nationally for every citizen in Wales across all of our health and social care organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, we recognise that we must be able to exchange information with others, within Wales and without; including organisations outside of Wales. The latter is vital for patients who live on the border between Wales and England, and for those specialist service providers who care for patients from a different region. For instance, many specialist services in North Wales are provided from Liverpool, and we send patients from South Wales to either Bristol, Birmingham or London for highly specialist support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But information exchange is not simply limited to health. We need to communicate with and build workflows across multiple disciplinary ‘borders’ including social care, the third-sector, academic researchers and service planners. Such communications must be acceptable to citizens, requiring implicit or explicit consent depending on purpose and level of aggregation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people think we should write national one-size-fits-all applications and think about the interoperability aspects later. I would argue that interoperability is not something that can be “added later on” but must be designed at the outset, understanding that we must not only support technical interoperability but exchange semantically-meaningful information within a broader legal data sharing environment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Legal interoperability covers the broader environment of laws, policies, procedures and
cooperation agreements needed to allow the seamless exchange of information
between different organisations, regions and countries.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Semantic interoperability refers to the ability to ensure that the precise meaning of
exchanged information is unambiguously interpretable by any other system, service or
user.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Technical interoperability means the ability of two or more information and
communication technology applications, to accept data from each other and perform a
given task in an appropriate and satisfactory manner without the need for extra
operator intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ec.europa.eu/health//sites/health/files/ehealth/docs/ev_20121107_wd02_en.pdf&quot;&gt;eHealth Governance Initiative - Discussion paper on semantic and technical interoperability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The important standards that should underpin our new open platform are SNOMED CT and HL7-FHIR. I have covered both of these technologies at length previously including a &lt;a href=&quot;/cis-design/2017/05/02/data-standards.html&quot;&gt;simple overview in this post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;digital-ecosystems&quot;&gt;Digital ecosystems&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, many of us in Wales recognise the need to prioritise our limited resources and form partnerships with others. We cannot do everything ourselves and we should bring in partners who have strengths to complement our own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In keeping with this view, Welsh Government have funded a new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lifescienceshubwales.com/dhew/&quot;&gt;Digital Health Ecosystem&lt;/a&gt; bringing together the Life Sciences Hub in Cardiff with the NHS Wales Informatics Service to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;accelerate the delivery and adoption of the latest digital solutions to improve patient outcomes and reduce costs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;create a pathway for access to health and care data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;foster innovation from all stakeholders, encouraging cross sector cooperation and implementation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support the development of new products and services to drive business growth, job security and creation, ensuring prosperity for all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, we are starting the journey towards opening up our architecture in order to make it easier to work in partnership with others. We need to identify the strengths and weaknesses across both the public and private sectors and create an ecosystem that permits us to leverage the strengths of both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is, how can we build healthcare information technology architectures that can connect with external systems and data sources outside of our traditional walls?  It should not be surprising that robust interoperability is essential to delivering a working digital ecosystem in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, interoperability isn’t something to think about later, it should be &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; we build our systems today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next question to ask is, do we currently have an architecture that can enable robust interoperability and satisfy our ambitions for our digital health ecosystem, and if we don’t, then we must also ask what we need to do in order to do so? Some of the answers are in the &lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-2.html&quot;&gt;next post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-2.html&quot;&gt;Part two&lt;/a&gt; assesses our current messaging-based architecture and highlights the benefits of an API-first enterprise architecture together with the new technologies that have facilitated the move to cloud computing in other industries. &lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3.html&quot;&gt;Part three&lt;/a&gt; ties together these strands into a manifesto for phase 1 of building our open platform.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is part one of a three-part series on why and how we should be building an open digital health platform in Wales. This part is a high-level overview of how standards and interoperability are critical in building a digital ecosystem. Part two assesses our current messaging-based architecture and highlights the benefits of an API-first enterprise architecture together with the new technologies that have facilitated the move to cloud computing in other industries. Part three ties together these strands into a manifesto for phase 1 of building our open platform.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">So I built an electronic patient record system in my spare time…</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/patientcare/2018/02/19/so-I-built-an-EPR.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="So I built an electronic patient record system in my spare time..." /><published>2018-02-19T19:19:19+00:00</published><updated>2018-02-19T19:19:19+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/patientcare/2018/02/19/so-I-built-an-EPR</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/patientcare/2018/02/19/so-I-built-an-EPR.html">&lt;p&gt;This blog post is based on a series of threads I posted on Twitter, which I have refined and expanded for this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/1zZtnV44vgU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My electronic patient record system uses SNOMED-CT as its lingua-franca. Notice in the video how it maps free text into the UK dm+d (dictionary of medicines and devices), parsing dose route and directions and handling units and equivalence. It suggests a correction when I mistype salbutamol. There is a lot going on under the surface!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the entered term acetaminophen is switched to the preferred term, paracetamol. Doctors of a certain age will recognise that bendrofluazide was the term for the drug now known as bendroflumethiazide. Likewise, the doses, frequencies and routes are parsed from free-text into structured, coded, SNOMED-CT data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/so-i-wrote/medication-mapped.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Medication Mapped&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using that information, the software generates a permanent artefact of the consultation, combining human-viewable PDF with structured semantically-useful information for machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It calculates in real-time what medications have started, have stopped, are unchanged or have had a change made. If you start doing that, you can track medication changes over a long period of time and show them graphically. The software can calculate the total daily dose, understanding the dose, units and frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/so-i-wrote/medication-graphed.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Medication Graphed&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice how we can see how the doses have changed or started or stopped over time. For our patients with long-term health conditions, this is very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;structured-documents&quot;&gt;Structured documents&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t understand how some folk think about structured documents as simply documents with the same types of headings. To me, clinical documents should be structured so that they are useful to humans but also useful to machines. The headings and the information models needed are related but different. We have to make medical data understandable by both humans and machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For too long we have created documents from which we hope to derive data. Why not create documents from our data, instead?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here we record what botulinum toxin injections we have used and generate a letter that goes into the organisation’s document repository…. but we keep the data in a useful and structured format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3ekeblq9YEg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, if I record a patient’s specialist walking assessment then we can use SNOMED-CT as a useful, intermediary structure to allow semantic interoperability. Semantic interoperability means that software written by other people can derive meaning from the data that I exchange with it. Users don’t need to see this, but computers do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This form, viewable by the professional in the EPR, was populated by the patient entering their information into their iPad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/so-i-wrote/edss.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Edss&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for interoperability, behind-the-scenes, other software can understand what we’ve done, without necessarily having to understand the Kurtzke EDSS scale. They can, in essence, answer the question “Can this patient walk?” without difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a simple flat representation of the information from this encounter, recording diagnoses, treatments and outcomes. Even a flat representation allows us to later perform sophisticated searches such as, which patients are currently taking methotrexate. Similarly, I have exposed internal data as HL7 FHIR endpoints using the HAPI libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/so-i-wrote/snomed-intermediary.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Snomed Intermediary&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My document therefore consists of a PDF for human consumption and large amounts of structured and semantically useful data that can be processed for that individual or for a whole cohort of patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;cohorts&quot;&gt;Cohorts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Defining cohorts is important to me, based on service, diagnosis, problem, treatment, intervention or any arbitrary combination thereof. Understanding cohorts is a pre-requisite for understanding outcomes and value. See my previous blog post on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/8MCOn73pCZ&quot;&gt;importance of cohorts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most users have no idea that they are using SNOMED, if you do this right. Here we are entering country of birth, ethnicity and occupation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/so-i-wrote/background.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Background&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice how the countries are grouped as American, Asian and European. This isn’t hard-coded but instead I have set a single property to categorise each country-of-birth term by region in the SNOMED-CT hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Internally, I have built a range of different UI components that are configured declaratively to allow choice of SNOMED concept from different subsets or parts of the hierarchy. Here are the rules defining the country of birth pop-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/so-i-wrote/rule-engine.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Rule Engine&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Declarative architectures are extremely powerful and support building systems responsive to need. I can change most of the application’s behaviour at runtime by using an administrative portal and the rule engine. Most data collection forms are automatically generated from the underlying data model without any additional work for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Entering terms should be quicker than using free text. Try entering “MI” into my basic demonstration application - &lt;a href=&quot;https://msdata.org.uk/apps/WebObjects/SnomedBrowser.woa/&quot;&gt;https://msdata.org.uk/apps/WebObjects/SnomedBrowser.woa/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/so-i-wrote/snomed-search.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Snomed Search&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you give tools to professionals that make it easier to enter coded structured information than free-text, they will do so. Coding diagnoses, procedures and background information is critical in understanding outcome data; they are a foundation on which more complex and sophisticated analytics can be built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;patients&quot;&gt;Patients&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2015, I have been trialling the use of iPads to allow patients to directly contribute to their records. The obvious next step is to roll this out more fully and permit patients to use their own devices, rather than devices we lend them in the clinic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, a member of the clinic staff logs in and chooses a patient from the clinic list for the day. This is fetched by the iPad via the EPR to one of two PAS in Wales to which I have interfaced, depending on clinic context. For demonstration purposes, I have built a fake PAS so I don’t inadvertently share patient-identifiable information for these videos:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/NGbQIT5uFQ4&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The iPad is handed to the patient for them to complete. As the experience is locked to that patient, they cannot “go back” and look at the list of patients or see any information that they shouldn’t be able to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can configure what to show dynamically based on diagnosis, context and previous responses. I want to start showing the complete patient record at some point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here is it running in “Parkinson’s clinic” mode, showing different questionnaires adaptively. The important feature is that patient data is available immediately for the consultation for clinical care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/pAmaUXMu_bk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, most of the useful data goes into the automatically generated letter and is obviously available to be charted over time for that single patient, or aggregated later on for audit and research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/so-i-wrote/m4-epr-results.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;M4 Epr Results&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The patient is asked whether they wish to take part in research and then shown research projects and consent forms suitable to them, by virtue of applied inclusion and exclusion criteria, mainly using SNOMED-CT subsumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/so-i-wrote/m2-research-registration.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;M2 Research Registration&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is all configured at runtime obviously using my administrative portal. Here I edit the consent form interactively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/so-i-wrote/m5-epr-consent.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;M5 Epr Consent&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/so-i-wrote/m5-epr-edit-consent.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;M5 Epr Edit Consent&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And once I sign off that consent form, it is used immediately by all iPads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/KBLDA42TwzU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;technical-architecture&quot;&gt;Technical architecture&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have built it slowly and incrementally using PostgreSQL and java for the web-based application. This exposes an interface for humans via a web front-end and a range of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representational_state_transfer&quot;&gt;RESTful services&lt;/a&gt; for use by machines. I built the iOS applications in objective-C originally and then migrated to Swift for the current versions. These talk to the main EPR via HTTPS. The iOS applications use &lt;a href=&quot;http://researchkit.org/&quot;&gt;Apple’s ResearchKit framework&lt;/a&gt; to implement dynamic questionnaires and active tasks such as a finger tapping test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most important facets is the abstraction of multiple other external services, such as services provided by a hospital PAS (patient administrative system) and document repositories. While my software could be used standalone, it isn’t really designed to work like that and instead wants to interoperate with a broad set of external services. It wants to talk and exchange structured codified clinically-driven data with other systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much software is focused on a single organisation, but our multidisciplinary teams cross both disciplinary and organisation divides! Therefore, my application can be configured to interact with multiple external software systems to make the user experience more seamless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-has-this-taught-me&quot;&gt;What has this taught me?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefits of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Technical and semantic interoperability with the use of standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encapsulation and substitutability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Decoupling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coherent architectural design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the hard work has been in getting permission and then implementing technical interfaces to other systems. It would have been much easier for me to create valuable software if I had a set of tools and frameworks on which to build. This is reason why I am a advocate for an open platform approach in healthcare information technology so that we can build a stable infrastructure and yet still enable transformative innovation and embrace new digital technologies such as machine learning. I shouldn’t be wasting my time building the foundations of applications, but instead I should be able to leverage a suite of frameworks and tools on which hitherto unconsidered new and exciting functionality can be built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When any of us build an application for iOS or Android, we don’t start with nothing but have a suite of frameworks and tools to enable drag-and-drop user interface design, data persistence and cloud synchronisation. Why don’t we have the same for healthcare yet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My future plans are to break-up the application into a suite of interoperating microservices. I have already done that for my SNOMED-CT terminology engine, first of all as a java-based microservice and now one built using golang. As I do this, I rewrite my original application to make use of the standalone service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have written about the potential benefits of &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/04/serverless.html&quot;&gt;microservices and serverless architectures in healthcare previously&lt;/a&gt;), including the declarative nature of combining those services together by carefully considering how data flows between them in order to deliver value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need open architectures that interoperate, are standards-compliant and multi-layered. Foundational services, such as data persistence and core services like terminology should be used by more specialist and increasingly high-value functionality such as read-time analytics and aggregators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see a future in which those foundational services are provided via open-source tools and new commercial models evolve selling advanced services on a pay-as-you-go model. For example, would any of you want to take advantage of a disease-modifying treatment service that monitors your patients on drugs like methotrexate and orders blood tests when needed and lets you know when their blood counts drop?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to define a standards-based framework which means that we can not only deploy such innovative technology, but enable their assessment and evaluation in a safe way. One of the ways of enabling that are the principles of decoupling, encapsulation and substitutability, in which we can safely replace a modular component without other modules being aware. Only then can we enable safe technological-focused quality improvement and research, by running A-B testing in which different algorithms can be tested in isolation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such aspirations require a renewed focus on consent and in particular, making it possible to seek explicit opt-in consent in an easy way from citizens. Why not use technology to show informative video, interactive consent tools and start to recruit the majority of our patients into many different types of research project, obtaining robust and useful data on the effects of interventions, including the applied use of machine learning and algorithms, across our health systems?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can no longer think in terms of monolithic applications and think of interoperability as something to tack on after those applications are finished. Instead, we should focus on how we build an open platform to enable distributed applications and services and permit innovators to stitch together that functionality in novel ways to support and improve and re-imagine our healthcare services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This blog post is based on a series of threads I posted on Twitter, which I have refined and expanded for this post.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Focus : meeting the challenges</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-solutions.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Focus : meeting the challenges" /><published>2018-01-19T14:46:46+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-19T14:46:46+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-solutions</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-solutions.html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html&quot;&gt;part one of this series&lt;/a&gt;, I introduced the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/topics/health/nhswales/about/e-health/?lang=en&quot;&gt;“Informed health and care – A digital health and social care strategy for Wales”&lt;/a&gt; and talked in broad terms about the importance of a coherent strategy to deliver that vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges.html&quot;&gt;part two of this series&lt;/a&gt;, I attempted to articulate the challenges we face; concluding that essentially, we need to balance centralised planning and control with support for innovation and change, particularly given the new technologies on the horizon which offer the potential to transform how we configure and deliver care to our citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this part, I discuss some possible solutions to the obstacles we face including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adopting good information system design principles&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;focusing on process and workflow and user-centred design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;delivering an open enterprise health and care informatics platform&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;re-imagining the organisational structures and their responsibilities and governance in Wales&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prioritisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-do-we-meet-those-challenges&quot;&gt;How do we meet those challenges?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WAO rightly recommends deep clinical and managerial engagement and so suggests that NWIS and NHS bodies should work together to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“strengthen the relationship between developers and clinicians, particularly in designing and testing new systems and functions, so that there is a better collective understanding of what is wanted and what is possible; and [..] engage with managers to identify their information needs as well as the needs of clinicians.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I do not believe that this recommendation, or any of their other recommendations, to be sufficiently far-reaching to effect substantial change for NHS Wales IT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is helpful to review the UK &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/guidance/government-design-principles&quot;&gt;“Government Digital Service” design principles&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start with user needs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do less&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design with data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do the hard work to make it simple&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iterate, then iterate again&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is for everyone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand context&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build digital services, not websites&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be consistent, not uniform&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make things open: it makes things better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital transformation is complex and needs deep involvement of the whole service and not simply an “information technology project”. Indeed, to make the most effective use of information technology, that technology must be used hand-in-hand to enable service transformation. Few would argue that organisational change is rather more difficult to execute that deploying software and yet why is it that we expect a third-party organisation to parachute into another organisation and deliver change? It is therefore evident that successful healthcare information technology requires partnerships and collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, at a clinical design meeting on Friday, the implementation of an “outpatient administrative outcome form” was discussed. For background, we were shown the advanced end-to-end service transformation work at Abertawe Bro Morgannwg involving linking up multiple disparate systems to digitise the outpatient department. This work combined a commercial patient-call system with access to clinical documents, investigation results and tracking the workflow from patient arrival to their attendance for investigations or procedures. The striking conclusion must be that service transformation must be driven by local NHS organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would not matter if there were three or three-hundred clinicians in the room to design an “outpatient administrative outcome form”, if the scope of the challenge is limited to the design of a form and not the end-to-end service change for which it is but one component; clinical engagement does not fix the inherent design flaw or failure of limited project scope that does not factor into the end-to-end process re-design required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another major obstacle within NHS Wales is the existing current and legacy information technology solutions in place across different organisations and as a result, their varying priorities in relation to digital transformation. There is significant variation in digital maturity across different Welsh Health Boards. Such differences risk placing any national strategy, or indeed any organisation tasked with delivering that strategy such as NWIS, into an impossible situation trying to meet disparate or even opposing priorities or accommodating compromise in design or functionality. Such conflicting priorities result only in user dissatisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge then is to ensure that innovation of design, of process and of information technology in one part of Wales can be rapidly spread to other areas. Rapidly scaling out good practice requires information technology that can work in different environments with minimal change. If software is developed interfacing to bespoke or proprietary local systems, then it is necessarily much more difficult to deploy it in other environments. We cannot, for example, take the clinician portal (CWS) used in Aneurin Bevan Health Board and deploy it into Cardiff and Vale, despite the fact that it offers valuable clinical functionality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;delivering-an-open-standards-based-digital-health-platform-for-wales&quot;&gt;Delivering an open, standards-based digital health platform for Wales&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a technical architecture that can support all of this complexity, allow innovation and parallel working at pace and yet provide assurance and governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of you heard my talk on Data-driven Healthcare at the inaugural Digital Health and Care Conference in August 2017.  In it, I advocate for a standards-based, open computing platform built on data and services. From McKinsey:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Consider an open innovation platform that holds healthcare data, and provides data access that is enabled for application programming interfaces as well as common technical IT services such as identity, access, or consent management.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;McKinsey, January 2016&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, Gartner, 2016, developed the theme of a computing platform onto which digital businesses can be built, exposing services to customers (patients), employees (professionals), things (devices such as home monitors, wearables, mobile device applications etc) and partners (a digital ecosystem).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.016.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.016&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, “Once for Wales” should mean we focus on delivering a suite of data and software services that support a suite of lightweight user-facing applications. The whole system must be designed to be interconnected and consists of lots of small pieces each one “channel agnostic” and each re-usable, perhaps in ways hitherto not considered in order to innovate in the future. Data flows between these components via application programming interfaces (APIs).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my illustrative schematic in which we open up our core services, create a platform leveraging new technologies (such as HL7 FHIR) to expose application programming interfaces that can be used by multiple applications providing different views and different perspectives on a single patient record or collections of those records.  We must focus on data standards and interoperability, creating lightweight applications at pace and design useful real-time analytics services for clinicians and managers. Critically, we build a platform that can provide the building blocks for future innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.018.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.018&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Interestingly, another definition of a “platform” is a set of services that bring together users and providers to form a multisided market. Is it possible then to take our “open platform” and start to think of a future in which we have products and services that actually do enable a re-imagining of healthcare provision to bring together patients, carers, health professionals, commissioners, analytics, researchers and all other stakeholders in a safe and secure manner?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html&quot;&gt;disruptive influences in healthcare blog post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment, our health platforms, if they exist at all, are lopsided asymmetric systems in which patients play little or no role. We must start thinking about creating a data-driven architecture that corrects this asymmetry in power and control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/docs/dhss/publications/180116reviewen.pdf&quot;&gt;Parliamentary Review of Health and Social Care report&lt;/a&gt;, there is explicit recognition of needing to balance enabling nuanced local response and specialisation with a centrally dictated state unable to adequately adapt to need at pace. It suggests a need for a set of agreed national broad principles with appropriate central governance and local involvement. Those broad principles should be focused on data standards and software services with a clear set of application programming interfaces using which, we can build the next generation of innovative user-facing applications, whether for professionals or patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must recognise that cooperation and standardisation must be mandated for our core platform of national services, with data structures and application programming interfaces defined clearly to the benefit of all. Likewise, creating a layered architecture in which data persistence, business rules and logic and presentation layers are separate and linked by well-defined human and technological contracts, defining the interactions and the results that are to be expected, permits us to have different governance structures. As I wrote in the &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html&quot;&gt;5 O’s of healthcare IT&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Recognise the relative unchanging components and iterate and prototype the components that change more quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;How can we develop a “can-do” digital culture in healthcare? Should we clone the “Move fast and break things” culture reported in technological startups? Not really! We need to approach information technology in a different way but we can’t “break things”! We work in a safety-critical environment, but we must recognise that the pace of change and the level of risk can be different at different levels of our enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html&quot;&gt;The 5 O’s of healthcare IT&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;re-organising-healthcare-it-in-wales&quot;&gt;Re-organising healthcare IT in Wales&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A basic challenge we face is to match our clinical and administrative problems with technological opportunities including new ways of working that new technologies make possible. This challenge is particularly difficult because some of our day-to-day problems still have no straightforward technical solutions and many new technologies may impact on our provision of healthcare in ways that we cannot yet clearly articulate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To counter this challenge, we must accept that we do not have all of the answers and must build systems and software that can meet both current and future demands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, NWIS should be broken-up into functional units with clear lines of governance and focused responsibilities, with&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A platform group, responsible for core components of the “Once for Wales” health platform, providing data and services to professionals, the patient and third-parties with strong analytics support.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An applications group, providing lightweight building blocks of user-interface components which can be used by health organisations in conjunction with their existing resources.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A data standards and governance group, to oversee the platform and its design as well as provide governance and sign-off of permission to connect by both internal and external systems.   This group would contain WISB and WTSB and govern the performance of both the platform and applications group.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An infrastructure group&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current plan to deliver the strategy, created by NWIS, is focused on delivering a portal. This plan, in my opinion, is not fit-for-purpose and must be vigorously challenged. A portal approach, in which one plans a national portal through which all functionality is provided, risks creating a brittle top-down centralised design, needlessly limits innovation and does not take full advantage of the use of information technology to re-imagine and transform our clinical services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, NWIS should become a provider of a platform and a toolbox of components useful for building clinical applications that use open industry-standards such as HL7 FHIR and SNOMED-CT. The services and modules provided by the groups would be mandated by an all-Wales governance group on behalf of NHS Wales representing all stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we need to carefully balance decentralisation and ensure that no organisation is left behind. As such, centralised teams containing expertise in technology, user-experience and design should be made available to organisations to support their transformation programmes, leveraging our open platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;priorities---what-is-our-focus&quot;&gt;Priorities - what is our focus?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be surprised to hear that we still do not have access to clinical documents and investigation results across Wales. These two priorities must be delivered before any new projects are started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The platform team should focus, in the first year, on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exposing the Welsh Results Reporting Service (WRRS) as a national open service, ensuring all results are available across Wales irrespective of organisation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exposing the document service as a national open service.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building a national demographic service wrapping the existing eMPI and WDS/NSTS.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Creating a national pathway service, providing administrative support for tracking pathways across organisations and&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making the National Intelligent Integrated Audit Service (NIIAS) available as a service and at the service layer rather than only via specific applications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building a national test requesting concierge service handling investigation requests, whether laboratory or radiology, seamlessly by encapsulated lower-level systems such as RADIS and LIMS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should develop a range of key performance indicators for each core national service to include functionality and performance. For example, demographic services providing a unified wrap of the enterprise master patient index using a modern FHIR-based API might be expected to return results matching on &lt;em&gt;x&lt;/em&gt; demographic identifiers within &lt;em&gt;y&lt;/em&gt; microseconds. Breaking up an architecture into modular independent microservices permits automatic scaling and monitoring and simplifies testing which can be performed in isolation and automatically when software code is changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new website should be created, &lt;strong&gt;https://api.wales.nhs.uk&lt;/strong&gt; providing service documentation, code examples and governance procedures for each service as well as way for internal and external organisations to register user-facing applications and submit requests for connection to the wider platform. Our design and service work should be public, open and transparent. National services and the organisation running them should be the servant of users, including health and care organisations in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The applications group should focus on breaking-up WCP into modular re-usable components, identifying and removing important business logic which should be implemented at the service-layer. The results viewing component should simply leverage the underlying services and be a lightweight wrapper that can be used to support multiple workflows dependent on the clinical context. Applications should be ephemeral and lightweight; designed for customisation and integration into the myriad of complex healthcare workflows that exist across our country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The infrastructure group must begin an options analysis of the costs and security implications of running server infrastructure on existing hardware or commodity UK-based cloud providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must be honest about what we can and cannot do in Wales. There are existing commercial solutions for a range of user-facing applications and it makes little sense to duplicate that functionality. Similarly, why should NWIS develop software for outpatient outcome recording to fix a problem that ABM, ABHB and CAV have already solved? Instead, NWIS should be focused on delivering what no-one else can, an open, standards-based, consent-driven digital health platform. No health board or commercial entity can build that; let’s focus on creating an enabling technology platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an approach will allow health boards to adopt new functionality at their own pace and develop solutions themselves leveraging the same shared platform. One current failing across Wales is that local developments are orthogonal to the national shared interest because, in the absence of a truly open standards-based platform, software is developed tightly bound to local systems. As such, those new developments are not easily scaled across the wider economy. As such, we should mandate that local developments leverage the national platform and that those developments are made available to other NHS organisations when complete via a shared open-source code repository. It would then be possible for new developments developed elsewhere to be scaled rapidly across all of our services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Separately, the standards and governance team should provide an interoperability toolkit to be used for scoring both internal and external applications on a range of interoperability factors including the use of existing national services, adoption of approved data standards and plans for the future. Such a toolkit would be used to drive the adoption of standards over time and improve compatibility with the national platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we should be working in the open. My blog is one example of this; we should foster debate of the difficult issues, acknowledging that there is no easy or straightforward solution, but only compromise, collaboration and cooperation to do the right thing for patients in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other posts in this series:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part 1 : &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html&quot;&gt;The importance of strategy : focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part 2 : &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges.html&quot;&gt;The challenges we face in delivering the vision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part 3 : &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-solutions.html&quot;&gt;Pragmatic solutions to those challenges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In part one of this series, I introduced the “Informed health and care – A digital health and social care strategy for Wales” and talked in broad terms about the importance of a coherent strategy to deliver that vision.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Focus: the challenges</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Focus: the challenges" /><published>2018-01-19T14:45:45+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-19T14:45:45+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges.html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html&quot;&gt;part one of this series&lt;/a&gt;, I introduced the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/topics/health/nhswales/about/e-health/?lang=en&quot;&gt;“Informed health and care – A digital health and social care strategy for Wales”&lt;/a&gt; and talked in broad terms about the importance of a coherent strategy - a specific action-focused plan -  to deliver that vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this part, I try to articulate the importance challenges we face in delivering the vision, concluding that essentially, we need to balance centralised planning and control with support for innovation and change, particularly given the new technologies on the horizon which offer the potential to transform how we configure and deliver care to our citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a coherent plan to deliver our vision. In &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-solutions.html&quot;&gt;part 3, I discuss the best way to meet those challenges.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-are-the-challenges-we-face&quot;&gt;What are the challenges we face?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what are our challenges in delivering the vision today?  We can look to the recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wao.gov.uk/publication/informatics-systems-nhs-wales&quot;&gt;Welsh Audit Office report&lt;/a&gt;; this has raised important concerns about healthcare information technology in Wales including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Highlighting the inherent complexity of deploying information technology across a large complex system, spread across multiple organisations, with staff operating out of hospitals, GP practices and in the community.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Significant delays in delivery of projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lack of strategic prioritisation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Disagreements between some NHS bodies and NWIS in relation to delivery and the meaning of “Once for Wales”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A need to strengthen leadership&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weakness in governance arrangements, lack of independent scrutiny and unbalanced reporting of progress&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inadequate funding&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Inconsistent planning with a need to aligning plans across organisations&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Issues of information technology staff capacity.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Issues of clinical engagement and dissatisfaction.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Concerns about the quality and functionality of many national systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unclear lines of responsibility in relation to delivering and monitoring the benefits of projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, we must also consider what challenges our services will face in the future. Healthcare is ever-changing and there are a number of transformative and disruptive influences in health that, together with new technology, are driving and will continue to drive new ways of working. I wrote about these in my &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/07/07/disruptive-influences-health.html&quot;&gt;disruptive challenges series of blog posts&lt;/a&gt;. Are we confident that we have an environment in Wales that is primed to take advantage of current and future technologies?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changes in model of care:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Management of multiple long-term health conditions, cross-disciplinary teamwork, non-health partnerships including social care and third-sector&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Shared care and shared records&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Remote monitoring using modern technology including wearables and the “Internet of things”.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Focus on health outcomes and prudent healthcare, a need to support big data and real-time analytics and embed artificial intelligence into management and clinical practice.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patients as active participants:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;View and contribute to their own records, recording their own aims and objectives and target outcomes&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Communication with the healthcare team&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Control the sharing of their information for direct care, for service evaluation and for research via consent and robust citizen identity services&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Hospitals without walls:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Increasing availability of personal mobile devices, wearables and smart home monitoring&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;New commercial models of care and software provision&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/docs/dhss/publications/180116reviewen.pdf&quot;&gt;Parliamentary Review of Health and Social Care report&lt;/a&gt;, published in January 2018 highlights the need for a seamless health and care system in Wales, centred around the citizen irrespective of where they live with the avoidance of creating artificial barriers between services and organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It highlights that service redesign can be enabled by the appropriate use of digital technology. In addition, it explains how frontline innovation across different parts of Wales has already emerged and the importance of being able to disseminate good practice once proven stressing the importance of adopting continuous quality improvement methodologies to create a learning health and care system. Similarly, it recognises that different localities across Wales do not need to operate in the same way or that services must be identical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that report, similar concerns to that from the WAO were raised :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Simply put, activity is just too dispersed and stretched, and lacks overall commitment around a unified vision and set of priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, the report draws out the seemingly conflicting goals between local variation and harmonisation and standardisation. We want to support innovation, appropriate variation in services and the delivery of a thriving digital ecosystem supporting local industry and at the same time reduce needless variation, share good practice and harmonise across systems?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I do not, for example, want patients to be disadvantaged because the technology used in one health board is different to another and the information available is incomplete and the pathway of care disrupted. This is why Wales has committed to working together to adopt common information services and I expect all parts of the NHS in Wales, supported by the Informatics Service, to adopt them&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dr Andrew Goodall,  Chief Executive, NHS Wales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we deliver these two seemingly mutually exclusive goals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer, of course, is to understand that coordination and central control can be applied differently depending on what is being discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Thus we should seek coordinated policies only when the gains are very large. There will be costs to demanding coordination, because it will ride roughshod over economies of specialization and more nuanced local responses. The brilliance of good organization is not in making sure that everything is connected to everything else. How that road lies a frozen maladaptive stasis. Good strategy and good organization lie in specializing on the right activities and imposing only the essential amount of coordination.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;from “Good Strategy Bad Strategy”, 2011 by Richard Rumelt&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our strategy must therefore take into account a need for national coordination for some areas of our work and yet enable innovation and variation in others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a coherent plan to deliver our vision. In &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-solutions.html&quot;&gt;part 3, I discuss the best way to meet these challenges.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other posts in this series:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part 1 : &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html&quot;&gt;The importance of strategy : focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part 2 : &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges.html&quot;&gt;The challenges we face in delivering the vision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part 3 : &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-solutions.html&quot;&gt;Pragmatic solutions to those challenges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In part one of this series, I introduced the “Informed health and care – A digital health and social care strategy for Wales” and talked in broad terms about the importance of a coherent strategy - a specific action-focused plan - to deliver that vision.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Focus focus focus</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Focus focus focus" /><published>2018-01-19T14:44:44+00:00</published><updated>2018-01-19T14:44:44+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/topics/health/nhswales/about/e-health/?lang=en&quot;&gt;“Informed health and care – A digital health and social care strategy for Wales”&lt;/a&gt; sets out a clear vision for the use of information technology to support the provision of healthcare for citizens within Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This vision is split into four key themes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Information for You”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Supporting professionals”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Improvement and innovation”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“A Planned future”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We want a future where staff, service users, patients and carers are empowered and better informed, where organisational boundaries are not a barrier to effective care, as information is available electronically and joined-up, and where innovation and improvement can flourish built on a solid technical infrastructure and a safe environment for those who work in or are served by health and care services in Wales.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key question for us to answer is, what are the challenges that must be overcome to deliver this vision? As part of that process, we must identify current and future impediments to successful delivery. It is easy to fall into a trap of thinking of the “Informed Health and Care” strategy as an finished product instead of what it is, a set of high level goals which requires us to build a tangible and specific roadmap bringing together multiple strands of work into a truly cohesive vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, we must be honest about the economical and political environment in which we work, acknowledging the limitations in resources. We face a multitude of potentially conflicting demands and interests; as such, delivering the “Informed Health and Care Strategy” requires us to not only understand what we must do to achieve those goals but critically to understand what we must stop doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what is our strategy to deliver the vision?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;difficult-choices--we-cannot-do-it-all&quot;&gt;Difficult choices : we cannot do it all&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NHS Wales must face some difficult choices.  For too long, external factors have resulted in incoherent and inconsistent delivery or projects, frequency orthogonal to delivery of the wider vision; in many cases it has been driven by the budgeting process and the availability of funds in any single financial year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A coherent plan to deliver the strategy needs more than a list of disconnected and incompatible goals but instead a clear understanding of what needs to be done and what doesn’t need to be done; we must know when to say “no”. Instead, we focus our limited resources on specific tangible actions and make some difficult decisions to prune areas of work that do not support delivery of the wider vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… you should have a very short list of the most important things for the company to do. Then you will have a basis for moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Good-Strategy-Bad-Difference-Matters/dp/1846684811&quot;&gt;“Good Strategy Bad Strategy”, 2011 by Richard Rumelt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we need a coordinated all-Wales approach that permits all stakeholders to work cooperatively and collaboratively with clear lines of responsibility and governance. We need to re-organise our approach to healthcare information technology taking into account the steps needed to deliver the vision, the principles of enterprise architectural design, modern information standards and interoperability, modern quality improvement methodology and user-centred design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that the only logical response to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wao.gov.uk/publication/informatics-systems-nhs-wales&quot;&gt;Welsh Audit Office report&lt;/a&gt; is to re-imagine the relationship between the NHS Wales Informatics Service (NWIS) and the health boards. Such a re-imagining requires us to stop ignoring the, in my view, currently incoherent set of responsibilities and divisions of labour that exist within Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, is NWIS a standards and governance body, a consultancy, a software development house, a provider of a computing platform, a user experience and design shop, a procurement specialist, a business intelligence and analytics service or a provider of information technology infrastructure? Who is responsible? Who takes the credit for successful delivery and who takes the blame when something is not delivered? If we cannot answer such questions, we have to question our governance and organisational structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, while it makes sense that the “Informed Health and Care” strategy is divided into four workstreams, I believe it is incorrect to assume that the safe and efficient delivery of those objectives is necessarily delineated into separate workstreams. Such separation works only if work may continue semi-independently without consideration to other projects. There are, in my opinion, too many common goals and solutions to solve those goals that cross-cut those workstreams to consider them independently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, we must consider a “target architecture”, an enterprise master-plan which lays out an overall set of systems and functions that will support delivery of our shared vision. For example, understanding the similarities and differences between providing information for patients or professionals provides important insight into the shared data and software components that must serve both sets of requirements. For example, patients and health professionals need to see past and prior appointments and entries on waiting lists; there is no doubt that there are shared needs that cut across those workstreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, transformational change, enabled by technology, must be driven from the bottom-up, from those who deliver healthcare permitting incremental development and innovation while at the same time lowering risk. When a project is small and developed incrementally in an agile-way, our risk of failure is minimised. Likewise, don’t we all know that we must have top-down governance to ensure that solutions are standards-compliant, fit-for-purpose and safe as well as checking that developments are not orthogonal to the overall strategic vision so eloquently described in four workstreams of the Informed Health and Care Strategy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we need an all-Wales plan to deliver the vision that balances the need for centralised planning and yet enables local innovation. The paradox, put simply, is that currently we appear to have centralised the day-to-day management and delivery of individual projects and yet high-level strategic and prioritisation decisions are decentralised, haphazard and dependant on capital funding with little or no consideration or control as to how those projects will fit into a wider technical all-Wales architecture. We have, in essence, failed to create a plan to delivery the strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges.html&quot;&gt;part 2 of this series, I discuss the challenges that we face in NHS Wales in delivering the vision in our strategy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other posts in this series:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part 1 : &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html&quot;&gt;The importance of strategy : focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part 2 : &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges.html&quot;&gt;The challenges we face in delivering the vision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Part 3 : &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-solutions.html&quot;&gt;Pragmatic solutions to those challenges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“Informed health and care – A digital health and social care strategy for Wales” sets out a clear vision for the use of information technology to support the provision of healthcare for citizens within Wales.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Applying artificial intelligence in healthcare</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/machine-learning/2017/12/17/diagnostic-inference.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Applying artificial intelligence in healthcare" /><published>2017-12-17T14:32:32+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-17T14:32:32+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/machine-learning/2017/12/17/diagnostic-inference</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/machine-learning/2017/12/17/diagnostic-inference.html">&lt;p&gt;In this post, I discuss machine learning and computer-aided decision support in healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I discuss the importance of understanding the process of clinical decision making and how we use information to support that process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I discuss how software can valuably support our clinical decision making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I would like to convince you of the need for an computable data structure which I have termed OCMR, the &lt;em&gt;“open computable medical record”&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We, as a community, must collaborate to define the structure of the OCMR. This structure must allow us to create large amounts of publicly-available training data to provide to machine learning algorithms. Likewise, when it comes to evaluation and use of that trained algorithm, we need a computable data structure that can be populated from the real records of an individual patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;applying-artificial-intelligence-in-healthcare&quot;&gt;Applying artificial intelligence in healthcare&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial intelligence is a term used to describe intelligent machines that makes inferences or decisions based on data with little or no human interaction. Such decisions might be simple and rule-based (“Does this patient have anaemia?”) or more complex inferences based on multiple variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistical modelling, in which we study an outcome and the covariates that contribute to that outcome is, in itself, not that different to machine learning, at least conceptually; they are akin to two sides of the same coin. The advent of powerful computing power in every desktop and even in your pocket has meant that computationally-intensive methods, such as machine learning, are a useful tool in any statistician’s armamentarium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, we could create a tool, such as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chadsvasc.org/&quot;&gt;“CHADSVASC”&lt;/a&gt;, that could calculate the risk of a patient having a stroke if they had atrial fibrillation. That tool was generated from a conventional statistical approach looking at thousands of patients, their outcomes and the possible determinants of that outcome; the statistical model would identify the important factors that influence the outcome and provide a coefficient for each factor giving an indication as to its influence. The tool, created based on an understanding of those factors and their influence, can then be evaluated in clinical practice to ensure it is safe and accurate; such analyses might include estimates of sensitivity and specificity in specific populations of patients. For example, a tool generated from data from a non-representative sample of patients is unlikely to be generalisable to other populations. If such a tool is proven valid for a population of patients, then it could be used in clinical practice to support clinical decision making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning approaches the problem from a different perspective using a computationally-intensive approach, often from data with many more variables than one could plan to use in a more conventional statistical approach such as logistic regression, to predict results from data. However, the end result is that machine learning can be used to understand data in a broadly similar way to more conventional statistical approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep learning is a type of machine learning that has seen rapid advances in the last decade; it is a technology that has been used in computer vision applications to recognise handwriting or categorise images based on the objects or things they contain. However, there are increasing applications outside of this field such as voice recognition, natural language processing and playing common computer and board games to a standard greater than that possible by humans, sooner than expected simply by virtue of advances in raw computing power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deep learning uses multiple layers of neural networks to extract, transform and process information in multiple steps, with each layer using the output from the previous layer as input and training performed by backpropagation using a type of gradient descent. This backpropagation is akin to maximum likelihood estimation (MLE) in statistical regression in which estimates of parameters are generated; backpropagation works to train the network to give the outputs as labelled in the training data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chains-of-inference&quot;&gt;Chains of inference&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already use multiple structured models in clinical practice - such as CHADSVASC or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.england.nhs.uk/wp-content/uploads/2014/06/psa-aki-alg.pdf&quot;&gt;identifying acute kidney injury&lt;/a&gt; - as part of the wider care of patients to support a range of purposes such as clinical decision support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such models can be considered, generically, as a black-box that when provided with inputs is expected to give an answer:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ai/generic-model.png&quot; alt=&quot;Generic Model&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, such a model does not only apply to proven tools or computer-based decision making but is also applicable to human decision-makers. In the &lt;a href=&quot;/medical-records/2017/10/08/the-broken-medical-record.html&quot;&gt;“Fractal medical record”&lt;/a&gt;, I discussed the concept of nested hierarchical data being used to make inferences which themselves are used as inputs to support further inferences:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fractal/angina-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Angina 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the patient reports a crushing tight chest pain when they exert themselves walking up a hill, investigations show a normal resting electrocardiogram (ECG) and a history of smoking, together with some other findings. A diagnosis of angina is made; a useful diagnostic label to aid communication and, importantly, to aid clinical decision making and pattern recognition. When the patient presents in the future with new chest pain and ST segment elevation in the anterior leads of an ECG, old and new factors are combined implicitly to derive two conceptual diagnoses: &lt;a href=&quot;/medical-records/2017/10/08/the-broken-medical-record.html&quot;&gt;one is the latent trait of arteriosclerotic disease, perhaps never recorded but concluded implicitly, and one is a new acute anterior myocardial infarction&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, a consultant radiologist will be given a brief summary of a patient’s clinical problems (“shortness of breath”, “wheeze”), the contextual clues (inpatient vs. outpatient, name of the referrer) and the imaging itself to provide a diagnostic opinion. A respiratory physician may take those same clinical problems, the radiology report and additional investigation results to provide a further diagnostic opinion. The diagnostic inferences become nested:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/fractal/angina-3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Angina 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end result? A chain of multiple abstract black-boxes representing models accepting input data and providing an output.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do all of these models need in order to provider inferences?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Models, whether human or algorithms built using software, need &lt;strong&gt;information&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make best use of that information we need, to paraphrase a well known commercial motto:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“to organise clinical information and make it universally accessible and useful”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-record-becomes-part-of-your-practice&quot;&gt;“The record becomes part of your practice”&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In relation to the medical record:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You’re a victim of it or a triumph because of it. The human mind simply cannot carry all the information without error so the record becomes part of your practice.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dr Larry Weed, Internal Medicine Grand Rounds, 1971&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how we structure and use our medical records, whether on paper or digitally, is critical in supporting good clinical care. So how do we use our records to come to a diagnosis?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-one-look-at-raw-information&quot;&gt;Step one: look at raw information&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see a list of investigation results from an individual patient in a tabular view sorted by descending date:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ai/flat-results.png&quot; alt=&quot;Flat Results&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A view like this is seen in many different electronic health record systems and it is usable. As clinicians, we can click on one of the rows and see the result. Most systems allow the graphical display of various results over time permitting us to assess trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, we will have gathered additional raw information directly from the patient or carers about current and past symptoms, established previous medical problems such as chronic obstructive airways disease, an allergy to penicillin or previous cholecystectomy. In addition, we can corroborate and supplement that information from a review of the previous medical records. Such records may be on paper, in which case it is unlikely that they will be available in the emergency department, or electronic, either as a summary problem list or from piecing together information from multiple pieces of correspondence from multiple specialties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most health professionals will have sympathy with the analogy that we work as hunter-gatherers; our job is to find the right information at the right time and most of us will readily admit that this is usually time-consuming and error-prone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, imagine a patient presents with drooping of the eyelids to their general practitioner, and that doctor checks for acetyl-choline receptor antibodies. This is an investigation that will take two weeks to be processed.  Imagine the patient deteriorates after the test result is back but before it is seen by the general practitioner. Imagine then that the patient presents to the emergency unit, do you have confidence that your current clinical systems will make that result available to the admitting team or, even if it is available, that the team will specifically look for that test result?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we have a problem: we must trawl through the medical record in order to manually organise information and make it useful. We take a problem with thousands of dimensions - our raw results - and reduce them to some high-level concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;step-two-summarise-and-synthesise&quot;&gt;Step two: summarise and synthesise&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, to make sense of an excess of information in the medical record, most clinicians will attempt to create a summary to aid decision making. This is, in machine learning terms, a process of dimensionality reduction to identify the latent traits that are giving rise to the measurements that we can see. For example, one might write:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;2-hours central chest pain&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Sweating&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Breathless&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;ECG: ST elevation anterior leads&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Known: 
angina
acute coronary syndrome 1997 -&amp;gt; stent in circumflex - angioplasty 1997
hypertension
smoker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We conceive of the important information and apply that information to arrive at a clinical diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;3-months of headache&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;subacute encephalopathy&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;deteriorating renal function&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;chronic lymphocytic meningitis&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;leptomeningeal enhancement on MRI brain&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;bilateral facial nerve palsies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each, just as in Dr Larry Weed’s problem orientated medical records (POMR), we summarise at the most specific conceptual level that is defensible. If only a single lumbar puncture had been performed, we’d probably conceive of “lymphocytic meningitis” only, unless we could make an inference that the pathological process was chronic because of other factors, such as chronic headache and a long history of multiple cranial neuropathies. We might conclude chronicity based on repeated lumbar punctures or from synthesising the temporal pattern of clinical symptoms and signs over time. We populate our problem list based on the synthesis of multiple inferences from multiple sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the first example, we have summarised the salient facts and have enough information to suggest “anterior myocardial infarction” as a most likely diagnosis. Indeed, we could use our anatomical knowledge to opine that the patient most likely has an occlusion in the left anterior descending coronary artery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the second example, we do not have sufficient information to arrive at a single most likely diagnosis, but we can arrive at a sensible differential diagnosis, a list of possible diagnoses such as “malignant meningitis”, “neurosarcoidosis” or “tuberculous meningitis”. The cause of the deteriorating renal function is unclear; we need more information to solve that problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have defined the &lt;em&gt;essence&lt;/em&gt; of the clinical scenario in order to help us make clinical decisions; we reduce the uncertainty about those decisions to a level which permits rational decision making. As I have &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/20/machine-learning-2.html&quot;&gt;previously quoted&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;We care about measurements because measurements inform uncertain decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;For any decision or set of decisions, there are a large combination of things to measure and ways to measure them—but perfect certainty is rarely a realistic option.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Therefore, we need a method to analyse options for reducing uncertainty about decisions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-three-iterate&quot;&gt;Step three: iterate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generating a differential diagnostic list is important; it allows us to consider the &lt;em&gt;next steps&lt;/em&gt; of the diagnostic pathway: what questions to ask previously omitted and what tests to arrange. Such a methodology re-affirms the nested hierarchical nature of diagnostic inference and the importance of understanding &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; probabilities and the &lt;em&gt;a posteriori&lt;/em&gt; probability after our measurement, test or indeed any other method of obtaining more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A test can only be interpreted in a wider clinical context. Acetyl-choline receptor antibodies, tested in a patient with a pattern of symptoms (what the patient says) and signs (what we find on examination) suggestive of myasthenia gravis, are highly, but not perfectly sensitive to a diagnosis of myasthenia gravis. As I have &lt;a href=&quot;/medical-records/2017/10/08/the-broken-medical-record.html&quot;&gt;written before&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Similarly, if we have imperfect measurements that are not 100% sensitive or 100% specific, then we have to ask, sensitive and specific to &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt;? Realising this provides an important insight: when applied, say to clinical diagnosis, is that almost all of our measurements in medicine are as if we are looking at the truth out of the corner of our eye. We cannot see the &lt;em&gt;hidden truth&lt;/em&gt; but a combination of our measurements are, together, governed by a few simpler variables or concepts that are actually the cause of the results of the measurements that we can measure. As a result, we hope that our measurements can be used to understand the &lt;em&gt;latent&lt;/em&gt; variable(s) that are actually the hidden cause of those measurements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A latent variable is a variable that cannot be measured directly but we can infer its value from measurement of other observable measurements. In essence, we might conceptualise a latent trait as the real process to which our tests and assessments, combined together, provide an imperfect measurement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-four--reduce-dimensionality-reduction&quot;&gt;Step four : reduce (dimensionality reduction)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, our highly complex, multi-dimensional medical record, combining symptoms, signs and investigation results, can potentially be simplified in terms of latent traits. Such a process is termed &lt;em&gt;dimensionality reduction&lt;/em&gt; and humans perform this task implicitly to simplify both the process of decision making and the communication required around that decision-making between professionals and the patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, a 72-year-old patient with a long history of smoking cigarettes and a prior myocardial infarction is likely to have atherosclerotic vascular disease. When that patient presents with new right sided arm and face weakness, we are likely to assume that their stroke has been caused by emboli from atherosclerosis rather than a dissection, even if both causes are possible. The same clinical event occurring in a 32-year-old patient during high-intensity exercise is likely to have had a stroke due to arterial dissection. Humans perform such inferences without necessarily being explicit in documenting their chain of inference; over years we build a set of heuristics, rough and ready rules of thumb, that mean we make reasonable conclusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-five--avoid-biases&quot;&gt;Step five : avoid biases&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, humans are subject to a range of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_bias&quot;&gt;cognitive biases&lt;/a&gt; (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Thinking-Fast-Slow-Daniel-Kahneman/dp/0141033576/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1513438649&amp;amp;sr=8-2&amp;amp;keywords=cognitive+biases&quot;&gt;“Thinking fast and slow” by Prof. Daniel Kahneman&lt;/a&gt;) which results in a failure of our heuristics. For example, in confirmation bias, we may place greater emphasis on new information if it confirms a pre-existing belief or conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;By Jm3 (Own work) [CC BY-SA 4.0 (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0)], via Wikimedia Commons&quot; href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3AThe_Cognitive_Bias_Codex_-_180%2B_biases%2C_designed_by_John_Manoogian_III_(jm3).png&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;512&quot; alt=&quot;The Cognitive Bias Codex - 180+ biases, designed by John Manoogian III (jm3)&quot; src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a4/The_Cognitive_Bias_Codex_-_180%2B_biases%2C_designed_by_John_Manoogian_III_%28jm3%29.png/512px-The_Cognitive_Bias_Codex_-_180%2B_biases%2C_designed_by_John_Manoogian_III_%28jm3%29.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, the structure of our medical records, whether on paper or electronic, can inadvertently exaggerate our own biases. Conversely, properly organised and well structured records may help us to spot our biases and support their avoidance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, it is easy to fall into the trap of “anchoring”, in which the first piece of information acquired skews all subsequent inference as it is prioritised ahead of subsequent information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;computer-assisted-care&quot;&gt;Computer-assisted care&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information technology can and should valuably support caring for patients. Unfortunately, healthcare has not adopted information technology as quickly or effectively as other industries. For others, information technology is now &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; way that those businesses operate. Healthcare could immediately benefit from better scheduling, planning and communication using off-the-shelf technologies widely used in other domains. In addition, we should be adopting other technologies as soon as possible : identity management, delegation and consent, evaluating &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privacy-enhancing_technologies&quot;&gt;privacy-enhancing technologies (PETs)&lt;/a&gt; with focus on re-imagining our services around patients and enabling that transformation with technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in this essay, I want to focus on discussing computer-aided decision support and the value of applying machine learning in supporting the care of patients. With the right tools, we could do much to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support presenting the right information at the right time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;suggest “measurements” (to obtain new information such as symptoms, signs or investigation results) that will add valuably to the decision-making process&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;suggest differential diagnoses or treatment plans&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;take steps to avoid common human cognitive biases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;machine-learning-and-healthcare&quot;&gt;Machine learning and healthcare&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reason that machine learning has been used so effectively for image interpretation was the creation of large amounts of training data. Training data, for machine learning, needs to provide the input parameters and the labelled expected output. For an image, you might have a human label an image of a cat as a “cat” and then, together with hundreds of thousands of other images, a machine learning model can be trained and tested. There are now many publicly available training datasets &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_datasets_for_machine_learning_research&quot;&gt;available&lt;/a&gt; from multiple sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how can we achieve superhuman performance for clinical decision making?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to start thinking now about how to structure medical information so that it is possible to create large-scale publicly available training datasets and to understand how to transform clinical data from electronic patient records into the same format to permit testing and application in real-life clinical scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, we need a &lt;em&gt;“open computable medical record”&lt;/em&gt;, the OCMR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;open-computable-medical-record-ocmr&quot;&gt;Open Computable Medical Record (OCMR)&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OCMR is a simple intermediary data structure that can be used to be build datasets representing clinical knowledge. Initially for version 1, its focus is on diagnostic inference, mapping a combination of clinical findings to a most likely diagnosis. We use SNOMED-CT, an international terminology to represent the concepts in our clinical knowledge model; they are the primitives around which we build our knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the simplest structure might be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[acute kidney injury:&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=14669001&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;14669001&lt;/a&gt;] + [naproxen:&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=11847009&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;11847009&lt;/a&gt;] = [Analgesic nephropathy:&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=59400006&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;59400006&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each link will take you to the NHS digital SNOMED CT browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why should we use SNOMED CT?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SNOMED CT is a human-curated ontology tracking clinical and non-clinical concepts and the relationships between them. For instance, SNOMED CT will tell you that [acute kidney injury] is a type of [kidney disease:&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=90708001&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;90708001&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My own SNOMED CT REST API provides this information in a computationally-useful manner : &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/concepts/14669001?include=recursiveParentConcepts&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;acute kidney injury&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/concepts/11847009?include=recursiveParentConcepts&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;naproxen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this means is that an algorithm can potentially learn generic knowledge from specific examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is conceivable that a model, knowing that naproxen can cause acute kidney injury, can also learn that the broad class of analgesics can cause acute kidney injury and so, when faced with a patient on ibuprofen, can suggest a correct judgement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While SNOMED CT contains many types of relationships permitting us to infer that “acute kidney injury” is a type of kidney disease, it does not contain any data providing support for diagnostic inference. As such, we need to embed SNOMED CT concepts within a wider OCMR information model in order to express potential diagnostic inferential relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not difficult to conceptualise the OCMR as a 2-dimensional image with each pixel representing a clinical finding:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ai/mi.png&quot; alt=&quot;Conceptualising the OCMR as an image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, the source “image”, a set of factors representing “chest pain”, “shortness of breath” and “ECG ST elevation” are analysed and the most likely diagnosis given: “acute MI” (myocardial infarction).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not difficult to envisage making an OCMR more structured and more refined to provide additional contextual information relating to clinical context, baseline characteristics of the patient such as age and sex as well as the severity and nature of each clinical finding; we might categorise these as acute, sub-acute, chronic or episodic for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have included an example OCMR record for a diagnosis of myocardial infarction. It is available as a JSON-formatted file including the clinical problems (and for each the higher-order more generic concepts) and the final diagnosis. The example file is available &lt;a href=&quot;/images/ai/question.json&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I would envisage converting this to a flat vector for ease of processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;meta-learning-and-dimensionality-reduction&quot;&gt;Meta-learning and dimensionality reduction&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rationale behind defining an OCMR is to provide machine learning models with a set of deep underlying (latent) traits that act as as the core principles supporting diagnostic inference, just as used by humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do not simply want a model that, given free text, outputs possible diagnoses, even though that might be an eventual result. Instead we want models that support building a more thorough foundation for clinical inference, that might even allow us, with the right right tools, to identify and understand inferential relationships and latent traits that we currently do not recognise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we might use the models to take new input from a patient’s medical record and support their direct care. In a patient with chest pain, a trained algorithm should be able to make diagnostic inferences and suggest information that is required such as “we need an ECG for this patient presenting with chest pain”. The model has learnt the relationship between chest pain and an ECG and even troponin results; with the right integration of decision support into our electronic health records, the algorithm could help us by highlighting the important information rather than simply showing all results in chronological order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;sources-of-training-data&quot;&gt;Sources of training data&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ai/model-generation.png&quot; alt=&quot;Model Generation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we build a corpus of medical knowledge containing diagnostic inferential relationships as well as codifying choice of next diagnostic steps, interventions and treatments?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would argue that we need to consider multiple sources of medical knowledge and make them usable by converting them into the OCMR format; the OCMR data model is essentially an intermediary data structure for medical information in the same way as images can be represented as a bitmap image file and readily analysed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential sources of information are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;core epidemiological data - providing information on incidence and prevalence for a range of disease&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;free-text monographs about diseases, such as those from rare disease databases&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;free-text monographs about drugs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;textbooks&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;exam questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;epidemiological-data&quot;&gt;Epidemiological data&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Epidemiological data relating to the incidence and prevalence of different diseases are usually well-described in the literature. Such data can provide important &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; probabilities of different diagnoses in different clinical contexts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such data could be supplemented by real-life data taken from known patients - for example, the GP research database (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.herc.ox.ac.uk/downloads/health_datasets/browse-data-sets/general-practice-research-database-gprd&quot;&gt;GPRD&lt;/a&gt;) or hospital episode statistics (HES) for hospital admission and discharges. Such data will be recorded either as Read codes or ICD-10, but these are readily convertible to SNOMED-CT and could contribute to an publicly-accessible OCMR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;free-text-monographs-literature-and-textbooks&quot;&gt;Free-text monographs, literature and textbooks&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many rare diseases, there are excellent semi-structured and authoritative descriptions of clinical features and types of presentation. It is not difficult to see how natural language processing could be used to extract the important phenotypic features of a range of rare diseases in order to support the identification of patients usually only possible by specialists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the OMIM (Online Mendelian Inheritance in Man) resource on &lt;a href=&quot;http://omim.org/entry/125370?search=drpla&amp;amp;highlight=drpla&quot;&gt;DRPLA&lt;/a&gt;, a rare neurodegenerative disorder is detailed and includes the important symptoms and signs. OMIM make their dataset available on the Internet in both human-readable and machine-readable formats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, adverse-effects of different pharmaceutical compounds could be imputed from monographs in standard pharmacopeiae and so potentially highlight to non-specialists where a drug might be contributing to a patient’s problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;exam-questions&quot;&gt;Exam questions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been building up large numbers of semi-structured questions in medical schools across the UK and have a collaborative national question bank run by the Medical Schools Council Assessment Alliance (MSC-AA). We also have similar banks of questions for the postgraduate examinations managed by our Royal Colleges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Could these question banks be useful as a corpus of knowledge for machine learning?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my prior role in the School of Medicine at Cardiff University, we used to encourage students to use assessments to drive their learning by sitting as many exam questions as possible. As part of that work, we implemented a “progress test” in which students sat 3-4 exams per year with detailed feedback to identify areas for which they needed more help. We now have thousands of questions in our bank alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can questions drive learning for machines?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, this is from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usmle.org/pdfs/step-
1/2015samples_step1.pdf&quot;&gt;USMLE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A 52-year- old woman comes to the physician because of a 1-month history of headache, weakness, tingling of her extremities, muscle cramping, and fatigue. Her blood pressure is 170/110 mm Hg. Physical examination shows no other abnormalities. Laboratory studies show a decreased serum potassium concentration, metabolic alkalosis, and decreased plasma renin activity; serum sodium concentration is within the reference range. Urine catecholamine concentrations are within the reference range.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Which of the following is the most likely diagnosis?
A. Adrenal adenoma
B. Focal segmental glomerulosclerosis
C. Hypothalamic tumor
D. Juxtaglomerular cell tumor
E. Renal artery stenosis&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Answer : A&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The important characteristics of exam questions are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they are a succinct distillation of important clinical concepts with a labelled answer; they usually do not contain extraneous information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they contain sufficient information information to identify a single best answer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is a single best answer, although the distractors should be reasonable to someone who doesn’t know the answer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;they are semi-structured - with a stem (the clinical scenario), a lead-in (the question), the possible answers and the correct keyed answer.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;medical schools and colleges &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; write questions on the most important and common clinical scenarios; they should represent a representative corpus of medical knowledge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential problems with exam questions are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is it possible to obtain sufficient questions in order to contribute to the learning of a model?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is it possible to use natural language processing to extract the terms from the lead-in and to map the possible answers into a structured format suitable for our OCMR?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these issues can be overcome, then the SNOMED-CT ontology tells us “headache” is a type of “pain” in the “head” so that any learning system can learn on the broad generic concepts and not only the concept used at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we can map each entity within that free text to a SNOMED-CT concept. Here I use my relatively rudimentary free-text mapping service:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/search?s=plasma%20renin%20activity&quot;&gt;Plasma renin activity&lt;/a&gt;
maps to to &lt;a href=&quot;http://browser.ihtsdotools.org/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=8883510000001
02&amp;amp;edition=uk-edition&amp;amp;release=v20170401&amp;amp;server=https://prod- browser-
exten.ihtsdotools.org/api/snomed&amp;amp;langRefset=900000000000508004&quot;&gt;8883510000001&lt;/a&gt;
or in JSON:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/concepts/888351000000102/recursiveP
arents&quot;&gt;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/concepts/888351000000102/recursiveP
arents&lt;/a&gt;
which tells us we’re measuring “renin”…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, we match on &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/search?s=headache&quot;&gt;“headache”&lt;/a&gt; and understand that this is a type of &lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/concepts/25064002/recursiveParents&quot;&gt;“pain”…. in the “head”…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the right answer is (A)… Adrenal adenoma, so, we can look that up too…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/search?s=adrenal adenoma&quot;&gt;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/search?s=adrenal adenoma&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/concepts/255036008/recursiveParents&quot;&gt;http://msdata.org.uk:8080/snomedct/concepts/255036008/recursiveParents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and then understand that this is a type of benign neoplasm of the adrenal gland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, for any single question, it might be possible to &lt;em&gt;impute&lt;/em&gt; a range of different data based on more generic high-level broad concepts. Likewise, if there is insufficient training data for creating a high-dimensional map at a high level of granularity, we can use techniques to reduce dimensionality and create a low-dimensional model. Indeed, it is likely that identifying the core principles and trends from high-dimensional datasets will permit better predictive models to be created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, this question not only links a diagnosis of adrenal adenoma with fatigue, hypertension, a low serum potassium concentration and metabolic alkalosis, but it is conceivable that the training data could be used to identify patients with similar symptoms and signs and suggest that renal profile should be checked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, the resultant model may be able to generate additional questions for subsequent training, by humans and algorithms alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information technology has the potential to revolutionise healthcare and augment our clinical decisions by helping us understand patient information in ways to directly improve care. Clinical decision making is complex and we need to consider ways to both understand and support our decision-making. We don’t want to abdicate responsibility for 
decision-making; indeed, decision-making is a partnership between professional and patient. However, for too long, human professionals have had to spend time gathering the right information instead of focussing on where our skills are needed most : high-level thinking and communication. We should be working towards building tools that support us in the care of our patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have started work on the first version of the OCMR and I am going to try to build some publicly-available datasets to kickstart the application of machine learning in healthcare. As an experiment, I have built a fake dataset generator (&lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/wardle/go-snomed&quot;&gt;go-snomed&lt;/a&gt;) which builds a fake OCMR JSON structure to try to understand the pitfalls of this approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the next steps are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build natural language processing tools to extract clinical terms from different sources of clinical knowledge such as monographs and questions from exam banks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work with universities and colleges to obtain questions for machine learning. In the interim, generate fake questions for testing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Generate dimensionality reduction techniques to genericise highly granular concepts and their relationships identifying the broad underlying principles at play.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work on collecting incidence and prevalence data from a variety of different clinical contexts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would love to hear from you if you would like to be involved or indeed, help support this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In this post, I discuss machine learning and computer-aided decision support in healthcare.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The 5 Os of healthcare IT</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The 5 Os of healthcare IT" /><published>2017-12-06T10:39:39+00:00</published><updated>2017-12-06T10:39:39+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html">&lt;p&gt;My writing on &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html&quot;&gt;domain-driven design&lt;/a&gt; arose because of my own experience building an electronic patient record system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“A model is an abstraction of the real-world distilling knowledge into core concepts and processes.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;from &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html&quot;&gt;Towards a domain-driven, model-based approach to developing clinical information systems: innovating for the future in NHS Wales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that development, I was fortunate to use technologies developed by NeXT (and continued by Apple - WebObjects), which enforced a strict separation of model, controllers and the view. Importantly, I learned an important principle: the importance of starting with a data model conceived with a deep understanding of the domain in which I worked in my day job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was only later that I read Eric Evans’ “Domain-driven design” which, while not about healthcare, has much to teach us in health information technology about the importance of data modelling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“There are many things that make software development complex. But the heart of this complexity is the essential intricacy of the problem domain itself. If you’re trying to add automation to complicated human enterprise, then your software cannot dodge this complexity—all it can do is control it.
The key to controlling complexity is a good domain model, a model that goes beyond a surface vision of a domain by introducing an underlying structure, which gives the software developers the leverage they need. A good domain model can be incredibly valuable, but it’s not something that’s easy to make. Few people can do it well, and it’s very hard to teach.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Martin Fowler&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Excerpt From: Eric Evans. &lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/gb/book/domain-driven-design-tackling-complexity-in-heart-software/id502848358?mt=11&quot;&gt;“Domain-Driven Design: Tackling Complexity in the Heart of Software.”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-digital-drive&quot;&gt;A digital drive&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to see information technology as a product rather than what it really is - an enabler of transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we deliver transformative change in healthcare using digital technologies? Why does a domain-driven design approach help us? Why and how should we start with domain models?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suggest that there are five broad principles… my 5 Os of healthcare IT:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-objectives&quot;&gt;1. Objectives&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Define a clear vision. For example, in Wales, the Welsh Government &lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/topics/health/nhswales/about/e-health/?lang=en&quot;&gt;Informed Health and Care strategy&lt;/a&gt; is a very good start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then define tangible definite high-level objectives. This should not be “deploy XXX” where XXX is a product you want to deploy, but instead focus on user need - the requirements, the problems you are solving and the transformation you enable. So, for me, in the next 3 months, NHS Wales should:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ensure laboratory and radiology results and clinical documents are available to all clinical users when they are seeing a patient, irrespective of where those investigations were performed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identify deteriorating patients on the ward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your prioritisation list might be different, but those objectives should support the aims in your overall vision. I have a different list for 6-months, 12-months and onwards (a subject for another post).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is sensible to define a list of all objectives, each a stepping stone on the way to delivering your overall vision. You will need to take into account political and business priorities as well so it is about negotiation, discussion and understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate this, we currently have a PACS replacement project ongoing. For me, replacing one PACS (picture archiving and communication systems) with another, in the absence of a well argued need, does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; meet the standard required. In a resource limited environment, wasting resources without good reason is difficult to defend. Always ask for a compelling reason &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; something is important! What value do we gain that cannot be achieved in more prudent manner?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, what is the point in forcing organisations to rip out a patient administrative system to replace with a new “Once for Wales” PAS if each will be configured differently with different information standards? Similarly, if the project to “deploy” the system doesn’t end up providing administrative and clinical staff or indeed the patient, information from across multiple organisations, then what are we trying to achieve?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your objectives define your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-ownership&quot;&gt;2. Ownership&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make information technology and the transformation agenda owned by the users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But who are the users? You need to consider : health professionals, administrators, managers, analysts, the patient, and more!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The users must be engaged, must be empowered to own and drive their work. We need to understand the areas in which there is synergy between requirements from different perspectives and design our enterprise to provide the common tools to solve their problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than top-down “You will…”, consider instead “Here are the tools to achieve your goals… do you want help?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all users, ask them what they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, what do our patients want from a healthcare services that recognises that digital is one way of providing a service? Are you sure that we know the answer to this yet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-openness&quot;&gt;3. Openness&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Allow debate. Make your work transparent.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information technology is difficult, so ensure plenty of debate to hear all of the views. There is no right way, but favour solutions to deploy quickly, get software in hands of users early and get feedback, favour an approach that set a foundation for future plans and don’t limit what you don’t know you don’t know. As I have said many times before:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We need to build an infrastructure that explicitly recognises that we don’t have all of the answers, and therefore must support innovation. Such innovation may simply be incremental improvement of existing technology, but also must cope with and embrace the introduction of transformative and disruptive technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;Once for Wales debate, March 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should debate and build in the open. There are few situations in which work, particularly funded by the public, should be behind closed doors. Transparency is key; options analyses of the most appropriate way to deliver solutions to our problems. Like everything in medicine, our decisions are rarely black-and-white, but careful  judgements balancing many different options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;4-optimise&quot;&gt;4. Optimise&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Permit failure.  Fail fast. Recognise the relative unchanging components and iterate and prototype the components that change more quickly.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we develop a “can-do” digital culture in healthcare? Should we clone the “Move fast and break things” culture reporting in technological startups? We need to approach information technology in a different way but we can’t “break things”! We work in a safety-critical environment, but we must recognise that the &lt;em&gt;pace of change&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;level of risk&lt;/em&gt; can be different at different levels of our enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/rate-of-change-layered.png&quot; alt=&quot;Rate Of Change Layered&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this diagram, we see that our architecture consists of an open platform approach, built using application programming interfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The data layer contains longitudinal episodic patient data relating to admissions, appointments, measurements and outcomes. This layer may consist of multiple data repositories for laboratory systems, documents, clinical data and aggregate data from across multiple patient administrative systems from multiple organisations. These complexities are abstracted within our architecture as a set of simple open application programming interfaces (APIs). This layer changes the least. A blood pressure in the right arm will always be a blood pressure recorded in the right arm.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The business logic, services and process/workflow layers provides important reusable services that execute business logic.  This ensures that user-facing applications do not make the mistake of embedding important business logic and rules. For example, if access to information needs to be logged, then it is better to perform this at the API level rather than within a user-facing application.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The user-facing components and applications leverage the underlying platform in order to provide value for users. User-facing applications are most likely to need to change frequently given our technological advances. You should consider these to be relatively ephemeral, taking advantage of new mobile devices and other new technology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can see this approach in more detail in my &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;plan for an open platform in NHS Wales&lt;/a&gt; :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/platform/platform-overall.png&quot; alt=&quot;Platform Overall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without a platform, one ends up procuring multiple systems that need to be connected together, rather than to a common enterprise platform. This results in:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data silos: most current products store their data in a proprietary format within that product. As a result, we create multiple silos. If one can access that information and connect it to your other deployed products, you hit the complexity of n*(n-1)/2 data interoperability, in which you have to somehow connect that product to everything else (2 systems need one connection, 3 needs 3, 4 needs 6, 5 needs 10, 6 needs 15,7 needs 21!) so one ends up with a combinatorial nightmare. &lt;img src=&quot;/images/cis_design/multiple-interfaces.png&quot; alt=&quot;Multiple Interfaces&quot; /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Procurement rules: it is difficult to scale a solution across a wide enterprise as costs hit thresholds for OJEU rules and suddenly, you and your team are committing large sums of money in a high risk deployment in which failure cannot be countenanced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, think “open platform”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;5-organic&quot;&gt;5. Organic&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scale organically, enthusiasts and early adopters, grow horizontally; get people asking “can we have that too?”, until your solutions are the default, that they make process easier and not more difficult.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to support innovation if we cannot tolerate variation. It is easy to assume that all variation across health services is bad, and so it is easy to think you should harmonise people and processes with technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an approach is wrong. Firstly, harmonisation is a people and processes issue, not technological, and secondly, how can you be sure you are harmonising to raise standards? What if you are standardising to the lowest common denominator? Variation allows you, as part of systems continuous improvement, to innovate, appraise and improve. Conversely, unmeasured and unmonitored variation is difficult to justify.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, recognise that information technology is fundamentally an enabler for transformation and that transformation needs to be driven from the bottom-up; imposing a software solution from central diktat rarely results in satisfied users or effective change. Design the health enterprise to instead allow iteration and innovation in a safe way, playing by a well-defined rulebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/DiffusionOfInnovation.png&quot; alt=&quot;DiffusionOfInnovation&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(CC BY 2.5, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?curid=11484459&quot;&gt;https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?curid=11484459&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work with early adopters and enthusiasts and then plan to scale organically, proving benefit using a quality improvement methodology such as DMAIC. Measure!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cis_design/dmaic.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dmaic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects relating to information technology fail frequently and this is seen in many industries, including healthcare. Healthcare enterprises are complex heterogeneous environments with many stakeholders and significant complexity; mistakes may cost lives. It is easy to assume that, faced with such risks, one should centralise and control and drive change from above, but such an approach actually results in a greater risk of failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is an important paradox in many health services, including Wales, is that there is a tendency to centralise the day-to-day management and delivery of individual products and yet high-level strategic and prioritisation decisions are decentralised, haphazard and dependant on capital funding with little or no consideration or control as to how those projects will fit into a wider technical healthcare enterprise architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html&quot;&gt;“A paradox of control”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The high-level strategic roadmap to deliver our shared vision should be centralised across an enterprise. Similarly, the rules of engagement, the the contractual obligations at a human and technical level that permit interaction with the open platform (API and data standards etc.) should be defined centrally. Conversely, the day-to-day management and delivery of individual projects should be driven, bottom-up, by the users and for the users and scaled out when appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;“Once for Wales debate”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-design/2017/03/23/scope-framing-clinical-design.html&quot;&gt;Scope and framing in clinical information system design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/04/04/test-requesting.html&quot;&gt;Test requesting design: building an open API-based architecture&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data driven healthcare information technology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">My writing on domain-driven design arose because of my own experience building an electronic patient record system:</summary></entry></feed>