<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.wardle.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.wardle.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-10-18T14:13:22+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/</id><title type="html">Health informatics and information technology</title><subtitle>by Dr Mark Wardle, Consultant Neurologist, clinical informatics and software developer. Founder, Eldrix Ltd.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Demographics and identity: A fundamental service in a health and care platform</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/platform/2019/10/18/demographics-patient-identity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Demographics and identity: A fundamental service in a health and care platform" /><published>2019-10-18T11:10:10+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-18T11:10:10+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/platform/2019/10/18/demographics-patient-identity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/platform/2019/10/18/demographics-patient-identity.html">&lt;p&gt;This blog post is a slightly expanded version of a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mwardle/status/1184578331041247233?s=21&quot;&gt;Twitter thread&lt;/a&gt; that I live tweeted during the creation of a Wardley map looking at health and care architecture in relation to identity services and specifically, how we manage patient demographic information.  You can read more about Wardley mapping from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/wardleymaps&quot;&gt;Simon Wardley’s own blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve been practicing my @swardley mapping to try to look at one facet of our health and care architecture and ecosystem: patient demographics. Wardley maps use a value chain to show user need and their dependencies running from top to bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding patient identity is pretty much essential to all that we do in health and care. One of major problems in health is that legacy applications have tended to be “full stack”, containing different components that are user-facing, do business logic and that do data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach is shown in this schematic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Value%20chain%200.png&quot; alt=&quot;Value Chain 0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application is dependent on components that support user-facing logic, components that handle business logic, and components that provide data storage. All are dependent on computing power and computing power is dependent on power (electricity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The historic approach to health and care software is the procurement of multiple ‘full-stack’ applications and consequently we, within health and care, have to consider how to integrate these applications in order to ensure information is available at the right time across different systems. In general, however, we have seen multiple applications in silos, resulting in patients being surprised that updating their address at their general practitioner might not be propagated to, for example, the radiology booking office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We realised that running multiple health and care applications each with their own idea of patient demographics was a &lt;em&gt;BAD IDEA&lt;/em&gt;. Many applications switched to using demographic information from the local (organisation-bound) “patient administrative system” (PAS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Value%20chain%201.png&quot; alt=&quot;Value Chain 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, the user facing application becomes dependent on local (organisation) patient administrative system. However, that might work in one organisation, with the PAS acting as an authoritative source of patient identity (demographic) information,  but we have multiple organisations! So what happened? We ended up with multiple applications and multiple organisations, all in silos:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Value%20chain%202.png&quot; alt=&quot;Value Chain 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now we have a problem. How do we share information about patients if we can’t match identities between organisations? How can we track the progress of a pathway of care across organisational boundaries without this? Patients don’t experience a “single seamless system” but the fractured, silo approach is evident for all to see - they update their telephone number with their general practitioner and are surprised when the hospital doesn’t know about the change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the EMPI, or “enterprise master patient index”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Value%20chain%203.png&quot; alt=&quot;Value Chain 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, you will also see that we need a new national identifier service, the WDS, that can reach out to NHS England who provides NHS number generation. This is getting complicated. How do we write applications that can deal with this? And what if the patient wants to get involved?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Value%20chain%204.png&quot; alt=&quot;Value Chain 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we now expecting applications to handle understanding demographics across multiple PAS, and to manage the ongoing updates and calls to the NHS Number Tracing Service?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely we want a “one system” approach in Wales, centred on the patient and not the organisation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And hold on. We need to start running analytics across our whole enterprise, seeing how patients fare in the course of their care. How do we track them in our analytics software? We’re going to take A&amp;amp;E attendance data from a PAS and then, how do we match up information?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Value%20chain%205.png&quot; alt=&quot;Value Chain 5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Wales, there is an enterprise service bus (ESB) which securely carries HL7 V2 messages to request, update and merge demographic information. This approach means that your application will need to plug-in to what is essentially a firehose and deal with filtering and managing these messages to track changes over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;mapping&quot;&gt;Mapping&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mapping allows us to add another axis - the maturity of our components - from components that are brand new and being developed, to those that are custom-built, to those we can buy, to those that are a commodity (readily interchangeable alternatives exist). Let’s do that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Map%201.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a problem and the map demonstrates it for us. The map allows us to start to test our models &amp;amp; starts our discussions. Are we really expecting each of our user facing applications &amp;amp; analytics to try to deal with this mess? Instead, surely we need a single authoritative source of identity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Map%202.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means we can break apart the tight (organisationally-centric) coupling between our applications &amp;amp; individual PAS Instead, we do the hard work to hide the complexity inherent in what is a complex adaptive enterprise containing multiple sources of demographic information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Map%203.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see that our single authoritative source, abstracting (hiding) the complexity of our legacy problems with patient identity, will itself evolve towards being a commodity over time as we switch to using it. The red arrow shows the movement over time, as we first build and then deploy this service, and applications move from directly integrating with local administrative systems to a new shared national service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how to permit such an evolution? Such a switch will be best driven by adoption of robust open technical standards that make it easy for applications to consume and process patient identity information using this service. That means making it easier for applications to use our new service rather than directly integrating with proprietary lower level systems. To enable that transformation, we must recognise the value of open standards. So that means we must add standards and the supporting processes for their adoption to our map:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Map%204.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final step is that this new service encapsulates and hides underlying platform implementation details. It is conceivable that, over time, that underlying implementation can be changed, simplified and &lt;em&gt;removed&lt;/em&gt; without changing client application code, because we’ve ensured loose coupling via the use of open standards and APIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Map%205.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map 5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I think this demonstrates that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need a single authoritative source of patient identity information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Applications should delegate identity services to that module rather than trying to manage demographics themselves …&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need to adopt robust open technical standards (e.g. HL7 FHIR Patient)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need to support the ongoing processes to curate, manage and adopt technical standards to drive the commoditisation of a new “one system” approach to demographic, patient identity services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demographics is but one foundational service that are needed to build a modern open platform for health and care. I discuss the wider issues on the next steps in building an &lt;a href=&quot;/strategy/2019/09/22/health-technology.html&quot;&gt;open platform in different blog post&lt;/a&gt;, including the importance of demographics and appointments/scheduling as good examples of programmes of work, focused on implementing &lt;em&gt;products&lt;/em&gt; not projects, that will give us valuable learning for our next steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark Wardle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This blog post is a slightly expanded version of a recent Twitter thread that I live tweeted during the creation of a Wardley map looking at health and care architecture in relation to identity services and specifically, how we manage patient demographic information. You can read more about Wardley mapping from Simon Wardley’s own blog.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An open letter to the new chief digital officer for health and care in Wales</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/10/06/an-open-letter-to-the-cdo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An open letter to the new chief digital officer for health and care in Wales" /><published>2019-10-06T10:09:09+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-06T10:09:09+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/10/06/an-open-letter-to-the-cdo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/10/06/an-open-letter-to-the-cdo.html">&lt;p&gt;This post is an open letter to whoever will become the new chief digital officer for health and care in Wales, prompted by this exciting announcement by the Health and Social Services Minister on 30th September 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;£50 million and new body to transform digital health and care services in Wales
The plans include creating the role of Chief Digital Officer for Health and Care and a new NHS Wales organisation to deliver national digital services, supported by £50 million new funding.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The Chief Digital Officer for Health and Care will define national standards for digital software and services, as part of moving to an open digital architecture, across all digital systems. The CDO will also advise Welsh Government on digital strategy, lead the digital profession, and be a champion for digital health and care in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Vaughan Gething, Health and Social Services Minister, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://gov.wales/ps50-million-and-new-body-transform-digital-health-and-care-services-wales&quot;&gt;https://gov.wales/ps50-million-and-new-body-transform-digital-health-and-care-services-wales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear Sir / Madam,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations on being successfully appointed as the new Chief Digital Officer for Health and Care in Wales. This is an exciting time and I thought I’d take the opportunity to help you get started with your work; I want to highlight some opportunities, some challenges and suggest some priorities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-people&quot;&gt;1. People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have some amazing people, projects and products in Wales. You will need to understand that somehow, at the moment, the total is currently less than the sum of the parts. However, there aren’t too many changes you’ll need to make to fix this paradox: I would say the two most important issues are &lt;em&gt;trust&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;collaboration&lt;/em&gt;. Ask: what can we do to help people achieve what they want to achieve, and what should be provided at a national scale to most support those efforts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-data&quot;&gt;2. Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have historically not prioritised &lt;em&gt;meaningful, interpretable data&lt;/em&gt; as the core foundation of our services - you need to understand that &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; underpins what we want to achieve - whether for direct care, service management, quality improvement or clinical research. Please understand how &lt;em&gt;arbitrary&lt;/em&gt; boundaries between these different uses are a risk to building a truly learning health and care system. You must change this while taking into account the legal and regulatory constraints defined by the purpose for which those data are used. Carefully question proponents of an application-centred strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-transparency&quot;&gt;3. Transparency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a digital leader, you will already know that there is often no clear right choice or single solution, but instead decisions need a fine balance between the advantages and disadvantages of any specific solution, sprinkled with a healthy dose of pragmatism, and a need to consider the future roadmap. An easy way to address this challenge is to be open and transparent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-collaboration&quot;&gt;4. Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set broad principles and empower, don’t control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to be dogmatic in setting the broad principles and defining the ‘guard-rails’ that will define how we will use digital technology to support solving the problems in health and care that we need to solve. In keeping with our need for transparency, it should be straightforward to understand what approach should be used and what kind of work should be funded, because the rules we work by are explicit. But that doesn’t mean centralised command-and-control or mandating a specific application. What we do need is an approach predicated upon adoption of pragmatic open standards and the creation of a toolbox of software code and data services that can be used to solve our day-to-day problems in a &lt;em&gt;collaborative&lt;/em&gt; manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-agility&quot;&gt;5. Agility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agility means recognising the benefits of adaptability, flexibility and fast feedback. We must learn from other industries who are adopting these practices with pace, and improving the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/articles/path-devops&quot;&gt;safety and reliability of their software delivery pipeline&lt;/a&gt;. We must build systems that can adapt and evolve to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will already know about the benefits of modularisation of software and data services and particularly how the unbundling of services means that they can be developed independently, in parallel, with agreed technical standards defining their interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just because we have multiple modules all being built, deployed and continuously improved independently, it doesn’t mean that each doesn’t form a cog in the wider &lt;em&gt;single system&lt;/em&gt;. By single system, we should mean a credible, coherent, overall high-level strategic approach means that there are clear principles that guide all of our work, with definite and explicit direction-of-travel, but empowered teams delivering the incremental steps on that, truly collaborative, journey. That means a shared vision, but small steps, and that doesn’t mean only for our technology products but in our overall approach to management and leadership. Our work will never be complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-technical-expertise&quot;&gt;6. Technical expertise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our work in health and care in Wales needs to be built on a solid foundation of technical skills. You will need to consider whether you need the support of a Chief Technical Officer, and emulate the highest performing technology companies of the world by fostering developer productivity and adopting a ‘products not projects’ approach. Our efforts to make the right information available at the right time, for both patients and professionals, will succeed or fail based on our ability to make use of the very best technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-standards-ecosystems-and-driving-the-commercial-market&quot;&gt;7. Standards, ecosystems and driving the commercial market&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will need to understand how we need to reboot our relationship with commercial and academic partners, and see how this can be fostered by building a truly open platform in which software and data services are made available for both internal and external users. You need to understand the meaning of “dogfooding”. You will need to see how programmes like the Digital Health Ecosystem cannot remain as a separate or external programme but in fact are &lt;em&gt;central&lt;/em&gt; in achieving what we want to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8-think-outside-of-health&quot;&gt;8. Think outside of health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should seek to work across Welsh Government to share the same design patterns and user-centred approaches, understand how health and care can fit into the wider strategic government-as-a-platform approach, and shape the way we design services using data. You will need to look for common ground and shared learning across health and care as well as other departments, particularly in relation to user-centred design and the adoption of standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9-be-humble&quot;&gt;9. Be humble&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognising that we don’t have &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;all of the answers&lt;/a&gt; is absolutely essential, but that doesn’t stop us taking responsibility for the broad over-arching principles and guard-rails that define our overall mission. I’m pretty sure that you will have to adapt and modify our plans as we go along, and be open and transparent about how we discover hitherto unconsidered challenges and how we will learn to overcome them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-have-fun&quot;&gt;10. Have fun&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wales could be the very best place in the world to deliver digital health and care; we are small, we pretty much all know one another and we have a health system that in theory lacks many of the arbitrary boundaries between organisations and services. There has been some very good work already that has delivered benefit for both patients and professionals. Your job will be to see the common thread that runs through our systems, our services and our nation and help us to use digital technology to create a truly learning, data-driven and person-centric health and care system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll quickly see that there are some  basics to get right - user login, single sign-on - but you will also need to have the clarity of vision to see how getting those fundamentals solved in the right way forms the foundation to deliver, iteratively and with pace, ever more sophisticated technology to support our health and care services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to do this together to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark Wardle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-health-technology-and-digital-transformation&quot;&gt;On health technology and digital transformation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/strategy/2019/09/22/health-technology.html&quot;&gt;Digital transformation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/strategy/2018/11/12/manifesto-wales.html&quot;&gt;A manifesto for digital health in Wales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-once-for-wales&quot;&gt;On “Once for Wales”&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;Once for Wales : a debate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-trust-and-innovation&quot;&gt;On trust and innovation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/paradox-of-ambition.html&quot;&gt;The paradox of ambition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html&quot;&gt;The paradox of control&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html&quot;&gt;The 5 Os of healthcare IT - objectives, ownership, openness, optimise, organic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-platforms&quot;&gt;On platforms:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/strategy/2018/10/02/open-platform-wales.html&quot;&gt;An open platform for Wales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data-driven healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-1.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 1/3. Standards and interoperability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-2.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 2/3. An API-first approach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 3/3. What we need to do next&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-focus&quot;&gt;On focus:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html&quot;&gt;Focus 1/3. The importance of strategy : focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges.html&quot;&gt;Focus 2/3. The challenges we face in delivering the vision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-solutions.html&quot;&gt;Focus 3/3. Pragmatic solutions to those challenges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-data&quot;&gt;On data:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/22/health-data.html&quot;&gt;Health data - start with a problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data-driven healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-development-standards-and-ecosystems&quot;&gt;On development standards and ecosystems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/cloud-ehr.html&quot;&gt;Creative 1/3: creative destruction in health IT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;Creative 2/3: the value of software for healthcare: quality improvement and service transformation underpinned by software, and software underpinning by quality improvement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html&quot;&gt;Creative 3/3: ecosystems and the platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This post is an open letter to whoever will become the new chief digital officer for health and care in Wales, prompted by this exciting announcement by the Health and Social Services Minister on 30th September 2019.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Healthcare and technology</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/09/22/health-technology.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Healthcare and technology" /><published>2019-09-22T17:16:16+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-22T17:16:16+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/09/22/health-technology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/09/22/health-technology.html">&lt;p&gt;This blog post is about digital transformation in health and care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I discuss our aspirations to create a seamless patient-centred service that blurs the boundaries between disciplines and organisations and how technology is an enabler of those ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I discuss the paradox that while the best way to build that seamless service is with technology, that technology should itself be highly modular, fragmented, and developed and continuously improved using an agile, responsive, adaptive approach that uses real-life fast feedback and a continuous learning culture. Modularisation permits rapid deployment and iteration in parallel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, I discuss the importance of an overarching set of broad principles, adoption of open technical standards, openness and transparency to set strategic direction (“this is where we want to go”) while at the same time creating smaller, semi-independent teams trusted, and empowered, to take the incremental steps to get us closer to our intended destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, I reinforce the need to think carefully about how we structure our technical architecture and governance to start that journey - accepting that we will need to adapt and change our approach as we learn how to deliver health and care technology in a different way to that used previously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;transforming-health-and-care-creating-a-seamless-service&quot;&gt;Transforming health and care: creating a seamless service&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital technology is going to transform healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We’re at the beginning of the digital revolution”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;by Bill Gates in his foreword to Satya Nadella’s book “Hit Refresh”, published not, as you might initially guess, twenty years ago, but in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health and care organisations, and those in charge of running health care systems, such as those within the National Health Services in the UK, need to understand that it is no longer appropriate to treat information technology as something separate from their core business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The BMW Group’s CEO that said in the future the BMW Group expected more than half its R&amp;amp;D staff to be software developers.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Edward Taylor and Ilona Wissenbach, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/autoshow-geneva-software/exclusive-at-100-bmw-sees-radical-new-future-in-world-of-driverless-cars-idUSKCN0W60HP&quot;&gt;“Exclusive—At 100, BMW Sees Radical New Future in World of Driverless Cars,” Reuters, March 3, 2016&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see that in many industries - and that’s not only because of modern innovations such as mobile devices, machine learning and our ability to process enormous sets of data, but simply because information technology is the best way to deliver the results that we want: a seamless, responsive, patient-centred, evidence-based healthcare system that, at its heart, is driven by patients and professionals working together; collaboration, communication and a data-driven approach to building health and care services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, our goal must be to achieve a seamless, responsive, patient-centred “one system” healthcare service within NHS Wales, and technology is critical in enabling that. We need to break down silos between disciplines and organisations and draw together the common strands of work that underpin care for an individual patient while also caring for populations of patients and enabling better service design, supporting ongoing continuous improvement and transforming clinical research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be no surprise to see that a seamless “one system” outcome is explicit in the new NHS Wales health and care strategy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://gov.wales/sites/default/files/publications/2019-04/in-brief-a-healthier-wales-our-plan-for-health-and-social-care.pdf&quot;&gt;A Healthier Wales.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have have to ask a question: what is the right approach to delivering technology for health and care to deliver that seamless service?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One option is to think that we can use top-down centrally-driven diktat to build a single solution for our “single” service and impose that solution on our services, but is that the right way to deliver software in health and care?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-software-value-chain-delivering-what-we-need&quot;&gt;The software value chain: delivering what we need&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health and care needs &lt;em&gt;software delivery at scale&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to become much much better at developing, deploying and constantly evaluating and improving software, because software is critical to what we need to do improve our health and care system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The problem is not with our organizations realizing that they need to transform; the problem is that organizations are using managerial frameworks and infrastructure models from past revolutions to manage their businesses in this one.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Kersten, Mik. Project to Product . IT Revolution Press. Kindle Edition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health and care needs to learn how to deliver software : reliably, safely, reproducibly, at scale and to ensure ongoing monitoring, evaluation and continuous improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is a paradox. We know that the &lt;em&gt;worst&lt;/em&gt; ways to create a seamless “one system” approach are thinking we can build a single monolithic application or expect the procurement of a “system” to solve, for example, closer working and communication between health and social care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to &lt;em&gt;slow down&lt;/em&gt; delivery is to have an approach to technical architecture and wider governance structures that slows down the &lt;em&gt;software value chain&lt;/em&gt;. The key to software delivery is delivery, and yet some organisations treat software as if they were managing capital projects such as building a new road or a bridge. In most cases, the technology is the easy bit; its the implementation on the ground across multiple complex adaptive systems that is most difficult. But we also need a design that makes it easy and safe to &lt;em&gt;change&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who think building technology is difficult and complex tend to want to centralise and control its development, because that feels less risky, but that approach is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the advent of readily-available frameworks, rapid application development tools and drag-and-drop user interface design, building software is actually quite easy! What is hard is integration and deployment - the actual implementation of technology to support the transformation of health and care services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the best ways to speed up delivery of valuable technology are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) to become &lt;em&gt;agile&lt;/em&gt;,
b) break up our software architecture into smaller, easier-to-manage products and, 
c) create strong leadership to ensure a cohesive credible strategic approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agility means recognising the benefits of adaptability, flexibility and fast feedback. Health and care need to learn from other industries who are adopting these practices with pace, and improving the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/articles/path-devops&quot;&gt;safety and reliability of their software delivery pipeline&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modularisation and unbundling of services means that they can be developed independently, in parallel, with agreed technical standards defining their interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just because we have multiple modules all being built, deployed and continuously improved independently, it doesn’t mean that each doesn’t form a cog in the wider &lt;em&gt;single system&lt;/em&gt;. By single system, we should mean a credible, coherent, overall high-level strategic approach means that there are clear principles that guide all of our work, with definite and explicit direction-of-travel, but empowered teams delivering the incremental steps on that, truly collaborative, journey. That means a shared vision, but small steps, and that doesn’t mean only for our technology products but in our overall approach to management and leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To succeed, a team must be a real working group with proper time to devote to change, rather than a ‘steering committee’ who meet once a quarter for lunch. The team will achieve little if the ‘Agile’ element is merely added on top of their existing jobs. Proper time and space must be devoted to this, which means freeing individuals from existing commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.emergn.com/blog/7-steps-to-building-an-agile-organization/&quot;&gt;Seven steps to building an agile organisation &lt;/a&gt;, checked on 18/9/2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of our decisions are nuanced and a balance of positives and negatives, not unlike the practise of medicine itself, and such decisions must surely balance a range of factors including existing investments, cost, value, opportunity cost of not delivering valuable software. As such, we need to also focus on openness and transparency and that means clearly articulating the decisions that need to be made, how we are going to approach them, and finally the delicate balancing act that weighs up those factors. One important principle of agility is to make smaller, incremental decisions so that we lower risk and create greater opportunities to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-does-this-mean-for-wales&quot;&gt;What does this mean for Wales?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Admitting that we don’t know, leads to a better outcome”
War and Peace and IT by Mark Schwartz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Incremental releases for bigger changes”
from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kainos.com/making-safe-and-frequent-improvements-to-the-uk-passport-service&quot;&gt;Making Safe and Frequent Improvements to the UK Passport Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Our work can be used to engender culture change, and inculcate a respect for the appropriate use of technical standards across health and care in Wales. “
from my &lt;a href=&quot;https://standards.cymru/posts/2019-04-24-standards-culture/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; for the Welsh Technical Standards Board (WTSB)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have so many amazing individuals and teams across health and care in Wales, and so much drive to continuously improve and transform services. Our work, across health and care in Wales, should be one to provide a toolbox of computing and data services that can be used to support the transformation of how we work, collaboratively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I don’t really care what patient administrative system an organisation uses; I’m far more interested in the articulation of the &lt;em&gt;outcomes we want&lt;/em&gt;, and a balanced decision as to the best way to achieve those outcomes with some broad principles to provide consistency on that weighing up procedure, together with what information goes in and what information comes out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, we have seen different PAS replaced with a “national PAS” in different organisations in Wales, but each has been configured differently and we still have no easy way of tracking pathways for patients across organisations, and any clear consistency on how specialities are coded. Likewise, I have used a “national application” to view a patient and found out that patient is alive when I’m sitting in one clinic, and dead in another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to see how we’d reach agreement on high-level outcomes - what I do care about for PAS is that we have a single patient record, that record is accurate and up-to-date, and that I can track pathways of care across organisational boundaries; once we agree the desired outcomes within a specific domain, we can apply our broad principles to start to tackle those needs by standardising our contracts between software components, without necessarily having to standardise the components themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;strategic-flexible-programmes-but-specific-products-and-small-long-lived-teams&quot;&gt;Strategic, flexible programmes but specific products and small, long-lived teams&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our goals is to generate a credible and &lt;em&gt;cohesive&lt;/em&gt; strategy to deliver valuable software for our teams across health and care in Wales. I’m interested in finding the natural fault lines in our overall work to create strategic programmes that can work semi-independently from others, and so minimise the need for constant checks and approvals from advisory groups, boards and stakeholders. Such an approach minimises dependencies and the lessens the need for constant coordination. Good governance is essential, but good governance is also streamlined and efficient governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is seductive to think about programmes of work delineated by specialty, service or organisation. That approach leads to programmes such as a “National imaging programme board”, who has led on procurement of a new Picture Archive Communication System (PACS) for radiology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is probably better to think of programmes of work aligned to strategic themes instead - orientated to the outcomes we want, so that there is alignment and cohesiveness, when possible. For example, it is possible that an imaging programme board might recommend procurement of electronic test requesting functionality at the same time as laboratory colleagues procure the same functionality for laboratory tests. If these programmes are not aligned, and occur independently, test requesting will not feel cohesive for end-users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One option is to ensure that all stakeholders for all programmes all talk to one another, but that results in an exponential need for cross-talk and slow, difficult decision-making because all programmes of work are dependent on one another. Instead, programmes of work should be aligned strategically in core domains aligned to operational outcomes, planning to minimise cross-dependencies and coordination, and explicitly recognising common needs and adopting a &lt;em&gt;platform&lt;/em&gt; approach to common national services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, it might well be best to procure separate electronic test requesting functionality to get early benefits, so that professionals and patients get functionality delivered quickly, but strategically, ensure that both radiology and laboratory procurements provide standards-based APIs so that a concierge service can be built to streamline workflow for end-users. It is almost certainly wrong to jump to a decision on this today, as it may be that electronic test requesting is provided at no cost bundled with a laboratory management system, for example: our goal surely is to build capacity for empowered teams to make these kinds of decisions because they will be the experts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognising that we don’t have &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;all of the answers&lt;/a&gt; is absolutely essential, but that doesn’t stop us taking responsibility for the broad over-arching principles and guard-rails that define our overall mission. I’m pretty sure that we will have to adapt and modify our plans as we go along, and be open and transparent about how we discover hitherto unconsidered challenges and how we will learn to overcome them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In keeping with an agile ethos, the best way to really understand how health and care in Wales can benefit from this approach is to try it with small experiments and get fast feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t need to have a big-bang approach to transformation, or indeed, plan massive re-organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, what can we do now to prove the effectiveness of this approach?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d prioritise three programmes of work in order to a) create early benefit, and b) learn whether this approach can work in health and care, identifying unforeseen challenges and refining our approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Demographics programme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Appointments and scheduling programme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;API management/authentication/authorisation logging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demographics are an essential core requirement for a single patient record, and this programme might focus on coordinating the following products:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A HL7 FHIR based canonical demographic application programming interface (API)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A legacy HL7v2 pull/push demographic update messaging service (for legacy applications)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enterprise master patient index&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patient administrative systems (PAS) - ie subsuming demographics user group and working with health boards to harmonise our understanding/processing of demographic data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, appointments and scheduling are a vital foundational service and the data and computing services underpin several important products such as professional-facing applications like a national portal as well as patient-facing portals and applications. In addition, our work on single cancer pathway and outcomes relies on an understanding of patient’s interactions across the health service, such as appointments in multiple hospitals and in different departments such as radiology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s already clear that appointments and scheduling have a dependency on demographics - we need to track a patient across organisations irrespective of their local identifiers. We can contractually define the dependency between these two programmes so that our appointments and scheduling programme can simply rely on an abstract computing service that manages the complexity and edge-cases inherent in demographic matching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appointments and scheduling strategic programme might initially include the following products:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A HL7 FHIR based unified appointments and scheduling view across multiple organisations and departments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An analytics product that streams and stores (warehouse) appointment and scheduling information to permit analytics and real-time dashboards of service use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A patient-facing portal to provide a simple view of upcoming appointments, with an initial concierge service to provide functionality to change appointments (this could be managed by humans initially and yet still provide valuable functionality for citizens).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integration with commercial off-the-shelf patient portals, such as the “Patients Know Best” portal in pilot in Swansea Bay and Cardiff &amp;amp; Vale, so that appointments are visible to patients using these products.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could include work to look at how we might manage to provide similar functionality for healthcare services for NHS Wales citizens whose care involves crossing over into NHS England, reinforcing the need to adopt open technical standards and work in partnership with external stakeholders. I’ve sketched out a more detailed “Appointments and scheduling” programme &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1aXDqANyTzPzwf9I2Rvq6yIEnaj-qYqi0a0VuMttDHWg/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One key aspect to this approach is a flexible, prioritised and adaptive approach to deciding on the structure of programmes, but software delivery made up of small, focused, and long-lived cross-functional developer teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried to show this in the following schematic, but this is simply a broad-brush, illustrative approach and not a fixed, regimented plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/governance.png&quot; alt=&quot;Governance&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see “guilds” or “tribes”, with specialist expertise in specific vertical domains such as security, engineering, and design, advising and being brought together into specific small teams to deliver specific products, such as an API for demographic data that are governed and coordinated, at least initially, by a strategic programme, because at the moment, we are starting from a fragmented and incoherent set of national and local systems, services and applications. Over time, our strategic programmes can and must evolve to meet the ever changing challenges we face, while our product teams continue to work to deliver valuable software components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, we might recognise three different categories of small, long-lived team that will be needed as we mature in our approach in health and care:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A value-stream aligned team type - focused on solving problems by understanding and then delivering software for end-users. This might be a team responsible for building a patient-facing application.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An enabling team type - a “squad” - focused on supporting product teams in specific technical domains - in other words, a technical consulting team that works across product teams to empower and up-skill, in a collaborative way. For example, I understand that this is how Google’s Site Reliability Engineers (SRE) work. Such teams might extend their work across other public sector services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A platform team type - focused on building core, common data and computing services that underpin delivering applications to end-users, often hiding underlying complexity or specialisms by providing an easy-to-use self-service API.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an approach similar to that outlined in &lt;a href=&quot;https://teamtopologies.com&quot;&gt;Team Topologies by Matthew Skelton&lt;/a&gt;, and indeed, we can see that it is likely that, over time, platform services will become increasingly more complex, and leverage other platform services as our demands and expectations rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of our work here is in building &lt;em&gt;capability&lt;/em&gt; - capability to adapt to change and deliver at pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;governance-that-follows-architecture&quot;&gt;Governance that follows architecture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implicit in this approach is recognition that our technical architecture and governance must go hand-in-hand. As we know:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Any organization that designs a system (defined broadly) will produce a design whose structure is a copy of the organization’s communication structure.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dr Conway, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.melconway.com/Home/Conways_Law.html&quot;&gt;http://www.melconway.com/Home/Conways_Law.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means recognising that a modern, health and care enterprise architecture might look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/domains-functional-and-business.png&quot; alt=&quot;Domains Functional And Business&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In which there is loose-coupling between modular components providing software and data services, orientated and aligned with important strategic business (operational) domains. We will move towards lightweight applications that are focused on creating delightful user-centred workflows, that leverage platform services for business logic and data services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This blog post is about digital transformation in health and care.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reading list</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/05/16/reading-list.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reading list" /><published>2019-05-16T11:05:05+01:00</published><updated>2019-05-16T11:05:05+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/05/16/reading-list</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/05/16/reading-list.html">&lt;p&gt;These are books that I have enjoyed and found useful. I recommend them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=16&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiZqPf585_iAhXQSxUIHXWnDEQQFjAPegQIBRAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FDomain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software%2Fdp%2F0321125215&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0t-MzcuNObPOLp3MloCBt_&quot;&gt;Domain-Driven Design: Tackling Complexity in the Heart of Software&lt;/a&gt; by Eric Evans&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/War-Peace-Business-Leadership-Technology/dp/1942788711&quot;&gt;War and Peace and IT: Business Leadership, Technology, and Success in the Digital Age&lt;/a&gt; by Mark Schwartz&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Seat-Table-Leadership-Age-Agility/dp/1942788118&quot;&gt;A Seat at the Table: IT Leadership in the Age of Agility&lt;/a&gt; by Mark Schwartz&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Accelerate-Building-Performing-Technology-Organizations/dp/B07BLYJ4HR&quot;&gt;Accelerate: Building and Scaling High Performing Technology Organizations&lt;/a&gt; by Nicole Forsgren,  Jez Humble, Gene Kim&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjMmIPN7Z_iAhXiTxUIHfBRDjQQFjAAegQIBRAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FPhoenix-Project-Helping-Business-Anniversary%2Fdp%2FB00VBEBRK6&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2Vpyz5uZj3Dekuv3QbZSGa&quot;&gt;The Phoenix Project: A Novel about IT, DevOps, and Helping Your Business Win&lt;/a&gt; by Gene Kim, Kevin Behr, George Spafford&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwj935rb7Z_iAhU8SRUIHUf7AVoQFjAAegQIAxAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FThinking-Fast-Slow-Daniel-Kahneman%2Fdp%2F0141033576&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2DrhLGTE9IzK9ZIN1G4wVt&quot;&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow&lt;/a&gt; by Daniel Kahneman&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Hit-Refresh-Rediscover-Microsofts-Everyone-ebook/dp/B01HOT5SQA&quot;&gt;Hit Refresh&lt;/a&gt; by Satya Nadella&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=4&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjzlMv07Z_iAhWKRhUIHVoQANYQFjADegQIARAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FDevops-Handbook-World-Class-Reliability-Organizations%2Fdp%2F1942788002&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2KNX9830TcnjCmlLxp53PR&quot;&gt;The DevOps Handbook: How to Create World-Class Agility, Reliability, and Security in Technology Organizations&lt;/a&gt; by Gene Kim,Patrick Debois, John Willis, Jez Humble&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Startup-Way-Entrepreneurial-Management-Transforms/dp/0241197260&quot;&gt;The Startup Way: How Entrepreneurial Management Transforms Culture and Drives Growth&lt;/a&gt; by Eric Ries&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Lean-Startup-Innovation-Successful-Businesses/dp/0670921602/ref=pd_lpo_sbs_14_t_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&amp;amp;refRID=1K8FBPY06VDPM15DQNF7&quot;&gt;The Lean Startup: How Constant Innovation Creates Radically Successful Businesses&lt;/a&gt; by Eric Ries&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwj5uZeu95_iAhWlThUIHe-xDZkQFjAAegQIAxAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FBuilding-Evolutionary-Architectures-Neal-Ford%2Fdp%2F1491986360&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3bcrPv8RyP9zfZrTfsOXIu&quot;&gt;Building evolutionary architectures&lt;/a&gt; by Neal Ford&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiTqPq595_iAhWLQxUIHXKcAwEQFjAAegQIBBAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FPrinciples-Health-Interoperability-Information-Technology%2Fdp%2F3319303686&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3OjhLqYzPZ74izL0uL-aG8&quot;&gt;Principles of Health Interoperability HL7 and SNOMED&lt;/a&gt; by Tim Benson and Graham Grieve&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/How-Measure-Anything-Intangibles-Business/dp/1452654204&quot;&gt;How to Measure Anything: Finding the Value of ‘Intangibles’ in Business&lt;/a&gt; by Douglas W. Hubbard&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Black-Box-Thinking-Surprising-Success/dp/1473613779&quot;&gt;Black Box Thinking: The Surprising Truth About Success&lt;/a&gt; by Matthew Syed&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Work-Rules-Insights-Inside-Transform/dp/1444792369&quot;&gt;Work Rules!: Insights From Inside GoogleThat Will Transform How You Live and Lead&lt;/a&gt; by Laszlo Bock&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwil-vr375_iAhVQUhUIHTotCSUQFjAAegQIABAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FDigital-Doctor-Hope-Medicines-Computer%2Fdp%2F0071849467&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0ckCrG86Z0pK8FTaDNNDGI&quot;&gt;The Digital Doctor: Hope, Hype, and Harm at the Dawn of Medicine’s Computer Age&lt;/a&gt; by Robert Wachter&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Hard-Thing-About-Things-Building/dp/0062273205&quot;&gt;The Hard Thing About Hard Things: Building a Business When There Are No Easy Answers&lt;/a&gt; by Ben Horowitz&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjcxL6N8J_iAhWCUBUIHYcABDQQFjAAegQIAhAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FGood-Strategy-Bad-Difference-Matters%2Fdp%2F1846684811&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0hTYQmAhteo5bg90onBbVT&quot;&gt;Good Strategy/Bad Strategy: The Difference and Why It Matters&lt;/a&gt; by Richard P. Rumelt&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Tribes-We-need-you-lead/dp/0749939753&quot;&gt;Tribes: We Need You to Lead Us&lt;/a&gt; by Seth Godin&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/aclk?sa=L&amp;amp;ai=DChcSEwi0-NCg8J_iAhWuu-0KHbGxAFoYABABGgJkZw&amp;amp;sig=AOD64_1sx_nZ7mLepXsbjc8y41NJ5xO1OQ&amp;amp;ctype=5&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwiq68Wg8J_iAhXbSBUIHYdxBOwQ9aACCDY&amp;amp;adurl=&quot;&gt;The Lean Startup: How Today’s Entrepreneurs Use Continuous Innovation to Create Radically Successful Businesses&lt;/a&gt; by Eric Ries&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=3&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiig4it8J_iAhW3SBUIHe-nC6YQFjACegQIERAK&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.com%2FStart-Why-Leaders-Inspire-Everyone%2Fdp%2F1591846447&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2dceDsbE2RA1TaPcqip1mL&quot;&gt;Start with Why: How Great Leaders Inspire Everyone to Take Action&lt;/a&gt; by Simon Sinek&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Innovators-Dilemma-Technologies-Management-Innovation/dp/1633691780/ref=pd_lpo_sbs_14_t_2?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&amp;amp;refRID=YBWTH3N4N7ZVTPQ2DWAJ&quot;&gt;The Innovator’s Dilemma: When New Technologies Cause Great Firms to Fail (Management of Innovation and Change)&lt;/a&gt; by Clayton M. Christensen.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;books-recommended-to-me-via-twitter&quot;&gt;Books recommended to me via Twitter&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Update: 18th May 2019&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since posting on Twitter, other people have recommended a range of books that I haven’t read, yet. Here’s the list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Innovators-Prescription-Disruptive-Solution-Health/dp/0071592083&quot;&gt;The Innovator’s Prescription&lt;/a&gt; by Clayton Christiansen, Jerome Grossman and Jason Hwang. Recommended by Chris Minmnagh.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Machine-That-Changed-World/dp/1847370551&quot;&gt;The Machine That Changed The World&lt;/a&gt; by James Womack, Daniel Jones and Daniel Roos. Recommended by Mike Broomhead.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cyber.harvard.edu/publications/2012/interop&quot;&gt;Interop: The Promise and Perils of Highly Interconnected Systems&lt;/a&gt; by John Palfrey and Urs Gasser. Recommended by Ian McNicoll.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Design-Essays-Computer-Scientist/dp/0201362988&quot;&gt;The Design of Design&lt;/a&gt; by Fred Brooks. Recommended by Thomas Beale.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Bad-Blood-Secrets-Silicon-Startup/dp/1509868062&quot;&gt;Bad blood&lt;/a&gt; by John Carreyrou. Recommended by Mike Broomhead.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Mythical-Man-Month-Software-Engineering-Anniversary/dp/0201835959/ref=sr_1_1?crid=3FKT2201SYVPZ&amp;amp;keywords=mythical+man+month&amp;amp;qid=1558215791&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;sprefix=mythical+man%2Cstripbooks%2C136&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;The Mythical Man Month&lt;/a&gt; by Fred Brooks. Recommended by Joe Hunter.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Before-Disrupting-Healthcare-What-Innovators/dp/1532923864/ref=sr_1_fkmrnull_1?keywords=before+disrupting+healthcare&amp;amp;qid=1558215900&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;sr=1-1-fkmrnull&quot;&gt;Before Disrupting Healthcare:  What Innovators Need to Know&lt;/a&gt; by Pallav Sharda. Recommended by Mian Sanon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Learn-Think-Systems-Archetypes-Understand-ebook/dp/B07MZWTJHC/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=learn+to+think+in+systems&amp;amp;qid=1558215930&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;Learn to Think in Systems&lt;/a&gt; by Albert Rutherford. Recommended by Mian Sanon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Implementing-Domain-Driven-Design-Vaughn-Vernon/dp/0321834577&quot;&gt;Implementing Domain-driven design&lt;/a&gt; by Vaughn Vernon. Recommended by Seref Arikan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Getting-Yes-Negotiating-agreement-without/dp/1847940935&quot;&gt;Getting to Yes: Negotiating an agreement without giving in&lt;/a&gt; by Roger Fisher. Recommended by Steve Baguley&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;New blog post, 16th May 2019: my reading list on information technology and healthcare... &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/zcmuSeym2c&quot;&gt;https://t.co/zcmuSeym2c&lt;/a&gt; Any other books I&amp;#39;ve missed or that you&amp;#39;d recommend? &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/HO6AFcRs43&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/HO6AFcRs43&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mark Wardle (@mwardle) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mwardle/status/1128981734262005761?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Have you read &amp;quot;the innovators prescription &amp;quot; by Clayton Christensen.&lt;br /&gt;Has a great breakdown of which bits of health can go off the mainframe first.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dr Chris Mimnagh (@ChrisMimnagh) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ChrisMimnagh/status/1129275722223300608?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 17, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Also: &amp;quot; The Machine That Changed The World&amp;quot; -- evidence-based explanation of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ToyotaMotorCorp?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@ToyotaMotorCorp&lt;/a&gt; Production System, essential learning about Lean. Am part-way through reading and already finding it to be a must-read for &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Lean?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#Lean&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Agile?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#Agile&lt;/a&gt; (meaning not just software dev)&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mike Broomhead (@MikeBroomhead) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MikeBroomhead/status/1129854878996684801?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 18, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;und&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/ApbqA104jv&quot;&gt;https://t.co/ApbqA104jv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ian McNicoll (@ianmcnicoll) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ianmcnicoll/status/1129088003178151936?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Fred Brooks The Design of Design &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/UnKkW64Vdg&quot;&gt;https://t.co/UnKkW64Vdg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Woland&amp;#39;s cat (@wolands_cat) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/wolands_cat/status/1129078609887584257?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Well &amp;quot;Bad Blood&amp;quot; - the Theranos story by John Carreyrou is utterly and horrifically fascinating !&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mike Broomhead (@MikeBroomhead) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MikeBroomhead/status/1129708924687589376?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 18, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Fred brooks mythical man month&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Joe Hunter (@joehunter) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/joehunter/status/1128988774900408323?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Before Disrupting Healthcare - Pallav Sharda&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Learn to Think in Systems- Albert Rutherford &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Not that I agree 100% with either. But the broad perspectives are important.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mian Sanon (@MianSanon) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MianSanon/status/1128984704630308869?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I’d suggest Vaugh Vernon for Ddd Lots of lessons were learned whilst industry followed Evans, V.V gives you those, more solid examples and relevant practices too.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Seref Arikan (@SerefArikan) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SerefArikan/status/1129075962329665536?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I found Getting to Yes pretty useful when it comes to implementation.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Steve Baguley (@stevebaguley) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/stevebaguley/status/1129053887850270720?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">These are books that I have enjoyed and found useful. I recommend them!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A manifesto for digital transformation in healthcare in Wales</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/11/12/manifesto-wales.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A manifesto for digital transformation in healthcare in Wales" /><published>2018-11-12T12:12:12+00:00</published><updated>2018-11-12T12:12:12+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/11/12/manifesto-wales</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/11/12/manifesto-wales.html">&lt;p&gt;We have an extraordinary opportunity to transform the way we think about the use of digital technology in healthcare in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My manifesto has five core principles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We don’t have all of the answers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only constant is change.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We should work in the open; we must be transparent and foster rigorous debate.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We set broad top-down principles and standards, but empower trusted teams who have freedom to deliver but also take responsibility for their work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We must deliver, deliver and then deliver again; we iterate, we improve and we continuously learn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology is a tool; our work in developing and deploying technology is not an end in itself but instead, its use should help us to deliver our wider strategic aims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It therefore follows that our goals must be to deliver technology as quickly and as safely as possible. Some argue that those goals are contradictory, but evidence from the highest performing technology teams shows that adding more processes and procedures designed to add safety has the paradoxical effect of worsening safety. As such, we need to rethink our approach to project management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our culture must be open so that we are transparent about our success and our failures. We must foster constructive debate. Challenge me to defend this approach and let’s all learn from it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is seductive to think that, as a small nation, we should centralise. It is similarly seductive to think that we lower risk by centralisation. Neither are true. Getting more and more engagement to understand requirements up front &lt;em&gt;does not work&lt;/em&gt;. The best approach is to deliver functioning technology and then improve it based on rapid and continuous feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As none of us have all of the answers and we work in a complex and highly adaptive group of organisations, we must recognise that any credible plan must, itself, be adaptive and capable of evolutionary change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, we must recognise that one size truly does not fit all. While Wales is of similar size to a strategic health authority in England, our structures and existing technological investments are much more complex. One of our goals must be to safely reduce needless variation, and yet at the same time foster innovation, permitting that new work to scale across all of our services when it is proven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not one approach solves everything we face; instead we should buy products that are an established solution to a problem and focus our in-house work on solving problems that only the public sector can do. That means blending different approaches and being transparent about the decisions we make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The steps we need to take are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;focus on our customers; that means professionals &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; patients. We align our information technology work with our wider service goals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;modularisation, so we break apart our architecture into smaller, discrete components that can be developed independently of the whole.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;create small, cross-functional teams who are tasked with delivering those modules, iteratively, building in quality and safety from the onset.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adopt open standards, so that we standardise the interactions between our modules speeding up delivery by permitting parallel developments and limiting the number of people from different teams who need to be involved in any decision.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prioritise tools to acquire, store and make sense of meaningful clinical data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;become open by default; for example, one of our first debates must be whether it makes any sense to run two data centres in Wales. Let’s debate!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;focus on developer productivity, let’s copy the architectural and cultural practices from the most productive technology teams.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we should consider developers in three broad categories, and treat them equally with the same tools, frameworks and documentation available, those providing shared national services and components, those working in and across health boards developing solutions using the national toolbox of services and those outside of the NHS in a thriving commercial and academic ecosystem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I truly believe that Wales could have the best health information technology in the World. We are small, we have a unique and special health service that could be transformed by the safe and efficient deployment of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we need to do things differently to what has been tried in the past. Almost all of my blog posts explore these issues in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tell me what you think, let’s debate… and &lt;em&gt;learn&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We have an extraordinary opportunity to transform the way we think about the use of digital technology in healthcare in Wales.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Semantic interoperability: SNOMED CT, post-coordination and the model</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/terminology/2018/10/27/snomed-postcoordination-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Semantic interoperability: SNOMED CT, post-coordination and the model" /><published>2018-10-27T20:10:19+01:00</published><updated>2018-10-27T20:10:19+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/terminology/2018/10/27/snomed-postcoordination-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/terminology/2018/10/27/snomed-postcoordination-1.html">&lt;p&gt;One of our goals in healthcare information technology is to enable the meaningful exchange of information between distributed systems in the support of three broad purposes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;direct care,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;management and quality improvement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clinical research.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is insufficient to simply exchange information at a technical level, but we must aim for &lt;em&gt;semantic&lt;/em&gt; interoperability so that we exchange &lt;em&gt;meaningful data&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I say meaningful data, I mean data that has meaning and can be used for decisions, in order to reduce uncertainty about those decisions. Those decisions may be made by a professional, by a patient or carer, or much more likely, shared decisions among groups of those individuals. Those decisions may be clinical, such as should we start anticoagulation to prevent a stroke, or administrative, such as how many patients should we book into that clinic?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I use the term meaningful data, I also  include the ability to use software to process that information; it is computable. It is important to understanding the benefits of computable information, because computer software is quite simply the best way to make sense of large amounts of information. Making data computable means our clinical work can become &lt;em&gt;data-driven&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making our data computable means that machines can help in processing and understanding, and with the advent of machine learning, even make or suggest decisions based on information. But this post isn’t about machine learning, although it is, I believe, a foundational step for the appropriate and meaningful development and application of machine learning in healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this blog post is about how we can record information in a way that is useful to both humans and machines. For humans it should mean data can be entered more quickly and for machines, it permits better processing so that they can support us humans!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-be-data-driven&quot;&gt;How to be data-driven&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SNOMED CT is a comprehensive terminology and ontology for use in healthcare and it forms an important component of the solution to semantic interoperability. I implemented SNOMED CT in a electronic patient record system and it has been live and running for clinical use in the UK since 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SNOMED CT model consists of three core entities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;concepts, represents a unique concept&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;descriptions, represents synonyms for a concept&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;relationships, represents relationships between concepts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve written extensively about SNOMED-CT on this blog; the best way of understanding the ontology is to browse using an &lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk&quot;&gt;online browser&lt;/a&gt; but SNOMED International provide &lt;a href=&quot;https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCSTART/1.+Introduction&quot;&gt;a useful introductory guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;concepts&quot;&gt;Concepts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many concepts represent a single independent concept, but many are actually &lt;em&gt;compound&lt;/em&gt;, representing a number of concepts combined into a meaningful whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cholecystectomy&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=38102005&quot;&gt;38102005&lt;/a&gt;) is a single concept representing removal of the gallbladder. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Laparoscopic cholecystectomy&lt;/code&gt; is single concept representing removal of the gallbladder with a laparoscope (&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=45595009&quot;&gt;45595009&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A SNOMED CT &lt;em&gt;expression&lt;/em&gt; combines concepts without needing every possible combination of concepts to be created within the terminology. For example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;80146002|appendectomy|
   :260870009|priority|=25876001|emergency|,
   425391005|using access device|=86174004|laparoscope|
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;represents performing an appendicectomy as an emergency using an laparoscope. We could add this as a distinct single concept into SNOMED CT but that would result in a combinatorial explosion; that means we’d have to have single concepts representing all possible permutations which is simply not practical. However, mainly for historical reasons or to ease implementation, SNOMED CT does already contains many single concepts that combines multiple concepts into one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, SNOMED CT expressions are a powerful way of refining a concept with additional information, creating, in effect, a clinical phrase. This technique is called &lt;em&gt;post-coordination&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-not-use-post-coordination&quot;&gt;Why not use post-coordination?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have usually advocated keeping the implementation of SNOMED CT simple by using only pre-coordinated concepts. My concerns about using post-coordination have been that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it added complexity to end-users in terms of selection and display of terms,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it made data storage more difficult, and would break referential integrity in my own system.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it would complicate using those terms at a computational level e.g. in automated decision support.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we gain significant value simply from recording pre-coordinated concepts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is (1) and (3) that concerned me most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in my own electronic health record software, users don’t know that they are selecting SNOMED terms; they start typing and it autocompletes or simply choose an option using a pop-up, choose a part of the anatomy from a picture or a term is imputed on the basis of other data entered. Adding complexity in adding refinements or qualifiers or embedding expressions worried me. I wanted to make SNOMED CT invisible to end-users and yet enable new decision support and analytics capabilities, hitherto not possible using unstructured free-text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t conceived of a simple way to make using SNOMED invisible if I created functionality to build expressions; I now think differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;information-models&quot;&gt;Information models&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in the majority of cases, I think many uses of post-coordination such as qualification or refinement or additional information should instead be a function of the wider information model in which the SNOMED CT concept is recorded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the FHIR definition of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/condition.html&quot;&gt;Condition&lt;/a&gt;, which includes metadata about the problem/diagnosis concept is shown here:
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/snomed-postcoord/fhir-condition.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Fhir Condition&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It includes information relating to status (active/inactive etc), verification (provisional, differential) and severity (severe, moderate, mild), as well as information about the condition’s onset and abatement (remission/resolution).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we use post-coordination without carefully considering the consequences and their mitigation, given that there is an overlap between information recorded within an expression and the wider information model, we risk duplication, complexity and inconsistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;computing-attributes&quot;&gt;Computing attributes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are clearly situations where refining a concept with additional information would be helpful. For example, we really wanted to be able to add a more specific anatomical location when we recorded that a patient had a brain abscess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SNOMED-CT ontology helps us, at the computational level, determine &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; “cerebral abscess” can be refined:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=60404007&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cerebral abscess&lt;/code&gt; (60404007)&lt;/a&gt; is an abscess in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, we can determine a way to &lt;em&gt;refine&lt;/em&gt; this concept using post-coordination to specifically give the location. The ontology provides, as part of its model, attribute relationships for this concept, at a computational level:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; Is a (attribute)                   -&amp;gt; Abscess of brain (disorder)	
 Associated morphology (attribute)  -&amp;gt; Abscess (morphologic abnormality)
 Finding site (attribute)           -&amp;gt; Cerebral structure (body structure)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we can see that we can refine the concept &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cerebral abscess&lt;/code&gt; with a finding site that is a child of the concept &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Cerebral structure (body structure)&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=83678007&quot;&gt;83678007&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, computationally, we can offer a choice to the end-user to refine this concept with any finding site, such as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Structure of parahippocampal gyrus&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=13989007&quot;&gt;13989007&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we can add refinements as a result of our concept being in one of the nine main SNOMED CT hierarchies. The attributes appropriate for each hierarchy are listed &lt;a href=&quot;https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCSTART/6.+SNOMED+CT+Concept+Model&quot;&gt;on the SNOMED International concept model documentation&lt;/a&gt;. For example, a clinical finding can be qualified by adding concepts representing a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Finding Site&lt;/code&gt;, a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Causative Agent&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Severity&lt;/code&gt; among others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we can add refinements because of the existence of our concept within a certain reference set. For example, there is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=723264001&quot;&gt;laterality reference set&lt;/a&gt; that tells us which concepts can be lateralised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is therefore straightforward to imagine that, if a cerebral abscess is entered by a user as a diagnostic concept, we might configure our user interface or natural language parser to look for and refine that diagnostic concept with additional information relating to finding site, appropriately limited to the brain using subsumption, given that we have entered cerebral abscess, and offering a choice of laterality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we can see that location, laterality and causative agents &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be very appropriate options for refinement, but should we let users post-coordinate diagnostic concepts with a type of ```Severity’’’? This matters because we need to think about how we write software to process these terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;equivalence-and-the-importance-of-meaning&quot;&gt;Equivalence and the importance of meaning&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key issue with processing SNOMED CT, either as pre-coordinated terms or as expressions, is to ensure that we can process &lt;em&gt;meaning&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means that, in any implementation of SNOMED CT, whether using only pre-coordinated terms or post-coordination to create an expression, we need to handle equivalence at not just the level of SNOMED, but also take into account the wider information model, providing the context in which that concept or expression sits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a HL7 FHIR representation of a condition looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;resourceType&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Condition&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Resource&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;meta,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;implicitRules,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;language&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;DomainResource&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;contained,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;extension,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;modifierExtension&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;identifier&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Identifier&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}],&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;External&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Ids&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;condition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;clinicalStatus&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&amp;lt;code&amp;gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;C?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;active&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;recurrence&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;inactive&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;remission&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;resolved&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;verificationStatus&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&amp;lt;code&amp;gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;C?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;provisional&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;differential&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;confirmed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;refuted&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;entered-in-error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;unknown&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;category&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;CodeableConcept&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}],&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;problem-list-item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;encounter-diagnosis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;severity&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;CodeableConcept&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Subjective&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;severity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;condition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;code&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;CodeableConcept&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Identification&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;the&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;condition,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;problem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;or&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;diagnosis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;bodySite&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;CodeableConcept&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}],&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Anatomical&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;location,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;relevant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;subject&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Reference(Patient|Group)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;R!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Who&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;has&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;the&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;condition?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;context&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Reference(Encounter|EpisodeOfCare)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Encounter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;or&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;episode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;when&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;condition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;first&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/datatypes.html#codeableconcept&quot;&gt;CodeableConcept&lt;/a&gt; is a complex HL7 FHIR type that provides a reference to an arbitrary terminology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/snomed-postcoord/codeable-concept.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Codeable Concept&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens if we put a concept representing “SEVERE” as the severity in the FHIR model but record a post-coordinated SNOMED CT expression of “MILD” as a qualifier of our diagnostic concept?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;meaningful-data-in-context&quot;&gt;Meaningful data, in context&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means our analytics, for direct individual care, processing data as part of an electronic health record in real-time, or for quality improvement, service management or research use, must interpret the meaning of SNOMED CT concepts and expressions &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; the wider information model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do we need from our software?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need to be able to process an arbitrary SNOMED concepts, provide the standard attribute relationships to client software so that those developers can easily understand how to refine, for example, a diagnostic term. This should include the value sets or necessary search constraints so that only appropriate values can be used for any specific attribute (e.g. if you are refining an anatomical location in the central nervous system, your values should only be anatomical locations within the central nervous system!)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need a set of tools that can parse SNOMED expressions into a useful internal representation and vice versa, so that expressions can be persisted and exchanged as well as permitting the information to be used effectively by humans and machines.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need to be able to process an arbitrary SNOMED concept or expression and normalise it into a canonical expression so that it can be used for analytics.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need tools to be able to offer additional refinement of SNOMED concepts and expressions by virtue of the wider information model in which they sit. For example, normalisation of a concept within a FHIR condition model could be automatically refined by the appropriate attributes from the wider model, such as severity.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, I have been working on a set of open-source tools that not only support deriving understanding of meaning from pre-coordinated single terms in isolation, but from SNOMED expressions and those terms &lt;em&gt;in their wider context&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of this work, I have made use of the Google HL7 FHIR protobuf definitions, which can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/google/fhir&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and are now vendored in the go-terminology code repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My next blog post in this series will cover the details of a practical implementation. Like all standards, it is only with the development and availability of quality (open-source) implementations that a standard can truly become valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">One of our goals in healthcare information technology is to enable the meaningful exchange of information between distributed systems in the support of three broad purposes:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Digital transformation in healthcare</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/digital/2018/10/23/on-digital.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digital transformation in healthcare" /><published>2018-10-23T22:21:21+01:00</published><updated>2018-10-23T22:21:21+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/digital/2018/10/23/on-digital</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/digital/2018/10/23/on-digital.html">&lt;p&gt;“We’re at the beginning of the digital revolution” wrote Bill Gates in his foreword to Satya Nadella’s book “Hit Refresh”, published not, as you might initially guess, twenty years ago, but in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This explicitly recognises that, while we have already seen remarkable changes to our lives, our societies and our cultures as a result of software, and the microprocessors on which they rely, we are actually only at the beginning of our journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2016/08/20/why-software-is-eating-the-world/&quot;&gt;“Software is eating the World”&lt;/a&gt; said Marc Andreessen, referring to the fact that in every aspect of our lives, software has disrupted the status quo and has revolutionised industries, sometimes quietly, and sometimes by storm. Commercially, we have seen businesses that have put software at the heart of their business overtaking incumbents slower to adopt technology and slower to realise the role of technology as an intrinsic foundation of all they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I work as a full-time consultant neurologist caring for patients with a range of neurological illnesses. Like most senior clinical staff, have a range of academic and leadership roles in addition to my clinical practice; in all of these roles, I see, first-hand, how the right technology could help my work and, most importantly, help the patients I directly care as well as the populations I serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what do we mean by nebulous terms such as ‘digital’ and ‘technology’ and are we right to think about a digital ‘revolution’, particularly in my own field, healthcare? After all, the technologies at our disposal continuously change improve and we have ever more computing power at our fingertips. The word ‘revolution’ suggests a fundamental and relatively sudden change and while it is true, the maturity of our digital tools sometimes advances quickly, such as near ubiquity of smart phones in the developed world, would we not be better to talk about the “digital era”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But whether we talk about a “digital revolution” or the start of a journey into a new “digital era”, what do we actually mean by “digital”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would argue that the starting point in trying to understand the implications of true digital thinking, in any industry,  is our ability to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;transfer and process information to make it accessible and useful&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rapid-and-sophisticated-processing--faster-learning&quot;&gt;Rapid and sophisticated processing = faster learning&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But weren’t we were able to transfer and process information before we had digital tools?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, most of us in healthcare still rely on paper notes but that doesn’t stop our teams collecting piles of them to audit an important quality measure of our work.  So perhaps we need to refine our understanding of the “digital revolution”, to explicitly recognise the importance of &lt;em&gt;speed, accuracy and sophistication of our processing&lt;/em&gt; enabling us to make our information ever more useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transition from film to digital cameras is a useful example of how digital technology has impacted our lives. The digital camera speeds up processing; you no longer wait weeks to see the pictures you have taken but instead see your pictures immediately, but digital tools do more than simply improve the speed of feedback, I can now also crop my images and share with friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when we talk about “accessible and useful”, aren’t we actually talking about &lt;em&gt;creating value&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;improving outcomes&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcomes in photography that are important to me are recording a cherished memory and sharing with those closest to me, and digital tools support these outcomes in a way that was not as easy with traditional film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the benefit of digital technologies over paper-based processes is that the feedback loops between our decision, in this case to take a photograph, and the outcome, can be made so much more quickly. With the right digital tools, my understanding of the best aperture and shutter speed to use in those conditions and in that situation improves; I learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting the right information at the right time, synthesised appropriately to make it useful, informs our learning and therefore our ability to make decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And digital is, quite simply, the best way to enable a learning culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-continuous-learning-system&quot;&gt;A continuous learning system&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why we are at the cusp of a true transformational change, because so many of our procedures and policies, our structures and services and even our budgets and planning, in so many industries, are rooted in the pre-digital era. That means our purchasing or budgeting decisions for solutions to problems are made on a cycle involving years. We plan projects because the pre-digital era required us to meticulous plan our work, deliver what was needed and then evaluate what we did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, digital is an important enabler of changing our mindset in all areas of our work, in healthcare and in other industries, mainly as a result of the speed and acuity of the feedback we can create by the right use of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lean methodologies teach us to defer decisions to the last &lt;em&gt;responsible&lt;/em&gt; moment, understanding that there is always uncertainty and delaying decisions permits time to gain more information and reduce that uncertainty. Agile methodologies teach us that we should be iterative in our work, breaking it up into small chunks and gaining constant feedback to guide continuous improvement. We should be adopting these principles not only in our work to develop healthcare software, but to manage and improve our services. Digital is a vital ingredient to support those methodologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, digital, and being data-driven, means our planning cycles should become shorter and shorter, because we’re using small focused interventions and data to constantly evaluate our hypotheses and build a continuously learning healthcare system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means changing the way we think about budgets and financing our work.  Similarly, our real-life prospectively recorded outcome data should be used to inform our clinical practice; we have small examples of how this can already be done but the potential of the digital era is to make such an approach ubiquitous by understanding the importance of routinely collected meaningful data and how it can be used to support decision making by patients and professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True digital transformation isn’t simply digitising our existing processes and replacing paper with a digital equivalent but instead, it is a complete change in mindset. We need to re-imagine our healthcare services with the benefit of the digital tools we have available to us and realise the value and improved outcomes that we can build on this data-driven foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;software-is-like-magic&quot;&gt;Software is like magic&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software is like magic, automating and systematising even complex tasks. My mission is to make the most effective use of software in healthcare, and I think we’ve barely even started that journey yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a new and vast array of technologies available to us, from enormous quantities of data to real-time analytics, machine learning and applied artificial intelligence, with computing power and different sources of data all growing exponentially. None of us know what the future holds, and none of us have all of the answers, so whether we are talking about ambient sensors or interacting with software using our voice, the essence of our digital work is not just the technology, but instead our ability to make use of data to learn and to inform our decision making. And that means learning how to build software that supports that goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we bring digital technologies into play, we speed up feedback on our actions and can perform complex processing tasks to make sense of burgeoning quantities of information and so “digital”, to me, is inextricably linked to becoming data-driven, because digital tools are the best way to combine and process information. That means understanding the best, evidence-based ways of creating and delivering safe, secure and valuable software code to end-users. And the best ways to deliver software like that is to use those same data-driven methodologies and build our software incrementally in small chunks with constant feedback to guide continuous improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-next&quot;&gt;So what next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, our biggest risk is to think that we have all of the answers. Instead, we can set the broad principles to which we must work but build trusted teams to deliver against the outcomes we set, whether that be our healthcare services or the software that supports and enables transformation of those services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The true digital revolution will come when we focus on generating meaningful data and use appropriate tools to make sense of that data, to drive our decision making, to use those data to reduce our uncertainty about our decisions, so that, we, in whatever role we have, are supported to make the right judgments at the right time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to &lt;em&gt;learn&lt;/em&gt;, and digital technology is an essential part of building a continuously learning culture, in whatever industry you work. And that is the essence of digital transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“We’re at the beginning of the digital revolution” wrote Bill Gates in his foreword to Satya Nadella’s book “Hit Refresh”, published not, as you might initially guess, twenty years ago, but in 2017.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">WTSB 27th September 2018</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/10/07/wtsb.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WTSB 27th September 2018" /><published>2018-10-07T08:07:07+01:00</published><updated>2018-10-07T08:07:07+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/10/07/wtsb</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/10/07/wtsb.html">&lt;p&gt;Our September NHS Wales Technical Standards Board was held on the 27th September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been asked to identify, assess, set and assure technical principles and standards in NHS Wales. That means we need to build a catalogue of standards, including standards that are already in use as well as standards that should be used for new developments. We must recognise a need for pragmatism, so a catalogue must include not only information about that technical standard but how it should be implemented and used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this meeting, we discussed how to build safe, reliable, functioning processes to assess a technical standard for use within NHS Wales. It is important to recognise that this blog post is a snapshot of my reflections. As a board with an explicit adopted principle to be open and transparent and adopt an iterative approach to our work, fostering a culture of continuous improvement, these notes are simply that: notes and a work-in-progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that caveat, what broad range of issues did we discuss?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;things-to-consider&quot;&gt;Things to consider&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For any standard, we discussed a range of factors that might need to be teased out during any open, transparent process we wanted to design:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what is the user need? what are the use-cases?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is the standard already used?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is the standard already deprecated?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;are others using, working on or interested in this standard already?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what can we learn from others using or working in domain in which the standard operates, and how do we engage with others who are using, working on or interested in this domain?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is the scope of the functional requirements correct, or does it need to be broadened or made more specific?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;is the standard supported or due to be supported by the market? do we need to explore the market?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what scoring mechanisms (e.g. procurement) can we use to discourage the use of standards at their end-of-life, and likewise, what can we do to drive market adoption?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what are the false barriers to entry?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;what are the lifecycle issues to consider? (draft, draft-for-use, standard, deprecated but still in use, deprecated and not for use, planned?)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how does one identify or drive traction of a standard?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;how do we judge the need and the content of a standard, particularly for new developments?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;architecture-and-interoperability&quot;&gt;Architecture and interoperability&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we think of technical standards, we thought it helpful to consider the different places in which those standards might be used for interoperability. Interoperability is how we make make computer systems or software exchange information. Most of us recognise that simply exchanging information is insufficient but instead we must aim for meaningful (semantic) interoperability in which systems exchange information and make use of that information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost all computer systems try to break down complex problems into discrete modular components, each of which do a limited set of things very well and traditional applications stitches these together into what appears to be a cohesive whole. Modularity means that teams can work semi-independently of one another and so long as they interact appropriately (at technical, legal and human levels).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interoperability is usually used to define the interactions between distributed systems and software. This enables technologies such as the World Wide Web, in which your computer has no difficulty in interacting with software running on a completely different computer somewhere else in the world to show you a web page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already use interoperability in healthcare as almost all health enterprises use a range of computer systems that need to be made to work together. A common, if old-fashioned example, is the use of HL7v2 to send messages regarding &lt;a href=&quot;http://healthstandards.com/blog/2006/10/05/what-is-an-adt-message/&quot;&gt;admissions, discharges and transfers&lt;/a&gt;. As a source system notifies dependent systems about a change by sending a message, we call this approach &lt;em&gt;push messaging&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Push messaging is well established within health enterprises and most have adopted a messaging fabric that acts as a safe bus to transport messages across systems with high levels of scalability, monitoring and queuing as well as often providing assertions as to reliability and performance. But there are problems with it. Dependent systems need to potentially deal with a constant influx of messages being sent to them and managing security is difficult. A source system sends out messages and therefore controlling which subscribed systems should be notified can prove challenging; many push enterprises adopt a patient-of-interest list that defines a subset of patients for whom a target system should receive messages. Inherent in this architectural design, is the concept that each application maintains its own state, with messages being used to keep disparate disconnected systems consistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, modern enterprises have moved towards a model of “pull messaging”, in which a system retrieves data from another and we decouple software logic from data so that many applications and services become stateless. This means that security checks become much easier because we can understand, at the time of the request to retrieve that data, which application is making the request on behalf of which user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sketched a version of this schematic in order to try to understand the use cases and the difference between a “pull” and “push” approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/open-platform/wtsb-architecture-standard.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb Architecture Standard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a laboratory test result is pushed from a laboratory information management service (LIMS) and is stored in a vendor-neutral archive. In Wales, we call this the Welsh Results Reporting Service (WRRS). We could expose that archive as a FHIR diagnostic report &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/diagnosticreport.html&quot;&gt;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/diagnosticreport.html&lt;/a&gt; as a microservice. Multiple independent services like that are blended together into a cohesive whole to create what appears to be an enterprise-wide cohesive API acting as a gateway and hiding (abstracting) the underlying implementation. Importantly, if we wanted to show laboratory results from other centres, we could either use one of two approaches to provide a unified view:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a federate/delegate/aggregate model, in which a service accepts a request for data, sends that request to multiple other private services, collects the responses to create a unified view&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a shared repository model, in which all centres push data into a shared repository via health information exchange.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach to architecture means that, while we have a LIMS that does not support HL7 FHIR and appropriate UK-wide shared profiles, we can still expose our laboratory data via HL7 FHIR. Once LIMS is replaced by a version that natively supports the more modern technical standards, we can deploy and existing modern applications &lt;em&gt;do not need to be modified in order to continue to run&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The important considerations are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;use of vendor neutral data repositories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;move towards an application programming interface (API) approach built on open standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;understand that need to liberate data from legacy applications and make use of existing infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;existing legacy includes tightly-coupled bespoke integrations that do not fit into this schematic. Such an approach needs to be deprecated in favour of a more modular loosely coupled architecture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we surely need to consider technical standards at multiple levels of our architecture, taking into account existing infrastructure and a clear future direction. This is shown graphically with the arrows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that the future of electronic health records is based on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;open standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;distributed systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;lightweight applications&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;shared common services for data and logic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;domain-driven modelling for clinical and administrative data, as well as clinical workflow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;process&quot;&gt;Process&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So given these considerations, how can we define a process that we can use in order to make rapid, pragmatic process while keeping within the broad principles and cohesive, credible technical architecture for our health and care data?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We worked through an example request for a standard - one of our colleagues from Aneurin Bevan submitted a request for a “Technical standard to support exchange of eObservations information using HL7 version 2 (HL7v2) messages”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a really useful example, and it led to a draft standards assessment process which I have drawn out here: 
notes
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/open-platform/wtsb-process.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb Process&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the important considerations is to ensure the scope is defined, particularly in relation to high level clinical requirements - &lt;em&gt;user need&lt;/em&gt;. Understanding the alignment between information technology and our wider strategic objectives is critical. For this technical standard, we need to understand &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; we are being asked to help with eObservations and put that in context of our wider architectural and technical infrastructure plans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was immediately clear that there was uncertainty about the scope of this request, as it specifically requested an NHS Wales standard on the format of HL7 v2 messages. In my view, we must broaden the scope to understand the wider clinical need, perhaps in terms of user stories, to see that what we are trying to solve is not simply exchanging HL7v2 messages but providing a wider framework for handling and making use of eObservation data. As a result, this request could be broadened to include technical standards for HL7 FHIR resources representing those data as well as HL7v2 messages that are sent by applications and services that do not, as yet, support HL7 FHIR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our plan now is to draft a more broad eObservations technical standards paper to include some of the factors outlined in my process diagram to see whether the process works and is helpful. I will write another blog post when we have learnt more about this!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I would like to re-iterate the importance of a learning culture in our work: we adopted the GDS design principles. One of those is the use of iteration and incremental improvement. While you might consider such an agile approach for our software development processes, I would argue that we also need to approach our wider technological leadership and management approaches in an agile way; that means we test our assumptions and make incremental improvements to the way we work. This post is my attempt to embrace that approach. Let me know what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Our September NHS Wales Technical Standards Board was held on the 27th September.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Building an open health and care platform for Wales</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/10/02/open-platform-wales.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Building an open health and care platform for Wales" /><published>2018-10-02T16:15:15+01:00</published><updated>2018-10-02T16:15:15+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/10/02/open-platform-wales</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/10/02/open-platform-wales.html">&lt;p&gt;We should use information technology to better deliver our broad health and care objectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means using information technology to support, improve, transform and re-imagine the delivery of health care; that means we must move away from delegating information technology to a separate department or even, as we do in Wales, a separate organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most modern enterprises have recognised the integral role information technology plays in operating their business. A failure in technology is a failure of business. That means services that have responsibility for delivering health and care objectives need to be responsible for the acquisition and development of technology used to support their work in delivering and improving care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alignment of information technology with business objectives requires a careful balance between top-down standardisation and enabling local, ‘bottom-up’ innovation. Standardisation, executed badly, creates fragility and inertia but when done well it creates an environment in which we can deliver technology at pace because we can decouple our developer teams and let them work independently. We know that pace of work is inversely proportional to the number of people who need to be involved in decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to re-imagine our organisational structures, governance and architecture to reflect modern information technology best practice. This means understanding the challenges we face:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we work in complex, constantly changing, heterogeneous clinical environments across Wales&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we need a single patient record with all of our user-facing applications giving a view on the same information.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we need to improve productivity; that means delivering technology at pace to meet the demands of the service&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we need to be able to make changes while adhering to legal, regulatory, safety and ethical standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we need to share common national services avoiding wasteful duplication&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we need to permit local innovation and learning, particularly when we recognise that there is no already established &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; way of delivering business value, and rapidly scale success across organisations in Wales&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we need to understand that we have existing applications hosted nationally and locally, with health boards all at different levels of maturity, we want to harmonise but not suffocate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;both healthcare, and the design of software to support healthcare, must be data-driven.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that we are not meeting these challenges in Wales; the Welsh Audit Office report is damning in the failure of delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-are-our-options&quot;&gt;What are our options?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three potential options for us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Continue the status quo.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Buy an off-the-shelf electronic health record “mega-suite” from a large vendor and deploy across Wales, e.g. Cerner Millennium or Epic.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change our strategy, creating an open health and care platform&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that there are substantial problems with information technology in healthcare in Wales including issues of governance, leadership, organisational structure and architecture. Is there anyone who thinks we can continue the status quo?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favoured approach is to recognise that our technical architecture determines our organisational and governance structures in Wales, and that architecture needs to be designed for&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;improving developer productivity&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;supporting extremely high reliability as well as enabling testability, safety and performance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;permitting the use of structured, meaningful clinical data for direct care, service management, quality improvement as well as clinical research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, we can look at how other technology companies have achieved these goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;an-evolutionary-architecture&quot;&gt;An evolutionary architecture&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An evolutionary architecture is one that can adapt to change. We must understand that our work in technology will never be complete and we will need to continually improve, adapting to changing clinical need and new technological advances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the recognised characteristics of an evolutionary architecture is &lt;em&gt;modularity&lt;/em&gt;, in which we break-up our enterprise into modules, each with a well defined and usually constrained purpose. Modern architecture usually focuses on modularity at the domain-level while more old-fashioned service-orientated architectures are partitioned at a technical-level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NHS Wales currently uses the latter which means that end-to-end testing is very difficult and, in effect, one ends up with a distributed monolith and paradoxically makes change more difficult, the whole system less predictable and resilient. It might takes weeks to create developer or test environments that replicate live and it becomes difficult to keep those different environments synchronised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, domain-driven design recognises the need to modularise and align modules to meaningful constructs in the business domain; we recognise inherent partitions in functionality and then tightly define the interactions between those modules. In essence, we need a microservice based architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example platform services needed to support a modern electronic health record might be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patient demographic services, providing a single authoritative snapshot of demographic information about a single patient.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Scheduling services, providing an aggregated view across multiple administrative systems to provide scheduling across multiple organisations.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Staff identity services, providing canonical staff information, bringing together information information from the electronic staff record and national active directory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clinical document repository, storing clinical documents and associated metadata&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Results repository, storing laboratory and radiology results&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Test requesting concierge service&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Security (authentication/authorisation) and logging services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clinical data repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scheduling services are a great example because they are needed to satisfy the vision from multiple workstreams of the Informed Health and Care strategy; patients and professionals need to be able to see and schedule appointments in order to deliver care more efficiently and more safely. At the moment, I login to Welsh Clinical Portal in Cwm Taf and see only Cwm Taf appointments, and login to Welsh Clinical Portal in Cardiff and see only Cardiff appointments. We have something wrong with our current architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there has been much good work in Wales on some of these core services, but these services need to be resourced appropriately and recognised as key enablers for building the next generation of user-facing applications. That means prioritising the deliver of these discrete services. Importantly, those services need to adopt open standards and be well-defined, loosely-coupled, documented and permit federation. As discrete modules, it becomes possible for use to run automated tests so that we know how our computing services provide accurate results and perform under pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;contracts-abstract-computing-services&quot;&gt;Contracts: abstract computing services&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the fundamental characteristics of an evolutionary architecture is that developers are able to work independently from one another, as long as they work within the defined contracts that document the functionality needed and how that module will interact with others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, our modules create an &lt;em&gt;abstractions&lt;/em&gt; of a computing service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstraction is an important software engineering principle which means that developers do not need to be concerned with how a service or application is implemented, only that it meets the agreed contracts. This is powerful because it acts to &lt;em&gt;decouple&lt;/em&gt; components meaning that they can be developed independently and in parallel, as long as they each work to the contracts specified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, the processes of simplification and abstraction mean reduce the interactions between discrete components within an architecture to a well-defined, constrained set of agreed contracts between parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those contracts may be technical, defining &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to interact at a technical level with the underlying services providing using that platform. Technical contracts usually define an &lt;em&gt;application programming interface&lt;/em&gt; (API), but those must be supplemented by a range of legal and regulatory contracts defining how those services may be used and for what purposes. In addition, those contracts can define how the different teams might work with one another and provide assurances regarding performance and reliability. In essence, the contracts document obligations for all parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible to ensure that parties are working appropriately to those contracts by the use of automated tests and &lt;em&gt;fitness functions&lt;/em&gt;. Such an approach means that changes that break an agreed contract are recognised early in the development pipeline, rather than at a late stage. We should aim for an efficient flow of work from conception, development, testing, assurance to deployment, and we should question any step that delays or reverses that flow of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in our scheduling example, the developer team simply needs to deliver an API, probably based on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/appointment.html&quot;&gt;HL7 FHIR Appointment resource&lt;/a&gt;. Our initial version could simply provide a read-only view and satisfy the request by sending out its own request to all of the multiple patient administrative systems in Wales, collect and aggregate the results and return a unified view. That might work, but we would ensure fitness functions would assess not only the data returned but the performance metrics. We might expect to get results within 100 milliseconds, and so the team might instead create a vendor-neutral scheduling repository which takes a feed of data from each patient administrative system and, essentially, caches the results for performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The important thing is that, from an architectural point of view, we don’t care. We set the specifications for that service and trust our team to work out how to deliver what we need, bringing together expertise from across organisations in Wales in order to safely deliver a service that meets our requirements. If the team improve the implementation, or create a new implementation, our client applications do not ever need to know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;multiple-services-create-a-platform&quot;&gt;Multiple services create a platform&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A computing platform is the environment in which a piece of software is executed; they provide a range of software and data services that make it easier to develop applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the Apple developer platform provides a range of sophisticated building blocks that permit developers to create applications for mobile devices. Similarly, there are core services and frameworks that developers can use for common operations such as data storage or processing. This means developers can focus on delivering value to their end-users, building on a foundation of different building blocks that factor out some of the complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach means that applications become lightweight and often ephemeral, simply stitching together functionality from the underlying platform. A proprietary platform can lock developers into that platform, while open platforms, build using open standards can commoditise core computing functionality, foster innovation and create new marketplaces and ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we need to design our modules to work together to provide the building blocks of the next-generation of electronic health records, recognising that, when combined, those modules will provide a cohesive platform. That platform encwhile developed independently, those modules must be designed to work together to provide a platform&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not difficult to see the range of discrete computing services that are needed to create a functional health and care platform, but this model needs a change in culture and change in the way that we think about information technology, moving away from purchasing applications towards a separation of data from the software that acts upon those data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been some fantastic work in NHS Wales and there is a real appetite for cooperation and collaboration; we now need to work out how to take the next steps and build an open, standards-based computing platform for NHS Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-whats-next&quot;&gt;So what’s next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need a national platform group that will define the platform and the contractual obligations for each service, documenting the technical (API) interactions and other dependencies. This architectural design group will need to work closely with the technical and information standards boards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need multiple independent cross-functional teams each tasked with delivering discrete modular computing services that meet the standards defined by the national platform group. Those teams need to bring together developers with members of other teams, including security, operations, patient safety and assurance.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need a national applications group that to build example national applications, like a national modular portal, that can be used by all but, importantly, permit the different modules to be stitched together by developers irrespective of their location.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need to recognise that our platform services three categories of developer: those working for NHS Wales developing national applications, those working for NHS Wales developing local applications (that might end up being scaled out if successful), and those working for academia and commercial organisations as part of our ecosystem. All three should be treated equally, using the same APIs. We cannot have a situation where internal and external developers are treated differently, or that successful local innovation cannot be easily scaled to other regions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our organisational and governance structures need to reflect these changes and we need to adequately resource, on a recurring basis, the ongoing development and improvement of these core national services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;and-what-about-a-portal&quot;&gt;And what about a portal?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We do need a national portal. But our national strategy cannot be defined by a portal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes little sense to duplicate portal functionality in different places, but each organisation needs a realistic convergence strategy that takes into account existing solutions and avoids long delays in providing functionality for our users. For example, we need to be able to embed portal functionality into emergency unit systems across Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we also need to ensure that our portal gives an accurate view of the single patient record; our focus must be on data. We cannot repeat the situation where different instances of portal provides the same view of different data. That means redesigning our national portal to be a lightweight, modular wrapper around national services; it too needs to use our national platform and provide common user-facing elements for use by all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To move towards a modular portal, we will embrace the idea that we will stitch together components of the national platform, including components of that portal, to meet our user needs. I believe that, given the right architecture, we will see a natural convergence as it will be possible to rapidly scale solutions developed locally to other organisations, as those new developments should use those standardised APIs. We should aim for true application portability, collaboration and cooperation. At the moment, local developments are difficult to scale because there isn’t truly, an open standards-based platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we cannot do this, then we should continue to consider procuring a mega-suite electronic health record system, because without change, we will be failing our staff and our patients in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We should use information technology to better deliver our broad health and care objectives.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">10 design principles for building electronic patient record systems</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/09/23/10-steps-epr.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="10 design principles for building electronic patient record systems" /><published>2018-09-23T10:09:09+01:00</published><updated>2018-09-23T10:09:09+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/09/23/10-steps-epr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/09/23/10-steps-epr.html">&lt;p&gt;Here are my suggested 10 broad principles for building the next generation of electronic health record systems:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Separate application code from data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data, as in the patient record, must be longitudinal, immutable, federated, structured and meaningful, with a focus on the patient.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;User-facing applications should be lightweight and ephemeral, with a focus on process and workflow. Ideally build your applications out of re-usable components. Applications should almost always be stateless because state should be a function of your data and process models.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on user need. It subsumes everything else. That means helping professionals and patients to understand and refine their needs, as well as needing to create a culture of continuous improvement. Remember our work will never be complete.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build trust. Teams need to trust one another. Likewise, our systems need to be secure-by-design, ensuring consent and transparency are integral to the use of personal data; work to build public trust maximises the opportunities to use data to manage and improve our health services and advance our knowledge and understanding.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build platforms and use use open standards, even if you think you only need a single user-facing application.  But, understand you are wrong, on multiple levels, to think one user-facing application will be sufficient for your needs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Modularisation is key; limit the surface area of interactions between those modules. Allow parallel independent development. That means understanding bounded contexts and two pizza rules. Think contracts: technical (API), performance, reliability, legal, regulatory and cultural. The more people who need to be involved in a decision, the slower you will deliver; your architecture and organisational structures should be designed to streamline that decision making.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand that reliability and risk are not homogeneous across our enterprises. One size does not fit all. Remember that adding more process or checks, particularly if it requires manual checks from multiple stakeholders, can have a paradoxical effect on making systems &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; safe. Also never forget the frequently forgotten consequences of failure to deliver.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adopt a mobile first strategy; always consider multiple channels of interaction for your users and give due regard to digital inclusion. How are our tools going to support different types of users with different needs?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on developer velocity. The consequences of this is automating end-to-test testing and safety assurance, as well as doubling-down efforts to modularise services. We are not building something that will ever be complete so embrace and design for change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Here are my suggested 10 broad principles for building the next generation of electronic health record systems:</summary></entry></feed>