<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.wardle.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.wardle.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-03-08T22:19:13+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/</id><title type="html">Dr. Mark Wardle</title><subtitle>Consultant Neurologist, clinical informatics, entrepreneur and software developer.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Thinking about medications</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/08/thinking-about-medications.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thinking about medications" /><published>2017-03-08T22:11:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-03-08T22:11:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/08/thinking-about-medications</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/08/thinking-about-medications.html">&lt;p&gt;Handling medications in clinical medicine is difficult. One of the easy wins for information technology in medicine is electronic prescribing. Our colleagues in general practice have had such systems for many years but those of us working in hospitals have lagged behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hospital, many of us prescribe on paper prescriptions – sometimes I use a proper prescription when I am starting a drug that is hospital-only – on most occasions, hospital doctors now write a GP communication note or simply add the recommendation to a clinical letter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is tremendous value in electronic prescribing. It is one of the quick-wins for information technology in healthcare. There are many advantages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advantages-of-keeping-track-of-medications-electronically&quot;&gt;Advantages of keeping track of medications electronically&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, keeping track of patients is critical. If you are non-medical, you might think that once you are under ongoing follow-up with a hospital doctor, there is some automatic system to let us know that you missed your last appointment or that your appointment was cancelled. In fact, you’d assume we also had a system to track your diagnoses so that we could potentially find all of our patients with, say, Parkinson’s disease. Sadly, this isn’t common; the way many clinicians handle this is to keep a spreadsheet with names and diagnoses or use something like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theabn.org/what-we-do/bnsu.html&quot;&gt;British Neurological Surveillance Unit (BNSU)&lt;/a&gt; to report rare cases seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a number of patients with a range of disorders on high-dose corticosteroids. Similarly, I have patients on other immunotherapy drugs (e.g. methotrexate) for whom I need to know that their blood monitoring is performed appropriately and that their blood indices are stable. For me, knowing a) who those patients are and b) when I last saw them, are critical for patient-safety. Too often, we avoid disaster simply through good fortune rather than any systematic approach to patient safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-patientcare-web-application&quot;&gt;The PatientCare web application&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here in Cardiff, we now use a patient electronic health record system to track all such diagnostic, treatment, interventional and outcome data. I have been developing it since 2009 and we now have over 15,000 patients recorded. It is accessed across Wales, mainly for neurological diseases, but we also track a number of rare diseases. Many of these rare disorders are rare individually, but collectively, they are common! There is a sophisticated access-control mechanism into which groups of patients and groups of clinical staff are linked by virtue of clinical services or research projects, so that access is limited to the group of patients to which you are responsible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Topics to be covered in future blog posts are information governance and a detailed guide on how to implement SNOMED-CT. Both difficult but both solved!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;electronic-prescribing-and-the-nhs&quot;&gt;Electronic prescribing and the NHS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start thinking about electronic prescribing and recording of current and past medication, I suggest you first have a look at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nhsbsa.nhs.uk/1121.aspx&quot;&gt;NHS DM&amp;amp;D (dictionary of medicines and devices)&lt;/a&gt; and a good look at the implementation guidance. There are a number of complexities. In hospital, we are encouraged to prescribe using generic drug names rather than branded drug names. This means that “prescribing” is a distinct process to dispensing. In hospital, the dispensing is performing by a nurse on the ward and a pharmacist for outpatients. Dispensing turns the generic prescription into an appropriate formulation. There are a number of issues to consider during dispensing including differences between formulations (actual medicinal products – AMPs) and issues of cost. Most hospital doctors are not used to selecting appropriate formulations and instead prescribe by generic drug name and dose. A general practitioner prescribes using products. For more information on this,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a hospital doctor may prescribe “ramipril 7.5mg od”. This means the patient should receive 7.5mg of this drug once per day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A general practitioner would prescribe “ramipril 5mg 1 tablet od” and “ramipril 2.5mg 1 tablet od”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are additional complexities. For instance, some hospital clinicians wish to prescribe by product because of differences between formulations. For example, many of us who work with patients with epilepsy prescribe “epilim chrono”. While the active ingredient is sodium valproate, different products may vary in terms of bioavailability / absorption and so we would not want our patient’s medications to be swapped around – imagine a situation in which a generic formulation is substituted in a patient who is seizure free and the substitution results in a seizure when the patient is driving!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another issue is that medication data is already held in general practitioner systems and so it should be possible to import that list of current and past medications into hospital systems automatically. Having different implementations / models of electronic prescribing in primary and secondary care complicates such automatic import and export of medications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NHS DM&amp;amp;D implementation guidance suggests a 3-step prescribing process for each drug. Step 1 is specifying the drug and the route (e.g. oral, inhaled, intravenous). Step 2 involves reviewing the rules for that specific drug and step 3 involves identifying appropriate sub-types of that medication for safe prescribing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might imagine, this is quite an involved and potentially time-consuming process. However, prescribing is potentially dangerous and should be performed with caution and careful consideration. However, different degrees of rigour are required depending on whether the electronic record is acting as a prescription or simply an electronic record of what the patient is taking or an advice letter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in outpatient clinic, most clinicians will want to quickly record the current and past medications so that we can easily answer questions like “Which anticonvulsant therapies have we already tried in this patient?”. As such, the strict rigour of an electronic prescribing system can be relaxed depending on use-case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-implementation&quot;&gt;My implementation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve implemented a system to rapidly enter an existing list of medications and make changes to that medication list. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/3tRyjJk-71M&quot;&gt;PatientCare medication entry&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/F2LSHpdCPvo&quot;&gt;Advanced medication entry&lt;/a&gt; for two video demonstrations. Here we enter a list of medications which are automatically mapped into SNOMED-CT DM&amp;amp;D drugs. There is a semantic understanding for drugs so that programmatically, we can tell whether a patient is on a thiazide diuretic or anticonvulsant – ie. this is not simply a free-text list! In addition, there is dose equivalence so that the system recognises that 1000mg is the same as 1g etc. Once the list is edited, the software calculates the changes – drugs changed, started, stopped etc. and then applies those changes to the longitudinal record of medication so that there is a complete list of all current and past medications that have been used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a balance of speed and efficiency for expert users and hand-holding for beginners. As such, there is an older pick-list based system which allows users to add drugs manually using drop-downs controls. However, expert users should be allowed to follow a more efficient process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This balance requires careful planning to ensure process safety and yet remain quick and usable in a busy outpatient clinic or in the assessment unit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only do I now record diagnostic information for my patients (SNOMED-CT coding) but it is now feasible to record all current and past treatments. Such information is very helpful for a range of conditions including Parkinson’s disease and epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, because the software recognises that some drugs are unchanged, some have been stopped and some have been started, we can now automatically generate summary reports of encounters. This results in a huge reduction in administrative support requirements as rather than dictating medication changes, the computer does it automatically and in a well-presented summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve just released the new version of the PatientCare application that contains this new medication functionality – this is available across NHS Wales. It is much better to have a rapid development lifecycle in which one gets early feedback on design, reviews early implementations and we iterate rapidly. By rapidly, I mean going from initial plans to mock-ups to an early version to this current (“finished”?) version within 3 weeks. I’m looking forward to more feedback from our other users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Handling medications in clinical medicine is difficult. One of the easy wins for information technology in medicine is electronic prescribing. Our colleagues in general practice have had such systems for many years but those of us working in hospitals have lagged behind.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">SNOMED CT terminology server</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/08/rsterminology.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SNOMED CT terminology server" /><published>2017-03-08T21:39:10+00:00</published><updated>2017-03-08T21:39:10+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/08/rsterminology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/08/rsterminology.html">&lt;p&gt;SNOMED CT is a modern, comprehensive medical terminology. For a detailed understanding of SNOMED CT, please see Chapter 4 in my &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html&quot;&gt;clinical design document&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key issue with SNOMED CT is an effective implementation. A good implementation, in my opinion, results in a system in which users do not actually know that they are using a terminology system at all. It should be intuitive and most importantly, usable from a clinical point-of-view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been using SNOMED CT since 2009. I think my electronic health record system (PatientCare) was the first deployed system in the UK to use SNOMED CT. SNOMED CT is the lingua franca within the system, internally the application and its business logic layers make ubiquitous use of SNOMED CT to make inferences about the care of a patient and to update the user interface to enable or disable functionality depending on the data entered so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, while one can bolt-on SNOMED CT as a terminology as an after-thought, it is preferable to design systems from the ground up to use and understand SNOMED CT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this doesn’t mean every system needs to re-implement SNOMED CT from the ground up. Indeed, I’d suggest using my new &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wardle/rsterminology&quot;&gt;SNOMED CT terminology microservice&lt;/a&gt;. This provides very fast browse and search function as well as subsumption so that one can ask whether, given a diagnosis of progressive bulbar palsy, does a patient have a type of motor neurone disease, and get “yes” as the answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also provides an electronic prescribing function for real-time natural language parsing of prescriptions. There is more work to do, and I continue to work on new developments including round-tripping from VTMs to VMPs and AMPs with automatic dose calculations and support for automatic natural language post-coordination. Post-coordination is, in my opinion, in scope of the information model in which SNOMED CT terms are used, but automatic NLP-based post-coordination will make entry more intuitive for the user.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">SNOMED CT is a modern, comprehensive medical terminology. For a detailed understanding of SNOMED CT, please see Chapter 4 in my clinical design document.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Supporting clinical care</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/02/18/supporting-clinic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Supporting clinical care" /><published>2017-02-18T10:16:10+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-18T10:16:10+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/02/18/supporting-clinic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/02/18/supporting-clinic.html">&lt;p&gt;Clinical information systems should support patient care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We generate our clinical correspondence from data. This is, unusually, the opposite of what almost everyone else does when they get data from correspondence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to prepare a full video as a demonstration, but for now I will link to a series of tweets that demonstrate this functionality in the clinic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we give the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mwardle/status/833062051283136518&quot;&gt;patient an iPad in clinic&lt;/a&gt;. The same infrastructure and platform will be used for patient-held devices, but for now, we use clinic-based applications. This uses Apple’s ResearchKit software. However, the clever thing here is the use of SNOMED CT. The application derives semantic understanding of the patient’s problems from the electronic health record and queues the correct questionnaires for that patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, if that patient has already indicated that they don’t wish to be involved in research, it won’t ask them again, but if not, they will be asked to consent for appropriate research projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used to use paper questionnaires. These were duly completed and then filed, not to be used. In addition, paper questionnaires can’t adapt to what has been entered. Here, the iPad applicaton &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mwardle/status/833063821828878336&quot;&gt;queues a different set of questions based on the responses so far&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, while there is excitement about the use of patient’s own devices and patient reported outcomes, what is the point of those data if they cannot be used for clinical care? Here, the data entered by the patient is immediately presented to the clinician and is &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mwardle/status/833064699977691137&quot;&gt;automatically incorporated into the clinic letter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice in the last video, I also tweak the current medication list (mapped to the NHS dictionary of medicines and devices) and those changes appear in our correspondence automatically.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Clinical information systems should support patient care.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Multiple sclerosis</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/multiple-sclerosis/2017/02/12/new-ms-portal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Multiple sclerosis" /><published>2017-02-12T10:16:10+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-12T10:16:10+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/multiple-sclerosis/2017/02/12/new-ms-portal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/multiple-sclerosis/2017/02/12/new-ms-portal.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to announce the release of my new data-linkage pseudonymous patient portal &lt;a href=&quot;https://msdata.org.uk&quot;&gt;msdata.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings the full power of my existing electronic patient record (EPR) - currently hosted and only accessible within NHS Wales - to the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, no patient identifiable information is stored, but instead, the system acts as a data-linkage platform, allowing information entered from patient-held devices and clinicians outside of Wales to be brought into the EPR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, one can see how many relapses a patient has had due to multiple sclerosis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/msdata-relapses.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MS relapses&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, while we have over 20,000 patients registered with a variety of disorders, wouldn’t it be useful to show clinicians and the patient how they are progressing compared to patients with the same disorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, while there are lots of SNOMED-CT concepts that mean the same as “multiple sclerosis”, it is possible to use the SNOMED-CT hierarchy to derive semantic understanding of the relationships between terms. In this way, we can easily find patients with say, a type of motor neurone disease, even if they have been recorded as having “progressive bulbar palsy”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we chart a single patient’s progress over the years compared to a whole population-based cohort of patients’ progress. The median progress of the whole cohort is shown with a dotted green line. Just like a growth chart for a baby, a patient crossing the centile charts is either doing better or worse than expected. The EDSS is a score of disability in multiple sclerosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/edss-graph.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MS progress&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an added bonus, we can chart the use of disease-modifying treatments as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m delighted to announce the release of my new data-linkage pseudonymous patient portal msdata.org.uk.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Domain-driven design in clinical informatics</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Domain-driven design in clinical informatics" /><published>2017-02-03T10:16:10+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-03T10:16:10+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html">&lt;p&gt;I have written this document to explain my thoughts on the most appropriate way to design and clinical information systems that valuably support the process of healthcare.  As such, it includes a methodology for creating software for use by clinicians,  managers  and  administrators  to  support  both  the  day-to-day  care  of patients and the management of services for groups of patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I divide the “process of healthcare” into three core themes which are related and inter-dependent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘day-to-day’ care of a single patient; data relates to a single individual.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The management, audit and governance of clinical services; data relates togrouped, aggregated patient data and is service-specific.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supporting clinical research;  data relating to a patient’s suitability for research projects as well as enrolment, consent and research-level data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete document is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/62sg71a19voxpts/cis_design.pdf?dl=0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I have written this document to explain my thoughts on the most appropriate way to design and clinical information systems that valuably support the process of healthcare. As such, it includes a methodology for creating software for use by clinicians, managers and administrators to support both the day-to-day care of patients and the management of services for groups of patients.</summary></entry></feed>