<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.wardle.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.wardle.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-06-30T22:00:08+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/</id><title type="html">Health informatics and information technology</title><subtitle>by Dr Mark Wardle, Consultant Neurologist, clinical informatics and software developer. Founder, Eldrix Ltd.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">User need! Agile! Platform!</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/platform/2018/06/30/user-need-agile-platform.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="User need! Agile! Platform!" /><published>2018-06-30T08:14:28+01:00</published><updated>2018-06-30T08:14:28+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/platform/2018/06/30/user-need-agile-platform</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/platform/2018/06/30/user-need-agile-platform.html">&lt;p&gt;We need some substantial changes in the way we think about healthcare information technology in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that we need to, figuratively speaking, pull the &lt;a href=&quot;https://itrevolution.com/kata/&quot;&gt;Andon cord&lt;/a&gt; and call a stop to the status quo, to stop building significant &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technical_debt&quot;&gt;technical debt&lt;/a&gt; and move away from long procurement cycles and success judged by the deployment of different products from different vendors in different organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our architecture is becoming ever more tightly coupled, ever more brittle mostly bespoke point-to-point integration. With each expansion or integration, the whole enterprise from end-to-end becomes ever more brittle and less predictable. We have increasing problems with reliability in critical national systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paradoxically of course, this is itself extremely predictable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-simple-single-answer&quot;&gt;A simple single answer?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there is no simple single answer to our problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamental steps now are to recognise that there are problems and that we need to improve and to be open and transparent about the issues we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the responses at the recent public accounts committee meetings suggest that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;perhaps not all recognise that there are problems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that there is a lack of ambition to enable transformational change using digital technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is a lack of strategic leadership who prioritise delivery of benefit and understand how to do that effectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the solution will, given the NHS is a complex and adaptive environment with lots of moving parts, lots of variation and significant complexity, to look at improving things both from the top-down and the bottom-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;top-down--cohesion-credible-principles-and-plans&quot;&gt;Top-down : cohesion, credible principles and plans&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we have the “Informed Health and Care” strategy, it is only a &lt;em&gt;vision&lt;/em&gt; of what is needed and we must ask, where is the the specific executable plan to deliver that vision. There are those of us who are now trying to draft that, but where has it been up until now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This needs to be a thoughtful and informed piece of work, noting the successes and failures in a non-judgmental way and highlighting the areas of priority, as well as reflections and robust options-appraisals of different options. If it can’t do that, then the top-down delivery plan must create a tangible plan to understand those options to inform the balancing judgement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It necessarily follows that this work must adopt the broad principles of &lt;em&gt;openness&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;transparency&lt;/em&gt; in which our work as a service is open to inspection and evaluation. As a result, adopting the &lt;a href=&quot;[https://www.gov.uk/guidance/government-design-principles](https://www.gov.uk/guidance/government-design-principles)&quot;&gt;GDS design principles&lt;/a&gt; (https://www.gov.uk/guidance/government-design-principles) has been a good first step, acknowledging that we do not have all of the answers is the second, understanding that we can already define some good broad principles that will enable us to deliver the third, and being open to outside help the fourth! For the latter, we need to bring in expertise on digital transformation and adopt agile methodologies and user interface and needs expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What must follow from this is the need for an overarching strategic group who is tasked with setting broad directions as well as the principles and standards to be used by any team working to deliver functionality for users across Wales, including professionals and patients. Overarching principles and technical approach includes a credible plan for a cohesive architecture, making the best use of existing infrastructure and yet creating something to allow us to deliver solutions to our problems, both now and in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must change from command-and-control with centralised project management to instead clearly defining our end goals together with the broad principles and standards to be used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;bottom-up-empowerment-cooperation-and-trust&quot;&gt;Bottom-up: empowerment, cooperation and trust&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For improvements from the bottom-up, we need to change the narrative and, most importantly the culture, from command-and-control to collaboration and cooperation. We need to focus our resources on that work only the public sector can do and make information technology the enabler for change by the service itself. This means that we provide a toolbox of data and computing services and applications from which the service can stitch together solutions to their problems at a local level and share those solutions between organisations when they are successful. This means that we aim towards an &lt;em&gt;open platform&lt;/em&gt; approach in which data is the key and application programming interfaces provide access to important shared software services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a shared platform of discrete modular loosely-coupled components available to use for both internal and external teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to build trust between organisations, but fundamentally, information technology needs to be &lt;em&gt;owned&lt;/em&gt; by the service working collaboratively and in partnership, and bringing in commercial expertise and solutions when necessary. Most businesses recognise that IT does not simply support their business, but it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the way that they do business and we need to do that for health. Such recognition has meant that digital leaders are at board level and that information technology should not be considered a separate department. In Wales, IT is outsourced to a separate poorly governed organisation!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What therefore must follow from this is the need for a &lt;em&gt;national platforms group&lt;/em&gt;, made up of cross-functional teams bringing together expertise from different specialties such as management, development, testing, quality assurance, safety and operations. These individual teams must be given responsibility to deliver discrete components of a modular, loosely-coupled architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parallel, we should plan robust API management lifecycle to build APIs with a focus on ease of use for application developers (whether internal or external), consistent security policies, automated testing and deployment, documentation and analytics to gain better insights into API usage and performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;striking-a-balance&quot;&gt;Striking a balance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a balance and none of what we need to do is particularly easy, but I struggle with the paradox of Wales attempting to run hugely ambitious, top-down, multi-million pound IT projects given both local and international experience of the likelihood of failure vs a genuine lack of ambition to use digital tools to transform how we care for our population and enable an ecosystem of innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are people around who want to make a difference and recognise the need for change. There are pockets of good work at all levels, including government, NWIS and the health boards. I think for many of us it feels as if we are swimming against the current however. It is also important to recognise that there has been historic under-funding compared to peers in England, but it is difficult to justify more expenditure when there has been a consistent historic failure to prioritise and to deliver using the resources we have had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have written on my blog on aspects of this. These are the most important bits I guess:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I talk about open platforms in healthcare here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data-driven healthcare: integration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;Once-for-Wales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I talk about governance and top-down vs bottom up here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html&quot;&gt;Paradox of control&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/paradox-of-ambition.html&quot;&gt;Paradox of ambition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More stuff on platforms here…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-1.html&quot;&gt;Platforms #1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-2.html&quot;&gt;Platforms #2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3.html&quot;&gt;Platforms #2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need to a national architecture review to help define a modern, standards-based loosely-coupled evolutionary adaptive architecture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change our metrics so that we focus on user need and delivery of benefit, rather than deployment of a specific product.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change governance and ownership. Give the health boards ownership and control, ask them to form a partnership with each other and government tasked to set top-down principles and technical and information standards and provide expertise and oversight to define a national open platform.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change delivery - by empowering developer teams whether national, local or commercial to use that open platform to solve problems, and ensure that those solutions can be built collaboratively and shared and scaled when shown to be safe and successful.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change our culture - become open by default, make Wales a beacon of safe, secure healthcare informatics underpinning service transformation and improvement - and teach everyone else how we did it, the difficulties we faced and the strategies we used to overcome those difficulties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible to have a single organisation acting as both overseer, strategist and software supplier, but that needs a change in behaviour towards transparency so that decision-making is open, subject to external scrutiny and there are clear appraisals of different options. In my view, the NHS Wales Informatics Service fails to behave in this way. My preference is to change the behaviour, but if that is not possible, then we must surely consider re-organisation instead.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We need some substantial changes in the way we think about healthcare information technology in Wales.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">WTSB 19th June 2018</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/06/19/wtsb.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WTSB 19th June 2018" /><published>2018-06-19T15:14:14+01:00</published><updated>2018-06-19T15:14:14+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/06/19/wtsb</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/06/19/wtsb.html">&lt;p&gt;We held the second meeting of the Welsh Technical Standards Board (WTSB) today and I am delighted to announce that we have formally adopted the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/guidance/government-design-principles&quot;&gt;GDS Design Principles&lt;/a&gt; for use by NHS Wales. These are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start with user needs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do less&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design with data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do the hard work to make it simple&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iterate. Then iterate again&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is for everyone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand context&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build digital services, not websites&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be consistent, not uniform&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make things open: it makes things better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we have agreed to adopt the Welsh Government Digital Service Standard:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Undertake research of who the service users are, to understand user needs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a plan in place for ongoing user research and usability testing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a multidisciplinary team.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build your service using agile iterative and user-centred methods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build a service that can be iterated and improved on a frequent basis and make sure you have the capacity, resources and technical flexibility to do so.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evaluate what tools and systems will be used to build, host, operate and measure the service, and how to procure them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand security and privacy issues.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider making source code open and reusable, and, if appropriate, publish it under relevant licenses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use open standards and common platforms where available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Test the end-to-end service.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make a plan for being offline.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a service that’s simple and intuitive that users succeed first time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make the user experience consistent with the rest of Welsh Government.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage everyone to use the digital service with assisted digital support if required.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify your baseline information to measure performance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collect that performance information regularly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Report on that performance data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Test your service from beginning to end [with your minister]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implicit in adopting these standards is a focus on the citizen as the user of services and that digital transformation is better thought of as &lt;em&gt;service transformation&lt;/em&gt;. We need to provide tools so that our services can be transformed to provide modern, efficient and safe healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end, we are starting a transformation journey, with collaboration, cooperation and openness the key enablers for us to &lt;em&gt;make things better&lt;/em&gt;. In essence, we need to balance top-down standards with creating a culture of openness and transparency to enable safe innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our remit, as a board, is to define the technical principles and standards supporting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;integration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;interoperability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;software development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are accountable to the National Informatics Management Board (NIMB).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;making-things-better-for-users&quot;&gt;Making things better for users&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only should NHS Wales work to GDS principles, but we as a board should too. To that end, we must ask&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a technical standards board, who are &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; users?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see &lt;em&gt;developers&lt;/em&gt;, together with the teams in which they work, as the prime user for our technical standards because they are the ones who will make things better for the real users, patients and professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what do developers need? Can we apply the GDS principles in our task to maintain a catalogue of principles and standards?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, our standards will specify the structure and function of our national architecture and documentation of those standards should, if we take an open-approach, foster a change in culture towards collaboration and cooperation and trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will, in essence, define the specifications for an open platform onto which we can build innovation and enable true service transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-next&quot;&gt;So what next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some logical consequences to this approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We must open up our documentation relating to services and their standards and develop a roadmap to assess and set new standards and decommission old ones.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We must move to creating cross-functional teams that combine developers, project management, user researchers, UX designers with testing, safety and deployment experts to deliver modular, domain-constrained functionality that can be developed and improved in isolation to other components. Such components should, in essence, be loosely-coupling with technical and human contracts defining interactions between teams. For Wales, we should encourage teams that combine members that span organisational boundaries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A focus on automated end-to-end testing and scalability with testing in production-like environments available on-demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the rest of this post, I want to talk about &lt;em&gt;documentation&lt;/em&gt; as it is a key enabler for building collaboration, cooperation and trust in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;documentation&quot;&gt;Documentation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do other developer-focused digital companies do when they want to create an open platform? They create a developer-friendly set of documentation with application programming interface (API) specifications together with how-to and getting started guides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you are a developer wishing to build software using the NHS Wales open platform. You might work for the NHS Wales Informatics Service (NWIS), one of the health boards or a commercial or academic partner  What do you need to get your work done?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at how others have done this…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the current landing page of &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com&quot;&gt;https://docs.microsoft.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.003.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.003&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here there are links to documentation covering the range of Microsoft platforms, including Azure, their cloud platform. Let’s explore…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.004.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.004&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can read broad overviews of the architecture, and see links to more detailed specifications in the API reference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.005.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.005&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the documentation is interspersed with example code and links to frameworks that make it easy to make use of the software services provided by the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.006.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.006&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.007.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.007&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how do Microsoft keep their work updated? The source code for their documentation is either automatically generated from their code, or maintained itself as an open-source repository on github - see &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MicrosoftDocs&quot;&gt;https://github.com/MicrosoftDocs&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.008.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.008&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fosters collaboration. Internal users can contribute to changes and have them accepted by the project team, but so can external users. I could make my own local copy of this document repository, make my changes and submit them for review as a “pull-request”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.009.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.009&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can edit the original source to the documentation, here in Markdown format, a simple-to-use and process text markup language. Microsoft maintains control of the source, but permits open access and review and collaboration. Have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MicrosoftDocs/azure-docs&quot;&gt;https://github.com/MicrosoftDocs/azure-docs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.010.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.010&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And from these source files, Microsoft generate their website:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.011.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.011&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon Web Services (AWS) have adopted the same approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.014.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.014&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we have their landing page, linking to lots of different resources, including guides, lists of API specifications etc. And here are the github pages containing the source for those documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.015.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.015&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.016.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.016&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.017.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.017&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the same way as for Microsoft, developers can flag omissions or errors and contribute. This user is submitting a patch to add a link to another resource. Other users might simply create an “issue” to be examined and possibly fixed by the project team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.023.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.023&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today we agreed that, in line with our remit, we must start work on building an online catalogue of existing services and the standards that are used, and, by adopting GDS-principles ourselves, do this in the open and in small incremental steps. As such, we are going to pick a current service and see how we can take some tentative first steps in publishing that documentation as well as making use of tools to support cooperation and collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any comments or thoughts, let me know. I promise to tell you how we get on, and share the learning, the results (good or bad) with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We held the second meeting of the Welsh Technical Standards Board (WTSB) today and I am delighted to announce that we have formally adopted the GDS Design Principles for use by NHS Wales. These are:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Informed Health and Care: Delivery</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/05/27/delivery.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Informed Health and Care: Delivery" /><published>2018-05-27T21:20:20+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-27T21:20:20+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/05/27/delivery</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/05/27/delivery.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/topics/health/nhswales/about/e-health/?lang=en&quot;&gt;“Informed health and care – A digital health and social care strategy for Wales”&lt;/a&gt; sets out a clear vision for the use of information technology to support the provision of healthcare for citizens within Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This vision is split into four key themes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Information for You”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Supporting professionals”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Improvement and innovation”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“A Planned future”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We want a future where staff, service users, patients and carers are empowered and better informed, where organisational boundaries are not a barrier to effective care, as information is available electronically and joined-up, and where innovation and improvement can flourish built on a solid technical infrastructure and a safe environment for those who work in or are served by health and care services in Wales.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key question for us to answer is, what are the challenges that must be overcome to deliver this vision? As part of that process, we must identify current and future impediments to successful delivery and look to changing how we work to meet those challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-partnership-for-delivery&quot;&gt;A partnership for delivery&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my five-step plan to deliver the strategy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-change-our-metrics&quot;&gt;1. Change our metrics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metrics, quantifiable measures of progress, are important indicators of what we want to achieve and so must represent those ambitions. Our National Informatics Management Board (NIMB) in Wales uses delivery of certain products into different health boards as a measure of success, but is that appropriate? We need to focus instead on &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;outcomes&lt;/em&gt; for our population, and therefore change our metrics to represent &lt;em&gt;solving problems&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach forces us to step back and focus on the problems we are solving with information technology and ensures that we don’t become blinkered into adopting a certain approach that will delay realising value for patients and professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-change-our-governance-and-ownership&quot;&gt;2. Change our governance and ownership&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have health boards working to deliver care for their citizens but a separate organisation, the NHS Wales Informatics Service (NWIS) acting in multiple, potentially conflicting, roles as a source of IT expertise for the service, as a source oversight and assurance, as a supplier of software and supplier of infrastructure. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.audit.wales/system/files/publications/NHS_-Informatics-2018%20-%20English.pdf&quot;&gt;Welsh Audit Office (WAO) report&lt;/a&gt; strongly criticises the governance arrangements and the imbalanced reporting of success and progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t we need to consider instead, a partnership, owned by the health service for the health service working to increase cooperation and collaboration providing top-down governance and assurance separate from an any organisation with supplier status? Surely we need a strategic assurance group able to set broad principles and define, maintain and assure technical and information standards for use across NHS Wales and its partners?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must  encourage trust, collaboration and cooperation to encourage bottom-up working to solve real-life local problems and share good practice among peers. This means getting the right balance between governance and delivery, whether those projects are delivered in-house, by collaborative working groups working across and for NHS organisations or by third-parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-change-our-architecture-and-our-team-structures&quot;&gt;3. Change our architecture and our team structures&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current architecture in NHS Wales is built from an enterprise service bus (ESB) messaging service but much of our software integration is bespoke and point-to-point and there is a lack of robust automated unit and integration test environments offering end-to-end assurance of proper functionality. There are significant delays between design and getting software to end-users, limiting feedback on quality, performance and failing to identify user need by iterative ongoing continuous improvement and iteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to modularise our architecture and realise the productivity and safety benefits from combining development, testing and operations into cross-functional teams with shared common goals to deliver discrete modules of functionality that can be independently developed and improved with loose-coupling with other components.  A change in architecture should prompt us to create task-driven teams bringing together expertise from our existing functional units with a single goal: delivery of quality software to solve our problems, create value and as a result, improve the outcomes for our population. We need to see information technology as a tool for continuous improvement and service transformation and we need to speed up and isolate modules of our information technology work in order to delivery and improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an approach builds on our existing work to adopt a standards-based approach to our healthcare enterprise architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-change-our-culture&quot;&gt;4. Change our culture&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to adopt the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/guidance/government-design-principles&quot;&gt;UK Government Digital Service (GDS) design principles&lt;/a&gt; and focus on openness and transparency in our work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthcare information technology is hard, and we need to be able to step back and re-evaluate our progress and our plan for delivery, bring in outside expertise when needed and justify our decisions with a clear and informed appraisal of our options, without conflicts of interest. This relates, of course, to the changes we need in governance; an organisation who runs two data centres itself is unlikely to be able to make the difficult decisions to switch to using commodity cloud providers or to judge itself against agreed service level agreements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I was asked to take “down this blog” as my posts on strategy and technical architecture were perceived as criticism and this was “particularly difficult” to tolerate as I was working (at the time) for the NHS Wales Informatics Service. How can that be right? We must encourage and foster debate, be transparent in our decision making, which, after all, will always be a compromise and balance between advantages and disadvantages, and recognise that we should bring in expert help when appropriate in order for us to make the right decisions for Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;5-change-our-focus&quot;&gt;5. Change our focus&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NHS Wales must face some difficult choices.  For too long, external factors have resulted in incoherent and inconsistent delivery or projects, frequency orthogonal to delivery of the wider vision; in many cases it has been driven by the budgeting process and the availability of funds in any single financial year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A coherent plan to deliver the strategy needs more than a list of disconnected and incompatible goals but instead a clear understanding of what needs to be done and what doesn’t need to be done; we must know when to say “no”. Instead, we focus our limited resources on specific tangible actions and make some difficult decisions to prune areas of work that do not support delivery of the wider vision, or those areas of work that can be easily provided by third-parties. We need to prioritise our work and focus on delivery of value and improved outcomes. We must focus on user need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must recognise that technology evolves quickly and so we must build culture and architecture to encourage and enable innovation and partnership working recognising that our population can benefit from a digital-first approach to healthcare, whether directly in their interactions with out services or indirectly as a result of better planning, scheduling and clinical decision support. Our ecosystem should be focused on building tools and frameworks to make the work of both internal and external developers, safe, productive and efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, we must raise our focus away from only healthcare in Wales and recognise that we must exchange meaningful information with partner organisations in other regions and in other disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we must become focused on being &lt;em&gt;data-driven&lt;/em&gt;, so that we focus firstly on the capture and analysis of clinically meaningful structured and semantically interoperable data, and use those data to shape and improve our services. Similarly, our information technology developments should, themselves, be driven by data, by usage and by metrics of performance, stability and security. The data driving our work should be meaningful and standards-based.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-once-for-wales&quot;&gt;On “Once for Wales”&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;Once for Wales : a debate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-trust-and-innovation&quot;&gt;On trust and innovation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/paradox-of-ambition.html&quot;&gt;The paradox of ambition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html&quot;&gt;The paradox of control&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html&quot;&gt;The 5 Os of healthcare IT - objectives, ownership, openness, optimise, organic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-platforms&quot;&gt;On platforms:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data-driven healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-1.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 1/3. Standards and interoperability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-2.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 2/3. An API-first approach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 3/3. What we need to do next&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-focus&quot;&gt;On focus:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html&quot;&gt;Focus 1/3. The importance of strategy : focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges.html&quot;&gt;Focus 2/3. The challenges we face in delivering the vision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-solutions.html&quot;&gt;Focus 3/3. Pragmatic solutions to those challenges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-data&quot;&gt;On data:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/22/health-data.html&quot;&gt;Health data - start with a problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data-driven healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-development-standards-and-ecosystems&quot;&gt;On development standards and ecosystems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/cloud-ehr.html&quot;&gt;Creative 1/3: creative destruction in health IT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;Creative 2/3: the value of software for healthcare: quality improvement and service transformation underpinned by software, and software underpinning by quality improvement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html&quot;&gt;Creative 3/3: ecosystems and the platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“Informed health and care – A digital health and social care strategy for Wales” sets out a clear vision for the use of information technology to support the provision of healthcare for citizens within Wales.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welsh Technical Standards Board</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/05/15/wtsb.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welsh Technical Standards Board" /><published>2018-05-15T10:09:09+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-15T10:09:09+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/05/15/wtsb</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/05/15/wtsb.html">&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to announce that I have been asked to chair the new Welsh Technical Standards Board (WTSB) for NHS Wales. We will support the creation and maintenance of a catalogue of standards and requirements to enable integration and interoperability across all health and care systems in a consistent and secure manner, and to support local innovation and the use of third party delivery partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scope of this Board covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integration standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software development standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Infrastructure standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cyber security standards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our responsibilities will be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the identification, assessment and setting of standards and for assuring the application of agreed standards across the national architecture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ongoing maintenance of the catalogue of standards, including:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;establishing a road map to support the implementation of agreed standards, including how each standard should be implemented and used&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;periodically assessing agreed standards to ensure they remain relevant and appropriate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;establishing a road map to support the decommissioning of standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identifying opportunities locally, regionally and nationally to adopt standards providing quick wins, case studies and learning to inform the road map.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;embedding an interoperability framework within NHS procurement at a local and national level to ensure that procurements are appropriately scored as to their level of interoperability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our inaugural meeting will be the 22nd May 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;openness-transparency-and-public-working&quot;&gt;Openness, transparency and public working&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my ambitions is to make the WTSB open and transparent; to this end, one of our first agenda items is to determine the best way to ensure that our work and the results of our work, are fully open. In addition, can’t we take this approach further? While we can ensure that our work is visible to any member of the public, I aspire to encourage active participation, recognising that we work for many stakeholders. That means not only will our catalogue of standards be publicly available, but the day-to-day working of our group will, by default, be similarly available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, our remit is broad and we will need to look to bring in outside expertise as and when required to support different streams of work. With such a broad remit, we will need to break down our goals into smaller chunks via more specialised work groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;who-do-we-work-for&quot;&gt;Who do we work for?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, we work for patients, to define standards in an attempt to improve patient care, by supporting the development, testing, evaluation and deployment of valuable healthcare software for citizens in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, our immediate audience comprises three core groups:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The NHS Wales Informatics Service (NWIS) who are responsible for delivering “shared for Wales” services underpinning the &lt;em&gt;single patient record&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Health organisations in Wales, who have a statutory responsibility to deliver healthcare to citizens and need to procure or develop local software to meet local needs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;External partners including the third sector and commercial entities in order to permit a digital ecosystem and ensure innovation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, we should treat these three audiences with the same importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My key aim is to foster cooperation and collaboration and encourage the adoption best practices. We should aim to have software code and documentation publicly available, and encourage contributions from stakeholders, from developers, across all interested groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;agenda-22nd-may-2018&quot;&gt;Agenda 22nd May 2018&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-welcome-and-introductions&quot;&gt;1. Welcome and introductions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-terms-of-reference-and-discussion-of-membership&quot;&gt;2. Terms of reference and discussion of membership&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1jMLpNP5w6-SvO9ChUPGjqGU-1_HHo0T7/view?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Document 1&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is it right. Are we missing important people? e.g. What about security input?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is it appropriate to bring in expertise on an ad-hoc basis, particularly when considering working groups?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-in-relation-to-how-the-board-will-function&quot;&gt;3. In relation to how the board will function&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/16J7BRN7-WfgH2Rh1B0v6pO867CuvjpB7/view?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Document 2&lt;/a&gt;, do you agree that we need:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A catalogue of existing system services and functions within the national architecture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A corresponding record of the standards used already&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A roadmap to identify services and functions that would benefit from the adoption of standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To register https://api.wales.nhs.uk with three consumers in mind, NWIS, health boards and third-parties via the digital ecosystem, and as such, encourage open collaboration and trust by sharing documentation publicly?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To invite external speakers with specific industry knowledge to inform our working such as
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Open source and collaboration experts to talk about openness and transparency, about shared working. (e.g. what can we learn from methods used by open source collaborative groups such as the Apache Software Foundation?)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Experts on best practices for software development methodologies, including agile, DevOps, infrastructure-as-code, production-like test environments&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Industry representatives e.g. commercial suppliers, integration and interoperability experts -&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That we will need five broad categories of interoperability standards, relating to:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Security, staff identity management and logging. We will need to identify expertise in federated security models such as OAUTH2.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Demographics and citizen identity&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Diagnostic test standards (e.g. laboratory and radiology standards) relating to the requesting, reporting and viewing of diagnostic testing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Clinical Document standards relating to the creation, storage and transmission of clinical documents&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Clinical data standards relating to the recording of structured clinical information such as diagnoses, treatments and procedures as part of the wider logical single patient record.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-proposed-technical-standards-for-consideration&quot;&gt;4. Proposed technical standards for consideration:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;API specifications for services supporting the storage and retrieval of e-Observations data such as temperature, pulse rate, respiratory rate, level of consciousness, weight and height.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;API specifications for services supporting the storage and retrieval of clinical documents and their associated metadata&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;5-links-with-other-groups&quot;&gt;5. Links with other groups&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do you agree that we need to ensure communication with other groups across the UK and Internationally, to ensure that there is harmonisation of technical standards, where possible?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If so, to which groups do we already have links and to which groups must we approach to ensure representation for Wales?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;6-any-other-business&quot;&gt;6. Any other business?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have comments on any of these agenda items, then please contact me. As this will be our inaugural meeting, the best way to feed back your comments is directly to me, at mark@wardle.org&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I am delighted to announce that I have been asked to chair the new Welsh Technical Standards Board (WTSB) for NHS Wales. We will support the creation and maintenance of a catalogue of standards and requirements to enable integration and interoperability across all health and care systems in a consistent and secure manner, and to support local innovation and the use of third party delivery partners.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creative 3/3: Ecosystems and the platform</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creative 3/3: Ecosystems and the platform" /><published>2018-05-08T09:08:08+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-08T09:08:08+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;part one, I highlighted four drivers that will result in creative destruction&lt;/a&gt; in the healthcare IT industry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was the recognition that software and data are critical enablers of clinical quality improvement, service transformation and advancing our knowledge (research).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second was that the best way to build healthcare software is to adopt the behaviours, processes and culture from the most highly productive technology companies. This means adopting quality improvement and research methodologies to develop, test and deploy the software that use to improve our clinical quality, service and research endeavours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I covered these two first points in more detail in &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;part two&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third was the importance of separating data storage and transmission from the software operating on those data, with a shared domain language uniting multi-disciplinary cross-functional, semi-autonomous teams creating discrete, carefully bounded components with loose coupling with other components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth was the recognition of a transformation in software engineering practices with the increasing adoption of cloud and serverless technologies, permitting the development and commodification of components of what will become, a distributed and patient-centred logical electronic health record. The end result? A variety of interoperable applications, both clinical and administrative indeed, focused on workflow and usually task-orientated, making use of that shared health platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I delve into the importance of software architecture and the use of standards in designing healthcare software systems fit for the 21st Century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;architecture-and-standards&quot;&gt;Architecture and standards&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our efforts to transform health services are critically dependent on technology, we need to change our approach to health information technology projects to maximise safety, quality, productivity and pace using the best evidence-based practices. This means building in continuous improvement methodologies to ensure we keep on improving our approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how can create an environment which makes it easy and safe to develop, test, evaluate and deploy software for use in healthcare?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/04/26/lean-healthcare-devops.html&quot;&gt;“Lean Healthcare”&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about the quality improvement methodologies and process changes that can be used to develop software faster and more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the important conclusions is the benefit of small cross-functional teams. Such teams must be able to work independently, aligned to a wider strategy, given the right tools and responsibility to get their work done and most importantly, work on discrete components by breaking down work into smaller, less risky units that can evolve independently with only loose-coupling with other components. We &lt;em&gt;modularise&lt;/em&gt; our work and limit the interactions between those modules to well-defined publicly documented contracts. It is reported that Jeff Bezos, founder and CEO of Amazon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“All service interfaces, without exception, must be designed from the ground up to be externalizable. That is to say, the team must plan and design to be able to expose the interface to developers in the outside world. No exceptions”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Jeff Bezos quoted &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/+RipRowan/posts/eVeouesvaVX&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting this kind of &lt;em&gt;broad architectural principle&lt;/em&gt; means a lot and when you write down this and other guiding principles, and they are actionable and meaningful, they drive a change in behaviour and &lt;em&gt;change your culture&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Action 1: We need to be explicit in the broad principles we will use in our architecture and culture in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cross-functional-teams-and-delivery&quot;&gt;Cross-functional teams and delivery&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I mean by a cross-functional team? A cross-functional team brings together people with different expertise to work together towards a common goal. I want to convince you that we need to modularise our technical architecture in Wales and as a result, we need to &lt;em&gt;modularise our teams&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, it is easy to see software development as a process of generating value akin to a factory assembly line, in which a clinical system is designed, built, tested and then deployed to the end-customer. This is what is called a “value stream”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to fall into the trap, usually brought about by naivety mixed with arrogance, that we can define the specifications of what is needed from our software, build it, and then deploy into clinical environments and immediately realise that value, sitting back to announce “our work is done”. As a result, you will have a design team, a development team, a testing team and a deployment (operations) team, and at each step, the “work” is passed from one team to another. When an incident occurs, and they do, perhaps a patient safety team will swing into action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is that the right way to structure and operate your organisation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cross-functional team brings together those experts into the right sized teams, in which communication between members is easy, there is a shared goal, usually focused on &lt;em&gt;delivery&lt;/em&gt;. Members of different functional teams are brought together, for possibly a fixed duration, in order to deliver a goal bringing together design, development, testing, evaluation and deployment and speeding up the lifecycle between these processes so that we aim for &lt;em&gt;continuous integration&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;continuous delivery&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Action 2: We need to modularise our architecture and modularise our teams, creating cross-functional teams whose task is to &lt;em&gt;deliver&lt;/em&gt; discrete components of our architecture which are loosely-coupled from one another, with a focus on automated unit and end-to-end integration testing and continuous delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;creative-destruction--ecosystems-thinking&quot;&gt;Creative destruction &amp;amp; ecosystems-thinking&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we want to develop a distributed, standards-driven platform that provides the building blocks with which to build the next generation of electronic health applications?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice I don’t say “electronic health record software”, because I want to convince you that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Data persistence and transfer &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be considered separately to the applications and software services that operate upon those data.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need multiple applications giving different views and bespoke utility using the same data. A single logical record of patient information.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#single-patient-record&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefits of an open ecosystem extend beyond only a new marketplace for health applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Interestingly, another definition of a “platform” is a set of services that bring together users and providers to form a multisided market. Is it possible then to take our “open platform” and start to think of a future in which we have products and services that actually do enable a re-imagining of healthcare provision to bring together patients, carers, health professionals, commissioners, analytics, researchers and all other stakeholders in a safe and secure manner?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html&quot;&gt;disruptive influences in healthcare blog post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, a new ecosystem permits us to step-back and re-imagine our healthcare services. When you have physical notes, the team looking after your chronic health conditions or your primary care physician need to be physically located near those notes and near to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be the same with online banking in which your local branch held your account. We see the artefact of this configuration even today with account numbers and sort-codes tracking the bank and branch at which your bank account is held. Digital technology was an important tool in re-imagining how we interact with our banks; for them, digital is now &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; way of doing business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can we do the same for healthcare?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Action 3: We need to think ‘open’ and build software services and data repositories that are usable by both internal and external developers to create value and innovation; ecosystems-thinking. We need to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eating_your_own_dog_food&quot;&gt;“eat our own dog food”&lt;/a&gt; and ensure external developers are treated the same as internal development teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;posts-in-this-series&quot;&gt;Posts in this series&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/cloud-ehr.html&quot;&gt;Part one: creative destruction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;Part two: the value of software for healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html&quot;&gt;Part three: ecosystems and the platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/04/26/lean-healthcare-devops.html&quot;&gt;“Lean healthcare” &lt;/a&gt;: Value stream: transforming health and care technology implementations using lean, agile, “DevOps” and serverless with small, cross-functional teams.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/30/where-is-the-value.html&quot;&gt;“Where is the value?”&lt;/a&gt;: Creative destruction and ecosystems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In part one, I highlighted four drivers that will result in creative destruction in the healthcare IT industry:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creative 2/3: The value of software for healthcare</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creative 2/3: The value of software for healthcare" /><published>2018-05-06T10:09:09+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-06T10:09:09+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;part one, I highlighted four drivers that will result in creative destruction&lt;/a&gt; in the healthcare IT industry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was the recognition that software and data are critical enablers of clinical quality improvement, service transformation and advancing our knowledge (research).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second was that the best way to build healthcare software is to adopt the behaviours, processes and culture from the most highly productive technology companies. This means adopting quality improvement and research methodologies to develop, test and deploy the software that use to improve our clinical quality, service and research endeavours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third was the importance of separating data storage and transmission from the software operating on those data, with a shared domain language uniting multi-disciplinary cross-functional, semi-autonomous teams creating discrete, carefully bounded components with loose coupling with other components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth was the recognition of a transformation in software engineering practices with the increasing adoption of cloud and serverless technologies, permitting the development and commodification of components of what will become, a distributed and patient-centred logical electronic health record. The end result? A variety of interoperable applications, both clinical and administrative indeed, focused on workflow and usually task-orientated, making use of that shared health platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In [, part two covers the importance of software in our efforts to transform clinical services and improve quality.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;software-and-healthcare&quot;&gt;Software and healthcare&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Software is eating the world.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424053111903480904576512250915629460&quot;&gt;Marc Andreeson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Every industry that is not bringing software to the core of their business will be disrupted.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Immelt, CEO and Chairman, General Electric, 2001-2017&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I truly believe that software is critical to the future of healthcare, in supporting both patients and health professionals in their respective roles. Current software usually does little but replace existing paper processes but we should be aiming to use software to transform our health services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our clinical quality improvement and service transformation endeavours must be supported by new technology, by software and data, to support our efforts to effect change and measure the outcomes of that change in a virtuous cycle of continuous improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such continuous improvement requires us to be able to rapidly develop, test, integrate and deploy software. That software could be hand-coded or be the product of machine learning; whatever the case, it needs to be developed, tested, integrated and deployed continuously monitored to ensure it works safely and reliably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we confident that we have the right culture and architecture in order to do that, because if we don’t, won’t we need to transform our organisations, our culture and our technical architecture to support those needs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, we must recognise that our technology, quality improvement and research endeavours are best considered as related and mutually supportive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tech-qual-research.png&quot; alt=&quot;The relationship between technology, quality improvement and research&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quality improvement relies on measurement, analysis and action and therefore most effectively supported by the provision of digital tools to those who wish to transform their services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, development and deployment of technology should, itself, be subject to the same approach to quality improvement so that we develop, test, measure, analyse and deploy in the same virtuous cycle of &lt;em&gt;continuous&lt;/em&gt; improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/devops-qi.png&quot; alt=&quot;Devops Qi&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, &lt;em&gt;research&lt;/em&gt;, a process to advance our knowledge, requires very similar but more robust and formal protocols and oversight. But technology can help us here, supporting our decision making when in situations of genuine equipoise by providing transformative technology supporting identification, recruitment and randomisation of patients into complex, multi-arm trials currently require manual labour-intensive work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;metrics-of-success&quot;&gt;Metrics of success&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must admit that our work will &lt;em&gt;never be complete&lt;/em&gt;. As a result, whether we are talking about our clinical services, our technology or our research, we should never use metrics that simply talk about &lt;em&gt;deployment&lt;/em&gt;, but instead consider &lt;em&gt;outcomes&lt;/em&gt; and our efforts should be focused on improving those &lt;em&gt;outcomes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many others, NHS Wales currently uses deployment as a metric for success, but we need to change the conversation to &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;outcome&lt;/em&gt; and shift to adopting the best industry practices for creating safe, reliable and valuable clinical software &lt;em&gt;at pace&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html&quot;&gt;part three&lt;/a&gt;, I talk about the importance of technical and information standards, standardised application programming interfaces and frameworks to create &lt;em&gt;ecosystems&lt;/em&gt; of interoperating smaller, well-defined contextually domain bound components sharing the same platform. &lt;a href=&quot;(/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html)&quot;&gt;Continue reading…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;posts-in-this-series&quot;&gt;Posts in this series&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/cloud-ehr.html&quot;&gt;Part one: creative destruction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;Part two: the value of software for healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html&quot;&gt;Part three: ecosystems and the platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/04/26/lean-healthcare-devops.html&quot;&gt;“Lean healthcare” &lt;/a&gt;: Value stream: transforming health and care technology implementations using lean, agile, “DevOps” and serverless with small, cross-functional teams.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/30/where-is-the-value.html&quot;&gt;“Where is the value?”&lt;/a&gt;: Creative destruction and ecosystems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;single-patient-record&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;:The single patient record is a good idea - a logical single source-of-truth that is the canonical repository of information. Except, i) there is no truth in healthcare so you are better with models of uncertainty and ii) a medical record must be faceted so that it is possible to regulate access to different categories of information such as source (e.g. provider) and type (e.g. sexual or reproductive health matters, mental health, genetics, general medical etc). But, for now, “single patient record” is a useful pragmatic label.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In part one, I highlighted four drivers that will result in creative destruction in the healthcare IT industry:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creative 1/3: Next generation electronic health records</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/cloud-ehr.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creative 1/3: Next generation electronic health records" /><published>2018-05-06T10:09:09+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-06T10:09:09+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/cloud-ehr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/cloud-ehr.html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/30/where-is-the-value.html&quot;&gt;“Where is the value?”&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about market disruption by the cycle of commoditisation and creative destruction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon, there will be a period of creative destruction for the healthcare information technology industry resulting from four important drivers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The recognition that software and data are critical enablers of clinical quality improvement, service transformation and advancing our knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That to support quality improvement, we will adopt practices used in the most highly productive technology companies to permit the supporting software to be developed, tested and deployed rapidly, iteratively, safely and securely. At the same time, we will increasingly see the benefits from building smaller self-contained components via small cross-functional teams with bounded contexts and loose coupling with other components. In essence, we will adopt software quality improvement methodologies in our development processes to drive clinical quality improvement. Adoption of these approaches will result in changes to our culture, our enterprise architecture and drive the use of standards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That complex, adaptive environments such as healthcare benefit from a domain-driven approach and separation of the storage / transmission of data from software functions that operate upon those data. Our adoption of shared data standards is critical to this; essentially this means a shared language used within bounded but shared interdisciplinary contexts. Separation of software functionality from the way those data are persisted is essential in building software systems for cultures that recognise our work will never be complete and we will always strive to improve.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That software-as-a-service is becoming commonplace; as a result, we will increasingly blend functionality from in-house teams with that provided by multiple other service providers. In essence, many computing functions will become commoditised and others will become specialist and pay-per-use; almost all will be provided by commodity cloud providers and infrastructure-as-a-service. As a result, we will adopt an ecosystem of compute functions operating upon data stored or transmitted independently; monolithic applications will be quickly overtaken by blended applications stitching together software functionality from multiple vendors to create increasing value for end-users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My next blog posts will take each of these in turn and explore the best way for us all, whether health providers or software companies, to take advantage of the changes that new technology can bring. I truly believe that this must inform how we build the next generation of electronic health record software: distributed, cloud-based and centred on the patient and not the organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tech-qual-research.png&quot; alt=&quot;The overlap between our efforts in service transformation and quality improvement, research and advancing our knowledge and technology&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to recognise the overlap and mutually dependent relationships between:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;our efforts in healthcare service transformation and quality improvement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;research and advancing our knowledge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;technology and digital tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding these relationships, and the fact that software is truly a transformative force for good, is critical for those of us who want to support healthcare with technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continue reading… &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;part two covers the importance of software in our efforts to transform clinical services and improve quality.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;posts-in-this-series&quot;&gt;Posts in this series&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/cloud-ehr.html&quot;&gt;Part one: creative destruction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;Part two: the value of software for healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html&quot;&gt;Part three: ecosystems and the platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/30/where-is-the-value.html&quot;&gt;“Where is the value?”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/04/26/lean-healthcare-devops.html&quot;&gt;Lean healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In “Where is the value?”, I talked about market disruption by the cycle of commoditisation and creative destruction.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Lean healthcare</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/04/26/lean-healthcare-devops.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Lean healthcare" /><published>2018-04-26T07:06:06+01:00</published><updated>2018-04-26T07:06:06+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/04/26/lean-healthcare-devops</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/04/26/lean-healthcare-devops.html">&lt;p&gt;In this blog post, I want to talk about transforming our health services using technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four core messages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Most of us working in healthcare are already familiar with a range of quality improvement methodologies -  we see them at work when we discuss our healthcare services - and yet we frequently fail to use those same improvement techniques in our information technology projects.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We can learn from how technology companies have adopted similar quality improvement methodologies (&lt;em&gt;lean&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;agile&lt;/em&gt;) in their efforts to develop new technology, and use the same approaches to both develop and manage healthcare information technology.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That small, cross-functional teams can be given responsibility for delivering discrete functional components of a wider software architecture, bringing together development, testing and deployment as part of a wider “DevOps” strategy. Increasing adoption of ‘serverless’ technologies is a logical result of this strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That these same approaches can be extended to include our existing quality improvement and research methodologies so that we accelerate the adoption of data-driven value-based healthcare in a virtuous cycle of improvement. We use technology to re-imagine how we deliver healthcare to our citizens, with information technology an enabler of transformation; &lt;em&gt;ownership&lt;/em&gt; is key here with IT and quality improvement going hand-in-hand.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve included some links to resources for further reading at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;healthcare-transformation&quot;&gt;Healthcare transformation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to consider &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; we most effectively use information technology in healthcare so that we do more than simply replace our paper records with electronic equivalents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must think deeply about how we can use technology to &lt;em&gt;transform&lt;/em&gt; how we deliver healthcare to our citizens. We must be ambitious and yet plan to deliver those ambitions incrementally, safely, carefully and within the constraints within which we work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Every industry that is not bringing software to the core of their business will be disrupted.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Immelt, CEO and Chairman, General Electric, 2001-2017&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, we need to re-imagine a new technical architecture - an &lt;em&gt;open platform&lt;/em&gt; at its core - built on standards and interoperability. But, we must also go much further than simply talk about technical architectures and drive a change in culture and trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, to deliver IT-enabled healthcare transformation, we need the right:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;open architecture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;cultural ‘norms’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;technical and information standards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These should underpin our software development and technical operations.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#wtsb&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-cohesive-strategy&quot;&gt;A cohesive strategy&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information technology projects must be ‘owned’ by the organisations delivering care with a focus on quality improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The key to creating a lean enterprise is to enable those doing the work to solve their customers’ problems in a way that is aligned with the strategy of the wider organization. To achieve this, we rely on people being able to make local decisions that are sound at a strategic level—which, in turn, relies critically on the flow of information, including feedback loops.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Lean-Enterprise-Performance-Organizations-Innovate/dp/1449368425&quot;&gt;Lean Enterprise, 2015, Jez Humble, Joanne Molesky, and Barry O’Reilly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is difficult to defend organisational structures in which ownership of information technology projects is outsourced to an external agency. Such issues of ownership are a fundamental problem when something goes wrong&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ptsafety&quot;&gt;b&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;;  a safer approach is to make the ownership explicit with a clear purchaser/commissional-provider split in which lines of responsibility are explicit. The health organisation as a whole  must “own” the information technology solutions and take responsibility for any consequences of failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, given that all organisations and businesses are now, in effect, information technology companies (including healthcare organisations), information technology should not be the responsibility of a single department but cut across all internal departments. What changes can be made to the way we deliver healthcare that doesn’t have some need for information technology change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Historically, the adoption and management of health care IT has been left to an organization’s chief information officer and other technical personnel. This is a mistake. … health care IT is effective only when all members of an organization work to unlock its potential.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“… many health care organizations use IT as a tool to monitor current processes and protocols; what only a small number have done is leverage those same IT systems to see if those processes and protocols can be improved—and if so, to act accordingly.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“… [we need to] embrace [IT] as an instrument to help transform the way they deliver medical care. This will entail prioritizing quality improvement over cost cutting, making data collection easier and better, turning the data into actionable information for clinicians, and forging new operating and business models. We have found that while numerous health care organizations are moving in this direction, the majority are not making the holistic changes needed for transformation.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2017/11/the-it-transformation-health-care-needs&quot;&gt;Harvard Business Review (HBR) The IT Transformation Health Care Needs, Dec 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-are-our-goals&quot;&gt;So what are our goals?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we make the right decisions about architecture, culture and standards to enable us to use information technology effectively to monitor, improve and transform our health services?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are our goals, given we work in complex, heterogeneous, ever-changing adaptive systems, with a high degree of uncertainty?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At our foundation, we need a high-trust collaborative cross-organisational culture. What culture do you have in your own organisation, or across multiple organisations in your wider health economy? We need a ‘generative’ culture:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Pathological organizations are characterized by large amounts of fear and threat. People often hoard information or withhold it for political reasons, or distort it to make themselves look better.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Bureaucratic organizations protect departments. Those in the department want to maintain their “turf,” insist on their own rules, and generally do things by the book—their book.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Generative organizations focus on the mission. How do we accomplish our goal? Everything is subordinated to good performance, to doing what we are supposed to do.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Lean-Enterprise-Performance-Organizations-Innovate/dp/1449368425&quot;&gt;Lean Enterprise, 2015, Jez Humble, Joanne Molesky, and Barry O’Reilly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of that culture, we must recognise that we do not have all of the answers and that we must be able to adapt to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to fall into a trap of thinking the best way of dealing with uncertainty is building “command-and-control” like structures in which we analyse the work to be done and deliver it by breaking it up into components or projects. It is, unfortunately, naive to think that centralised command-and-control reduces risk in delivering valuable information technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, we must focus our efforts around high-level strategic objectives and then create small cross-functional teams empowered to deliver components of that vision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“According to the Principle of Mission, we create alignment not by making a detailed plan of how we achieve our objective but by describing the intent of our mission and communicating why we are undertaking it.The key to the Principle of Mission is to create alignment and enable autonomy by setting out clear, high-level target conditions with an agreed time frame—which gets smaller under conditions of greater uncertainty—and then leaving the details of how to achieve the conditions to teams.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Lean Enterprise, 2015 quoting “The Principles of Product Development Flow” by Donald Reinertsen&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wrote in “The paradox of control”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“There is an important paradox in many health services, including Wales, is that there is a tendency to centralise the day-to-day management and delivery of individual products and yet high-level strategic and prioritisation decisions are decentralised, haphazard and dependant on capital funding with little or no consideration or control as to how those projects will fit into a wider technical healthcare enterprise architecture.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html&quot;&gt;“A paradox of control”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;balancing-inherent-conflicts&quot;&gt;Balancing inherent conflicts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to explicitly create a) an architecture, b) a culture and c) appropriate standards that result in overall solutions that are safe and secure and yet at the same time enable innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to see how such goals can be in conflict, unless we explicitly mitigate that conflict in how we design and manage that architecture, that culture and those technical standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are just three examples of what appear to such conflicts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;we need software to respond to our changing needs and provide ever increasing value via automation (IT “developments”) while at the same time, we need to provide stable, reliable and secure services (IT “operations”)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;we need local innovation and local decision making but ensure that local developments are not orthogonal to the wider strategic roadmap.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;we need to adopt technical and information standards and yet support innovation and flexibility in approach.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such conflicts are magnified if we have the wrong architecture, culture and standards. Similarly, the right architecture, culture and standards can minimise or entirely mitigate these apparently intractable conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to adopt “DevOps”, agility and lean thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;devops&quot;&gt;DevOps&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“DevOps” refers to creating cross-functional teams who break-down the traditional barriers between IT developments and operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern technology companies have seen huge productivity gains from creating small teams to quickly and independently develop, test and deploy software and therefore deliver value at pace. They minimise risk by breaking down work into smaller, less risky units that can evolve independently with only loose-coupling with other components. They combine the development of new functionality with highly automated testing and deployment, often building in “feature switches” which optionally turn specific new functionality on or off depending on runtime configuration for testing in limited real-life environments before more widespread use is permitted. Such teams may deploy multiple versions per day, each deployment small and low risk, dependent on successfully passing automated testing and easily rolled back in the event of problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key is that developers can deploy into potentially multiple production-like test environments with little or no manual effort. Deployment is automated from a technical point-of-view, and, &lt;em&gt;codified&lt;/em&gt;. As a result, testing and deployment are both designed and executed using code or configuration files and is therefore &lt;em&gt;automated&lt;/em&gt;. It is entirely reasonable to delay actual deployment into production until other requirements are met, but that process becomes one of simply migrating provenly reliable code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an approach is very different to what usually happens in healthcare IT. Those of you who work within the NHS will be familiar with long development cycles, entirely separate teams running the different stages of development, testing, deployment, and maintaining services. The process for creating and deploying new functionality typically requires long test-cycles, user-acceptance tests and then, at some indeterminate time in the future, features are rolled into a high-risk big-bang deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.eu/ekRxYte&quot;&gt;DevOps Handbook&lt;/a&gt; talks about a “downward spiral” in three acts, in which components of a wider architecture become fragile and increasingly difficult to change, building an increasing “technical debt”, of attempting to make changes by cutting corners and never really having time to fix the underlying issues and so adding to that “debt”, and resulting in a situation in which:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“everything becomes just a little more difficult, bit by bit— everybody gets a little busier, work takes a little more time, communications become a little slower, and work queues get a little longer.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Our work becomes more tightly-coupled, smaller actions cause bigger failures, and we become more fearful and less tolerant of making changes.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“Work requires more communication, coordination, and approvals; teams must wait just a little longer for their dependent work to get done; and our quality keeps getting worse. The wheels begin grinding slower and require more effort to keep turning.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.eu/ekRxYte&quot;&gt;The DevOps Handbook: How to Create World-Class Agility, Reliability, and Security in Technology Organizations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The natural conclusion is that we should aim for &lt;em&gt;continuous integration&lt;/em&gt; (CI) and &lt;em&gt;continuous deployment&lt;/em&gt; (CD), with a focus on splitting up what we need to deliver into manageable chunks to be worked upon semi-autonomously by small, independent, cross-functional teams themselves releasing software frequently and often with the confidence of automated toolchains to support extensive unit, integration and security testing with deployment into production-like environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The advent of “serverless” technologies supports and extends “DevOps” principles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Serverless computing allows users to run code without provisioning or managing any underlying system or application infrastructure, and they automatically scale to support increasing or decreasing loads. 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.gartner.com/andrew-lerner/2017/07/21/serverless-is-not-networkless/&quot;&gt;https://blogs.gartner.com/andrew-lerner/2017/07/21/serverless-is-not-networkless/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With “serverless” computing, we no longer need to manage our own infrastructure but instead make use of commodity cloud computing providers who take our code and run, monitor and scale to meet demand automatically. Our IT “operations” work is still needed however, but almost by default, software development is immediately deployable into production-like environments. Operations are still needed in order to orchestrate multiple semi-independent services but technologies such as API gateways can act to provide a unified single point of access to multiple services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;agile&quot;&gt;Agile&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;Agile Manifesto&quot;&gt;“Agile” manifesto&lt;/a&gt; was released in 2001; the key points for the purposes of this post are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;continuous delivery of quality software&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;delivering working software frequently&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;harnessing change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to see that “agile” is about culture change and that the consequences of a change in culture are a set of technical solutions such as DevOps and Serverless. Agile is, in effect an enabler of “DevOps”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Instead of large batches of work being processed sequentially through the design/ development value stream and then through the test/ operations value stream (such as when we have a large batch waterfall process or long-lived feature branches), our goal is to have testing and operations happening simultaneously with design/ development, enabling fast flow and high quality. This method succeeds when we work in small batches and build quality into every part of our value stream.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The DevOps Handbook&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;lean-principles-and-six-sigma&quot;&gt;Lean principles and Six Sigma&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While “Lean” was originally created by Toyota to improve productivity and quality, the principles are much more widely applicable to other industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The five &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.asme.org/engineering-topics/articles/manufacturing-design/5-lean-principles-every-should-know&quot;&gt;Lean principles are&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Value: what we want to do or deliver&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Value stream: the steps and processes needed to deliver the ‘value’, removing steps that do not add value&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flow: ensuring that the steps and processes that contribute to ‘value’ flow smoothly with no interruptions, delays or bottlenecks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pull: delivery of value as required ‘just-in-time’&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perfection: making lean thinking and process improvement part of the culture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, many readers might be more familiar with the Six Sigma methodology, now widely used within healthcare. Six Sigma focuses more on variation and design than flow and waste, but clearly these approaches are complementary and indeed, many now combine the two as “Lean Six Sigma”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have discussed the Six Sigma DMAIC cycle previously when discussing &lt;a href=&quot;/cis-design/2017/05/01/medical-record.html&quot;&gt;“The Medical Record”&lt;/a&gt; and the importance of a data-driven approach to quality improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cis_design/dmaic.png&quot; alt=&quot;Dmaic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;application-to-healthcare&quot;&gt;Application to healthcare&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we have a convergence that, at its core, is focused on delivering &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt;. Information technology is critical in our healthcare quality improvement endeavours and we can apply those same endeavours to &lt;em&gt;how we build&lt;/em&gt; our information technology tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is my view that quality improvement, in all its forms (e.g. our &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.1000livesplus.wales.nhs.uk/home&quot;&gt;1000 lives campaign in Wales&lt;/a&gt;), and information technology are inextricably linked and mutually beneficial. Quality improvement benefits from good information technology as the latter is fundamental in performance of the “measure”, “analyse” and “improve” steps of a typical DMAIC cycle. Similarly, information technology benefits from applying those same quality improvement methodologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need a “reset” in NHS Wales when it comes to information technology and I suspect this applies to other health economies as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to embed quality improvement at the heart of our information technology and information technology at the heart of our healthcare, adopt a generative culture and deliver at pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need less command-and-control and more trust and collaboration, with decision-making, clinical and design, based on &lt;em&gt;meaningful data&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Scott Cook, the founder of Intuit, has long advocated building a culture of innovation, encouraging teams to take an experimental approach to product development and exhorting leadership to support them. As he said, “Instead of focusing on the boss’s vote… the emphasis is on getting real people to really behave in real experiments, and basing your decisions on that.” This is the epitome of a scientific approach to product development.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The DevOps Handbook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;questions-to-ask&quot;&gt;Questions to ask&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are working in healthcare information technology, particularly if you’re in Wales, ask yourself these questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have a clear view of your “mission” and yet have sufficient autonomy to create teams to get things done?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have “can-do” ethos and a culture of trust and collaboration?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have a track record of delivering valuable products consistently, to time and within budget?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What is the time interval between development and deployment? Is it measured in hours, days, weeks or months?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Similarly, do you have ready access to production-like test environments to prove, via high-levels of automation, that changes in one system have no untoward effects in another? (Ask questions about test environments and automated checks that our systems are deterministic, both when running independently and when integrated with other systems).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Does your team view deployment in the same way as committing code instead of with trepidation, planning and prolonged downtime?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have robust investigation of failures, with a learning culture and codified tests to ensure such failures are prevented in the future?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have objective measures of quality improvement, do you routinely collect metrics on user satisfaction, performance, downtime or whatever else needs to improve? Have you adopted a &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;data-driven approach&lt;/a&gt; to informatics and quality improvement?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do you have a cadre of professional user-interface designers working across teams to focus on improving your user’s experience in using your software?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because, if you can answer yes to these questions, you are much more likely to be able to…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Move fast and &lt;del&gt;break&lt;/del&gt; fix healthcare…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you want to join me?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;wtsb&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;:That’s why I was delighted to be asked to chair the new Welsh Technical Standards Board (WTSB), a new group that will work in partnership with the Welsh Information Standards Board (WISB).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;ptsafety&quot;&gt;b&lt;/a&gt;: 3079 “parked” electronic referrals unintentionally unsent by general practitioners in Wales to secondary care services were deemed a “process issue” and not an “IT failure” and resulting investigation was “difficult due to lack of engagement from health boards” as the software supplier “owned” the project to digitise the referral pathways and not the organisations that owned the care pathways involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;see-also&quot;&gt;See also&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.eu/6F2n4Te&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/lean_enterprise.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Lean Enterprise&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;http://amzn.eu/4YoMrUS&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/devops-handbook.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Devops Handbook&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In this blog post, I want to talk about transforming our health services using technology.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Practical considerations for using SNOMED CT for analytics and machine learning</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/snomed/2018/04/16/snomed-understanding.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Practical considerations for using SNOMED CT for analytics and machine learning" /><published>2018-04-16T05:04:04+01:00</published><updated>2018-04-16T05:04:04+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/snomed/2018/04/16/snomed-understanding</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/snomed/2018/04/16/snomed-understanding.html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data-driven healthcare means using data to support and provide health services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personal medical data includes current and past medical problems, past and present treatments and interventions but we also increasingly recognise the value in data derived from personal devices and home monitoring. In addition, we need to take into account more generic medical information such as appropriate guidelines, literature and knowledge support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to support both patients and professionals in finding and making sense of that information in order to support decision-making. Similarly, we need to use these data to care not only for an individual patient but to look across groups of patients to understand outcomes and the effects of our interventions at a population-level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SNOMED CT is a comprehensive healthcare terminology; the UK distribution of SNOMED CT contains over 1,500,000 descriptions of over individual 500,000 concepts comprising problems, symptoms, signs, diagnoses, medications (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nhsbsa.nhs.uk/pharmacies-gp-practices-and-appliance-contractors/dictionary-medicines-and-devices-dmd&quot;&gt;dm+d&lt;/a&gt;) and procedures as well as supporting administrative concepts such as occupations, countries of birth and many others. SNOMED CT has been derived, in part, from the UK Read codes, widely used in general practice, but importantly, while Read codes provide only a single hierarchy, SNOMED CT supports the definition of multiple types of relationship between concepts. The most frequently used relationship, IS-A, provides a taxonomic hierarchy in which specific concepts, such as “myocardial infarction” are classified as a member of a higher class, such as “ischaemic heart disease” or “disorder of the heart”. As a result, SNOMED CT provides a medical ontology that is meaningful to professionals and is computable; I have previously demonstrated my own electronic patient record software that, using code, can systematically identify patients with a certain disease and highlight important outcome measures and compare disease progression with peers in conditions like motor neurone disease and multiple sclerosis (see &lt;a href=&quot;/patientcare/2018/02/19/so-I-built-an-EPR.html&quot;&gt;“so I built an EPR”&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While its size means that it is often very comprehensive, SNOMED CT can be difficult to implement technically and much effort is required to manage the quality of concepts and the relationships between them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, one of the ways of managing the complexity has been to set up a working group of interested clinicians in order to define a reference set of  curated terms in order to simplify the implementation for specific clinical workflows. Indeed, there are now over 250 reference sets in the UK distribution alone. Some of these, such as language reference sets, are now an essential part of the SNOMED CT model as they provide the data to support logic on which preferred synonym to use for a particular language or dialect. However, some simply provide a restricted list of concepts to aid implementation, user interface design and analysis for a specific clinical context or subspecialty. For instance, we now have a UK emergency care diagnosis reference set containing 770 clinical diagnoses that are thought to be useful in an emergency department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to argue that,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we should be spending our time as a community improving the quality of the concepts and relationships in the core SNOMED CT model in preference to thinking we should start by creating a new reference set that will need ongoing maintenance and curation; why unnecessarily limit choice? We can permit access to end-users the whole of SNOMED CT by making use of the taxonomic hierarchy to limit choice in a specific context as long as you design an appropriate user interface; we can limit choice to types of “countries of birth” for a country of birth data entry field and “diagnoses” for a diagnosis data entry field but why constrain only to a subset of diagnoses? The only use of optional constraints is to make it easier for the user to enter commonly used terms, and there are probably better ways of learning those that starting a new committee, such as tracking terms automatically and learning on-the-fly.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we can support analytics by using that taxonomic hierarchy to simplify and make sense of raw data; in essence, to reduce complex high-dimensionality data into something simpler and computable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My final point is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we need to build open-source tools to build an infrastructure that can act as a platform onto which more innovation, including the application of machine learning, can be built. We need to make this core functionality a commodity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;using-snomed-ct-in-real-life&quot;&gt;Using SNOMED CT in real-life&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I embedded SNOMED-CT into an &lt;a href=&quot;http://m.futurehospital.rcpjournal.org/content/4/2/126.full.pdf&quot;&gt;electronic patient record system in 2009&lt;/a&gt; and have used it since as the lingua-franca in handling semantic interoperability and appropriate isolation between modules of the application. An article briefly describing its functionality is available &lt;a href=&quot;http://m.futurehospital.rcpjournal.org/content/4/2/126&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three important learning points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is possible to implement SNOMED CT and make it accessible to users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;in my experience, you know you have good user interface design when your users do not actually know that they are using SNOMED CT&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the use of SNOMED CT does not mean you enter terms only by direct user entry such as an autocomplete textfield  or drop-down selections. SNOMED terms can be imputed as a result of other processes and as such, it can be used as an intermediary structure onto which to build clinical decision support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a user entering a country of birth:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/so-i-wrote/background.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Background&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this diagram, the user has no idea that they are entering SNOMED CT concepts, but their choice is constrained appropriately so that they cannot enter a diagnosis in a country of birth field and we can understand that being born in France means that a patient was born in Europe. I’ve obviously not hard-coded this logic, I’ve simply configured my user interface control to allow:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;selection of a commonly selected concept in this specific context, such as a particular type of clinical setting&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an ability to search for less frequently used concepts with a simple autocomplete search - the “Other…” link opens this link when the user wishes to select a term not in the most-frequently used pop-up.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;constraint of both to the appropriate context, in this case, countries of birth&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here I type MI and can readily select the diagnosis I wanted, in this case “myocardial infarction”. This is from a simple demo application rather than a proper electronic health record:
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/so-i-wrote/snomed-search.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Snomed Search&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use the same approach to simplify building clinical forms for data entry, with SNOMED CT terms either entered by the user:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cppjedy-hMo?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;autoplay; encrypted-media&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;or imputed based on logic from other data entered, such as “able to walk” based on entry of a disease-specific structured disability rating scale. Other modules do not need to ‘understand’ the disease-specific scale but use the intermediary SNOMED based data structures to make appropriate inferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you give tools to professionals that make it easier to enter coded structured information than free-text, they will do so. Coding diagnoses, procedures and background information is critical in understanding outcome data; they are a foundation on which more complex and sophisticated analytics can be built, particularly if you ensure that those analytics are immediately available to support clinical decision making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;analytics&quot;&gt;Analytics&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the point of collecting data if we don’t use them to support our clinical care? We must make data that is &lt;em&gt;computable&lt;/em&gt;, that is, to be processed and analysed so it is useful for decision making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computer-intensive analytics, just like more conventional statistic approaches, can struggle with high-dimensional data. Much of our work in data analytics is cleaning data in order to make it computable. In conventional linear modelling for example, we might hypothesise that a range of covariates, a range of factors, might influence an outcome measurement and so we might estimate that we will need a sample size of 3-20x the number of variables. However, determination of sample size is much more complex than that, needing to take into account effect size and degrees of freedom for each covariate in our regression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are our options here?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let me enter free-text&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ask me to record, manually, a general categorical data-entry instead of a specific concept.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Let me choose from a limited number of “choice” options.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Record the best, most specific concept at the time of data-entry that matches what I’m thinking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we might have a referral pathway that  uses free-text which makes it possible for human consumption when processing individual referrals but difficult to compute, aggregate or make sense when examining many thousands of referrals to understand demands on our services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, we could ask the referring professional to simply choose a type of referral, such as “ischaemic heart disease” or “valvular heart disease” so that the referral can be redirected to the appropriate subspecialty cardiac service. This limits what we collect so that it becomes easier to process, both for human consumption and for analytic purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are problems with this approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Categorisation needs to be done prospectively.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We deliberately lose specific information in favour of recording a general category only.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It adds an additional step for users.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If we change our categorisation because of changes in our service, we have to change what the users have to choose and subsequently deal with handling analytics before and after the change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe the best approach is to preserve the granularity, the specificity, of the clinical concept(s) chosen at source and permit arbitrary categorisation at a later date, depending on need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;open-source-tooling&quot;&gt;Open source tooling&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have released two open-source SNOMED CT terminology servers which support both the fast free-text search of SNOMED CT concepts as well as support for analytics and generalisation of specific SNOMED concepts into more general broad diagnoses or categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wardle/rsterminology&quot;&gt;rsterminology&lt;/a&gt; has its roots in 2007-2008 and used to be a module within a larger application; it is now a java microservice built using &lt;a href=&quot;Apache Cayenne&quot;&gt;Apache Cayenne&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://bootique.io/&quot;&gt;Bootique&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://linkrest.io/&quot;&gt;LinkRest&lt;/a&gt;. It supports SNOMED distributions in the RF1 release format, which is now deprecated.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wardle/go-terminology&quot;&gt;go-terminology&lt;/a&gt; is a new golang command-line tool and microservice whose main focus is in supporting analytics. It supports SNOMED RF2, the current release format. It is a work-in-progress but usable now. It is my first golang application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;obtaining-simple-information-about-a-concept&quot;&gt;Obtaining simple information about a concept&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using either web service, we can readily obtain information about a concept, including the preferred synonym for a particular locale, here British English, and simplified subsumption testing, showing all of the IS-A relationships for this concept walking all of the possible paths up to root.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example, we see that multiple sclerosis (24700007) is a type of demyelinating central nervous system disease (6118003) and a type of neurological disease (118940003)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/snomed/ms-concept.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Ms Concept&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;genericise-a-concept&quot;&gt;Genericise a concept&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genericising a concept finds the best equivalent match for a specified concept either from a manually chosen list of categories or from an existing refset. This requires the new &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wardle/go-terminology&quot;&gt;go-terminology service&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, here we take a chosen concept, multiple sclerosis, and map it to the curated UK emergency care diagnosis reference set (991411000000109):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/snomed/ms-to-eu-refset.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Ms To Eu Refset&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might expect, multiple sclerosis is in that refset, so the service simply returns it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, a rare disorder like acute disseminated encephalomyelitis (ADEM - 83942000) is not a member of the UK emergency diagnosis reference set. Can we genericise this to make it useful for our analytics? Indeed we can, and using the SNOMED hierarchy, we can determine that ADEM is a type of encephalitis and automatically return that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/snomed/adem-to-eu.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Adem To Eu&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to note that adequate genericisation needs to identify the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; match and not just any match as otherwise, ADEM might simply be classified as a neurological disorder; while true, a more specific match exists in that reference set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, here we ask to genericise “myocardial infarction” (22298006) to one of four broad categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Neurological disorder (118940003)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heart disease (56265001)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ischaemic heart disease (414545008)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Heart valve stenosis (44241007)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple subsumption test would indicate that myocardial infarction could be either (2) or (3), so what result do we get?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/snomed/mi-to-category.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Mi To Category&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Appropriately, the service maps to “ischaemic heart disease” as the closest best match of the four categories available as it is more specific than the more general term “heart disease”, which subsumes it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, aortic stenosis is appropriately mapped to a type of heart valve stenosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/snomed/as-to-category.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;As To Category&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have successfully deployed SNOMED CT in real-life clinical environments since 2009, with almost all users entirely unaware that they were using SNOMED CT. I would argue that it is possible to safely permit access to all concepts with limits only on the basis of the taxonomic hierarchy and not on the basis of reference sets. I do limit the initial pop-up list to concepts most frequently used in a specific clinical context and might consider using an existing reference set as a starting list for those. While reference sets are now vital for some functionality, such as supporting localisation, I am sometimes disapppointed by what appears to be the default initial thoughts of working groups and committees, on starting to consider SNOMED CT implementation, to think about defining a new reference set for their purposes. Instead, we should improve the quality of the overall product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For decision support, analytics and benchmarking our services to others, we can use the taxonomic hierarchy to “understand” the specific concepts entered by our users, mapping them to higher level, broad concepts; we need simple tools to process and simplify structured clinical information, made available to multiple data processing pipelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to create an open-source foundation of services with which to build the next generation of advanced and valuable clinical information systems. We need to make an open and free infrastructure on which we create value, adopting open-source and building communities in order to create a &lt;em&gt;commodity platform&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this end, I hope to continue to build these open-source tools to support complex data transformation and simplification and would be keen to get collaborators who wish to do the same. Much of the go-terminology tool is to support the work I outlined in &lt;a href=&quot;/machine-learning/2017/12/17/diagnostic-inference.html&quot;&gt;my diagnostic inference blog post&lt;/a&gt;), particularly the need for dimensionality reduction in machine learning. Let me know if you want to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Introduction</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Where is the value?</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/30/where-is-the-value.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Where is the value?" /><published>2018-03-30T13:12:12+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-30T13:12:12+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/30/where-is-the-value</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/30/where-is-the-value.html">&lt;p&gt;Why is digital technology so important for the future of our healthcare services?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we consider how we can most effectively use digital technology in healthcare, It is easy to fall into a trap and simply support existing models and processes of care. Instead, we must raise our ambitions and look to digital technology to enable new ways to transform our health services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we mustn’t only limit our transformation agenda to only using digital channels to enable new ways of delivering care either. Fundamentally, we should be looking to digital tools to improve healthcare to provide &lt;em&gt;better outcomes for the populations that we serve&lt;/em&gt;. It is easy to lose sight of this ultimate aim: &lt;em&gt;outcomes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, we need to embed &lt;em&gt;digital thinking&lt;/em&gt; across all facets of our health services; digital is more than simply using technology but broad-based fundamental change which, at its core, means we focus on the data to become &lt;em&gt;data-driven&lt;/em&gt;, and what are we driven to do? We must be driven to improve outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means we need to create structured, meaningful data that will provide the foundation on which we create added value. Meaningful data means data that can be used for making decisions, reducing the uncertainty inherent in any decision. That decision may be whether to recommend a particular treatment for a specific patient, it might decide where your emergency medical team needs to intervene with a deteriorating patient on a ward in a hospital but it might also be used to inform us how and why we need to reconfigure or restructure our health services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, our healthcare digital transformation agenda must, like many other enterprises, invest in data analytical capability and, consequently, in computing power to help us store, retrieve and make sense of burgeoning amounts of data. We must make data the bedrock of our health enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, healthcare has always used data to inform practice. This is the basis of evidence-based medicine, but the cycle of clinical research from data collection, analysis, intervention and assessment can be too slow and usually, data collection has been designed specifically for that trial in a carefully selected population of patients. We use a similar approach with service transformation and quality improvement but fully embracing digital should mean that we improve the efficiency and effectiveness of our quality improvement interventions and embed those process in day-to-day care; the important difference is the use of systematically and routinely collected real-life data on process and outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/cis_design/dmaic.png&quot; alt=&quot;Quality improvement lifecycle - define, measure, analyse, improve, control&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, such analytics should run in real-time, providing us continuously updated information about the patients and services for whom we care. The logical conclusion is that we will see a convergence of ‘business analytics’ with our electronic health records built on a single source of “truth”: meaningful data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do we enable data-driven digital transformation? In my view, it is with open data standards, open application programming interfaces and citizen engagement with transparency and control over the use of data. Together, those pieces fit together to form a ‘platform’ onto which other valuable services and applications can be built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open data standards, open protocols and open application programming interfaces are powerful disruptive technological advances which cause creative disruptive and commodification in an industry. We are about to see the result of this in healthcare. But what is creative destruction?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;creative-destruction&quot;&gt;Creative destruction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is useful to examine how ‘value’ in technological terms evolves over the years as it helps to understand and perhaps predict what might happen in the coming years. To do so, we must look at how new technology has evolved and disrupted the technological advances of the previous generation as part of a continuous cycle of &lt;em&gt;creative destruction&lt;/em&gt; and commodification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A commodity refers to goods or services which have value but are &lt;em&gt;fungible&lt;/em&gt;; that is, it doesn’t really matter who produces or provides that commodity, essentially they are interchangeable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In software, the creative destruction cycle can result in the commodification of technology. For example, historically, computing networking protocols were proprietary resulting in networking that was both expensive and incompatible with other proprietary network systems. The open networking protocol (TCP/IP) has disrupted the marketplace for proprietary networking; we now regard networking as a commodity on which most of our modern information technology solutions are built. Networking itself has permitted worldwide communication and collaboration permitting new ways of working, new approaches to distributed software development and ‘open source’ technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the world’s most valuable companies have arisen due to near ubiquitous personal networking; commoditisation can create a new market far larger than that achieved than when the same technology was proprietary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current software technology such as cloud computing, in which applications and services can be provisioned and scaled on demand by a hosting provider, are the end result of this continuous cycle of innovation and commoditisation. Indeed, with container and serverless technology, we see the hosting providers becoming increasingly fungible. But what do these providers gain from making their services a commodity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-where-is-the-value&quot;&gt;So where is the ‘value’?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; in creative destruction and commoditisation derives from building valuable innovative products in the new markets created by those processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As cloud computing becomes more ubiquitous, healthcare enterprises will increasingly switch away from purchasing and installing software locally and instead make use of software-as-a-service. We can see the beginnings of this in non-health markets already with the advent of marketplaces like &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/serverless/serverlessrepo/&quot;&gt;Amazon’s Serverless Application Repository&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/compute/monetize-your-apis-in-aws-marketplace-using-api-gateway/&quot;&gt;AWS Marketplace / API gateway&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this mean for healthcare information technology? What will happen if as we build open systems, open standards and open application programming interfaces creating an &lt;em&gt;open platform&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will see a commodification of that platform and we will enable an ecosystem of innovation products that can use that platform to add value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Interestingly, another definition of a “platform” is a set of services that bring together users and providers to form a multisided market. Is it possible then to take our “open platform” and start to think of a future in which we have products and services that actually do enable a re-imagining of healthcare provision to bring together patients, carers, health professionals, commissioners, analytics, researchers and all other stakeholders in a safe and secure manner?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;My blog post: &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html&quot;&gt;Disruptive influences, the future. August 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it likely that the technology giants, such as Amazon, Apple, Google and Microsoft, already recognise the value in creating a new multi-sided marketplace for healthcare by the use of open standards and commodification of a platform. We already see how Apple has worked to permit patient access to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2018/03/doctors-put-patients-in-charge-with-apples-health-records-feature/&quot;&gt;medical records via the use of HL7 FHIR&lt;/a&gt;, Google has &lt;a href=&quot;https://healthitanalytics.com/news/google-using-fhir-deep-learning-for-healthcare-predictive-analytics&quot;&gt;embraced HL7 FHIR for predictive analytics and machine learning&lt;/a&gt; and launched a new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.digitalhealth.net/2018/03/google-launches-cloud-healthcare-api/&quot;&gt;cloud application programming interface to manage DICOM and HL7 FHIR data&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Google Cloud’s goal for healthcare is very much a reflection of Google’s overall mission: to organize the world’s information and make it universally accessible and useful. Applying this mission to healthcare means using open standards to help enable data sharing and interactive collaboration, while also providing a secure platform. Just imagine if all healthcare providers could easily, securely and instantaneously collaborate while caring for you. Ultimately, we hope that better flow of data will inspire new discoveries with artificial intelligence (AI) and machine learning (ML), leading to insights that improve patient outcomes.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Google Cloud blog, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.google/topics/google-cloud/google-cloud-healthcare-new-apis-customers-partners-and-security-updates/&quot;&gt;https://blog.google/topics/google-cloud/google-cloud-healthcare-new-apis-customers-partners-and-security-updates/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must recognise that unlocking healthcare data opens up extraordinary potential advances and that, the use of open standards will enable a new generation of value-added data-driven services and applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal goal is to create the next generation of electronic patient record systems with the aim to improve outcomes, but I recognise that to do that, we must strive for a open, dynamic data-driven healthcare environment onto which we can build innovation and build value. And that doesn’t yet exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With ubiquitous computing power available on demand, we should be planning now on how we will build and evaluate and then deploy automated tools to add value in healthcare. Such tools might triage, risk assess, interpret investigation results and support diagnosis and management, but we should aspire also to build tools, built on a foundation of meaningful data, to aid redesigning our healthcare systems around patients and not organisations and to, most importantly, improve outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I want to see a future in which the platform becomes an interchangeable commodity with innovation and differentiation occurring at a higher conceptual level of support for medical practice. Rather than simple data collection, our mission must be to imagine a future in which medical practice, which at its most fundamental is about clinical decision making, is supported by the most sophisticated tools possible to improve patient care.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This mission’s greatest risk is in the continued creation of data silos in which health information is locked away in proprietary systems. The answer is to create an open, extensible platform on which innovation can thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;My blog post: &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/06/15/embedding-data.html&quot;&gt;Embedding data in routine clinical practice, June 2017&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPR is dead, long live the EPR!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Why is digital technology so important for the future of our healthcare services?</summary></entry></feed>