<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.wardle.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.wardle.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-08-31T07:38:59+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/</id><title type="html">Health informatics and information technology</title><subtitle>by Dr Mark Wardle, Consultant Neurologist, clinical informatics and software developer. Founder, Eldrix Ltd.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Using algorithms in healthcare</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/08/30/algorithm-strategy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Using algorithms in healthcare" /><published>2018-08-30T10:09:09+01:00</published><updated>2018-08-30T10:09:09+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/08/30/algorithm-strategy</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/08/30/algorithm-strategy.html">&lt;p&gt;I want to convince you that our use of machine learning in healthcare, building algorithms that learn for themselves, depends on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;developing expertise in data analytics and machine learning,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;structuring, generating and aggregating clinically meaningful clinical data, and,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;building robust evaluation processes using a combination of synthetic, randomised controlled and real-life implementation phases.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An algorithm is simply a list of rules to follow in order to solve a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;machine-learning&quot;&gt;Machine learning&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning uses statistical methods to allow computers to learn from data; in effect, an algorithm is generated by a computer based on data.  Modern advances in computationally-intensive methods, such as deep learning, enabled by advances in computing power, have resulted in widespread recent adoption in many domains such as image and speech recognition and excitement about its potential use in healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning is already being used in fields outside of image and speech recognition. For example, in 2016, Google DeepMind built a automated recommendation algorithm to improve the energy efficiency of Google’s data centres; the algorithm analyses data from thousands of sensors and is optimised to minimise energy consumption. After two years, with the benefit of real-world experience as well as a range of additional safety measures, the teams took the &lt;a href=&quot;https://deepmind.com/blog/safety-first-ai-autonomous-data-centre-cooling-and-industrial-control/&quot;&gt;decision to make the system directly implement its recommendations&lt;/a&gt;. As an adaptive algorithm tasked with optimising energy efficiency, the teams have demonstrated an improvement with performance improves over time, as a result of more data being available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google DeepMind’s AlphaGo &lt;a href=&quot;https://deepmind.com/blog/exploring-mysteries-alphago/&quot;&gt;took on and defeated one of the World champions of the game Go&lt;/a&gt;. Rather than simply applying a brute force, combinatorial approach to generate the best moves from a finite set of possible moves, the team used deep learning to create a continuously-learning algorithm that improved over time; such learning provided human players with new insights into tactics and strategy as the algorithm used &lt;a href=&quot;https://deepmind.com/blog/innovations-alphago/&quot;&gt;unconventional and unintuitive moves&lt;/a&gt; during its play. Their later AlphaGo Zero algorithm, while not needing bootstrapping with even the rules of the game, or from records of previous games, benefitted from a novel approach to reinforcement learning in which it learnt outcomes from games it played against itself, generating data about outcomes in a feedback loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about machine learning and healthcare?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IBM announced that they would build Watson for Health in 2013, launching services for cancer care that could recommend treatment regimens based on individual patient data and the latest research. During development, IBM acquired a number of companies possessing large amounts of health data, but within four years, the project had been &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.technologyreview.com/s/607965/a-reality-check-for-ibms-ai-ambitions/&quot;&gt;shut down at the M.D. Cancer Centre, in Houston, USA&lt;/a&gt; and this year, it was reported that internal IBM reports documented &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statnews.com/2018/07/25/ibm-watson-recommended-unsafe-incorrect-treatments/&quot;&gt;that unsafe and incorrect cancer treatments were being recommended&lt;/a&gt;. In writing this blog post, I’ve found conflicting anecdotal reports of its success so it is difficult to conclude anything definitively at present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite such controversies, there have been some successes; Google DeepMind, in a collaboration with Moorfields Eye Hospital, have created an algorithm to interpret optical coherence tomography (OCT) scans, used to examine the structures of the retina in great detail, in order to &lt;a href=&quot;https://deepmind.com/documents/239/De%20Fauw%20et.%20al%20Nature%20Medicine%202018%20.pdf&quot;&gt;triage patients by identifying pathology requiring referral&lt;/a&gt;. In that paper, the authors compare performance of their algorithm with humans, identifying risks of over- and under-diagnosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;advances in machine learning have created powerful, adaptive, learning algorithms that can outperform humans in niche areas.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we need need labelled data, including outcome data, in order to teach an algorithm effectively.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;performance of machine learning in healthcare has been subject to hype and relatively few proven success stories&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;progress in healthcare, so far, has been associated with taking decisions that have tightly defined scope and that are made in specific clinical contexts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;algorithms-in-healthcare&quot;&gt;Algorithms in healthcare&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Algorithms are already widely used in medicine, formally and informally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if you have atrial fibrillation, we can use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chadsvasc.org/&quot;&gt;CHADS-VASC atrial fibrillation risk score calculator&lt;/a&gt; to estimate your risk of developing a stroke and therefore guide preventative treatment; should you be given anticoagulation, or not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How has such a scoring system been accepted and adopted in healthcare?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This score has been in development over many years, with multiple iterations. Initial calculators such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/193912&quot;&gt;CHADS2 being published back in 2001&lt;/a&gt; were created by pooling data from 1733 patients with a total of 2121 patient-years of follow-up and have subsequent been refined and validated in different cohorts of patients and adapted as a result of new advances such as the availability of novel anticoagulants that do not need close monitoring. An example of how iterative changes were made in this particular risk algorithm has been documented by &lt;a href=&quot;https://academic.oup.com/eurheartj/advance-article-pdf/doi/10.1093/eurheartj/ehv431/10800295/ehv431.pdf&quot;&gt;Professor Lip from the University of Birmingham&lt;/a&gt;, emphasising the importance of ongoing validation and improvement with larger data sets and more representative population samples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of risk score can be generated by examining baseline characteristics and building a statistical model, such as Cox proportional hazards, to identify whether each characteristic has an effect on the outcome measure; such models also tell us the magnitude of that effect. Typically in conventional statistical methodology, the choice of which characteristics to examine is made by the investigators based on existing knowledge about the outcome in question; the approach is hypothesis-driven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We use the magnitude of effect on outcome to generate a meaningful scoring system which can subsequently be validated as a prediction tool in a particular population. In essence, we predict an endpoint, in this case an outcome, with the presence or absence of characteristics, with information, known at the time of a decision in that population; validation in one population does not mean that an algorithm is appropriate in another. This prediction will itself be uncertain, with the model able to provide prediction of outcome with some degree of confidence; a 95% confidence interval means that we can be 95% certain that our prediction is within the range specified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adoption of clinical decision tools therefore result from rigorous process of academic work and &lt;em&gt;ongoing&lt;/em&gt; development and validation but is anything more needed?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, adoption of clinical algorithms is also the consequence of a more informal set of processes and cultures that influence whether a tool gains sufficient traction within the wider community. Similarly, even if a tool is widely adopted, the use of the algorithm and any decision made as a result of that algorithm, in any individual clinical scenario, is usually at the discretion of the professional at the time; if it is used then it is used to attempt to reduce the uncertainty about a clinical decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we already use algorithms&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;algorithms become part of clinical practice after going through a set of formal and informal processes, with use dependent on culture, values and perceptions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ongoing monitoring and validation is required in order to safely apply an algorithm in a specific population.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;validation of algorithms is currently time-consuming and usually a once-off project, sometimes repeated at intervals. For example, in validating techniques to prevent stroke, there has been dedicated data collection of outcome data, such as whether the patient has had a stroke or not, usually as part of a registry study, because such data is not collected in a meaningful fashion in routine clinical practice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;heuristics-in-healthcare&quot;&gt;Heuristics in healthcare&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also use a range of heuristics, sets of informal rules, in our day-to-day clinical work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started as a pre-registration house officer on the neurology ward in 1999, I quickly learned that patients with neuropathy almost certainly have a condition called chronic inflammatory demyelinating polyneuropathy (CIDP), based on my “experience”. Almost every patient I saw with those symptoms had this condition, and my diagnostic sleuthing was calibrated based on this experience. I had quickly and unconsciously developed a heuristic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Except I was wrong; my calibration was broken because patients with CIDP were the ones who were brought to the ward for their intravenous immunoglobulins and so they were the only patients with neuropathy I saw!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s not to say that heuristics are not useful; indeed, heuristics are short-cuts that permit decision making at times of extreme uncertainty, frequently learnt by formal and informal teaching together with experience. For example, a heuristic might be used to take the right action if a life-threatening illness is simply a possibility, even if improbable. In many situations, we chain heuristics together, so that we don’t aim to make a diagnosis in a single cognitive step but instead using a chain of multiple, adaptive heuristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I might think you have migraine, but you are 65 years old and your headaches are waking you at night and I proceed to arrange a brain scan. From a purely Bayesian point-of-view, the probability of you having a brain tumour is low; this &lt;em&gt;a priori&lt;/em&gt; probability is a consequence of dealing with rarer disorders. My use of &lt;em&gt;red flags&lt;/em&gt;, a set of heuristics that, we hope, prompt me to arrange an investigation to reduce the uncertainty in diagnosis in any individual patient, will result in lots of normal scans in the patients that I see. I accept a high rate of negative scans to increase my own sensitivity in identifying a patient with a serious underlying neurological disease; missing such a diagnosis has grave implications for the patient and I endeavour to calibrate my assessment to minimise the possibility, for that specific issue in that specific context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might think that heuristics used in clinical practice have been validated in the same way as any other decision aid, but frequently, there is very little data on the positive or negative predictive value of such tools. In addition, humans are subject to a range of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_bias&quot;&gt;cognitive biases&lt;/a&gt; (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Thinking-Fast-Slow-Daniel-Kahneman/dp/0141033576/ref=sr_1_2?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1513438649&amp;amp;sr=8-2&amp;amp;keywords=cognitive+biases&quot;&gt;“Thinking fast and slow” by Prof. Daniel Kahneman&lt;/a&gt;) which results in failures of our heuristics. For example, in confirmation bias, we may place greater emphasis on new information if it confirms a pre-existing belief or conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;By Jm3 (Own work) [CC BY-SA 4.0 (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0)], via Wikimedia Commons&quot; href=&quot;https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3AThe_Cognitive_Bias_Codex_-_180%2B_biases%2C_designed_by_John_Manoogian_III_(jm3).png&quot;&gt;&lt;img width=&quot;512&quot; alt=&quot;The Cognitive Bias Codex - 180+ biases, designed by John Manoogian III (jm3)&quot; src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/a/a4/The_Cognitive_Bias_Codex_-_180%2B_biases%2C_designed_by_John_Manoogian_III_%28jm3%29.png/512px-The_Cognitive_Bias_Codex_-_180%2B_biases%2C_designed_by_John_Manoogian_III_%28jm3%29.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;humans use heuristics to help them make decisions, particularly at times of high uncertainty&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;humans are prone to a range of biases which result in mistaken decisions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we will benefit from understanding more about our own decision-making and improving the heuristics we use in daily clinical work; many of our own heuristics would benefit from further evaluation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;specific heuristics are useful, even if of low predictive value, if they increase sensitivity to identify life-threatening illness, in specific clinical contexts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;becoming-data-driven&quot;&gt;Becoming data-driven&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decision-making in healthcare, whether by human or machine, whether for making a decision or evaluating a prior decision, needs clinically meaningful &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What kinds of health data do we have?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;data used for administration, e.g. hospital administrative data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;data for individual clinical care (traditionally paper based), e.g. medical records&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;data used for quality improvement and assessment of interventions in real-life environments, e.g. data acquired during specific clinical audit or service improvement projects&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;data used for for specific clinical research&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;data from the patient, either directly or via their own smart devices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These data are usually separated in silos. It is uncommon for research studies to make use of real-life clinical data and similarly, research data is not usually made available for routine direct care purposes. Similarly, how can we evaluate quality-of-life data without understanding a patient’s long-term health conditions or surgical procedures?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, each type of data is, itself, highly fragmented. For example, data from one research project are held separately to those from another, and even data for direct clinical care usually collected and stored on a per-organisation basis, shared in only a limited fashion, if at all, between organisations providing care for a single patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problems are compounded by the fact that data relating to direct care is frequently paper-based. That’s why most hospitals cannot tell you how many patients with, for example, motor neurone disease , their teams look after or indeed their outcomes, without a project to specifically look at answering those questions for a set period of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when healthcare professionals use electronic means of capturing information, such as electronic health record software, much of that information is not recorded in a way that makes it easily usable, neither by human nor machine, because it is unstructured or, at best, semi-structured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many users, those electronic health record systems are essentially monolithic so that user interface code, business logic and backend data storage is proprietary and must be integrated with other systems to achieve interoperability. When such systems need to be replaced, data must be migrated from the old to the new. We now recognise the benefits of separating data and its structure from the software code that operates upon that data; in healthcare, our data and its structure should be domain-driven given the complex, adaptive environment in which we work and our code can be stateless and often lightweight and ephemeral, particularly those components which are user-facing and most subject to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we need clinically meaningful data to be recorded and used to support a range of purposes, including: clinical decision making for the care of individual patients, managing our services, quality improvement and clinical research.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;as we capture clinically meaningful data during many different processes and for many different purposes, we must routinely aggregate information of different types, from different sources.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we need open data standards to build a complete holistic, aggregated &lt;em&gt;view&lt;/em&gt; of an individual patient or service; much information is not interpretable without understanding information from elsewhere or from different processes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we need semantic interoperability so that we can exchange and combine information from multiple sources.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we need to move away from procuring ‘full-stack’ applications that combine user interface code, business logic and data storage and move to lightweight, ephemeral user-facing applications each providing different perspectives on the same logical, structured healthcare record.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;as a result, we need to consider the benefit of an open platform, made up of open-source implementations of open standards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;evaluation-and-closed-feedback-loops&quot;&gt;Evaluation and closed feedback loops&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to consider multiple ways to evaluate our decisions, whether those decisions were made by human or machine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For human students, we now use simulation at medical schools to help perform and learn in a safe, controlled environment; our human students are exposed to synthetic and real data in order to learn. In my role in assessments for the undergraduate medical course in Cardiff, I helped build a large multiple choice question bank so that we could implement continuous assessment, guiding learning through assessments and feedback on performance at multiple times during the academic year. Our human education has focused on creating a feedback loop in order to help learners improve. Contrived data are useful in testing that a clinician is &lt;em&gt;safe&lt;/em&gt;; we might issue a “yellow card” to a student missing a classic presentation of septicaemia in an examination and that student might fail, even if their overall score is in the pass range.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In pharmaceutical drug development, sequential processes are used ranging from drug discovery, preclinical and clinical research, review and post-marketing surveillance. Each step examines the potential or actual efficacy of a drug; initially in models, then in control subjects, then in selected patients and then in real-life clinical environments. Each step makes use of different approaches and provides different insights into the performance of that drug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In clinical research, such as a &lt;em&gt;randomised controlled trial&lt;/em&gt;, we attempt to avoid biases; for example, if we only evaluate an intervention, such as a new drug, in real-life clinical practice, we would fail to control for clinicians inadvertently giving a new treatment only to a most healthy subset of patients. A controlled trial means that we control for spurious differences between a population that receives an intervention and a population that doesn’t, and ensure we remove as many biases as possible in our assessment of that intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The results of randomised controlled trials are usually considered highly generalisable to other populations; however we recognise that this is often not the case when trials exclude patients with, for example, multiple co-morbidities or have failed to recruit patients at the extremes of age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, changes in the way that we deliver care are difficult to evaluate as part of a randomised controlled trial; instead we might adopt an approach of &lt;em&gt;quality improvement&lt;/em&gt;. We use these type of methodologies when what we are studying is subject to considerable local variation such as differing local organisational structures; our learning may not necessarily be as generalisable as a randomised controlled trial.  Conversely this type of study may provide valuable information about how an intervention performs in the real world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a range of quality improvement methodologies that act to iteratively define, measure, analyse, improve and control; a common feature of all is a cycle of measurement and intervention to examine and improve process and outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthcare, as yet, has failed to use technology to transform the way randomised trials and quality improvement are delivered. In modern technology companies, thousands of small randomised trials can be performed every day with closed feedback loops providing rapid assessment of outcome. For example, Google have embedded randomised trials into their software development pipeline, making it possible to run simple trials to assess the effect of changing, for example, font colour, on click-through rates by users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Routinely collected health data and randomised trials are dependent on a high-quality infrastructure which can collect clinically meaningful data and help to randomise, at any point of clinical equipoise, an individual into a trial of one intervention over another as well as streamlining the process of trial design and ethical approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;underpinning all approaches to evaluation is the collection and analysis of meaningful data, linking eventual outcome to the data known at the time of a decision; in essence, evaluation of any decision is predicated on a closed feedback loop.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;synthetic data is valuable in many circumstances, particularly for beginners.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;randomised controlled trials assess an intervention in a defined group, such as a specific cohort of patients and attempts to control for biases; they may be controlled with a placebo or the best current intervention. Modern trials are frequently complex, expensive and time-consuming and are difficult to run for any complex intervention and usually have very limited follow-up.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;quality improvement approaches assess interventions in real-life contexts but are subject to inherent biases.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we currently lack a cohesive technical infrastructure that supports the definition, collection and analysis of meaningful, structured clinical data. Likewise, we lack tools to streamline and support the processes needed to undertake randomised trials in humans including design, ethical approval and the day-to-day identification, recruitment, consent and randomisation.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;all clinicians will tell you that we face thousands of situations of clinical equipoise every day, a decision needs to be made in which one choice is no known to be better than another; we must endeavour to build an infrastructure that supports the systematic recruitment of patients into clinical trials as a matter of routine. We are seeing the start of this in oncology.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;such an infrastructure would support our current need for quality improvement and research, but also would support the use of systematic algorithmic decision support in clinical care to shape its development, its evaluation and ongoing post-marketing surveillance of safety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;and-so-what&quot;&gt;And so what?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I truly believe that software and data are of vital importance to the future of healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need, as professionals and as patients, to have the right information at the right time, in order for us to develop a shared understanding and make the right decisions in any given context. We use data to reduce the uncertainty about our decisions and we need the right tools to create and make sense of those data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Machine learning is an exciting and continuously-evolving field. I would argue that many of the changes we need to make in order to support the routine development, deployment, evaluation and monitoring of advanced algorithms in healthcare are the same ones that we need to use, right now, for our routine clinical practice. Whether our decisions are made by human or machine, or more likely a combination of both, whether those decisions are for an individual patient and for whole groups of our patients as part of developing our health services, understanding and assessing those decisions by the routine and systematic collection of meaningful data is vital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can start to understand what we need to do to achieve this by creating a &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/wardleymaps&quot;&gt;Wardley map&lt;/a&gt;. We can start to build a map by thinking about a &lt;em&gt;value chain&lt;/em&gt;, in which we start with user need and try to understand the dependencies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ai-healthcare/ai-healthcare--part1.png&quot; alt=&quot;AI Healthcare value chain&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see that, to provide algorithmic decision support for patients and professionals, we need to consider&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;machine learning expertise&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clinically meaningful data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;trust - by the public and professionals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have, for each of those, shown what I consider to be the dependencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can plot our value chain on a map, with the horizontal axis giving an indication as to whether that dependency is already available as a commodity, as a product to be bought or rented, as something we are developing or as something that is in its infancy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ai-healthcare/ai-healthcare--part2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ai Healthcare  Part2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, here we see that public and professional trust is dependent on professional and public engagement as well as an evaluation pipeline that creates a continuously monitored feedback loop driven by data. Their location on the map shows that we are only just starting to work on engaging the public on the use of data, while adopting randomised trials and quality improvement such as six sigma in healthcare is more mature but not yet a commodity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can add more information. Here, I’ve highlighted whether healthcare organisations or technology companies can provide one of the dependencies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ai-healthcare/ai-healthcare--part3.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ai Healthcare  Part3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we see that machine learning expertise from technology companies must be combined with data expertise from healthcare organisations in order to successfully deliver algorithmic decision support in healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we can use our map to work out what we need to do in order to deliver the vision, incorporating an indication of evolution over time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ai-healthcare/ai-healthcare.png&quot; alt=&quot;Ai Healthcare&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can conclude from our map that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clinically meaningful data is dependent on ongoing work to adopt open standards, and those standards are themselves dependent on an open-source toolchain that makes it easy to implement those open standards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;aggregation of data from multiple sources is dependent on a scheme of data control and consent, so that citizens can opt-out and opt-in to share data for different purposes. This control and consent, I would argue, is also dependent on readily-available open source solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;continued professional and public engagement will result in an increasing recognition of the value of data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;semantic interoperability, itself dependent on open standards, will result in the creation of routinely aggregated interoperable health records&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;trust is dependent on engagement and building an evaluation pipeline supporting development, testing, deployment and real-life evaluation using a variety of processes, themselves supported by an enabling infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, if we want to revolutionise the use of technology in healthcare, we must become data-driven, and to do that, we need to create a suite of, likely open-source, tools that support the implementation of open standards, of consent and of quality improvement/research within day-to-day clinical practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I want to convince you that our use of machine learning in healthcare, building algorithms that learn for themselves, depends on:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Consent-driven distributed master patient index 1/2</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/07/25/empi-internet.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Consent-driven distributed master patient index 1/2" /><published>2018-07-25T22:21:21+01:00</published><updated>2018-07-25T22:21:21+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/07/25/empi-internet</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/07/25/empi-internet.html">&lt;p&gt;I would like to introduce the concept of a consent-driven distributed master patient index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many healthcare organisations already use  master patient index  software in order to try to integrate multiple disparate applications but my suggestion is that we update this concept for the Internet-era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, we need to build a distributed and open system in order to provide resource location and authorisation services, driven by consent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Existing enterprise master patient indices (EMPIs) provide matching and linkage across systems within an enterprise.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are already seeing a move to open platforms underpinned by modern information and technical standards.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We will need to federate data from multiple providers to create a consolidated health record for an individual citizen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Such federation across platforms will require functionality to support resource location, so that the consolidated view includes information from any healthcare providers involved in that citizen’s care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That consolidated view may not need to contain personally-identifiable information for many purposes but even when de-identified or aggregated, it is possible to re-identity individuals. There is a identifiability continuum with re-identification risk proportionate to the number of different types of health and care data that form the consolidated view.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Citizens need appropriate tools and support in order to make their data sharing wishes clear and will need to be able to make their preferences clear for a range of different purposes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To solve this, I suggest that we need a &lt;em&gt;consent-driven distributed master patient index&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-the-enterprise-master-patient-index-empi&quot;&gt;1. The enterprise master patient index (EMPI)&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An enterprise master patient index (EMPI) acts as a consistent up-to-date registry of patient information across multiple systems, allowing matching and linkage across those systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design of such a system derives from a historic use of individual healthcare applications that maintain their own patient indexes and need to be integrated with others. Those applications would usually store their own indexes in their own closed, proprietary backend storing the individual patient data against a local case record number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An EMPI acts to link these disparate applications by matching patient demographics and as a result, can  derive a list of identifiers for any given patient in any of the applications across an enterprise. EMPI products, such as IBM’s Initiate, generally use HL7 v2 messaging in order to provide lookup and matching services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-platforms-and-commoditisation&quot;&gt;2. Platforms and commoditisation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I truly believe that we are at the cusp of a revolution in healthcare information technology in which we will adopt Internet-era thinking and technology to support the transformation of healthcare. This transformation will permit a renewed focus on the needs of individual citizens and their caregivers, and how our services are designed to meet those needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest changes will be the spread of open platforms providing multiple components with standards-based application programming interfaces. Initially, these components will be part of a wider organisation-centric electronic health record system (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.cerner.com/&quot;&gt;https://code.cerner.com/&lt;/a&gt;), but, we will quickly see many components becoming commoditised and provided via cloud-based platforms (e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/genomics/&quot;&gt;https://cloud.google.com/genomics/&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This scenario playing out is shown in this Wardley map:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mapping/maps-system-future-future-simple-map.png&quot; alt=&quot;Maps System Future Future Simple Map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must recognise that several components of this architecture already have well-established solutions and are best bought or rented but that other components are, as yet, unknown and need more work in order to understand the best way to design, build and deploy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we still have procured and installed locally software like radiology systems (Picture Archiving and Communication System - PACS) but even some of those could be provided as a service instead. For example, in Aneurin Bevan Health Board, they are using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drdoctor.co.uk/&quot;&gt;DrDoctor services&lt;/a&gt; for patient communication prior to outpatient clinic visits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In parallel with this modularisation will be the move towards separating application code and logic from the data and its representations. As a result, we will have a new marketplace of new components will appear providing discrete computing services on-demand, making use of open data standards and readily available open-source tools to implement those standards. For example, could discrete computing functionality be provided to perform monitoring for acute kidney injury (AKI), currently using the state-of-the-art national AKI guidance? Similarly, could such an architecture permit the parallel testing and evaluation of &lt;em&gt;new&lt;/em&gt; implementations of AKI detection before more widespread adoption?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, it is likely that the data and the application code (logic) will separate and themselves distributed as a &lt;em&gt;modular&lt;/em&gt; architecture founded on open standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-federation-and-caching&quot;&gt;3. Federation and caching&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Federation is the process in which we can build a unified single view of data from across multiple distributed information systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a federation service might take a request for information about a patient, decompose that query across multiple source systems and return a unified composite view. Federation may combine the same or different types of data from multiple systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Federation might simply directly pass on a query to multiple source systems at the time of the request; such an approach might be fine if each source system has predictably high levels of performance. Alternatively, it may instead implement a vendor-neutral archive updated from multiple source systems as they themselves are updated, providing a performant cache of information updated from source systems. Indeed, one might implement federation as a combination of both; in essence, federation provides a consolidated view across multiple systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;4-resource-location&quot;&gt;4. Resource location&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Federation is dependent on appropriately locating resources for patients across a range of providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2018/01/apple-announces-effortless-solution-bringing-health-records-to-iPhone/&quot;&gt;built a federated health records service&lt;/a&gt; to iOS via the Health app and associated &lt;a href=&quot;https://developer.apple.com/documentation/healthkit/health_and_fitness_samples/accessing_health_records&quot;&gt;application programming interfaces&lt;/a&gt;. This now provides a consolidated view of data from multiple healthcare providers in the United States, making use of the increasing available of data via &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/&quot;&gt;HL7 FHIR&lt;/a&gt;. To do this, health providers must specifically &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/healthcare/&quot;&gt;link with Apple&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google DeepMind built a &lt;a href=&quot;https://deepmind.com/applied/deepmind-health/working-partners/how-were-helping-today/&quot;&gt;federated records service&lt;/a&gt; to support their Streams app, providing a consolidated view of legacy data held within one organisation but across multiple sites and multiple software products. Those data populated, via &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.hl7.org/implement/standards/product_brief.cfm?product_id=185&quot;&gt;HL7 V2&lt;/a&gt;, are stored in a modern archive for performance reasons and made available via HL7 FHIR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both, I understand that resource location is centrally managed, requiring registration or bespoke integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any distributed system needs to be able to offer accurate and performant resource location, much as the domain name service (DNS) for the internet provides distributed conversion of user friendly domain names into numeric addresses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;5-privacy-and-identifiable-data&quot;&gt;5. Privacy and identifiable data&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many situations, such as providing direct-care such as an outpatient clinic, professionals benefit from being able to access identifiable up-to-date information. In other situations, such as when we are planning services to meet the needs of a population, it is sufficient to simply process de-identified information. Using the least identifiable information for any given given purpose is a core principle of sound data governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://understandingpatientdata.org.uk/sites/default/files/2017-07/Identifiability%20briefing%205%20April.pdf&quot;&gt;spectrum of identifiability&lt;/a&gt; with fully identifiable data at one extreme and aggregated statistics about a populations of patients at the other. With aggregate statistics, re-identification is much more difficult, but is possible when numbers of individuals with a set of characteristics are small. With de-identified patient-level data, re-identification is possible and becomes increasingly possible proportional to the quantity of linked data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, you could not re-identify an individual if all you knew was that they were a &lt;em&gt;neurologist&lt;/em&gt;. If you knew they lived in &lt;em&gt;Wales&lt;/em&gt;, then you can narrow down the possibilities. A neurologist, from Wales interested in &lt;em&gt;information technology&lt;/em&gt;. You’ve re-identified me. Probably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way of trying to de-identify information is to simply replace all personally-identifiable information with a pseudonym, a random identifier. However, if all data on an individual is given the same identifier, the re-identification risk is higher than if only a single type of data is available. As such, we can augment de-identification by splitting data and giving each split a different identifier and permitting the creation of a dynamic consolidated view of data across multiple systems using multiple identifiers by virtue of a variable degree of linkage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Google Maps will track route journeys for traffic analysis, but reduces the privacy impact by splitting up the journey into smaller sections, each with a different identifier. Your progress during those sections is recorded to help others, but no-one is able to recombine those data to find out from where you travelled. Anonymisation occurs because there is no linkage from your identifiable information (your account details) and the traffic identifiers. If Google kept a record of your account and the identifiers used to track your journeys, then conceivably your journey could be recreated and your data has only be de-identified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, it is possible to further limit the risk of re-identification by deliberately adding &lt;em&gt;noise&lt;/em&gt; into datasets so that aggregate statistical analyses give the same results as the original source data; such an approach is called &lt;em&gt;differential privacy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we can work to protect privacy by both controlling the &lt;em&gt;linkage&lt;/em&gt; of data from different sources as well as deliberately adding &lt;em&gt;noise&lt;/em&gt; into data when aggregated and shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;6-consent-and-health-data&quot;&gt;6. Consent and health data&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health data have three broad purposes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for direct care of an individual patient&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for supporting and running services by aggregating individual-level data at the level of an organisation, service or cohort in order to monitor and improve services for those patients&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;for supporting research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are more detailed examples at &lt;a href=&quot;https://understandingpatientdata.org.uk/why&quot;&gt;https://understandingpatientdata.org.uk/why&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all health data are the same. For example, information relating to sexual health, termination of pregnancy, genetics, mental health, substance abuse, employment issues and stigmatising social data may, at the discretion of an individual, be considered quite differently from other health data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pharmaceutical companies and clinicians are interested in assessing the real-world outcomes of their treatments and projects like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.herc.ox.ac.uk/downloads/health_datasets/browse-data-sets/general-practice-research-database-gprd&quot;&gt;Clinical Practice Research Datalink (CPRD)&lt;/a&gt; demonstrate the usefulness of this post-marketing surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consent may be opt-in or opt-out and given implicitly or explicitly. When you sign up to a clinical research project, you must opt-in. When you don’t want your health data shared for secondary uses in NHS England, you can opt-out. When you attend a hospital and extend your arm in order to let someone take your blood, you have given &lt;em&gt;implicit&lt;/em&gt; consent. When you sign a consent form for your appendicectomy, you give &lt;em&gt;explicit&lt;/em&gt; consent. When you attend hospital unconscious and we work to treat you, we are working in your &lt;em&gt;best interests&lt;/em&gt;. When your advance decision to refuse treatment (ADRT) states that you do not want cardiopulmonary resuscitation, to perform that act would be an act of assault.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NHS England care.data project was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bmj.com/content/354/bmj.i3907&quot;&gt;halted in the face of widespread public criticism and loss of trust&lt;/a&gt;, despite the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bmj.com/content/354/bmj.i3852&quot;&gt;potential benefits&lt;/a&gt; for population health and clinical research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the outcomes of the debacle was a renewed focus on &lt;em&gt;building trust&lt;/em&gt; and obtaining &lt;em&gt;consent&lt;/em&gt;. As a result, we must work to ensure that we organise health information to make it accessible subject to &lt;em&gt;consent&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;control&lt;/em&gt; by the individual or their representative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-follows&quot;&gt;So what follows?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, I have argued that we need a distributed equivalent of a master patient index designed for the Internet-era and driven by consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This index needs, itself, to be distributed and federated, and yet designed to protect privacy. My next blog post in this series touches on some of the potential technical standards and services required to support such a system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS My previous posts on &lt;a href=&quot;/information-governance/2017/04/08/pseudonymous-consent.html&quot;&gt;pseudonymous consent&lt;/a&gt; and associated code were an experiment solving some of the issues that I’ve finally got around to documenting here.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I would like to introduce the concept of a consent-driven distributed master patient index.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Healthcare information technology strategy</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/07/19/mapping.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Healthcare information technology strategy" /><published>2018-07-19T20:19:19+01:00</published><updated>2018-07-19T20:19:19+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/07/19/mapping</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/07/19/mapping.html">&lt;p&gt;How can we make best use of technology to support healthcare?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we plan a coherent strategy that delivers, with pace, safety and reliability, solutions to the problems we face now while being adaptable enough to adapt to what is likely to come in the future?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to discuss &lt;em&gt;strategy&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While written for NHS Wales, I hope this has a broader appeal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-we-need-information-technology-for-health-and-care&quot;&gt;1. We need information technology for health and care&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health and social care are complex adaptive environments made up of many interdependent parts. They are usually the responsibility of multiple different organisations but ideally, they should all work in a &lt;em&gt;coordinated&lt;/em&gt; way to support us all, the citizen in our health and care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I truly believe that software is critical to the future of healthcare, in supporting both patients and health professionals in their respective roles. Current software usually does little but replace existing paper processes but we should be aiming to use software to transform our health services.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;My blog post, May 2018 &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;The value of software for healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information technology should be the foundation on which our health and care services run. We need to apply deep knowledge of the data, the systems and processes that are involved in those services in order to effectively design and build information technology services to underpin our efforts to support and improve health and social care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So much of the routine and systematic processes of care, quality improvement and research could be enhanced by the appropriate use of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many industries, digital &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the way that they now conduct their business. Digital technology offers scope to transform our services by making them safer, more efficient and better &lt;em&gt;learning systems&lt;/em&gt; by making our work &lt;em&gt;data-driven&lt;/em&gt;, whether for direct care of an individual patient, caring for groups of patients or working to research better ways of providing care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must stop thinking of information technology as a goal in itself and instead see it as a &lt;em&gt;tool&lt;/em&gt; to support our wider ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-we-need-a-cohesive-strategy&quot;&gt;2. We need a cohesive strategy&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Richard Rumelt, a strategy has three core parts that he calls the “kernel”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we must define the challenge&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we must have a guiding policy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we must have coherent action&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decisions we make are about &lt;em&gt;what&lt;/em&gt; to do, the broad principles as to &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; to do them and then ruthlessly acting to &lt;em&gt;deliver&lt;/em&gt;, each action coordinated and building upon others iteratively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must delicately balance top-down centralisation and standardisation with bottom-up local need and innovation. As such, we must define a set of enduring broad guiding principles about &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; we will solve problems, likely mandated or recommended across our enterprise while permitting adaptable coherent action at a more local level to solve local problems while not running counter to the overall direction. A guiding policy “directs and constrains action without fully defining its content.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to stubbornly defend and enforce our guiding policies but be flexible and adaptable on the actions that we take to meet our challenges. This is why my first action, as chair of the NHS Wales Technical Standards Board was to propose to our group that we adopt the GDS design principles; we agreed this in our June 2018 meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-components-and-modularisation&quot;&gt;3. Components and modularisation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must recognise that different parts of our enterprise are not all the same and so it helps to break up our problems into smaller problems which can be solved independently from the whole. Likewise, we can see that those components can change at different rates depending on user needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking up monolithic architectures and applications into components requires skill and experience but is an important part of improving reliability, testability and delivery across an enterprise. When components are tightly coupled then it becomes increasingly difficult to make changes, not only because changes have unpredictable side-effects but because teams need to constantly check with others in order to make progress. I have given a specific example in the footnotes.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#wcrs&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you break up our healthcare enterprise in Wales, we can see three broad categories of component:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some have already well-established solutions and need to focus on operational efficiency, metrics and analytics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some have to take what has been proven to work and improve and scale those solutions in order to deliver working products that are safe and reliable&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;some have to take user need and experiment and explore the best way of solving those needs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will recognise these three categories as Simon Wardley’s “Town planners”, “Settlers” and “Pioneers”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our healthcare information technology strategy must explicitly recognise &lt;em&gt;change&lt;/em&gt; and adaptability. One insight, from a healthcare perspective, is that different things change at different speeds and that, given the legal and regulatory aspects of our work in healthcare, data are the bedrock from which we can build. Those data should be structured and clinically meaningful. Conversely, we should regard the tools (applications) with which we interact with those data as much more ephemeral and driven by clinical and business workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A portal-centric approach has, in my opinion, created years of technical debt. We must work immediately to stop this approach and instead build an &lt;em&gt;open, standards-based platform&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;4-lets-map&quot;&gt;4. Let’s map&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;value-stream&lt;/em&gt; is a flow-chart helpful in illustrating, analysing and improving our &lt;em&gt;delivery&lt;/em&gt; of solutions to problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what we have in Wales:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mapping/maps-system-current-value-chain.png&quot; alt=&quot;Maps System Current Value Chain&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vertical axis gives a broad indication of &lt;em&gt;visibility&lt;/em&gt;, reflecting that users have needs and that they are supported by visible components of our architecture which themselves are supported by less visible pieces of infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks a bit complicated doesn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the top of the value chain, we have our users and some of their needs. The important points are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patients and caregivers are considered as well as professionals, reflecting our focus on the citizen and their interactions with health services. We should see digital as a way of transforming health services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The list of user needs is incomplete but I hope illustrative and useful as-is.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There are already items of user need from this limited list not met by the architecture as-is, particularly in relation to patients and their caregivers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Trying to integrate multiple applications each with their own storage and structure of data is &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; complicated and the complexity increases exponentially when we want to add new functionality.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I have omitted many important projects such as the Welsh Cancer system, CANISC.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I haven’t even included newer projects like e-Observations and flow, recording pulse, blood pressure etc. on mobile devices to identify the deteriorating patient - functionality of high benefit to patients and professionals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I haven’t included the interoperability need with other enterprises, such as cross-border transfers of care with England (particularly important for North Wales and specialist services) or social care.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patients and caregivers have extremely limited functionality presently; they can use a product called “My Health Online” which has failed to gain traction and there is pilot of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.patientsknowbest.com/&quot;&gt;PatientsKnowBest&lt;/a&gt; in Abertawe Bro Morgannwg. Renal patients can also see their own results via &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.patientview.org/#/&quot;&gt;PatientView&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of the complexity seems inherent in healthcare, in which there has traditionally been a cycle of procurement of “systems” or “products” which must be integrated into the wider enterprise. Fortunately, we can make decisions now that can mitigate this complexity. We should always aim for simplicity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have multiple local health boards, multiple patient administrative systems (PAS), most of which use the same product but are configured differently and do not support cross-PAS workflows, and multiple instances of a single “portal” (WCP) which are linked to the local PAS so show administrative data only from that health board. This means it is possible for me to login to WCP, a national product, in Cardiff and see that a patient is alive, and at the same time login to the same application in Cwm Taf and see that a patient has died. Similarly, as I sat in clinic yesterday, I could see a list of upcoming appointments for Cwm Taf only, and not for any other health board. We &lt;em&gt;do not&lt;/em&gt; have a single patient record but instead multiple instances of multiple applications giving different views of different data. In short, we have a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;5-evolution&quot;&gt;5. Evolution&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can help ourselves understand our architecture by adding an “evolution” dimension to our value chain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mapping/maps-system-current-map.png&quot; alt=&quot;Maps System Current Map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The horizontal axis is a broad indication of the level of &lt;em&gt;evolution&lt;/em&gt; of a component. If you are unfamiliar with Wardley mapping, then I suggest you read &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/wardleymaps&quot;&gt;Simon Wardley’s mapping book&lt;/a&gt;. I am a novice at this - these are my first maps and would value your comments. Power is a commodity; it is fungible - it doesn’t matter &lt;em&gt;who&lt;/em&gt; provides electricity. The laboratory information management software (LIMS) from Intersystems is a product, bought off-the-shelf and integrated with the wider enterprise via another off-the-shelf product, the enterprise service bus providing a messaging fabric. Custom-built software and components such as our data centres&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now see that we are using several off-the-shelf components - such as GP systems, emergency unit systems, laboratory systems etc. in conjunction with several custom-built applications and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefit of this type of map is that it helps us understand the options available to us. It also forces us to reconsider our architectural decisions and start to think about whether we have actually made the right decisions about the type of components we use. I think it is obvious from this map that focusing on products and projects is creating technical debt and making it more difficult to deliver solutions to end-users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, we see that we are building in-house some components that, with a basic knowledge of the commercial market, we could instead buy off-the-shelf. Can we justify, for example, running two data centres and building custom software that is already available elsewhere?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some in Wales who think that it is right to adopt a “portal” based approach, but this map clearly shows how that approach is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The map shows how professionals already use multiple software applications; we know the current  portal cannot replace that functionality in any timely fashion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The map shows the difficulties inherent in trying to integrate multiple applications without an underlying &lt;em&gt;single patient record&lt;/em&gt;. Many of the reliability and data inconsistency problems result from a lack of focus on that record&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There has been a historic focus on bespoke point-to-point integration with proprietary APIs that then become difficult to manage and impossible to change for fear of breaking another integration somewhere else.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We are spending time and resources on developing the things that others can do, and failing to build the things only Wales can build.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Our portal is a single code-base providing user-facing functionality (user interface), business logic and tightly-coupled bespoke interfaces to services that are usually not made available to any other application. This fails to recognise that different components can be developed at different speeds with different methodologies.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instead, we need to understand that different components are subject to different rules - so that components on the left of our diagram should be built in an agile-way, with rapid iterations and significant user engagement. Components to the right are commodities or components with well developed solutions that can be bought or rented. When a component can be provided as a commodity, we should &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be developing it in-house without very good reason. Our architecture needs to reflect these differences. As such, it makes more sense to create a portal using components of a wider platform than a monolithic application.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;adapting-to-change&quot;&gt;Adapting to change&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These maps also help us to understand how we are positioned to take advantage of new innovation and changing need. For example, we increasingly see adoption of cloud-computing, in which data centres become a commodity onto which computing power can be provided. We see an increasing marketplace of cloud-based functions, software code run on demand usually on a pay-as-you-go model, providing both core and specialist computing functionality such as data storage, speech-to-text and text-to-speech services, translation services etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I predict a marketplace of discrete computing services tailored for healthcare provision. Such services will make use of open industry standards to decouple code from the data on which they operate and offer increasingly valuable functionality such as clinical decision support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, patients and caregivers now expect to be able to interact with their health and care services by using technology. Part of digital inclusion is ensuring that multiple channels of interaction are possible, designed to suit different people. We see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2018/01/apple-announces-effortless-solution-bringing-health-records-to-iPhone/&quot;&gt;Apple rapidly bringing clinical data&lt;/a&gt; from multiple hospital sites in the United States to patient’s own devices via their Health app and the use of HL7 FHIR standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we can see that we will be wanting to evaluate and make use of machine learning within our healthcare systems very soon. We need to build systems that permit the safe deployment and evaluation of such systems and a much of that work will involve plumbing together data pipelines safely and securely, subject to patient consent and an option to opt-out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can we add all of these to our map?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mapping/maps-system-future-broken-map.png&quot; alt=&quot;Maps System Future Broken Map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the architecture lacks a cohesive design requiring multiple bespoke end-to-end integrations between systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;think-of-functional-services-not-products&quot;&gt;Think of functional services not products&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should instead be thinking of discrete, functional logical services which can be built and run independently or semi-independently that, together form part a &lt;em&gt;platform&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our core design principles is to &lt;em&gt;do the hard work to make things easy&lt;/em&gt;. This means rethinking our map. It is still complicated, but our user-facing applications like mobile applications and a modern rewritten portal can be developed in an agile way while using platform components that are either a built in-house,  bought or rented or, over time, a commodity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, we don’t expect client applications to understand the nuances of our local enterprise architecture, but instead provide a managed API gateway, offering simplifying access to a &lt;em&gt;logical single patient record&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mapping/maps-system-future-logical-map.png&quot; alt=&quot;Maps System Future Logical Map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, one can see that many of these components will increasingly become a commodity. I’ve shown this with the “data repositories” component, which spans the “product” and “commodity” evolutionary sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;6-delivery&quot;&gt;6. Delivery&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work informs our work on the technical standards we need to prioritise in order to deliver a modern, open, standards-based platform for Wales providing a single patient record for use by a &lt;em&gt;variety&lt;/em&gt; of user-facing applications. Such applications may be a commodity or custom-built but are ephemeral and lightweight, with business logic delegated to the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we need to reconfigure the way we work in Wales and create:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an applications group who have responsibility for delivering lightweight applications to solve user need. These teams should work in an agile-fashion and share code and frameworks, releasing their work as open-source, building libraries and components that, together with the open platform, provide a toolbox of functionality for building the next generation of healthcare applications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a platforms group made up of teams, each of which are responsible for developing, testing and deploying modular components of the wider platform according to our mandated technical standards and design principles. These teams should deliver components which are continuous deployed into multiple production-like test environments allowing automated testing of both operation and performance. Similarly, commodity computing power, such as that provided by commodity cloud providers like Amazon, Google and Microsoft, should be available on-demand with infrastructure-as-code, allowing teams to easily build, test and deploy without recourse to external teams. These principles underpin the “DevOps” movement.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;an architectural standards and strategy board, including both technical and information standards boards for operational and analytics use and defining the top-down broad principles for use across NHS Wales and its partners.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Welsh digital ecosystem project is critically dependent on an open platform. We can build that  open platform using a lot of the good work already done in Wales. We have a terrific opportunity to create a health and care enterprise fit for the 21st Century for the citizens of Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what might our map look like in the future? Here the platform and its components are evolving to become a commodity, but we can see that our work will be in developing the best user-facing components, focused on solving workflow and user need while taking advantage of new advances in machine learning, artificial intelligence and decision support. Who thinks we’ll be running our own data centres then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mapping/maps-system-future-future-simple-map.png&quot; alt=&quot;Maps System Future Future Simple Map&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;acronyms--descriptions&quot;&gt;Acronyms / descriptions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;API - application programming interface&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ESB - enterprise service bus. Messaging fabric carrying HL7 v2 messages between producers and listeners. Should allow decoupled development but caveat emptor! Continue to use for some uses but move to an API-based approach for most modern applications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ESR - electronic staff record&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NIIAS - “National Intelligent Integrated Audit Service” - currently used at the application-level. Needs to be embedded at the API-layer (platform) instead&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;OAUTH2 - authentication framework&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;PAS - patient administration systems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;WCP - Welsh Clinical Portal - a currently monolithic application providing a portal, one instance per health board coupled to the local PAS.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;WCRS - Welsh Care Records Service - a document repository and search service&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;wcrs&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;: Modularisation of architecture is important for reliability and pace of delivery. When components are loosely-coupled, the interactions between them are limited and it becomes possible to develop them independently, in parallel. A team can completely change the underlying implementation or even whether the service runs on-premises or in the cloud. Conversely, a tightly-coupled architecture makes change difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example in Wales is a service like the Welsh Care Records Service (WCRS) which provides a non-standard application programming interface to store and retrieve documents and the application Welsh Clinical Portal (WCP) uses that API, together with an associated instance of Apache Solr in order to provide search. In essence, these are tightly coupled because if the team working on WCRS wish to change the way the Solr index is built, they must link very closely with those building the user-facing application, WCP. It also means other parties cannot, independently, make use of WCRS to implement functionality in their systems at the application programming interface (API)-level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mapping/wcrs-architecture.png&quot; alt=&quot;Wcrs Architecture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is shown in this schematic, where “external” services such as document repositories in the health boards publish documents into WCRS but the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; way to view and search documents is via a portal application, WCP.  There are less than a handful of releases of WCP per year. Is it any wonder that users across Wales are dissatisfied with the pace of change?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">How can we make best use of technology to support healthcare?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cancer informatics</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/platform/2018/07/03/cancer-informatics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cancer informatics" /><published>2018-07-03T17:16:16+01:00</published><updated>2018-07-03T17:16:16+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/platform/2018/07/03/cancer-informatics</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/platform/2018/07/03/cancer-informatics.html">&lt;p&gt;The Public Accounts Committee (PAC) of the National Assembly for Wales heard evidence yesterday from Velindre NHS Trust on cancer informatics. You can see more &lt;a href=&quot;http://senedd.assembly.wales/ieListDocuments.aspx?CId=441&amp;amp;MId=4751&amp;amp;Ver=4&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; including the video. The minutes will appear soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The important messages were&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;CANISC, the Cancer Network Information System Cymru, has been running for over 20 years and is dependent on a now unsupported software platform. This has important security and reliability risks.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There have been a significant number of reliability issues resulting in service disruption and impact on patient care. There was no single reason for the multiple system failures.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That there are mitigations planned so that a PDF of the important information will be published into the Welsh Care Records Service and so be visible via Welsh Clinical Portal (WCP). WCP is currently mainly a read-only web portal but also has electronic test requesting and discharge summary functions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That a replacement is planned using two products: adoption of “Welsh PAS” a homegrown patient administrative system that is deployed in most other health organisations in Wales for administration, and WCP to be modified to create an electronic patient record system. This work is estimated to take 2 years.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#migration-pd&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d like to reflect on these issues in this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;our-role-as-informaticians&quot;&gt;Our role as informaticians&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of definitions of what we do in clinical informatics, but this is a good one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The overall aim of work in Clinical Informatics is to use modern technologies to advance our ability understand health and health problems, support translational research, develop effective interventions for healthcare delivery, and improve our ability to provide cutting-edge healthcare in the safest, most timely way possible.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.clinicalinformatics.group.cam.ac.uk/about-us/introduction-to-clinical-informatics/&quot;&gt;http://www.clinicalinformatics.group.cam.ac.uk/about-us/introduction-to-clinical-informatics/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;accessed on 3rd July 2018&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fundamentally, in order to be an effective clinical informatician, we need to deeply understand the problems we are trying to solve while at the same time applying our knowledge of best practices in information technology. We need to be cognisant on how teams can work effectively at scale and pace with a focus on delivery. Likewise, we need to bring together our understanding of user need with the very best in software development practices, understand the wider context and foster the adoption of technical and information standards to support semantic interoperability and use the principles outlined in domain-driven design to build data models and a shared vocabulary to bridge the gaps between users and developers. At the same time, we need to apply evidence-based best practice in development, testing, safety, security and deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-crisis-always-an-opportunity-to-reflect&quot;&gt;A crisis: always an opportunity to reflect&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A crisis is usually a good time to step back and take stock of our current state, to appraise ourselves of the options and really understand the problems we are trying to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s useful to structure our approach to how we understand need along the lines of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/docs/dhss/publications/151211reporten.pdf&quot;&gt;Informed Health and Care Strategy, 2015&lt;/a&gt; which sets out a clear vision for Wales to use digital technology and online services to support and enable care. The strategy is divided into four workstreams:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Information for you&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supporting Professionals&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improvement and Innovation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A Planned Future&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.003.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Informed Health and Care&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What kinds of requirements might arise from a deep-dive with our users? What kind of functionality do they need, noting that our “users” are not only professionals, but the citizen or their delegated representative?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not hard to start brainstorming and that’s a critical first step in solving our problems. So we might end up with a list that looks a bit like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patients:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patients to see their whole journey including forthcoming scheduled appointments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patients to be able to communicate securely with their healthcare team, at whichever point of the pathway they currently sit.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patients to be given tools to help them understand their condition, their prognosis and treatment options, perhaps with outcome data stratified according to their characteristics.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patients to see their own results.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professionals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Professionals to understand how many patients sit at each stage of the pathway and track progress and ongoing outcomes.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Professionals to have access to the right information at the right time. This means diagnostics from anywhere, including outside of Wales, as well as multidisciplinary meetings, histopathology, staging, previous treatments and interventions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Professionals to be able to communicate as a team, and have those interactions recorded as a narrative, irrespective of their organisation, specialty or profession.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Professionals to be given tools to aid shared decision-making, understanding outcomes for an individual patient compared to peers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improvement and Innovation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To support quality improvement methodologies by tracking measures of process &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; outcome using meaningful measures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To support the advancement of knowledge by offering support for identification, recruitment and randomisation into potentially complex, multi-phase clinical trials of new treatments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To capture aggregate data stratified by baseline characteristics to permit benchmarking.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To ensure digital inclusion with multiple channels so that patients have choice and multiple opportunities to contribute information in methods of their choosing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To permit innovative models of care, capture outcomes relating to those innovations and ensure that they are fit-for-purpose and not exclusionary to any group of individuals based on access to technology, age, socioeconomic class etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my experience however, users, whether professionals or patients, need help in understanding and articulating their need and once we’ve done that, we can frequently boil down requirements into their &lt;em&gt;essence&lt;/em&gt;. I love being able to solve a specific requirement by solving it in a generic way that helps not only that individual, but everyone else as well. Generic solutions are usually more robust and future-proof compared to solutions that simply solve a specific problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most generic problem-solving techniques is to become &lt;em&gt;data-driven&lt;/em&gt;. Almost every single post on my blog relates to this fundamental approach in which one thinks deeply about data, the structure of those data and how best to make use of those data in order to inform our clinical practice, whether at an individual patient level, at the service level, at a cohort level or by helping to advance our knowledge as part of research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I have just jotted those few down over 10 minutes. We need to sit down with colleagues across Wales and empower them to think big with data. My belief is that, when one sees a list of requirements as I have written above, the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;/em&gt; way to deliver that type of functionality is to &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/22/health-data.html&quot;&gt;start with data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, I believe that most of the requirements relating to cancer and cancer pathways are just as important to other non-cancer specialities. We must stop thinking about projects and products, and start thinking about &lt;em&gt;services&lt;/em&gt; and the data the underpin those services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;on-data&quot;&gt;On data&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Larry Weed opined:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You’re a victim of it or a triumph because of it. The human mind simply cannot carry all the information without error so the record becomes part of your practice.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dr Larry Weed, Internal Medicine Grand Rounds, 1971&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here he makes the critical point that the medical record is the foundation on which our clinical practice occurs and understanding this is critical for those of us interested in improving healthcare by the use of information technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I strongly believe that healthcare data should be stored in a persistent record as a model of the real-world and its storage should be &lt;em&gt;separate&lt;/em&gt; from the applications and logic which act upon it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This simple separation is a terrifically powerful paradigm because it means that others can use those data in ways that I might not even imagine at this point in time. What it means is that I have to think clearly, not about how an application might look or work, but how my data is structured to be meaningful, both now and in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I wrote in my &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;“Once for Wales” speech&lt;/a&gt; in which I pitched for interoperability and data standards for NHS Wales:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It is almost always the case that when building complex solutions to real-life problems, no-one person can conceive of all of the problems in one go. The natural solution to such complexity is to break-down a problem into manageable chunks. These chunks, much like “lego bricks”, can be joined together to form something greater than the sum of the parts. Importantly, it is more likely that we can vouch that a system is deterministic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, I believe that we need to move away from products, from projects and towards modular &lt;em&gt;services&lt;/em&gt;, that together create an open platform. I have written extensively about this in my blog including the &lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;talk I gave at the inaugural Welsh Digital Health and Care Conference in 2017.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.016.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.016&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.018.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.018&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;on-services&quot;&gt;On services&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I say we should focus on “services”, I mean two different things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I think about computing &lt;em&gt;services&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a proponent of a data-driven open platform, built from open standards and with a focus on providing a common set of modular, loosely-coupled computing services supporting citizen and professional identity, data and document repositories and other clinical information like laboratory, radiology and other investigation results. These services, abstracting complexity and possibly federating data from multiple providers,&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#federation&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, should be focused on building sane, cohesive application programming interfaces (API) suitable for both internal and external developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I think about healthcare &lt;em&gt;services&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe in digital transformation, in the use of technology to improve and transform our services. This cannot be led by an information technology department, or for that matter, an external agency acting independently from health services, but instead must be led and &lt;em&gt;owned&lt;/em&gt; by the service. There is, of course, need for expert digital teams to help &lt;em&gt;support&lt;/em&gt; those transformation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-future-welsh-pas-and-wcp&quot;&gt;The future: “Welsh PAS” and WCP?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now I come to the crux of the problem. We are told that the combination of “Welsh PAS” and WCP will solve my cancer colleagues’ problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current crisis with CANISC was foreseeable and clearly we, in Wales, must take action. I have one question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Where can I find an analysis of the different options available in order to fix this mess?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely we need to step back and cost and appraise a range of options, bringing together the advantages and disadvantages of any specific option in order to weight up and decide on the right choice. Given that this decision appears to be made by an organisation who is also acting as the supplier of said software seems to me, an important conflict of interest. To mitigate that, such decision-making should be published openly and transparently with the justifications and arguments in favour of this important decision for our cancer services. If these options analyses exist, then they should be published as with any other “procurement”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly I can make some comments about the proposed solution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welsh PAS is actually a misnomer as actually there are multiple instances of the software package running, all configured differently to different standards and Cardiff and Vale uses its own in-house administrative system. At the time of writing, as far as I know, there is no easy way of tracking a pathway between health boards, meaning that a patient starting their cancer journey in one health board and managed in another will not share the same national pathway identifier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WCP mainly stores documents as blobs of data with a proprietary and very limited metadata model. Some documents are in XML format and are rendered to PDF on-the-fly during viewing. If we view a document in a different health board, at the time of writing, it currently renders using the wrong stylesheet and so it appears as if was written by our own health board. Data within documents can be accessed by parsing the data from the XML, but there is currently &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; data persistence layer; indeed there is no single instance of WCP, so users have to login to their local, organisation-specific instance of WCP which is currently tightly integrated with whatever patient administrative system is running in that organisation. That means that a patient can appear alive in one instance of WCP but is shown as dead in another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The eForms project is meant to flexibly add data collection forms into WCP but at the time of writing, the lung cancer ETTF project has stalled and the diabetes project delayed. Change requests to electronic test requesting have been parked for many months in preparation for a new eForm based solution which has not yet been deployed. I am not aware that any decision has been made as to &lt;em&gt;where&lt;/em&gt; data recorded in an eForm is actually persisted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it difficult to understand how these solutions will solve even the simple requirements I’ve listed above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am therefore concerned that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have not fully understood the wider requirements underpinning a modern cancer information system, to solve our current and future problems. It is likely that, fundamentally, the requirements of cancer services are likely to be more widely applicable to a range of specialties and services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We have not adequately performed a open transparent appraisal of the options in relation to cancer informatics.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That the combination of Welsh PAS and WCP must be regarded as a significant &lt;em&gt;risk&lt;/em&gt; both in terms of delivery to the timescales and functionality, given the gaps between what is currently possible in “Welsh PAS” in WCP at the current time and what will be needed to support improvement and transformation in cancer informatics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, I would argue that we should be focusing our efforts on building a generic open standards-based healthcare platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-needing-to-stop-and-review-our-strategy&quot;&gt;On needing to stop and review our strategy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/platform/2018/06/30/user-need-agile-platform.html&quot;&gt;Pulling the “Andon Cord”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-once-for-wales&quot;&gt;On “Once for Wales”&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;Once for Wales : a debate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-trust-and-innovation&quot;&gt;On trust and innovation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/paradox-of-ambition.html&quot;&gt;The paradox of ambition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html&quot;&gt;The paradox of control&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html&quot;&gt;The 5 Os of healthcare IT - objectives, ownership, openness, optimise, organic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-platforms&quot;&gt;On platforms:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data-driven healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-1.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 1/3. Standards and interoperability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-2.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 2/3. An API-first approach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 3/3. What we need to do next&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-focus&quot;&gt;On focus:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html&quot;&gt;Focus 1/3. The importance of strategy : focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges.html&quot;&gt;Focus 2/3. The challenges we face in delivering the vision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-solutions.html&quot;&gt;Focus 3/3. Pragmatic solutions to those challenges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-data-1&quot;&gt;On data:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/22/health-data.html&quot;&gt;Health data - start with a problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data-driven healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-development-standards-and-ecosystems&quot;&gt;On development standards and ecosystems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/cloud-ehr.html&quot;&gt;Creative 1/3: creative destruction in health IT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;Creative 2/3: the value of software for healthcare: quality improvement and service transformation underpinned by software, and software underpinning by quality improvement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html&quot;&gt;Creative 3/3: ecosystems and the platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;migration-pd&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;: Few people are aware, but a few years ago, I migrated both Cardiff and Vale and Bridgend Parkinson’s services from CANISC to a new electronic patient record system, complete with demographics, diagnostic information, all encounters, clinic annotations and measurement data as well as drugs used past and present. Oh, and mapped all diagnoses and medications to SNOMED-CT at the same time. I did this over a few weekends and did the big migration over a single weekend. It was a hobby project but based on the fact that CANISC was end-of-life and we needed to do something. The database schema was a bit odd, but it wasn’t actually particularly difficult. We now track diagnoses and outcomes on a modern web-based platform across Wales that I built in my spare time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;federation&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;: Federation means encapsulating or abstracted multiple services under one, simple to use service. You might, for example, track professional identity by delegating authentication to social care or health care authentication services, and federate based on a namespace.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Public Accounts Committee (PAC) of the National Assembly for Wales heard evidence yesterday from Velindre NHS Trust on cancer informatics. You can see more here including the video. The minutes will appear soon.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pulling the Andon cord for healthcare IT in Wales</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/platform/2018/06/30/user-need-agile-platform.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pulling the Andon cord for healthcare IT in Wales" /><published>2018-06-30T08:14:28+01:00</published><updated>2018-06-30T08:14:28+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/platform/2018/06/30/user-need-agile-platform</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/platform/2018/06/30/user-need-agile-platform.html">&lt;p&gt;We need some substantial changes in the way we think about healthcare information technology in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that we need to, figuratively speaking, pull the &lt;a href=&quot;https://itrevolution.com/kata/&quot;&gt;Andon cord&lt;/a&gt; and call a stop to the status quo, to stop building significant &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technical_debt&quot;&gt;technical debt&lt;/a&gt; and move away from long procurement cycles and success judged by the deployment of different products from different vendors in different organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.audit.wales/system/files/publications/NHS_-Informatics-2018%20-%20English.pdf&quot;&gt;Welsh Audit Office (WAO) report&lt;/a&gt; strongly criticises the governance arrangements and the imbalanced reporting of success and progress. Our architecture is becoming ever more tightly coupled with, mostly bespoke, point-to-point integration. With each expansion or integration, the whole enterprise from end-to-end becomes ever more brittle and less predictable. We have increasing problems with reliability in critical national systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paradoxically of course, this is itself extremely predictable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-simple-single-answer&quot;&gt;A simple single answer?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there is no simple single answer to our problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fundamental steps now are to recognise that there are problems and that we need to improve and to be open and transparent about the issues we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the responses at the recent public accounts committee meetings suggest that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;perhaps not all recognise that there are problems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;that there is a lack of ambition to enable transformational change using digital technology&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there is a lack of priority on the delivery of benefit and understanding of how to do that effectively.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the solution will, given the NHS is a complex and adaptive environment with lots of moving parts, lots of variation and significant complexity, to look at improving things both from the top-down and the bottom-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;top-down--cohesive-principles-and-credible-plans&quot;&gt;Top-down : cohesive principles and credible plans&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the top, we need cohesive, credible plans based on broad design and technology principles and standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we have the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gov.wales/topics/health/nhswales/about/e-health/?lang=en&quot;&gt;“Informed Health and Care” strategy&lt;/a&gt;, it is only a &lt;em&gt;vision&lt;/em&gt; of what is needed and we must ask, where is the the specific executable plan to deliver that vision? There are those of us who are now trying to draft that, but where has it been up until now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This needs to be a thoughtful and informed piece of work, noting the successes and failures in a non-judgmental way and highlighting the areas of priority, as well as reflections and robust options-appraisals of different options. If it can’t do that, then the top-down delivery plan must create a tangible plan to understand those options to inform the balancing judgement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It necessarily follows that this work must adopt the broad principles of &lt;em&gt;openness&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;transparency&lt;/em&gt; in which our work as a service is open to inspection and evaluation. As a result, adopting the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/guidance/government-design-principles&quot;&gt;GDS design principles&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/guidance/government-design-principles&quot;&gt;https://www.gov.uk/guidance/government-design-principles&lt;/a&gt;) has been a good first step, acknowledging that we do not have all of the answers is the second, understanding that we can already define some good broad principles that will enable us to deliver the third, and being open to outside help the fourth! For the latter, we need to bring in expertise on digital transformation and adopt agile methodologies and user interface and needs expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What must follow from this is the creation of an overarching strategic group who is tasked with setting broad directions as well as the principles and standards to be used by any team working to deliver functionality for users across Wales, including professionals and patients. Those overarching principles and technical approach must include a credible plan for a cohesive architecture, making the best use of existing infrastructure and yet permitting delivery of solutions to both our immediate  problems, and not limiting our ability to solve tasks we must face in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;bottom-up-empowerment-cooperation-and-trust&quot;&gt;Bottom-up: empowerment, cooperation and trust&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For improvements from the bottom-up, we need to change the narrative and, most importantly the culture, from command-and-control to collaboration and cooperation. We need to focus our resources on that work only the public sector can do and make information technology the enabler for change by the service itself. This means that we provide a toolbox of data and computing services and applications from which the service can stitch together solutions to their problems at a local level and share those solutions between organisations when they are successful. This means that we aim towards an &lt;em&gt;open platform&lt;/em&gt; approach in which data is the key and application programming interfaces provide access to important shared software services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, our platform becomes the &lt;em&gt;servant&lt;/em&gt; of the health service so it can work more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, we need a shared platform of discrete modular loosely-coupled components available to use for both internal and external teams. Those components might include citizen and professional identity services, laboratory, radiology and other investigation services, document repositories and a messaging fabric, but critically, they must be open, documented, standards-based and secured with appropriate authentication, authorisation and verifiable logging at the service (API) level. Loose-coupling means that interactions between services and the teams that work on those services are limited, documented and form essentially a service contract. Importantly, this approach means the different components of the architecture can be improved and developed independently; critical in speeding up delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What therefore must follow from this is the need for a &lt;em&gt;national platform delivery group&lt;/em&gt;, made up of cross-functional teams bringing together expertise from different specialties such as management, development, testing, quality assurance, safety and operations. These individual teams must be given responsibility to deliver discrete components of a modular, loosely-coupled architecture. For example, these services underpin important outcomes in many different workstreams - citizen identity clear underpins both “Information for you” and “Supporting professionals”, the workstreams supporting patients and professionals respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our open platform needs robust API lifecycle management to build APIs with a focus on ease of use for application developers (whether internal or external), consistent security policies, automated testing and deployment, documentation and analytics to gain better insights into API usage and performance. Those APIs need to be used by both internal and external developers alike.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together with these technical changes, we need to build trust and collaboration between organisations. This means shared source code, teams made up of individuals from across Wales, irrespective of their organisations, focused on delivering their specific goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, information technology needs to be &lt;em&gt;owned&lt;/em&gt; by the service working collaboratively and in partnership, and bringing in commercial expertise and solutions when necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most businesses recognise that IT does not simply support their business, but it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the way that they do business and we need to do that for health. Such recognition has meant that digital leaders are at board level and that information technology should not be considered a separate department. In Wales, much IT is outsourced to a separate &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.audit.wales/publication/informatics-systems-nhs-wales&quot;&gt;poorly governed&lt;/a&gt; organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;striking-a-balance&quot;&gt;Striking a balance&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is, of course, a balance and none of what we need to do is particularly easy, but I struggle with the paradox of Wales attempting to run hugely ambitious, top-down, multi-million pound IT projects given both local and international experience of the likelihood of failure vs a genuine lack of ambition to use digital tools to transform how we care for our population and enable an ecosystem of innovation. I personally find decision-making to be opaque and rarely find published appraisals of different options explaining the advantages and disadvantages of any particular option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is quite easy to make excuses and blame lack of delivery on how difficult it is to effect change, but I would argue that our culture, our governance and our technical architecture conspire to make our work even more difficult. We should be aiming to stack the odds in our favour!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are people around who want to make a difference and recognise the need for change. There are pockets of good work at all levels, including government, NWIS and the health boards. I think for many of us it feels as if we are swimming against the current however. It is also important to recognise that there has been historic under-funding compared to peers in England, but it is difficult to justify more expenditure when there has been a consistent historic failure to prioritise and to deliver using the resources we have had.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would suggest that we need to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perform a national architecture review to help define a modern, standards-based loosely-coupled evolutionary adaptive architecture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change our metrics so that we focus on user need and delivery of benefit, rather than deployment of a specific product. Our metrics should reflect our focus: user need.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change governance and ownership. Give the health boards ownership and control, ask them to form a partnership with each other and government tasked to set top-down principles and technical and information standards and provide expertise and oversight to define a national open platform.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change delivery - by empowering developer teams whether national, local or commercial to use that open platform to solve problems, and ensure that those solutions can be built collaboratively and shared and scaled when shown to be safe and successful.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change development practices - with real agile working, cross-functional empowered teams made up of different specialists working together to deliver.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change our behaviour and culture - become open by default, make Wales a beacon of safe, secure healthcare informatics underpinning service transformation and improvement - and teach everyone else how we did it, the difficulties we faced and the strategies we used to overcome those difficulties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is possible to have a single organisation acting as both overseer, strategist and software supplier, but that needs a change in behaviour towards transparency so that decision-making is open, subject to external scrutiny and there are clear appraisals of different options. In my view, the NHS Wales Informatics Service fails to behave in this way. My preference is to change the behaviour, but if that is not possible, then we must surely consider re-organisation instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have written previously on many aspects of this. These are the most important bits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On open platforms in healthcare here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data-driven healthcare: integration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;Once-for-Wales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On governance and top-down vs bottom up here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html&quot;&gt;Paradox of control&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/paradox-of-ambition.html&quot;&gt;Paradox of ambition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On platforms here…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-1.html&quot;&gt;Platforms #1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-2.html&quot;&gt;Platforms #2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://wardle.org/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3.html&quot;&gt;Platforms #2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We need some substantial changes in the way we think about healthcare information technology in Wales.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">WTSB 19th June 2018</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/06/19/wtsb.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WTSB 19th June 2018" /><published>2018-06-19T15:14:14+01:00</published><updated>2018-06-19T15:14:14+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/06/19/wtsb</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/06/19/wtsb.html">&lt;p&gt;We held the second meeting of the Welsh Technical Standards Board (WTSB) today and I am delighted to announce that we have formally adopted the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/guidance/government-design-principles&quot;&gt;GDS Design Principles&lt;/a&gt; for use by NHS Wales. These are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Start with user needs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do less&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design with data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do the hard work to make it simple&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iterate. Then iterate again&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This is for everyone&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand context&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build digital services, not websites&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be consistent, not uniform&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make things open: it makes things better&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, we have agreed to adopt the Welsh Government Digital Service Standard:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Undertake research of who the service users are, to understand user needs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a plan in place for ongoing user research and usability testing.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a multidisciplinary team.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build your service using agile iterative and user-centred methods.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build a service that can be iterated and improved on a frequent basis and make sure you have the capacity, resources and technical flexibility to do so.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Evaluate what tools and systems will be used to build, host, operate and measure the service, and how to procure them.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understand security and privacy issues.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consider making source code open and reusable, and, if appropriate, publish it under relevant licenses.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Use open standards and common platforms where available.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Test the end-to-end service.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make a plan for being offline.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a service that’s simple and intuitive that users succeed first time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make the user experience consistent with the rest of Welsh Government.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Encourage everyone to use the digital service with assisted digital support if required.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Identify your baseline information to measure performance&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Collect that performance information regularly&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Report on that performance data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Test your service from beginning to end [with your minister]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implicit in adopting these standards is a focus on the citizen as the user of services and that digital transformation is better thought of as &lt;em&gt;service transformation&lt;/em&gt;. We need to provide tools so that our services can be transformed to provide modern, efficient and safe healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To that end, we are starting a transformation journey, with collaboration, cooperation and openness the key enablers for us to &lt;em&gt;make things better&lt;/em&gt;. In essence, we need to balance top-down standards with creating a culture of openness and transparency to enable safe innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our remit, as a board, is to define the technical principles and standards supporting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;integration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;interoperability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;software development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;security&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are accountable to the National Informatics Management Board (NIMB).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;making-things-better-for-users&quot;&gt;Making things better for users&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only should NHS Wales work to GDS principles, but we as a board should too. To that end, we must ask&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a technical standards board, who are &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; users?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see &lt;em&gt;developers&lt;/em&gt;, together with the teams in which they work, as the prime user for our technical standards because they are the ones who will make things better for the real users, patients and professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And what do developers need? Can we apply the GDS principles in our task to maintain a catalogue of principles and standards?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, our standards will specify the structure and function of our national architecture and documentation of those standards should, if we take an open-approach, foster a change in culture towards collaboration and cooperation and trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will, in essence, define the specifications for an open platform onto which we can build innovation and enable true service transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-next&quot;&gt;So what next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some logical consequences to this approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We must open up our documentation relating to services and their standards and develop a roadmap to assess and set new standards and decommission old ones.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We must move to creating cross-functional teams that combine developers, project management, user researchers, UX designers with testing, safety and deployment experts to deliver modular, domain-constrained functionality that can be developed and improved in isolation to other components. Such components should, in essence, be loosely-coupling with technical and human contracts defining interactions between teams. For Wales, we should encourage teams that combine members that span organisational boundaries&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A focus on automated end-to-end testing and scalability with testing in production-like environments available on-demand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the rest of this post, I want to talk about &lt;em&gt;documentation&lt;/em&gt; as it is a key enabler for building collaboration, cooperation and trust in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;documentation&quot;&gt;Documentation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do other developer-focused digital companies do when they want to create an open platform? They create a developer-friendly set of documentation with application programming interface (API) specifications together with how-to and getting started guides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine you are a developer wishing to build software using the NHS Wales open platform. You might work for the NHS Wales Informatics Service (NWIS), one of the health boards or a commercial or academic partner  What do you need to get your work done?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at how others have done this…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the current landing page of &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.microsoft.com&quot;&gt;https://docs.microsoft.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.003.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.003&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here there are links to documentation covering the range of Microsoft platforms, including Azure, their cloud platform. Let’s explore…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.004.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.004&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can read broad overviews of the architecture, and see links to more detailed specifications in the API reference:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.005.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.005&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the documentation is interspersed with example code and links to frameworks that make it easy to make use of the software services provided by the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.006.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.006&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.007.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.007&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how do Microsoft keep their work updated? The source code for their documentation is either automatically generated from their code, or maintained itself as an open-source repository on github - see &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MicrosoftDocs&quot;&gt;https://github.com/MicrosoftDocs&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.008.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.008&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This fosters collaboration. Internal users can contribute to changes and have them accepted by the project team, but so can external users. I could make my own local copy of this document repository, make my changes and submit them for review as a “pull-request”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.009.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.009&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can edit the original source to the documentation, here in Markdown format, a simple-to-use and process text markup language. Microsoft maintains control of the source, but permits open access and review and collaboration. Have a look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/MicrosoftDocs/azure-docs&quot;&gt;https://github.com/MicrosoftDocs/azure-docs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.010.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.010&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And from these source files, Microsoft generate their website:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.011.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.011&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazon Web Services (AWS) have adopted the same approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.014.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.014&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we have their landing page, linking to lots of different resources, including guides, lists of API specifications etc. And here are the github pages containing the source for those documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.015.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.015&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.016.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.016&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.017.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.017&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in the same way as for Microsoft, developers can flag omissions or errors and contribute. This user is submitting a patch to add a link to another resource. Other users might simply create an “issue” to be examined and possibly fixed by the project team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wtsb-opendocs/wtsb-2018-06-19.023.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wtsb 2018 06 19.023&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So today we agreed that, in line with our remit, we must start work on building an online catalogue of existing services and the standards that are used, and, by adopting GDS-principles ourselves, do this in the open and in small incremental steps. As such, we are going to pick a current service and see how we can take some tentative first steps in publishing that documentation as well as making use of tools to support cooperation and collaboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any comments or thoughts, let me know. I promise to tell you how we get on, and share the learning, the results (good or bad) with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We held the second meeting of the Welsh Technical Standards Board (WTSB) today and I am delighted to announce that we have formally adopted the GDS Design Principles for use by NHS Wales. These are:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Informed Health and Care: Delivery</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/05/27/delivery.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Informed Health and Care: Delivery" /><published>2018-05-27T21:20:20+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-27T21:20:20+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/05/27/delivery</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/05/27/delivery.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gov.wales/topics/health/nhswales/about/e-health/?lang=en&quot;&gt;“Informed health and care – A digital health and social care strategy for Wales”&lt;/a&gt; sets out a clear vision for the use of information technology to support the provision of healthcare for citizens within Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This vision is split into four key themes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Information for You”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Supporting professionals”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Improvement and innovation”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“A Planned future”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We want a future where staff, service users, patients and carers are empowered and better informed, where organisational boundaries are not a barrier to effective care, as information is available electronically and joined-up, and where innovation and improvement can flourish built on a solid technical infrastructure and a safe environment for those who work in or are served by health and care services in Wales.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key question for us to answer is, what are the challenges that must be overcome to deliver this vision? As part of that process, we must identify current and future impediments to successful delivery and look to changing how we work to meet those challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-partnership-for-delivery&quot;&gt;A partnership for delivery&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is my five-step plan to deliver the strategy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-change-our-metrics&quot;&gt;1. Change our metrics&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metrics, quantifiable measures of progress, are important indicators of what we want to achieve and so must represent those ambitions. Our National Informatics Management Board (NIMB) in Wales uses delivery of certain products into different health boards as a measure of success, but is that appropriate? We need to focus instead on &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;outcomes&lt;/em&gt; for our population, and therefore change our metrics to represent &lt;em&gt;solving problems&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach forces us to step back and focus on the problems we are solving with information technology and ensures that we don’t become blinkered into adopting a certain approach that will delay realising value for patients and professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-change-our-governance-and-ownership&quot;&gt;2. Change our governance and ownership&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have health boards working to deliver care for their citizens but a separate organisation, the NHS Wales Informatics Service (NWIS) acting in multiple, potentially conflicting, roles as a source of IT expertise for the service, as a source oversight and assurance, as a supplier of software and supplier of infrastructure. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.audit.wales/system/files/publications/NHS_-Informatics-2018%20-%20English.pdf&quot;&gt;Welsh Audit Office (WAO) report&lt;/a&gt; strongly criticises the governance arrangements and the imbalanced reporting of success and progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t we need to consider instead, a partnership, owned by the health service for the health service working to increase cooperation and collaboration providing top-down governance and assurance separate from an any organisation with supplier status? Surely we need a strategic assurance group able to set broad principles and define, maintain and assure technical and information standards for use across NHS Wales and its partners?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must  encourage trust, collaboration and cooperation to encourage bottom-up working to solve real-life local problems and share good practice among peers. This means getting the right balance between governance and delivery, whether those projects are delivered in-house, by collaborative working groups working across and for NHS organisations or by third-parties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-change-our-architecture-and-our-team-structures&quot;&gt;3. Change our architecture and our team structures&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current architecture in NHS Wales is built from an enterprise service bus (ESB) messaging service but much of our software integration is bespoke and point-to-point and there is a lack of robust automated unit and integration test environments offering end-to-end assurance of proper functionality. There are significant delays between design and getting software to end-users, limiting feedback on quality, performance and failing to identify user need by iterative ongoing continuous improvement and iteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to modularise our architecture and realise the productivity and safety benefits from combining development, testing and operations into cross-functional teams with shared common goals to deliver discrete modules of functionality that can be independently developed and improved with loose-coupling with other components.  A change in architecture should prompt us to create task-driven teams bringing together expertise from our existing functional units with a single goal: delivery of quality software to solve our problems, create value and as a result, improve the outcomes for our population. We need to see information technology as a tool for continuous improvement and service transformation and we need to speed up and isolate modules of our information technology work in order to delivery and improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an approach builds on our existing work to adopt a standards-based approach to our healthcare enterprise architecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-change-our-culture&quot;&gt;4. Change our culture&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to adopt the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gov.uk/guidance/government-design-principles&quot;&gt;UK Government Digital Service (GDS) design principles&lt;/a&gt; and focus on openness and transparency in our work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Healthcare information technology is hard, and we need to be able to step back and re-evaluate our progress and our plan for delivery, bring in outside expertise when needed and justify our decisions with a clear and informed appraisal of our options, without conflicts of interest. This relates, of course, to the changes we need in governance; an organisation who runs two data centres itself is unlikely to be able to make the difficult decisions to switch to using commodity cloud providers or to judge itself against agreed service level agreements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I was asked to take “down this blog” as my posts on strategy and technical architecture were perceived as criticism and this was “particularly difficult” to tolerate as I was working (at the time) for the NHS Wales Informatics Service. How can that be right? We must encourage and foster debate, be transparent in our decision making, which, after all, will always be a compromise and balance between advantages and disadvantages, and recognise that we should bring in expert help when appropriate in order for us to make the right decisions for Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;5-change-our-focus&quot;&gt;5. Change our focus&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NHS Wales must face some difficult choices.  For too long, external factors have resulted in incoherent and inconsistent delivery or projects, frequency orthogonal to delivery of the wider vision; in many cases it has been driven by the budgeting process and the availability of funds in any single financial year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A coherent plan to deliver the strategy needs more than a list of disconnected and incompatible goals but instead a clear understanding of what needs to be done and what doesn’t need to be done; we must know when to say “no”. Instead, we focus our limited resources on specific tangible actions and make some difficult decisions to prune areas of work that do not support delivery of the wider vision, or those areas of work that can be easily provided by third-parties. We need to prioritise our work and focus on delivery of value and improved outcomes. We must focus on user need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must recognise that technology evolves quickly and so we must build culture and architecture to encourage and enable innovation and partnership working recognising that our population can benefit from a digital-first approach to healthcare, whether directly in their interactions with out services or indirectly as a result of better planning, scheduling and clinical decision support. Our ecosystem should be focused on building tools and frameworks to make the work of both internal and external developers, safe, productive and efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, we must raise our focus away from only healthcare in Wales and recognise that we must exchange meaningful information with partner organisations in other regions and in other disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we must become focused on being &lt;em&gt;data-driven&lt;/em&gt;, so that we focus firstly on the capture and analysis of clinically meaningful structured and semantically interoperable data, and use those data to shape and improve our services. Similarly, our information technology developments should, themselves, be driven by data, by usage and by metrics of performance, stability and security. The data driving our work should be meaningful and standards-based.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-once-for-wales&quot;&gt;On “Once for Wales”&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;Once for Wales : a debate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-trust-and-innovation&quot;&gt;On trust and innovation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/paradox-of-ambition.html&quot;&gt;The paradox of ambition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html&quot;&gt;The paradox of control&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html&quot;&gt;The 5 Os of healthcare IT - objectives, ownership, openness, optimise, organic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-platforms&quot;&gt;On platforms:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data-driven healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-1.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 1/3. Standards and interoperability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-2.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 2/3. An API-first approach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 3/3. What we need to do next&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-focus&quot;&gt;On focus:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html&quot;&gt;Focus 1/3. The importance of strategy : focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges.html&quot;&gt;Focus 2/3. The challenges we face in delivering the vision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-solutions.html&quot;&gt;Focus 3/3. Pragmatic solutions to those challenges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-data&quot;&gt;On data:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/22/health-data.html&quot;&gt;Health data - start with a problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data-driven healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-development-standards-and-ecosystems&quot;&gt;On development standards and ecosystems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/cloud-ehr.html&quot;&gt;Creative 1/3: creative destruction in health IT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;Creative 2/3: the value of software for healthcare: quality improvement and service transformation underpinned by software, and software underpinning by quality improvement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html&quot;&gt;Creative 3/3: ecosystems and the platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“Informed health and care – A digital health and social care strategy for Wales” sets out a clear vision for the use of information technology to support the provision of healthcare for citizens within Wales.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welsh Technical Standards Board</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/05/15/wtsb.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welsh Technical Standards Board" /><published>2018-05-15T10:09:09+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-15T10:09:09+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/05/15/wtsb</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/wales/2018/05/15/wtsb.html">&lt;p&gt;I am delighted to announce that I have been asked to chair the new Welsh Technical Standards Board (WTSB) for NHS Wales. We will support the creation and maintenance of a catalogue of standards and requirements to enable integration and interoperability across all health and care systems in a consistent and secure manner, and to support local innovation and the use of third party delivery partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scope of this Board covers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integration standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software development standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Infrastructure standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cyber security standards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our responsibilities will be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the identification, assessment and setting of standards and for assuring the application of agreed standards across the national architecture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ongoing maintenance of the catalogue of standards, including:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;establishing a road map to support the implementation of agreed standards, including how each standard should be implemented and used&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;periodically assessing agreed standards to ensure they remain relevant and appropriate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;establishing a road map to support the decommissioning of standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;identifying opportunities locally, regionally and nationally to adopt standards providing quick wins, case studies and learning to inform the road map.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;embedding an interoperability framework within NHS procurement at a local and national level to ensure that procurements are appropriately scored as to their level of interoperability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our inaugural meeting will be the 22nd May 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;openness-transparency-and-public-working&quot;&gt;Openness, transparency and public working&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my ambitions is to make the WTSB open and transparent; to this end, one of our first agenda items is to determine the best way to ensure that our work and the results of our work, are fully open. In addition, can’t we take this approach further? While we can ensure that our work is visible to any member of the public, I aspire to encourage active participation, recognising that we work for many stakeholders. That means not only will our catalogue of standards be publicly available, but the day-to-day working of our group will, by default, be similarly available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, our remit is broad and we will need to look to bring in outside expertise as and when required to support different streams of work. With such a broad remit, we will need to break down our goals into smaller chunks via more specialised work groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;who-do-we-work-for&quot;&gt;Who do we work for?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, we work for patients, to define standards in an attempt to improve patient care, by supporting the development, testing, evaluation and deployment of valuable healthcare software for citizens in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, our immediate audience comprises three core groups:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The NHS Wales Informatics Service (NWIS) who are responsible for delivering “shared for Wales” services underpinning the &lt;em&gt;single patient record&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Health organisations in Wales, who have a statutory responsibility to deliver healthcare to citizens and need to procure or develop local software to meet local needs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;External partners including the third sector and commercial entities in order to permit a digital ecosystem and ensure innovation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, we should treat these three audiences with the same importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My key aim is to foster cooperation and collaboration and encourage the adoption best practices. We should aim to have software code and documentation publicly available, and encourage contributions from stakeholders, from developers, across all interested groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;agenda-22nd-may-2018&quot;&gt;Agenda 22nd May 2018&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-welcome-and-introductions&quot;&gt;1. Welcome and introductions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-terms-of-reference-and-discussion-of-membership&quot;&gt;2. Terms of reference and discussion of membership&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/1jMLpNP5w6-SvO9ChUPGjqGU-1_HHo0T7/view?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Document 1&lt;/a&gt;,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is it right. Are we missing important people? e.g. What about security input?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is it appropriate to bring in expertise on an ad-hoc basis, particularly when considering working groups?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;3-in-relation-to-how-the-board-will-function&quot;&gt;3. In relation to how the board will function&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/16J7BRN7-WfgH2Rh1B0v6pO867CuvjpB7/view?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;Document 2&lt;/a&gt;, do you agree that we need:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A catalogue of existing system services and functions within the national architecture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A corresponding record of the standards used already&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A roadmap to identify services and functions that would benefit from the adoption of standards&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To register https://api.wales.nhs.uk with three consumers in mind, NWIS, health boards and third-parties via the digital ecosystem, and as such, encourage open collaboration and trust by sharing documentation publicly?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To invite external speakers with specific industry knowledge to inform our working such as
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Open source and collaboration experts to talk about openness and transparency, about shared working. (e.g. what can we learn from methods used by open source collaborative groups such as the Apache Software Foundation?)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Experts on best practices for software development methodologies, including agile, DevOps, infrastructure-as-code, production-like test environments&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Industry representatives e.g. commercial suppliers, integration and interoperability experts -&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That we will need five broad categories of interoperability standards, relating to:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Security, staff identity management and logging. We will need to identify expertise in federated security models such as OAUTH2.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Demographics and citizen identity&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Diagnostic test standards (e.g. laboratory and radiology standards) relating to the requesting, reporting and viewing of diagnostic testing&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Clinical Document standards relating to the creation, storage and transmission of clinical documents&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Clinical data standards relating to the recording of structured clinical information such as diagnoses, treatments and procedures as part of the wider logical single patient record.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;4-proposed-technical-standards-for-consideration&quot;&gt;4. Proposed technical standards for consideration:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;API specifications for services supporting the storage and retrieval of e-Observations data such as temperature, pulse rate, respiratory rate, level of consciousness, weight and height.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;API specifications for services supporting the storage and retrieval of clinical documents and their associated metadata&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;5-links-with-other-groups&quot;&gt;5. Links with other groups&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Do you agree that we need to ensure communication with other groups across the UK and Internationally, to ensure that there is harmonisation of technical standards, where possible?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If so, to which groups do we already have links and to which groups must we approach to ensure representation for Wales?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;6-any-other-business&quot;&gt;6. Any other business?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have comments on any of these agenda items, then please contact me. As this will be our inaugural meeting, the best way to feed back your comments is directly to me, at mark@wardle.org&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I am delighted to announce that I have been asked to chair the new Welsh Technical Standards Board (WTSB) for NHS Wales. We will support the creation and maintenance of a catalogue of standards and requirements to enable integration and interoperability across all health and care systems in a consistent and secure manner, and to support local innovation and the use of third party delivery partners.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creative 3/3: Ecosystems and the platform</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creative 3/3: Ecosystems and the platform" /><published>2018-05-08T09:08:08+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-08T09:08:08+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;part one, I highlighted four drivers that will result in creative destruction&lt;/a&gt; in the healthcare IT industry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was the recognition that software and data are critical enablers of clinical quality improvement, service transformation and advancing our knowledge (research).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second was that the best way to build healthcare software is to adopt the behaviours, processes and culture from the most highly productive technology companies. This means adopting quality improvement and research methodologies to develop, test and deploy the software that use to improve our clinical quality, service and research endeavours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I covered these two first points in more detail in &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;part two&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third was the importance of separating data storage and transmission from the software operating on those data, with a shared domain language uniting multi-disciplinary cross-functional, semi-autonomous teams creating discrete, carefully bounded components with loose coupling with other components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth was the recognition of a transformation in software engineering practices with the increasing adoption of cloud and serverless technologies, permitting the development and commodification of components of what will become, a distributed and patient-centred logical electronic health record. The end result? A variety of interoperable applications, both clinical and administrative indeed, focused on workflow and usually task-orientated, making use of that shared health platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, I delve into the importance of software architecture and the use of standards in designing healthcare software systems fit for the 21st Century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;architecture-and-standards&quot;&gt;Architecture and standards&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our efforts to transform health services are critically dependent on technology, we need to change our approach to health information technology projects to maximise safety, quality, productivity and pace using the best evidence-based practices. This means building in continuous improvement methodologies to ensure we keep on improving our approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how can create an environment which makes it easy and safe to develop, test, evaluate and deploy software for use in healthcare?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/04/26/lean-healthcare-devops.html&quot;&gt;“Lean Healthcare”&lt;/a&gt;, I talked about the quality improvement methodologies and process changes that can be used to develop software faster and more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the important conclusions is the benefit of small cross-functional teams. Such teams must be able to work independently, aligned to a wider strategy, given the right tools and responsibility to get their work done and most importantly, work on discrete components by breaking down work into smaller, less risky units that can evolve independently with only loose-coupling with other components. We &lt;em&gt;modularise&lt;/em&gt; our work and limit the interactions between those modules to well-defined publicly documented contracts. It is reported that Jeff Bezos, founder and CEO of Amazon said:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“All service interfaces, without exception, must be designed from the ground up to be externalizable. That is to say, the team must plan and design to be able to expose the interface to developers in the outside world. No exceptions”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Jeff Bezos quoted &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/+RipRowan/posts/eVeouesvaVX&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting this kind of &lt;em&gt;broad architectural principle&lt;/em&gt; means a lot and when you write down this and other guiding principles, and they are actionable and meaningful, they drive a change in behaviour and &lt;em&gt;change your culture&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Action 1: We need to be explicit in the broad principles we will use in our architecture and culture in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cross-functional-teams-and-delivery&quot;&gt;Cross-functional teams and delivery&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I mean by a cross-functional team? A cross-functional team brings together people with different expertise to work together towards a common goal. I want to convince you that we need to modularise our technical architecture in Wales and as a result, we need to &lt;em&gt;modularise our teams&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, it is easy to see software development as a process of generating value akin to a factory assembly line, in which a clinical system is designed, built, tested and then deployed to the end-customer. This is what is called a “value stream”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to fall into the trap, usually brought about by naivety mixed with arrogance, that we can define the specifications of what is needed from our software, build it, and then deploy into clinical environments and immediately realise that value, sitting back to announce “our work is done”. As a result, you will have a design team, a development team, a testing team and a deployment (operations) team, and at each step, the “work” is passed from one team to another. When an incident occurs, and they do, perhaps a patient safety team will swing into action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is that the right way to structure and operate your organisation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cross-functional team brings together those experts into the right sized teams, in which communication between members is easy, there is a shared goal, usually focused on &lt;em&gt;delivery&lt;/em&gt;. Members of different functional teams are brought together, for possibly a fixed duration, in order to deliver a goal bringing together design, development, testing, evaluation and deployment and speeding up the lifecycle between these processes so that we aim for &lt;em&gt;continuous integration&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;continuous delivery&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Action 2: We need to modularise our architecture and modularise our teams, creating cross-functional teams whose task is to &lt;em&gt;deliver&lt;/em&gt; discrete components of our architecture which are loosely-coupled from one another, with a focus on automated unit and end-to-end integration testing and continuous delivery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;creative-destruction--ecosystems-thinking&quot;&gt;Creative destruction &amp;amp; ecosystems-thinking&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we want to develop a distributed, standards-driven platform that provides the building blocks with which to build the next generation of electronic health applications?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice I don’t say “electronic health record software”, because I want to convince you that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Data persistence and transfer &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; be considered separately to the applications and software services that operate upon those data.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need multiple applications giving different views and bespoke utility using the same data. A single logical record of patient information.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#single-patient-record&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefits of an open ecosystem extend beyond only a new marketplace for health applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Interestingly, another definition of a “platform” is a set of services that bring together users and providers to form a multisided market. Is it possible then to take our “open platform” and start to think of a future in which we have products and services that actually do enable a re-imagining of healthcare provision to bring together patients, carers, health professionals, commissioners, analytics, researchers and all other stakeholders in a safe and secure manner?&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;My &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/20/disruptive-influences-future.html&quot;&gt;disruptive influences in healthcare blog post&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, a new ecosystem permits us to step-back and re-imagine our healthcare services. When you have physical notes, the team looking after your chronic health conditions or your primary care physician need to be physically located near those notes and near to you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It used to be the same with online banking in which your local branch held your account. We see the artefact of this configuration even today with account numbers and sort-codes tracking the bank and branch at which your bank account is held. Digital technology was an important tool in re-imagining how we interact with our banks; for them, digital is now &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; way of doing business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can we do the same for healthcare?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Action 3: We need to think ‘open’ and build software services and data repositories that are usable by both internal and external developers to create value and innovation; ecosystems-thinking. We need to &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eating_your_own_dog_food&quot;&gt;“eat our own dog food”&lt;/a&gt; and ensure external developers are treated the same as internal development teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;posts-in-this-series&quot;&gt;Posts in this series&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/cloud-ehr.html&quot;&gt;Part one: creative destruction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;Part two: the value of software for healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html&quot;&gt;Part three: ecosystems and the platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/04/26/lean-healthcare-devops.html&quot;&gt;“Lean healthcare” &lt;/a&gt;: Value stream: transforming health and care technology implementations using lean, agile, “DevOps” and serverless with small, cross-functional teams.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/30/where-is-the-value.html&quot;&gt;“Where is the value?”&lt;/a&gt;: Creative destruction and ecosystems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In part one, I highlighted four drivers that will result in creative destruction in the healthcare IT industry:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Creative 2/3: The value of software for healthcare</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creative 2/3: The value of software for healthcare" /><published>2018-05-06T10:09:09+01:00</published><updated>2018-05-06T10:09:09+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html">&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;part one, I highlighted four drivers that will result in creative destruction&lt;/a&gt; in the healthcare IT industry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first was the recognition that software and data are critical enablers of clinical quality improvement, service transformation and advancing our knowledge (research).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second was that the best way to build healthcare software is to adopt the behaviours, processes and culture from the most highly productive technology companies. This means adopting quality improvement and research methodologies to develop, test and deploy the software that use to improve our clinical quality, service and research endeavours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third was the importance of separating data storage and transmission from the software operating on those data, with a shared domain language uniting multi-disciplinary cross-functional, semi-autonomous teams creating discrete, carefully bounded components with loose coupling with other components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth was the recognition of a transformation in software engineering practices with the increasing adoption of cloud and serverless technologies, permitting the development and commodification of components of what will become, a distributed and patient-centred logical electronic health record. The end result? A variety of interoperable applications, both clinical and administrative indeed, focused on workflow and usually task-orientated, making use of that shared health platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In [, part two covers the importance of software in our efforts to transform clinical services and improve quality.]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;software-and-healthcare&quot;&gt;Software and healthcare&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Software is eating the world.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424053111903480904576512250915629460&quot;&gt;Marc Andreeson&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Every industry that is not bringing software to the core of their business will be disrupted.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Jeffrey Immelt, CEO and Chairman, General Electric, 2001-2017&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I truly believe that software is critical to the future of healthcare, in supporting both patients and health professionals in their respective roles. Current software usually does little but replace existing paper processes but we should be aiming to use software to transform our health services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our clinical quality improvement and service transformation endeavours must be supported by new technology, by software and data, to support our efforts to effect change and measure the outcomes of that change in a virtuous cycle of continuous improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such continuous improvement requires us to be able to rapidly develop, test, integrate and deploy software. That software could be hand-coded or be the product of machine learning; whatever the case, it needs to be developed, tested, integrated and deployed continuously monitored to ensure it works safely and reliably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we confident that we have the right culture and architecture in order to do that, because if we don’t, won’t we need to transform our organisations, our culture and our technical architecture to support those needs?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, we must recognise that our technology, quality improvement and research endeavours are best considered as related and mutually supportive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/tech-qual-research.png&quot; alt=&quot;The relationship between technology, quality improvement and research&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quality improvement relies on measurement, analysis and action and therefore most effectively supported by the provision of digital tools to those who wish to transform their services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, development and deployment of technology should, itself, be subject to the same approach to quality improvement so that we develop, test, measure, analyse and deploy in the same virtuous cycle of &lt;em&gt;continuous&lt;/em&gt; improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/devops-qi.png&quot; alt=&quot;Devops Qi&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, &lt;em&gt;research&lt;/em&gt;, a process to advance our knowledge, requires very similar but more robust and formal protocols and oversight. But technology can help us here, supporting our decision making when in situations of genuine equipoise by providing transformative technology supporting identification, recruitment and randomisation of patients into complex, multi-arm trials currently require manual labour-intensive work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;metrics-of-success&quot;&gt;Metrics of success&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must admit that our work will &lt;em&gt;never be complete&lt;/em&gt;. As a result, whether we are talking about our clinical services, our technology or our research, we should never use metrics that simply talk about &lt;em&gt;deployment&lt;/em&gt;, but instead consider &lt;em&gt;outcomes&lt;/em&gt; and our efforts should be focused on improving those &lt;em&gt;outcomes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many others, NHS Wales currently uses deployment as a metric for success, but we need to change the conversation to &lt;em&gt;value&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;outcome&lt;/em&gt; and shift to adopting the best industry practices for creating safe, reliable and valuable clinical software &lt;em&gt;at pace&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html&quot;&gt;part three&lt;/a&gt;, I talk about the importance of technical and information standards, standardised application programming interfaces and frameworks to create &lt;em&gt;ecosystems&lt;/em&gt; of interoperating smaller, well-defined contextually domain bound components sharing the same platform. &lt;a href=&quot;(/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html)&quot;&gt;Continue reading…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;posts-in-this-series&quot;&gt;Posts in this series&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/cloud-ehr.html&quot;&gt;Part one: creative destruction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;Part two: the value of software for healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html&quot;&gt;Part three: ecosystems and the platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/04/26/lean-healthcare-devops.html&quot;&gt;“Lean healthcare” &lt;/a&gt;: Value stream: transforming health and care technology implementations using lean, agile, “DevOps” and serverless with small, cross-functional teams.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/30/where-is-the-value.html&quot;&gt;“Where is the value?”&lt;/a&gt;: Creative destruction and ecosystems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;single-patient-record&quot;&gt;a&lt;/a&gt;:The single patient record is a good idea - a logical single source-of-truth that is the canonical repository of information. Except, i) there is no truth in healthcare so you are better with models of uncertainty and ii) a medical record must be faceted so that it is possible to regulate access to different categories of information such as source (e.g. provider) and type (e.g. sexual or reproductive health matters, mental health, genetics, general medical etc). But, for now, “single patient record” is a useful pragmatic label.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In part one, I highlighted four drivers that will result in creative destruction in the healthcare IT industry:</summary></entry></feed>