<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.wardle.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.wardle.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-03-12T22:39:58+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/</id><title type="html">Dr. Mark Wardle</title><subtitle>Consultant Neurologist, clinical informatics, entrepreneur and software developer.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">What would I do if I were Google for health?</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What would I do if I were Google for health?" /><published>2017-03-09T10:05:10+00:00</published><updated>2017-03-09T10:05:10+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/09/google-information.html">&lt;p&gt;Google was created in 1998 with a mission statement:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“to organise the world’s information and make it universally accessible and useful”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember using Gopher for hypertext then switching to using the Mosaic web browser on Athena workstations on starting University in 1993, and then searching the web using Altavista in 1995. When Google was launched, most early internet users quickly switched for its fast and accurate search.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google has diversified since those halcyon days and the establishment of Alphabet as its parent company reflects this diversification into areas of technology such as self-driving cars, mobile devices including the Android platform, and even drone delivery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand that the original mission statement is under review and that is understandable when one considers the range and breadth of Alphabet’s interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I think the mission statement is exactly right for healthcare and we need to, as a health community, emphasise the importance of making the right information available to clinical professionals and our patients at the right time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;google-deepmind&quot;&gt;Google Deepmind&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am particularly interested in the current Deepmind push into healthcare. Indeed, &lt;a href=&quot;https://deepmind.com/applied/deepmind-health/&quot;&gt;Deepmind Health&lt;/a&gt; has announced collaborations with the Royal Free Hospital for the automatic computer-aided identification of acute kidney injury and with Moorfields Eye Hospital to use machine learning to automate the analysis of optical coherence tomography (OCT) scans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application &lt;a href=&quot;https://deepmind.com/applied/deepmind-health/streams/&quot;&gt;Streams&lt;/a&gt; is an important push to deploy applications running on mobile devices within the NHS. I think this is the most important result of their work; the fact that it is screening for acute kidney injury is simply a good choice of proof-of-concept. The greatest benefit is proving that a mixed economy of mobile applications that interoperate using data standards and standard application programming interfaces is not only possible but provides important advantages over the usual monolithic application architecture that is usually employed within a single organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is therefore logical that Deepmind Health should adopt, with vigour, the original mantra of Google at its own conception; to paraphrase:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To organise healthcare and patient information and make it universally accessible and useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;when-i-see-a-patient&quot;&gt;When I see a patient…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I quote in my &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html&quot;&gt;clinical design document&lt;/a&gt; from the legendary Larry Weed, in relation to the medical record:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“You’re a victim of it or a triumph because of it. The human mind simply cannot carry all the information without error so the record becomes part of your practice.”
Dr Larry Weed, Internal Medicine Grand Rounds, 1971&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have an abstract view of the “medical record”. To me, a medical record is all of the information pertaining to a patient that is useful in looking after the patient. At the moment, most clinicians use a myriad of different sources of information: the patient him or herself, carers and relatives, paper records as well as electronic systems. Early computerisation of laboratory and radiology systems means that most clinicians use electronic systems for these types of results, but most use paper for the narrative record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my own organisation, we have a range of systems, one of which I designed and built myself: the PatientCare suite of applications. In addition, we have access to a “digital health record” which is used to scan in paper records and make these available in a relatively unstructured way in an online browser. While this solves problems for medical records departments and allows a view of the record from multiple locations without having to track the notes, those data are not usable in any reasonable way: they are scanned documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important conclusion is that clinicians are faced with an information overload of unstructured information and few tools on hand to make sense of that information for a patient, or indeed group of patients, under their care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;supporting-clinicians-with-intelligent-computing&quot;&gt;Supporting clinicians with intelligent computing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a patient with motor neurone disease, I need to know several important pieces of information, including an indication of the severity of their disease, social circumstances, issues relating to feeding and weight, gastrostomy insertion and complications as well as their respiratory function. The key is that all of these pieces of information help me to help the patient at that point in time. It is no surprise that I extract all of this information in a disease-specific dashboard as part of my PatientCare electronic patient record:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/mnd-dashboard.png&quot; alt=&quot;MND dashboard&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, this information is extracted from a range of locations within the electronic record. The use of SNOMED CT means that computationally, we can simply ask “does this patient have a gastrostomy?”. In the logic to determine this, we look for procedures for the insertion and removal of gastrostomy and can therefore determine whether a gastrostomy is in-situ at any given time point. It doesn’t matter whether the gastrostomy is placed via a percutaneous endoscopic procedure (PEG), a radiologically-inserted gastrostomy (RIG) or even a surgical gastrostomy, because we can use the structures within SNOMED CT to make logical inferences about a type of procedure irrespective of how it is recorded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intelligent computing can work effectively if there is a coded and structured medical record. Historically, healthcare computing has been about supporting the administration of healthcare facilities and not supporting healthcare. The natural conclusion is that we need to improve our prospective longitudinal recording of structured information within the healthcare record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that the Deepmind Streams project could be much more powerful if it had structured information about medications, changes to medications, procedures and diagnoses at its disposal, and not simply, as I suspect, the raw data from the laboratory about renal function. Indeed, I understand that currently the Streams project is more about proving the idea of integrating a third-party application within the NHS than any use of artificial intelligence at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;patient-data-information-governance-and-confidentiality&quot;&gt;Patient data, information governance and confidentiality&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it easy to justify accessing a patient record. They are normally sitting in front of me at the time - I am their physician and I try to help them as much as I can. This is direct care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also manage local services and so use aggregated data in order to ensure my services are working effectively and safely. We frequently anonymise these data for aggregation purposes, but as we’re managing a service, and I’m working for an NHS organisation, there is usually no difficulty in using these data. This is secondary use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I am involved in research in which patients have explicitly consented for their data to be used as part of one of our observational, epidemiological or interventional studies. With explicit consent, I have no difficulty in using those data, usually anonymised, in the process of scientific research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information governance is frequently used as a reason to prevent sharing of information between organisations but this is difficult to justify. The important thing is what patients themselves would think and, whether they think it is reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commercial for-profit companies providing or supporting health care are subject to the same information governance rules. However, the media and public view commercial entities with suspicion - what will happen to patient data? In most cases, such suspicion is not justified, but examples such as the furore surrounding the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.england.nhs.uk/ourwork/tsd/care-data/&quot;&gt;care.data&lt;/a&gt; NHS England project demonstrate the issues at hand. A single misstep in either the use of data, the perceived use of data or lack of clarity surrounding either has the potential to close down any programme, however innovative. The debacle with care.data risks future projects to use patient data for the good. The Deepmind Streams project has already received &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-36783521&quot;&gt;criticism from patient and privacy groups&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-do-i-want-from-google-deepmind&quot;&gt;What do I want from Google Deepmind?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Artificial intelligence (AI) has amazing potential for taking information from disparate sources and present and analyse data in order to support clinical decision makers improving patient safety and care. Not only can we plan to bring together the right information at the right time, but make logical inferences from those data in order to improve patient care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are at an early stage of development and so it is vital that there is a robust framework in which such technologies can be tested and evaluated in a safe way. It is vital that AI is introduced within a quality improvement framework. Controversial deployments of AI such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/hospital-stumbles-in-bid-to-teach-a-computer-to-treat-cancer-1488969011?mod=e2tw&quot;&gt;IBM Watson - MD Anderson cancer project&lt;/a&gt;, which have ended in failure risking public and media support for the introduction of AI into healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want the most valuable and useful data accessible to me when I am looking after patients. Google Deepmind should be asking the same question: how can they best obtain those data in order to progress their individual mission: “Solve intelligence, use it to make the world a better place”. The answers are the same:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-make-more-structured-data-available&quot;&gt;1. Make more structured data available&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need robust interoperability, a focus on data standards and real-time, clinician led structured data capture. The fantastic &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.interopen.org/interop-summit&quot;&gt;interoperability summit&lt;/a&gt; on 2-3rd March 2017 demonstrated an enthusiasm and energy from those interested in clinical informatics in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;build-an-effective-open-source-toolchain&quot;&gt;Build an effective open-source toolchain&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, there are difficulties: a lack of tools for system suppliers, small enterprises and mobile app developers in order to make most effective use of such standards. I have released an open-source SNOMED CT terminology server in order to try to make these tools commodity items; essentially the foundation on which more innovative clinical solutions can be built. We need more. We need disruptive technologies that will lower the barrier for entry for start-ups and innovators into the health application marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would argue that we as a community should be working on a complete open-source software stack that can provide core platform functionality including integration with existing systems such as those relating to patient administration, laboratory and radiology. However, at its core are the tools necessary to rapidly and effectively build solutions to create and store structured healthcare data. We need to make the building-blocks of health applications freely available so that innovation can add value to patients and health professionals. For too long, any startup enterprise has had to begin by building the roads on which they will drive, before they can build the vehicles of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;build-an-interoperability-infrastructure&quot;&gt;Build an interoperability infrastructure&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regions where there is already large existing infrastructure, the platform could be installed as only an integration engine, bringing together information from existing services. As such, developers of user-facing applications and those who wish to support clinical care by using computer algorithms and artificial intelligence, can be used in any organisation in which the integration engine exists.  Much like an open-source version of Google’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://enterprise.google.com/search/products/gsa.html&quot;&gt;search appliances&lt;/a&gt; for health, we would be able to liberate data from proprietary systems, creating an open health data repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am building a FHIR-based microservice around our hospital PAS presently; it provides a proprietary, non-standard SOAP API for client applications. I’m going to do the same for our regional enterprise master patient index; it simply needs to create a FHIR end-point and wrap a HL7 PDQ call. It is not difficult to do but there are many such systems around, all of which need integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;natural-language-processing&quot;&gt;Natural language processing&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, there is an enormous amount of data held in clinical correspondence. We have need to make this information more accessible; there are already commercial solutions that use natural language processing to release structured data from narrative textual descriptions of clinical course and progress. Other divisions within Google have extensive experience of natural language processing, and these tools should be introduced and evaluated to make information accessible and useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-ensure-a-robust-framework-in-place-to-satisfy-public-perceptions&quot;&gt;2. Ensure a robust framework in place to satisfy public perceptions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, it is not possible to freely liberate health data and make it openly available. Instead, there must be appropriate governance and data flow arrangements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several options. Firstly, Deepmind’s current course takes an organisation-by-organisation approach, starting with small projects and iterating and proving the concepts. This is sensible initially but successful roll-out to other organisations will be slow and tortuous. For each organisation, an organisation must adopt Deepmind as a data controller. I would argue that the resulting infrastructure may be patchy and difficult to integrate, particularly when trying to work across organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second is to focus on explicitly consenting adults and create relationships with academic researchers, many of whom have large cohorts of well-phenotyped patients with outcome measures and highly-structured data. We have detailed longitudinal data on our patients with multiple sclerosis, Parkinson’s disease and motor neurone disease for example. There are parallels with the academic &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nature.com/openresearch/about-open-access/open-data/&quot;&gt;open data movement&lt;/a&gt; in which researchers share their data, code and methods with others in order to support reproducible research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third approach is to put the patient at the centre of the strategy. Apple’s ResearchKit has provided an open-source framework that makes it trivial to have patients sign-up and consent to research and complete patient-reported outcome measures. This is however, only a small piece of the jigsaw but it does conceptually mark a shift from targeting applications at health professionals to putting the patient at the centre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple’s ResearchKit does not solve where the resulting data is stored or how to make the most effective use of such data in a busy clinical environment or indeed, avoid the creation of multiple data silos. In addition, that framework is bound to the Apple device ecosystem, and my own experience has shown that we need a multimodal approach to data capture for patients: young patients with epilepsy may use their own devices but an elderly cohort of patients with Parkinson’s disease benefitted from supervised use of a shared tablet device actually in the outpatient clinic in our study. No framework should require devices from only a single vendor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;distributed-patient-control&quot;&gt;Distributed patient control&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, I would make a push for creating a distributed system to give individual patients control. In this, we design a framework in which patients control an account for recording explicit consent and logging health record access. This account provides pseudonymous data-linkage services so that one service cannot necessarily find out to what other services the patient is registered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in the United Kingdom, all patients have an NHS number. When a patient attends a healthcare organisation in the UK, that organisation can independently generate a pseudonym based on a mathematical hash of the NHS number and their organisation- or service-specific salt and register for access against the patient’s own consent account. For NHS organisations, a record access log entry can be made using this unique identifier. For research projects, the log entry records the request which can be subsequently shown to the patient with information about the project encrypted using the patient’s own private key: explicit consent results in the recording of that consent in the ledger. The ledger then becomes a distributed transactional record of record access and consent. Before a research project accesses a record, it can make a request using the known patient data, generating its own hash of those data, and makes a request to the distributed consent ledger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I write (9/3/17), Deepmind have announced work on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://deepmind.com/blog/trust-confidence-verifiable-data-audit/&quot;&gt;verifiable audit log&lt;/a&gt; in order to safely log the access and use of data, computing incremental hashes of the data as it is added so that it is possible to demonstrate, without doubt, that the data has not been changed at a later date point. It uses a nested tree design called Merkle trees but this is simply a optimisation to limit the computational requirements whenever data is added. Presently, I understand that this is designed to be a centralised record. Such centralisation means that potentially, whoever controls the ledger can change the ledger, simply by re-computing the hashes of the data to reflect the change. Computationally, this may be inefficient, but the verifiable log only becomes verifiable when the ledger is held by a trusted party. For the Deepmind collaboration, I would imagine the NHS organisation holds the ledger while Google writes to it. As such, the organisation can vouch that no log has been changed or deleted inappropriately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One key advantage of Merkle trees is in the ability to support the synchronisation of data by allowing the rapid identification of which data has been synchronised across a distributed system and which has not. Indeed, this approach is used in distributed databases such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://cassandra.apache.org&quot;&gt;Apache Cassandra&lt;/a&gt; to do just that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would therefore suggest that we as an interoperability community work towards developing an open-source distributed consent and log framework which is held securely by multiple trusted health organisations. By distributing and synchronising such data among multiple trusted parties, one can offer guarantees that no single organisation can make a change without it being identified by all other organisations, or indeed by the patient or their proxy. A holder of the ledger, and there could be many, cannot themselves re-identify the patients within as a result of the use of multiple service-specific pseudonymous identifiers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-worked-example&quot;&gt;A worked example&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A patient has a NHS number 111 111 1111. Their year of birth is 1975. A public and private key is generated for the patient at registration. This private key is used to encrypt information within the patient’s ledger but is itself encrypted using the patient’s password. If the patient changes their access password, then only the private key need be re-encrypted with the new password.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summary care record is generated from the general practitioner’s record - these data, including core diagnoses and medications are recorded against a unique identifier computed as a hash of the NHS number, the year of birth and a salt unique to the national summary care record service for that patient : a service-specific salt. Within a distributed ledger, the description of this service, the core data and a link to an end-point service providing more data is encrypted using the patient’s public key. As such, using one of potentially many third-party services, a patient could login to their account, access the information in their ledger and importantly, see who has accessed their record and choose those organisations or services who may see their record. An organisation holding the ledger cannot identify the patients within, or indeed, determine to which services or research projects any logs relate. Individual services who can generate a pseudonym using the appropriate recipe can consult the ledger, write to that ledger and determine patient consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3--encourage-a-mixed-economy-of-healthcare-applications&quot;&gt;3.  Encourage a mixed-economy of healthcare applications.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NHS organisations that tend to procure large-scale enterprise-wide clinical information systems such as Cerner’s Millennium platform or Epic limiting the scope for innovation and small to medium enterprises to interoperate and add value. The current environment within the NHS for small and medium sized enterprises is difficult. There are many procurement rules and even when an enterprise can sell to customers, deployment within the NHS is difficult. Hosting services within the NHS N3 are expensive and integrating with existing systems difficult. My final request for Google Deepmind, is to make the case for small, well-defined applications that interoperate with the wider data economy. Proving the effectiveness of this approach is difficult for those of us trying to create those applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Junior doctors use their own devices for communication within their teams in order to manage their workload. Why is it so difficult to contemplate creating a medical application that can provide similar functionality, but ensure that patient-relating communication is recorded against the patient’s record? We need to encourage and foster innovation within NHS information technology.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Google was created in 1998 with a mission statement:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Thinking about medications</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/08/thinking-about-medications.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thinking about medications" /><published>2017-03-08T22:11:00+00:00</published><updated>2017-03-08T22:11:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/08/thinking-about-medications</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/08/thinking-about-medications.html">&lt;p&gt;Handling medications in clinical medicine is difficult. One of the easy wins for information technology in medicine is electronic prescribing. Our colleagues in general practice have had such systems for many years but those of us working in hospitals have lagged behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In hospital, many of us prescribe on paper prescriptions – sometimes I use a proper prescription when I am starting a drug that is hospital-only – on most occasions, hospital doctors now write a GP communication note or simply add the recommendation to a clinical letter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is tremendous value in electronic prescribing. It is one of the quick-wins for information technology in healthcare. There are many advantages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advantages-of-keeping-track-of-medications-electronically&quot;&gt;Advantages of keeping track of medications electronically&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, keeping track of patients is critical. If you are non-medical, you might think that once you are under ongoing follow-up with a hospital doctor, there is some automatic system to let us know that you missed your last appointment or that your appointment was cancelled. In fact, you’d assume we also had a system to track your diagnoses so that we could potentially find all of our patients with, say, Parkinson’s disease. Sadly, this isn’t common; the way many clinicians handle this is to keep a spreadsheet with names and diagnoses or use something like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theabn.org/what-we-do/bnsu.html&quot;&gt;British Neurological Surveillance Unit (BNSU)&lt;/a&gt; to report rare cases seen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a number of patients with a range of disorders on high-dose corticosteroids. Similarly, I have patients on other immunotherapy drugs (e.g. methotrexate) for whom I need to know that their blood monitoring is performed appropriately and that their blood indices are stable. For me, knowing a) who those patients are and b) when I last saw them, are critical for patient-safety. Too often, we avoid disaster simply through good fortune rather than any systematic approach to patient safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-patientcare-web-application&quot;&gt;The PatientCare web application&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here in Cardiff, we now use a patient electronic health record system to track all such diagnostic, treatment, interventional and outcome data. I have been developing it since 2009 and we now have over 15,000 patients recorded. It is accessed across Wales, mainly for neurological diseases, but we also track a number of rare diseases. Many of these rare disorders are rare individually, but collectively, they are common! There is a sophisticated access-control mechanism into which groups of patients and groups of clinical staff are linked by virtue of clinical services or research projects, so that access is limited to the group of patients to which you are responsible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Topics to be covered in future blog posts are information governance and a detailed guide on how to implement SNOMED-CT. Both difficult but both solved!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;electronic-prescribing-and-the-nhs&quot;&gt;Electronic prescribing and the NHS&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start thinking about electronic prescribing and recording of current and past medication, I suggest you first have a look at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nhsbsa.nhs.uk/1121.aspx&quot;&gt;NHS DM&amp;amp;D (dictionary of medicines and devices)&lt;/a&gt; and a good look at the implementation guidance. There are a number of complexities. In hospital, we are encouraged to prescribe using generic drug names rather than branded drug names. This means that “prescribing” is a distinct process to dispensing. In hospital, the dispensing is performing by a nurse on the ward and a pharmacist for outpatients. Dispensing turns the generic prescription into an appropriate formulation. There are a number of issues to consider during dispensing including differences between formulations (actual medicinal products – AMPs) and issues of cost. Most hospital doctors are not used to selecting appropriate formulations and instead prescribe by generic drug name and dose. A general practitioner prescribes using products. For more information on this,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a hospital doctor may prescribe “ramipril 7.5mg od”. This means the patient should receive 7.5mg of this drug once per day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A general practitioner would prescribe “ramipril 5mg 1 tablet od” and “ramipril 2.5mg 1 tablet od”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are additional complexities. For instance, some hospital clinicians wish to prescribe by product because of differences between formulations. For example, many of us who work with patients with epilepsy prescribe “epilim chrono”. While the active ingredient is sodium valproate, different products may vary in terms of bioavailability / absorption and so we would not want our patient’s medications to be swapped around – imagine a situation in which a generic formulation is substituted in a patient who is seizure free and the substitution results in a seizure when the patient is driving!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another issue is that medication data is already held in general practitioner systems and so it should be possible to import that list of current and past medications into hospital systems automatically. Having different implementations / models of electronic prescribing in primary and secondary care complicates such automatic import and export of medications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The NHS DM&amp;amp;D implementation guidance suggests a 3-step prescribing process for each drug. Step 1 is specifying the drug and the route (e.g. oral, inhaled, intravenous). Step 2 involves reviewing the rules for that specific drug and step 3 involves identifying appropriate sub-types of that medication for safe prescribing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you might imagine, this is quite an involved and potentially time-consuming process. However, prescribing is potentially dangerous and should be performed with caution and careful consideration. However, different degrees of rigour are required depending on whether the electronic record is acting as a prescription or simply an electronic record of what the patient is taking or an advice letter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in outpatient clinic, most clinicians will want to quickly record the current and past medications so that we can easily answer questions like “Which anticonvulsant therapies have we already tried in this patient?”. As such, the strict rigour of an electronic prescribing system can be relaxed depending on use-case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-implementation&quot;&gt;My implementation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve implemented a system to rapidly enter an existing list of medications and make changes to that medication list. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/3tRyjJk-71M&quot;&gt;PatientCare medication entry&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/F2LSHpdCPvo&quot;&gt;Advanced medication entry&lt;/a&gt; for two video demonstrations. Here we enter a list of medications which are automatically mapped into SNOMED-CT DM&amp;amp;D drugs. There is a semantic understanding for drugs so that programmatically, we can tell whether a patient is on a thiazide diuretic or anticonvulsant – ie. this is not simply a free-text list! In addition, there is dose equivalence so that the system recognises that 1000mg is the same as 1g etc. Once the list is edited, the software calculates the changes – drugs changed, started, stopped etc. and then applies those changes to the longitudinal record of medication so that there is a complete list of all current and past medications that have been used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a balance of speed and efficiency for expert users and hand-holding for beginners. As such, there is an older pick-list based system which allows users to add drugs manually using drop-downs controls. However, expert users should be allowed to follow a more efficient process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This balance requires careful planning to ensure process safety and yet remain quick and usable in a busy outpatient clinic or in the assessment unit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The result&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only do I now record diagnostic information for my patients (SNOMED-CT coding) but it is now feasible to record all current and past treatments. Such information is very helpful for a range of conditions including Parkinson’s disease and epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, because the software recognises that some drugs are unchanged, some have been stopped and some have been started, we can now automatically generate summary reports of encounters. This results in a huge reduction in administrative support requirements as rather than dictating medication changes, the computer does it automatically and in a well-presented summary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Handling medications in clinical medicine is difficult. One of the easy wins for information technology in medicine is electronic prescribing. Our colleagues in general practice have had such systems for many years but those of us working in hospitals have lagged behind.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">SNOMED CT terminology server</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/08/rsterminology.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="SNOMED CT terminology server" /><published>2017-03-08T21:39:10+00:00</published><updated>2017-03-08T21:39:10+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/08/rsterminology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/03/08/rsterminology.html">&lt;p&gt;SNOMED CT is a modern, comprehensive medical terminology. For a detailed understanding of SNOMED CT, please see Chapter 4 in my &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html&quot;&gt;clinical design document&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key issue with SNOMED CT is an effective implementation. A good implementation, in my opinion, results in a system in which users do not actually know that they are using a terminology system at all. It should be intuitive and most importantly, usable from a clinical point-of-view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been using SNOMED CT since 2009. I think my electronic health record system (PatientCare) was the first deployed system in the UK to use SNOMED CT. SNOMED CT is the lingua franca within the system, internally the application and its business logic layers make ubiquitous use of SNOMED CT to make inferences about the care of a patient and to update the user interface to enable or disable functionality depending on the data entered so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, while one can bolt-on SNOMED CT as a terminology as an after-thought, it is preferable to design systems from the ground up to use and understand SNOMED CT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this doesn’t mean every system needs to re-implement SNOMED CT from the ground up. Indeed, I’d suggest using my new &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/wardle/rsterminology&quot;&gt;SNOMED CT terminology microservice&lt;/a&gt;. This provides very fast browse and search function as well as subsumption so that one can ask whether, given a diagnosis of progressive bulbar palsy, does a patient have a type of motor neurone disease, and get “yes” as the answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also provides an electronic prescribing function for real-time natural language parsing of prescriptions. There is more work to do, and I continue to work on new developments including round-tripping from VTMs to VMPs and AMPs with automatic dose calculations and support for automatic natural language post-coordination. Post-coordination is, in my opinion, in scope of the information model in which SNOMED CT terms are used, but automatic NLP-based post-coordination will make entry more intuitive for the user.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">SNOMED CT is a modern, comprehensive medical terminology. For a detailed understanding of SNOMED CT, please see Chapter 4 in my clinical design document.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Supporting clinical care</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/02/18/supporting-clinic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Supporting clinical care" /><published>2017-02-18T10:16:10+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-18T10:16:10+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/02/18/supporting-clinic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/02/18/supporting-clinic.html">&lt;p&gt;Clinical information systems should support patient care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We generate our clinical correspondence from data. This is, unusually, the opposite of what almost everyone else does when they get data from correspondence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to prepare a full video as a demonstration, but for now I will link to a series of tweets that demonstrate this functionality in the clinic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we give the &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mwardle/status/833062051283136518&quot;&gt;patient an iPad in clinic&lt;/a&gt;. The same infrastructure and platform will be used for patient-held devices, but for now, we use clinic-based applications. This uses Apple’s ResearchKit software. However, the clever thing here is the use of SNOMED CT. The application derives semantic understanding of the patient’s problems from the electronic health record and queues the correct questionnaires for that patient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, if that patient has already indicated that they don’t wish to be involved in research, it won’t ask them again, but if not, they will be asked to consent for appropriate research projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We used to use paper questionnaires. These were duly completed and then filed, not to be used. In addition, paper questionnaires can’t adapt to what has been entered. Here, the iPad applicaton &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mwardle/status/833063821828878336&quot;&gt;queues a different set of questions based on the responses so far&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, while there is excitement about the use of patient’s own devices and patient reported outcomes, what is the point of those data if they cannot be used for clinical care? Here, the data entered by the patient is immediately presented to the clinician and is &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mwardle/status/833064699977691137&quot;&gt;automatically incorporated into the clinic letter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll notice in the last video, I also tweak the current medication list (mapped to the NHS dictionary of medicines and devices) and those changes appear in our correspondence automatically.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Clinical information systems should support patient care.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Multiple sclerosis</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/multiple-sclerosis/2017/02/12/new-ms-portal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Multiple sclerosis" /><published>2017-02-12T10:16:10+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-12T10:16:10+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/multiple-sclerosis/2017/02/12/new-ms-portal</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/multiple-sclerosis/2017/02/12/new-ms-portal.html">&lt;p&gt;I’m delighted to announce the release of my new data-linkage pseudonymous patient portal &lt;a href=&quot;https://msdata.org.uk&quot;&gt;msdata.org.uk&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings the full power of my existing electronic patient record (EPR) - currently hosted and only accessible within NHS Wales - to the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, no patient identifiable information is stored, but instead, the system acts as a data-linkage platform, allowing information entered from patient-held devices and clinicians outside of Wales to be brought into the EPR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, one can see how many relapses a patient has had due to multiple sclerosis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/msdata-relapses.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MS relapses&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Importantly, while we have over 20,000 patients registered with a variety of disorders, wouldn’t it be useful to show clinicians and the patient how they are progressing compared to patients with the same disorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, while there are lots of SNOMED-CT concepts that mean the same as “multiple sclerosis”, it is possible to use the SNOMED-CT hierarchy to derive semantic understanding of the relationships between terms. In this way, we can easily find patients with say, a type of motor neurone disease, even if they have been recorded as having “progressive bulbar palsy”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here, we chart a single patient’s progress over the years compared to a whole population-based cohort of patients’ progress. The median progress of the whole cohort is shown with a dotted green line. Just like a growth chart for a baby, a patient crossing the centile charts is either doing better or worse than expected. The EDSS is a score of disability in multiple sclerosis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/edss-graph.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;MS progress&quot; class=&quot;img-responsive&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an added bonus, we can chart the use of disease-modifying treatments as well.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I’m delighted to announce the release of my new data-linkage pseudonymous patient portal msdata.org.uk.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Domain-driven design in clinical informatics</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Domain-driven design in clinical informatics" /><published>2017-02-03T10:16:10+00:00</published><updated>2017-02-03T10:16:10+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/clinical-informatics/2017/02/03/domain-driven-design.html">&lt;p&gt;I have written this document to explain my thoughts on the most appropriate way to design and clinical information systems that valuably support the process of healthcare.  As such, it includes a methodology for creating software for use by clinicians,  managers  and  administrators  to  support  both  the  day-to-day  care  of patients and the management of services for groups of patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I divide the “process of healthcare” into three core themes which are related and inter-dependent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The ‘day-to-day’ care of a single patient; data relates to a single individual.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The management, audit and governance of clinical services; data relates togrouped, aggregated patient data and is service-specific.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supporting clinical research;  data relating to a patient’s suitability for research projects as well as enrolment, consent and research-level data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The complete document is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/62sg71a19voxpts/cis_design.pdf?dl=0&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I have written this document to explain my thoughts on the most appropriate way to design and clinical information systems that valuably support the process of healthcare. As such, it includes a methodology for creating software for use by clinicians, managers and administrators to support both the day-to-day care of patients and the management of services for groups of patients.</summary></entry></feed>