<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.wardle.org/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.wardle.org/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-12-21T09:42:22+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/</id><title type="html">Health informatics and information technology</title><subtitle>by Dr Mark Wardle, Consultant Neurologist, clinical informatics and software developer. Founder, Eldrix Ltd.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Coherence in governance</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/12/21/coherent-governance.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coherence in governance" /><published>2019-12-21T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-12-21T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/12/21/coherent-governance</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/12/21/coherent-governance.html">&lt;p&gt;Our ability to adopt, deploy and improve technology is fundamental in our mission to build a health and care system that works seamlessly, for patients, families and staff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means building services that span organisational, disciplinary, geographical and care boundaries so that, for example, as a patient, you don’t receive an appointment for clinic at the same time as your appointment for an x-ray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We &lt;em&gt;must&lt;/em&gt; step back and re-imagine how health and care services can work with the technology now at our disposal, and that means focusing on the &lt;em&gt;outcomes&lt;/em&gt; we wish to deliver. One unifying outcome must surely be to create a truly &lt;em&gt;seamless service&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what must be our priorities in order to create such a &lt;em&gt;seamless services&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need an unerring focus on &lt;em&gt;user need&lt;/em&gt;, so that we design services that fundamentally put the patient at the centre and design through that perspective rather than one focused through the prism of an a single organisation or department.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We must improve our ability to adopt and deploy technology, by adopting best practices such as modularisation. Modularisation is the process in which a large problem is broken-up into smaller sized chunks, making it possible for a small team to fully understand the problem and fully own the solution to that problem, and permit rapid delivery by enabling parallel working and minimising the need for constant interaction and checking between those teams that would otherwise slow down our ability to continuously iterate and improve.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We must recognise the benefit of bringing diverse skills, experience and perspectives together to form cross-functional, multi-disciplinary teams who are trusted and empowered to understand and to solve these bite-sized problems. We need to avoid creating silos based on organisation, discipline or historic boundaries and instead understand ‘team-first’ boundaries aligned to business domains.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We must prioritise &lt;em&gt;meaningful data&lt;/em&gt;, and regard data and the computing services that operate on those data as first-class products that, when combined together, form a &lt;em&gt;cohesive&lt;/em&gt; open platform. Such work must be enabled by the adoption of open technical standards to define application programming interfaces (APIs) that act as technical contracts between those services.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;coherence-logical-and-consistent&quot;&gt;Coherence: “Logical and consistent”&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we want our work in technology to be logical and consistent, we must have an overall strategic vision which sets out, openly and transparently, a set of high-level broad principles and the rules, &lt;em&gt;guard-rails&lt;/em&gt; and design patterns that we will all use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s very easy to think that consistency can only be achieved by managing complex technology programmes with a centralised &lt;em&gt;command-and-control&lt;/em&gt; approach. Such an approach is naive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead we must look to devolve power from the centre while maintaining overall coherence by setting the broad direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We should be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Crossing the river by feeling the stones”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Deng Xiaoping&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means &lt;em&gt;empowering&lt;/em&gt; teams, to deliver, at pace and incrementally, by a range of measures including&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;being clear on overall strategic direction&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;understanding that the most difficult part of technology is not the technology itself, but the management of change -  in people, behaviour and the work itself that our best technology can empower&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;deciding on &lt;em&gt;appropriate&lt;/em&gt; modularisation and creating teams to deliver those products&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;aligning our governance, architecture and standards into a cohesive whole.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Governance structures, technical architecture and technical standards are mutually dependent; for example it is not possible to define coherent governance without understanding the technical architecture to which we aspire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-matrix-of-coherence&quot;&gt;A matrix of coherence&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need consistency across multiple domains. One way of thinking about structuring a coherent strategy is to consider two broad types of domain:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Business domains, aligning to business problems and their solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Functional domains, aligning to technology problems and their solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A business domain is a specific, tangible business problem, such as citizen identity. That problem might be solved through the provisioning of a range of coherent products, some bought off-the-shelf such as an enterprise master patient index, and some developed in-house, such as a microservice that acts to cache identity updates and provide a canonical authoritative source of demographics information via a FHIR Patient resource. It makes no sense to procure or develop products or services that aren’t &lt;em&gt;coherent&lt;/em&gt; with other products in this domain. &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#results-requests&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Domain-driven design is about designing data and computing services based on models of the business domain itself, with &lt;em&gt;bounded contexts&lt;/em&gt; a unit for breaking up a larger domain into smaller parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A functional domain is a specific, tangible technology domain, such as security engineering, system reliability engineering, infrastructure management, operations and user-centred design. Similarly, it will usually make little sense to not have a consistent approach to these core functional domains across a wider enterprise, although good judgement is needed to understand when to deviate in order to solve a specific problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This schematic shows business domains orientated vertically, and functional domains orientated horizontally as representing a set of coherent services providing an &lt;em&gt;open platform&lt;/em&gt; on which applications can run, with the use of an API gateway and a coherent scheme for authentication and authorisation on a per-application, per-user basis:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/domains-functional-and-business.png&quot; alt=&quot;Domains Functional And Business&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach should make it obvious that building security and logging at an application-level, as is currently the case in Wales, is a mistake, and data and computing services should be first-class products exposing their data and functionality through open service interfaces, via APIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;towards-technical-excellence---and-coherence-within-and-across-functional-domains&quot;&gt;Towards technical excellence - and coherence within and across functional domains&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, we need to aspire to technical excellence, with lead roles for experts in engineering and design, including security, software development, operations, infrastructure, standards and architecture, able to take a coherent “all-Wales” view and provide, openly and transparently, a set of guidelines and principles and design patterns that will shape our currently prioritised programmes of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means we need a separate programme of work to build and reward technical capability within health and care in Wales; for too long, the only way experienced engineers could progress was in management, and we have too many engineering teams led by managers with no technical skills or experience. Part of the blame must lie with the pay-scales within Agenda for Change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is convenient to think of technical experts grouped into guilds or tribes, sharing good practice and helping to contribute, openly and transparently, to a range of principles, standards and design patterns for their specific domain; such work providing core principles, design blueprints and support for programmes and the teams working on solving domain problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an approach doesn’t mean top-down control or even homogeneity. We must recognise that experts will need to deviate and innovate in order to solve real-life problems, and use that experience to feedback, inform and improve the guiding principles which we can all use. Through this, we build a continuously learning approach to technology. It is unlikely that a single technology stack or programming language would be appropriate across a complex system such as health and care, but we must endeavour to share good practice and harmonise our general approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This matrix approach to governance is shown in the following schematic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/coherent-governance.png&quot; alt=&quot;Coherent Governance&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The important features are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Long-lived but small cross-functional product teams&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multiple products grouped into dynamic and flexible programmes, created to meet our current and pending priorities.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Data and computing services as first-class products, creating an &lt;em&gt;open platform&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Functional domain experts providing all-Wales high-level principles, standards and design patterns on their domain, such as security, infrastructure, architecture and design as well as contributing to product teams when appropriate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;High-level overview board providing core high-level principles and oversight as well as responsibility for redefining the dynamic programme structure based on present needs, with membership drawn from clinical, managerial and technical experts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve already started some of this work via the Welsh Technical Standards Board; we have &lt;a href=&quot;https://standards.cymru/posts/2018-06-19-wtsb/&quot;&gt;adopted the GDS design principles&lt;/a&gt;, published our own &lt;a href=&quot;https://standards.cymru/posts/2018-12-01-wtsb/&quot;&gt;working principles&lt;/a&gt; and have submitted our &lt;a href=&quot;https://standards.cymru/posts/2019-10-29-architectural-principles/&quot;&gt;architectural principles&lt;/a&gt; for review. Through this, we want to inculcate debate, feedback and so transform our approach to health and care in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;results-requests&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;: We currently have an example in Wales in which a re-procurement of a laboratory management system is in one programme of work, and re-procurement of a radiology information system is in another. Both are considering including “test requesting” functionality and yet, for end-users, we want a seamless system that, in clinic or on the ward, allows us to request multiple &lt;em&gt;things&lt;/em&gt; including referrals, laboratory, radiology and other tests. We don’t want separate “systems” but instead what appears to be a streamlined “single system”. Therefore, programmes of work need to be framed with user need; one logical approach might be to consider “results and requests” as a business programme to manage a suite of products, that would include concierge services that take user requests and farm them to our different backend systems via APIs, as well as managing the re-procurement of laboratory and radiology services.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Our ability to adopt, deploy and improve technology is fundamental in our mission to build a health and care system that works seamlessly, for patients, families and staff.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning from building an electronic health record: a journey through data</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/ehr/2019/11/08/learning-from-creating-an-ehr.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning from building an electronic health record: a journey through data" /><published>2019-11-08T08:08:08+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-08T08:08:08+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/ehr/2019/11/08/learning-from-creating-an-ehr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/ehr/2019/11/08/learning-from-creating-an-ehr.html">&lt;p&gt;This blog post is based on a presentation given to the Welsh Medical Committee on 8th November 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the posts on this blog have focused on how we, as a clinical community in Wales, can use digital technology to drive improvements in our health and care services. The approach I have advocated, built on a foundation of open standards, interoperability with the provision of an open platform of data and computing services, has focused on the steps we need to take to improve the way we deliver technology in health and care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, this post is rather self-indulgent; it documents my own journey through health data science and the lessons I’ve learned, in building my own software systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lessons are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The importance of data in everything we do: whether that be in the direct care of individual patients, management of services and quality improvement and clinical research&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That software and data services are best delivered by breaking up bigger problems into smaller ones, and understanding that components used like this are &lt;em&gt;fractal&lt;/em&gt;, in which more complex, sophisticated problems can be solved by stitching together smaller components.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That the boundaries between direct care, service management and research are not the right boundaries to use when building software for health and care; instead model the legal and regulatory differences and modularise using domain-driven design principles.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;That our health and care teams across Wales are excited and enthused by technology, and want to improve; technology leaders should not be seeking to command-and-control this work, but provide toolboxes of computing and data services that can be used to solve problems. We should be setting the standards and principles and empowering teams to deliver.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;User problems (and needs) in health and care are usually about workflow and process, so once we have mechanisms for handling &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; and the way it is modelled, we can build software that works in different contexts. Think: not single applications giving views of different data (like we have now) but multiple applications giving views of the same data. This doesn’t mean you can’t have a style guide and user interface consistency via standards, and modular user-facing components so that users benefit from a toolbox of nationally-provided building blocks stitched together in different ways to suit their processes and workflows.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Software is our best way of acquiring, processing and making sense of data; that means being cognisant as to the architecture and governance that makes it possible for us to deliver safe, effective, high-quality software to users: that means needing &lt;em&gt;agility&lt;/em&gt;, building mechanisms for rapid, automated testing and deployment of software at pace.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need to build capabilities across health and care in software and data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Purchase of a commercial electronic health record, such as Cerner or Epic, means you need &lt;em&gt;greater&lt;/em&gt; capabilities in software and data; e.g. at the Wirral, their in-house developer team got &lt;em&gt;larger&lt;/em&gt; after purchase of Cerner because of the need to integrate and customise - in essence these software products are themselves &lt;em&gt;platforms&lt;/em&gt;, on which further valuable functionality can be built using the building blocks provided by that platform.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Many of the platform building blocks already exist in NHS Wales, and simply need modernisation. Platform components that don’t exist, such as off-the-shelf form designers, and components dealing with user interactions, can take advantage of modern generic technologic frameworks to build high-quality web-based and mobile-first applications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We don’t have all of the answers; either in technology or in healthcare - we need to build systems with fast-feedback so that we plan to continuously improve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;1-i-built-a-disease-specific-research-database&quot;&gt;1. I built a disease-specific research database.&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My doctoral research, undertaken during my higher training in neurology, started in 2005 and was focused on understanding the clinical features and disease progression of a range of rare neurological disorders: the ataxias, and in some cases drawing phenotype-genotype correlations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.003.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.003&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such research requires bringing together disparate data for analysis. The graphs show the effect of genetic changes on the onset of disease of a rare disorder.  I built an analytics pipeline that would run analyses automatically so that graphs and statistical tests would update immediately as I entered new data; that meant I was validating both the data and the software almost continuously, because errors would be evident immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are significant problems with a disease-specific database:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it usually exists alone; it creates a silo&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it might help to solve a specific problem but it doesn’t usually scale to solve new ones; it’s too specific.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we can’t easily make those data available to others; there were few governance or technical off-the-shelf solutions that make that possible. If we want data to be shared, we would need to rely on researchers to set-up mechanisms to do so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But amazingly, this is still the main way clinical research works - and single-disease charities continue to push “registries” as a solution in health and care. The typical approach for a registry is to build a web-based system that allows clinicians and researchers to submit data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.005.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.005&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s not to say a registry is a bad thing - but we need to recognise that the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; user need is defining a population of patients by virtue of a characteristic - a &lt;em&gt;cohort&lt;/em&gt;, and that might be diagnosis, symptom, clinical sign, procedure or intervention, and then usually collecting some specific additional information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We clearly need to be able to stratify patients like this, building systems that allow us to understand cohorts but the current approach to building registries is not the right approach and we need to ask charities to stop funding this broken model that ends up creating silos of data, and a workflow that isn’t embedded into clinical workflows. That means a registry of the make and model of breast implants is best delivered by ensuring data systems capture such information at the point-of-care, and instead we derive a “registry” at runtime based on shared characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.006.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.006&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;2-so-instead-i-built-a-generic-research-database&quot;&gt;2. So instead I built a generic research database&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recognised that &lt;em&gt;defining cohorts&lt;/em&gt; was critical, and started making SNOMED CT the lingua franca of my next system: a generic research database that went operational in 2007 - as far as I know the first system in the UK to use SNOMED CT in clinical operational use - it could combine generic and disease-specific outcome measures and permit multiple different “virtual” registries, derived at runtime by virtue of structured clinical data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.008.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.008&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here users can type in problems or diagnoses - each user interface control configured by a dynamic rules engine that is easy to change and modify. I can build forms dynamically without writing new code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/BUYvsMy-2EI&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.009.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.009&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SNOMED CT is an ontology: so that if a user enters, for example, a diagnostic term of “multiple sclerosis”, then computationally we know that it is a type of “demyelinating disease” and so we can derive cohorts of patients easily at any suitable level of granularity, either very specific or much more general. This works not only for diagnoses, but clinical characteristics, procedures interventions and even characteristics such as country of birth and ethnicity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LMaOL8Q8bzk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice how by virtue of SNOMED CT, the chosen list is grouped by region - “Born in China” is grouped under “Born in Asia” automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QcOoXOFJsBY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.010.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.010&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all cases, users don’t know that they are entering SNOMED CT; its use is invisible as terms are entered through drop-downs, autocompletion text fields and even clicking on anatomical diagrams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach to data is an important foundation in permitting the derivation of multiple “virtual” cohorts and understanding the meaning of outcome measures. After all, how can we interpret outcome measures without understanding the baseline characteristics such as diagnoses, co-morbidities, etc?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.012.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.012&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here we see the longitudinal outcome of two patients, shown by the red line on each of the charts, drawn in real-time, potentially using data entered only moments before, overlaid onto the longitudinal outcomes of thousands of other patients with the same diagnosis, again derived dynamically, at runtime. The median progress of the group is shown by the dotted green line together with lines representing centiles. EDSS is a scale from 0 to 10, in which 0 represents a patient without any clinical signs of disease, and 10 is death. We see one patient doing worse than expected, and another doing better. We can also see that the patient not deteriorating as expected received alemtuzumab therapy, shown graphically along with the outcome data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach shows the value of fast-feedback - making data &lt;em&gt;valuable&lt;/em&gt; and useful in reducing the uncertainty around a clinical decision - patients and professionals, for example, can use these charts to support shared decision making as to whether to start a high-cost, high-risk, low frequency but highly aggressive new therapy. Users enter data when it is made useful to them, and that applies to both professionals and patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to realise that we don’t yet know the best ways of presenting outcome data like this, either for professionals or patients,  to support such decision making - some of our work is to understand what is helpful and what is not - our mission is to make information available at the right time to the right people and we need to learn how to do this effectively for lots of different types of data. If we knew all of the answers, we could take a different approach to our digital technological endeavours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foundational software and data services, combined with an enthusiastic and high-performing team have advanced our understanding of, for example, multiple sclerosis. We gain insights through combining different types of data such as clinical outcomes, treatments and interventions with other data such as indices of socioeconomic deprivation; we build a more detailed understanding of individual patients and groups of patients through these different perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.013.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.013&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I ended up with a system to track outcomes and cohorts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.014.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.014&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But such an approach, while clearly valuable, still risks being something outside of the routine day-to-day workflow of our services; how can we do this at scale, unless data - its acquisition, synthesis and use - is part of how we do our daily work?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.015.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.015&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, general practitioners are years ahead of hospitals here: they’ve been collecting structured data and using that information to drive care; for instance, they have systems that ensure that patients with diabetes mellitus have an annual review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;3-so-i-worked-to-embed-data-in-workflows-it-became-an-electronic-health-record&quot;&gt;3. So, I worked to embed data in workflows; it became an electronic health record&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In moving from a generic research database to a system that supported the workflow and communication needs of our departments, I built an electronic health record. It now has over 50,000 patients and has tracked hundreds of thousands of patient contacts. It provides multiple interfaces: a web-based front-end, an iOS application and a FHIR based API.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what do we mean by “health record”, and is this an opportunity to really start to think about what we mean by a health and care record?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is Larry Weed in 1971:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.018.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.018&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our health record supports our practice. “We’re a victim of it or a triumph because of it”. This record is not simply a way of documenting our work; it is inherently a tool with which we carry out the practise of health and care, and digital technologies should be transforming that, for both professional and patient, because so much more is possible when we shake off our assumptions made in the paper era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paper records are expensive, poorly maintained, poorly accessible, do not support team working; they contain lots of data but not in a useful format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.017.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.017&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How many of us have supervised or performed paper notes review for audit and quality improvement purposes? Collecting piles of notes and going through them, trying to find the information we need? Technology should be helping us build a system that can continuously improve, by virtue of making the information we already collect useful and &lt;em&gt;valuable&lt;/em&gt;, and teaching us the measures that reduce our uncertainty about decisions, whether that be for an individual patient or for groups of patients:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.019.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.019&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And surely we already have lots of valuable data in health and care? Not really. Hospital episode statistics and most centrally collected data are collected outside of the process of clinical care:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.020.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.020&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issues are not new. The Bristol heart enquiry, in 2001, looked at the significant issues with data between 1984-1995. How many of us can say that much has changed since then?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.021.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.021&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why do we have arbitrary boundaries between the data we collect for administrative purposes, in the running of our hospitals and services, the data used in direct clinical care, the data for management of services and research data?  There are legal and regulatory differences in how such data can be used, and those need to be modelled in our systems, but we need to step back and understand that meaningful, interpretable data is the core foundation of our services. That means modelling &lt;em&gt;consent&lt;/em&gt; and ensuring that data can only be processed in line with the legal, regulatory frameworks, as an inherent feature of our data “system”. Likewise, we must move from data being collecting primarily for secondary uses (e.g. governmental data returns) to secondary use data being derived from prospectively collected, clinically-meaningful data captured at the point-of-care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the ways that we can make the acquisition, processing and use of data possible is to improve the software and data services that we use, at the point-of-care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we capture the current medications in an outpatient clinic. Behind the scenes, the drugs are mapped to the NHS dictionary of medicines and devices (dm+d) and the dosages parsed, automatically roundtripping between product-based and dose-based prescribing and allowing graphical display of total daily drug doses:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/yTiYz5ofKj0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.022.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.022&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an approach makes one realise that we need living systems that work hand-in-hand with the processes and workflows of our services. Users now record over 5000 clinical encounters in my homegrown software:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.023.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.023&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it quickly became apparent that users had other needs - users need to safely and securely communicate in order to orchestrate clinical care. So I added secure messaging so that users could easily send messages to one another, all linked to the electronic record, so any message sent about a patient appears in the record, as well as in the relevant users’ inbox/sent mail mailboxes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.024.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.024&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linking disparate data is powerful. How can we interpret step monitor counts, genomic data, patient-reported outcome measures, or anything else for that matter, without understanding the patient, their characteristics, their co-morbidities and the interventions they have received?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than considering research and clinical data as separate, we should think of them as simply different levels of specificity and granularity - and model the legal and regulatory rules defining the purposes to which data may be used. Similarly, even in clinical services, we expect to have more phenotypic information on a patient about to undergo epilepsy surgery compared to a new patient with an idiopathic generalised epilepsy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.025.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.025&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the logical conclusion is that we must start to build a range of &lt;em&gt;data capabilities&lt;/em&gt;: and that means building &lt;em&gt;analytics and software expertise within health and care&lt;/em&gt;. We cannot afford to outsource this work. Our health and care systems must become data-driven, in partnership with academia, the third-sector and commercial partners, but we must ourselves, in health and care, truly make &lt;em&gt;digital the way we do business&lt;/em&gt;. We shouldn’t only be attempting to describe what is happening right now (although in most outpatient departments, we can tell you how many patients are seen, but have little insight into what they are seen for or indeed how they fare!) but move towards much more advanced data capabilities such as predictive analytics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.026.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.026&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;4-a-more-integrated-approach---and-highlighting-the-need-for-a-platform&quot;&gt;4. A more integrated approach - and highlighting the need for a platform&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to really embed data acquisition and use in the workflows of our departments, across all organisations in Wales, I realised that my electronic health record could not live in isolation - instead it needed to integrate closely with other software and data systems within NHS Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this work was really difficult. In fact, this has been and continues to be the most challenging aspect. Bespoke, proprietary integrations with different systems in Wales, with no cohesive platform and no consistency in underlying data or its structure. I started doing this work back in 2008, and quickly found I had to somehow make decisions about the “source of truth”. For example, as a system used across different organisations in Wales, I built integrations with different patient administrative systems, attempting to provide a unified view. But I soon found that one system might record a patient as deceased while another would have the patient recorded as alive!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.028.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.028&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The even bigger problem was not even being able to get access to the data available for direct care, even when teams had built scalable national services such as repositories for laboratory and radiology data, there was seemingly no transparent process for gaining access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Irrespective of these limitations, being able to pull out patient information, clinic lists and write data back into document repositories has been sufficient to enable multiple workflows and create, I hope, valuable software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, this is from our botulinum toxin clinic. We knew how many patients attended, but didn’t know who received this costly treatment or indeed have any insight into their outcomes. We suspected that many patients were receiving treatment without benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The easiest way to help solve this problem was to build a solution focused on clinical workflow that made it easier in clinic - but as a side-effect allowed us to track what was done, who it was done to and combine that with postcode data mapped to organisational boundaries and calculate drug dose uses per local health board:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IbjaiEsMW-Q&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users see a list of the patients for the clinic, pulled from the local patient administrative system, record data and then create a structured document, coded with SNOMED-CT procedures, diagnoses and indications together with a PDF version - which is sent into local and national document repositories automatically:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.029.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.029&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly in our motor neurone disease service, we need to be able to valuably support professionals in our multi-disciplinary teams. One aspect of this is tracking weight to identify patients in need of nutritional support. Of course, these data are already recorded in clinic by nursing staff, but usually on post-it notes or copied into paper records.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.030.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.030&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution to this was two-fold. First, ensure that we had a mechanism to record body weight in the electronic record, and second, to use SNOMED CT to identify the cohort of patients with motor neurone disease or any subtype, and then provide a summary page that picked out the relevant information from the wider record to help clinical care:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.031.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.031&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pleased to say that we won an award at the NHS Wales 2019 awards for our work across South Wales for this type of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.032.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.032&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this looks simple, the software is determining baseline weight by determining the onset of the patient’s subtype of motor neurone disease and finding a recorded weight as close as possible to that date, and then calculating the percentage change for the most recently recorded weight: we usually need to have a conversation about intervention if you lose 10% of your baseline weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But integration remained &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; difficult, and I looked in envy at how other non health and care “platforms” provided a credible and cohesive set of data and software services, often cloud-based, that could be stitched together to create innovative solutions to solve user needs, hitherto not considered by the original developers of that “platform”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, I was spending more time looking at how others were solving these issues: megasuite EHR vendors such as Cerner and Epic were heavily customisable, and provided their own “platform” facilities which meant internal developer teams could leverage their common data and software services to solve workflow problems for their users. Indeed, we heard from one site that their in-house developer team had to &lt;em&gt;increase&lt;/em&gt; in size after the procurement of these products, highlighting the need for integration and customisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;5-the-active-patient&quot;&gt;5. The active patient&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next part of the journey was an increasing awareness of how we were missing the &lt;em&gt;patient&lt;/em&gt; in our work! Patients must not only have access to their records but also contribute. So in 2015, I released an iPad application, based on Apple’s ResearchKit framework, that my colleagues trialled in the Parkinson’s clinic. I am not aware of any other ResearchKit-based software deployed in the UK before this work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.034.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.034&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/so-i-wrote/ipad.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Ipad&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/oavWDjXkyic&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key was to ensure that the information was made available immediately for use in clinical care, but notice how the system can also ask the patient whether they are interested in research. In 2018, we successfully obtained ethical approval for a similar iPad application to be used to record consent, and so I can dynamically build consent forms in a web-based administrative interface and push it out to our iPads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/so-i-wrote/m5-epr-consent.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;M5 Epr Consent&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;6-strategy-and-complex-adaptive-systems&quot;&gt;6. Strategy and complex adaptive systems&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I realised that this work, in isolation, could not have the impact that I wanted it to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started to understand that I should try to spend more time influencing national and local information technology programmes within health and care in Wales, and start to advocate for a more modern approach to technology, trying to influence governance, team structures, architecture and encourage the adoption of open standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started talking to people with experience from other public sector and commercial digital initiatives, such as GDS, and learned more about user needs, the value chain and the importance of &lt;em&gt;delivery&lt;/em&gt; with the agile approach of fast-feedback resonating with my own experience of building a minimal viable product and getting early valuable feedback and iterating; after all, it was the only way I had been able to work for all of those years!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I presented at the inaugural &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Welsh digital health and care conference&lt;/a&gt; and pitched an approach based on user needs and an open technology platform made up of modular software and data services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.036.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.036&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gov.wales/sites/default/files/publications/2019-03/informed-health-and-care-a-digital-health-and-social-care-strategy-for-wales.pdf&quot;&gt;Informed Health and Care strategy&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.037.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.037&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This strategy is useful as a framework, useful to understand &lt;em&gt;needs&lt;/em&gt;, but not something to define governance or architecture, because it is self-evident that some core architectural building blocks are useful across multiple workstreams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.038.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.038&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of an open platform, in which there is separation of the data and the applications that process those data, is not new. Indeed, we know health and care &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; will outlast the applications that operate upon them; applications are increasingly ephemeral and very easy to create if the hard work is performed by services &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; the platform itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You almost certainly access your email using a variety of applications; web-based, multiple mobile applications and applications running on desktop computers - normally whatever suits your current context - your workflow might be that you respond with short replies using your mobile application but perhaps write longer messages on your desktop. The key is that you are viewing the same data through different prisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.040.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.040&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.041.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.041&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.042.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.042&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is danger in designing software through an application-centric perspective, because you make it much too easy to make the wrong design and architectural decisions and that builds technical debt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what such a platform approach might look in NHS Wales:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.043.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.043&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we’ve been discussing how the real-time analytics / data pipeline might be implemented via &lt;a href=&quot;https://kafka.apache.org&quot;&gt;Apache Kafka&lt;/a&gt; or similar pub/sub streaming pathway, while more interactive applications principally use FHIR APIs to interact with software and data services built into the platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that means that we can start to build partnerships and collaborations, not only within health and care services but with partners across academia, the third-sector and commercial entities; partners may provide some of the architectural building blocks for us, but such an approach, predicated upon the adoption of open technical standards, will allow us to build a thriving ecosystem, test innovation and scale solutions when proven, but taking steps to continuously evaluate and improve at a system-level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We move from this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.044.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.044&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;to this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.045.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.045&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We simply do not need multiple portals but we must recognise that we have a complex suite of different software products in different organisations - rather than top-down diktat, we need a convergence strategy that means that working systems across Wales can incrementally adopt nationally provided modular building blocks of functionality and yet still also be able to access the meaningful structured data that sits behind any modular user interface component if needed to solve user problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an approach is simply good software engineering practice. The NHS Wales “WCP” product has “logging” built into the application so that all access to patient records is logged by the application itself. This should always have been something at the API level; we have too much business logic within this application and that simply makes ongoing work &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; difficult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefit of APIs is that they are an &lt;em&gt;abstraction&lt;/em&gt;. I don’t need to know how my car works; my interactions with my car are to use a key, steering-wheel and pedals. It’s the same in software - and that means we can provide a simple-to-use open standards-based “platform” of different APIs that hide the underlying complexity of our wider enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vendors such as Cerner and Epic recognise the benefit of a platform approach: they each provide a set of FHIR APIs that mean that third-party applications can interact with the software and data services provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have three options in Wales: the status quo, the purchase of a megasuite EPR or the development of our own “platform” using a lot of the good work already done within Wales, but simply not (yet) exposed as first-class API products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s how it could look for us:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.046.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.046&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;becoming-data-driven---building-capabilities&quot;&gt;Becoming data-driven - building capabilities&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, our health and care services must become data-driven. Data are an essential ingredient of a prudent health and care service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.047.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.047&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But data aren’t only valuable in supporting our health and care services. We should be looking to use data to support our work in improving our software design, development, testing and deployment lifecycle, and we need to look at how the highest performing software teams develop safe and effective software in the modern age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.048.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.048&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That doesn’t only mean real-time dashboards of performance metrics, of live service status updates and numbers of mouse clicks for a specific process, but changing the way we design and build software systems in a much more agile and responsive way - with fast-feedback and continuous improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was fortunate to work with Lee Waters and others on the &lt;a href=&quot;/images/systemreboot.pdf&quot;&gt;“System Reboot” report&lt;/a&gt; for Welsh Government, which identified some of the capabilities we need to develop across the public sector - and we need to work hard to share experiences and look at what platform components might be shared - much like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.notifications.service.gov.uk&quot;&gt;Gov.uk Notify service&lt;/a&gt; permits organisations to send notifications to users via email or SMS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, my approach to SNOMED CT was to deliver the software and get fast-feedback on its utility and functionality and improve, building in processes to ensure clinical safety at the outset. I saw instead national programmes looking to get consultancy and spending time &lt;em&gt;planning&lt;/em&gt; instead of getting real-life feedback to shape progress. Fundamentally, we need to move away from thinking we can do &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterfall_model&quot;&gt;waterfall planning&lt;/a&gt; and procurement for healthcare technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-importance-of-expertise-in-data-and-software&quot;&gt;The importance of expertise in data and software&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we need to recognise that we cannot outsource data and software expertise, because we are still at the “beginning of the digital revolution” - this is what Bill Gates said in 2017!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.049.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.049&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital technology offers us the tools to transform our health and care services and design a more seamless, prudent, and continuously improving system for citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be focused on solving problems&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;encourage fast-feedback, for health and care services &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; the software that supports those services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;become data-driven&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;build partnerships and foster collaboration&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;be open, transparent and honest about our successes and our failures;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adopt open standards and encourage interoperability&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adopt approaches from outside of health and care&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;inculcate an inquisitive, searching and curious &lt;em&gt;learning&lt;/em&gt; culture.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/wmc-journey/wmc-journey.050.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wmc Journey.050&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark Wardle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-health-technology-and-digital-transformation&quot;&gt;On health technology and digital transformation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/strategy/2019/09/22/health-technology.html&quot;&gt;Digital transformation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/strategy/2018/11/12/manifesto-wales.html&quot;&gt;A manifesto for digital health in Wales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-once-for-wales&quot;&gt;On “Once for Wales”&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;Once for Wales : a debate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-trust-and-innovation&quot;&gt;On trust and innovation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/paradox-of-ambition.html&quot;&gt;The paradox of ambition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html&quot;&gt;The paradox of control&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html&quot;&gt;The 5 Os of healthcare IT - objectives, ownership, openness, optimise, organic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-platforms&quot;&gt;On platforms:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/strategy/2018/10/02/open-platform-wales.html&quot;&gt;An open platform for Wales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data-driven healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-1.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 1/3. Standards and interoperability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-2.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 2/3. An API-first approach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 3/3. What we need to do next&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-focus&quot;&gt;On focus:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html&quot;&gt;Focus 1/3. The importance of strategy : focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges.html&quot;&gt;Focus 2/3. The challenges we face in delivering the vision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-solutions.html&quot;&gt;Focus 3/3. Pragmatic solutions to those challenges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-data&quot;&gt;On data:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/22/health-data.html&quot;&gt;Health data - start with a problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data-driven healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-development-standards-and-ecosystems&quot;&gt;On development standards and ecosystems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/cloud-ehr.html&quot;&gt;Creative 1/3: creative destruction in health IT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;Creative 2/3: the value of software for healthcare: quality improvement and service transformation underpinned by software, and software underpinning by quality improvement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html&quot;&gt;Creative 3/3: ecosystems and the platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This blog post is based on a presentation given to the Welsh Medical Committee on 8th November 2019.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Appointments and scheduling: a programme of work for an open platform in NHS Wales</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/platform/2019/10/18/appointments-scheduling.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Appointments and scheduling: a programme of work for an open platform in NHS Wales" /><published>2019-10-18T19:18:18+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-18T19:18:18+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/platform/2019/10/18/appointments-scheduling</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/platform/2019/10/18/appointments-scheduling.html">&lt;p&gt;I propose a programme of work to demonstrate a new collaborative approach to technology across health and care in Wales, that recognises the fundamental, foundational requirement to understand a patient’s clinical encounters across disparate health and care services to create a “seamless” service via distributed modern technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is principally focused at health and care services in Wales, the design patterns have broad applicability, I hope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the important principles is to sketch out a piece of work that &lt;em&gt;helps us learn&lt;/em&gt;, rather than planning as if we have the answers. This is in line with our &lt;a href=&quot;https://standards.cymru/posts/2018-12-01-wtsb/&quot;&gt;broad design principles&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a programme of work that cuts across multiple workstreams of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gov.wales/sites/default/files/publications/2019-03/informed-health-and-care-a-digital-health-and-social-care-strategy-for-wales.pdf&quot;&gt;Informed Health and Care strategy&lt;/a&gt;. These workstreams are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Information for you”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Supporting professionals”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“Improvement and innovation”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“A planned future”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.003.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.003&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a bad way of thinking about the challenges we face; for example, it provides some structure on which we can think about user needs. This is from &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;my talk in 2017 at the inaugural Digital Health and Care Conference in Wales&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/digitalhealthconf/wardle-digital-health.007.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Wardle Digital Health.007&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these workstreams aren’t the right way to structure the architecture, governance or programmes of work, because it is self-evident that there are important common software or data components that underpin delivery of the goals from more than one work-stream. It’s helpful to assess user needs and delivery via the prisms of these workstreams, but there’s something wrong in technological programmes of work all being under the responsibility of one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-single-seamless-system&quot;&gt;A single seamless “system”&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our patients, their families and carers want our health services in Wales to work as a single seamless system, and the professionals that look after them, want to collaborate and work together to deliver that seamless care. This ‘single system’ approach aligns with the outcomes in “A Healthier Wales.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the moment, patients and families experience a patchwork of services that do not appear seamless at all. Some general practices permit booking of appointments electronically, but for many with multiple long-term health conditions, managing their appointments across the different health and care organisations is a difficult job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, users of Welsh Clinical Portal see what appears to be a single application, but in fact see different data depending on where they are sitting. We see only that health board’s appointments in a specific version of WCP. This demonstrates a fundamental error in the design of currently deployed national applications. For example, last year I sat in my clinic in Cwm Taf and a patient was recorded as deceased while the same patient was recorded alive in Cardiff. We have single applications but multiple patient records. We must strive for a single patient record but we will always need to have multiple applications, customised for context (e.g. critical care, emergency units, primary care, analytics) and user (e.g. patient, professional).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, work on our “Single Cancer Pathway” highlights how important it is to understand the pathway of patients from diagnosis to treatment, and manage this seamlessly across organisational boundaries. We cannot interpret our performance and our outcomes without understanding what has happened to our patients. For too long we have separated data used by clinicians from that by managers and administrators, and none of it has been available to our patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;proposal&quot;&gt;Proposal&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to create a core foundational national service to provide ‘appointments and scheduling’ services. Such a service needs to be a first-class “product” provided by the national ‘open’ platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially read-only, a view across multiple disparate systems including multiple PAS (patient administrative system), radiology and other systems including community care, providing a sane, standards-based API for use by multiple user-facing applications. It would be a unique and low-risk opportunity to build an architectural building block (ABB) that hides underlying complexity in favour of normalising and sanitising data from multiple sources to provide a seamless “single” record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This development would need:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a collaborative approach - we work across organisations in Wales&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a staged, incremental approach - it could start by providing only PAS data initially with additional integrations added piecemeal, not needing changes to applications using the API.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to design for future change - including the ability to schedule appointments when the underlying services permit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such an ABB would be used by multiple applications across multiple workstreams:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Workstream 1&lt;/em&gt; - this component would be an important enabler to allow patients to see their appointments across primary, community and  secondary care, including radiology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We could provide a rudimentary patient portal, but also make those same data available via PKB and DrDoctor, and even via a demonstrator mobile application for NHS Wales, similar to that created by NHS Digital (The “NHS App”).  If booking functionality is not provided by an underlying system (for example radiology), we could fake this functionality by providing a concierge service in which humans deal with requests and cancellations made via the service. This supports the identified “challenge project” within the recent architecture review of systems in NHS Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Workstream 2&lt;/em&gt; - allowing professionals to have a view of current, future and past appointments across our health and care organisations in Wales, no matter the site, or indeed which application, one is currently using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This work would teach us a lot about APIs and application lifecycle management, logging, and access control, and would fit with need to modularise WCP as outlined in the architecture review, making it less tightly integrated - making it loosely-coupled - with the local PAS and instead providing a true national view of a single patient record. It also fits with the strategic theme, because booking staff could be alerted to clashes in booking; patients receiving appointments from different NHS and care organisations for the same date and time are not experiencing a seamless service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A service does not feel seamless if you receive an appointment in one department or organisation that clashes with another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Workstream 3&lt;/em&gt; - we could feed scheduling information into a data warehouse and real-time analytics pipeline in order to understand our health and care demands across organisational boundaries in Wales, providing valuable learning to aid our “national data repository” work in an iterative, incremental way. This would teach us how to start to become &lt;em&gt;data-driven&lt;/em&gt;, and use novel computationally intensive techniques to analyse streaming data in real-time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Workstream 4&lt;/em&gt; - this work, and particularly our use of open technical standards to drive interoperability, will teach us how we can deliver valuable software quickly and require collaboration across multiple teams. It will teach us whether we can do this work collaboratively in the ways I have outlined in this blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;alternative-approaches&quot;&gt;Alternative approaches?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people might suggest that the best way of delivering the outcomes I have outlined here would be to ensure a single “patient administrative system” for Wales, but such an approach would not solve breaking down the artificial silos we have built between primary and secondary care, or the hospital outpatients and, for example, radiology. Do we really want to force CAV to switch PAS? What a waste. Simply expose the right data, in the right format, for national use. In general, an organisation’s PAS supports local administrative workflows and anyone suggesting a rip and replacement approach to such a system should be questioned carefully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, we should look at how we can use software design patterns such as vendor neutral archives or a facade pattern to provide a seamless view across multiple disparate services and organisations, without impacting operational services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal must be to have cohesive high-level strategic alignment of multiple, seemingly independent, products.  For example, in this approach, work to identify patients who are likely to not attend for their appointments can be developed, tested and subsequently scaled out with ongoing evaluation and continuous improvement, without needing changes within other systems and across a complex, heterogeneous enterprise. That’s the power of adopting robust open technical standards and strategic planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;synergies&quot;&gt;Synergies&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are synergies with the following other programmes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Value-based healthcare / patient reported outcomes - appointments/scheduling form the foundation on which interventions and outcomes depend, and appointment data and scheduling functions would support patient-facing applications.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Modular WCP - to show a coherent national view (“single patient record”) in patient portals, including WCP but also in ABHB’s CWS.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NDR - national data resource - as part of workstream 3 - appointments and scheduling are a clearly defined domain which will provide valuable learning and permit an iterative, agile approach to development with early delivery of benefits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Phased planning with metered funding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working on appointments and scheduling is one of the foundational building blocks of what would be a Welsh open platform (see &lt;a href=&quot;https://wardle.org/strategy/2018/10/02/open-platform-wales.html&quot;&gt;https://wardle.org/strategy/2018/10/02/open-platform-wales.html&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a logical extension to the challenge projects identified in the architecture review - and identifies common core foundational challenges that underpin those projects - e.g. a modular WCP would need to view appointments from a single patient record, and not be tied to health board systems, e.g. a patient portal or mobile app would need a unified “one system” view across our health and care organisations but we’d want the same data to drive solutions such as PKB and our analytics as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;challenges-and-their-mitigation&quot;&gt;Challenges and their mitigation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some obvious challenges, and I don’t have the answers yet. We need to fixed on creating teams that can solve these. We know from the most productive technology teams that the best way to deliver valuable software at pace is to work in an agile, iterative way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some risks and some clear challenges that we will need to solve:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can Wales work together like this?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can we get access to systems which we cannot control?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s the Myrddin (WelshPAS) database schema? Is it stable? Is it the same in different instances and configuration? Is there a standards-based API? What “standards” are used for encoding the information recorded, and are they harmonised between instances?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What about Cardiff and Vale, who use a different PAS?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Same question for RADIS, a ‘national’ radiology information system that is different in each organisation?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Same question for GP systems?  - we can’t have only a webview but we need the data itself. Are re-procurements sufficiently scoped to include what we would need to deliver our objectives?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What community systems should we know about?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s the minimum number of “systems” that we’d need to take data from, by stream replication or live API, to prove something useful?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What would it take for health boards to use the toolbox of data and APIs that will be developed by this programme?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What degree of churn is there in scheduling - do staff make changes repeatedly before the schedules are finalised and appointment letters sent out? How does this translate into a safe view for patients? Would you issue updates/notifications every 1, 2, 3, 6,8, or 24 hours?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do we solve the citizen identity/login issue? What work is there already in WG? What about gov.uk Verify? What does this look like, feel like for patients? Is it safe? Secure? High-risk/impact if we get this wrong?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What’s the delegation model? Carers, parents, power of attorney? Has anyone solved this?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Or can we fake it before we make it? Do we have to have patients login straightaway to a portal? What about making data available in PKB as part of that programme, and for anyone else, or everyone, nationalise the appointments/scheduling process so that letters are printed and sent out centrally? Are there economies of scale there? And doesn’t that mean we can get systems/processes right internally, and then safely switch over to electronic communications for those that opt-in? As a bonus, letters could go out to include the actual appointment letter, but also a wider NHS view - ie here are your other forthcoming appointments as well as this current appointment. Wouldn’t that make health and care much more seamless in feel? The idea is that on-the-ground, the teams doing scheduling wouldn’t have to necessarily know whether their patients are getting letters posted or sent electronically or by calendar invite!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Do we have a canonical source of “communication preferences” for citizens? I’ve seen this referenced in different PAS, but is it joined up? What are the scenarios? eg I’m a student and I want my appointments/schedule via mobile/email and also a letter to my parents. Or not.  Or most of the time, except for this clinic. How does this work for different clinical environments? What about the GU clinic?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Can we use the same approach to help patients who receive cross-border care - for example, North Wales and tertiary centres in Liverpool, the Birmingham liver service etc. What would we need to do to our approach to include data from other nations of the UK? Can we take advantage of the push towards open standards, the inception of NHSX and our collaborations with organisations such as HL7, INTEROpen etc.?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What are the technical standards needed here, and how do we align across the border?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If we’re combining appointment and scheduling data from disparate systems, is our demographic matching infrastructure (EMPI) up to the challenge? My testing suggests very slow response times against the test instance (&amp;gt;2s) so how could that be mitigated? Is a cache needed? What ‘fitness functions’ should be used to define the operational standards we expect from these services?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How can we limit our interactions with the “demographics” programme of work by adopting appropriate technical standards (API definitions, security, authentication, authorisation, scalability, responsiveness, quality of service indicators), so that we can work independently but rely on a single view of demographic information?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not a project but instead we are building and delivering services and products. We can be clear about our overall direction; we are opening up our architecture, building a data-driven learning health and care system that appears, to patients and professionals, as increasing seamless. However, we will find hurdles and difficulties not yet imagined, and so we must look to defer decisions until the last possible moment so that we minimise risk. We do not minimise risk by planning and developing long lists of requirements by stakeholders, but instead delivering software again and again and getting fast feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next steps must be focused on building capacity and capability - and identifying the obvious challenges - and then building teams, made up of different specialisms, working collaboratively, empowered and trusted, to deliver solutions to those challenges and teach the wider programme what worked and what didn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t have all of the answers. Let’s create work that teaches us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;addendum&quot;&gt;Addendum&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-press-releases-might-come-about-from-this-programme&quot;&gt;What press releases might come about from this programme?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about press release content is an interesting way to ensure we are aligning our technology programmes and the products/services that will be built to our wider health and care strategic goals. We can write a short press release, either for a programme or a specific service. This is something that organisations such as Amazon use in order to work out whether something is valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We challenge ourselves: &lt;em&gt;are we doing something valuable here?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never tried this before, and I’m not a public relations expert, so these are simply a way of &lt;em&gt;thinking&lt;/em&gt; about a problem, not an actual press release!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, outcomes in digital / technology &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; health and care outcomes. We need to stop thinking of digital (and IT) as a separate department or organisation, but instead focus on benefits for patients, carers and professionals. Digital technology is the enabler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So here are two example press releases to illustrate the importance of this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-seamless-health-and-care-in-nhs-wales&quot;&gt;1. Seamless health and care in NHS Wales&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As part of its “A Healthier Wales” programme, NHS Wales has announced a new patient and carer-focused approach to healthcare data. Stating the importance of a “single patient record” and the need for a “single seamless system” across all organisations providing health and care services, patient data will be made available via portals, mobile applications and third-parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We have been experimenting with products like ‘XXXX’ and ‘YYYY’ to provide ways for patients to see and contribute to their record,” says Dr xxxx, Chief Digital Officer for NHS Wales, “but these experiments have been piecemeal. Our approach is to focus on bringing together information from across Wales and making that available for patients and professionals by adopting open standards to support interoperability across Wales. Initially, patients and their representatives will be able to manage their appointments via a variety of channels, such as our new patient portal, an NHS Wales application and via third party providers such as XXX and YYYY but we expect to rollout additional functionality incrementally over time.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Speaking at the XXX event, Dr XXXX talked about the collaboration with partners across the UK so that patients receiving care from NHS services in other nations of the UK will experience a more joined-up and seamless service, irrespective of where they attend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-a-new-approach-to-managing-outpatients-using-ai&quot;&gt;2. A new approach to managing outpatients using AI.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;NHS Wales has announced a new national approach to scheduling and managing outpatients appointments. In collaboration with xxxx University, advanced mathematical algorithms and machine learning will identify patients most at need. “For example, additional support will be provided to patients predicted to be at higher risk of missing appointments”, says Dr XXXX,  “our Healthier Wales programme is focused on a person-centred approach in which care, irrespective of where and how it is provided, is seamless and joined-up. We can use data to identify those most in need of help, particularly those with long-term health conditions.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I propose a programme of work to demonstrate a new collaborative approach to technology across health and care in Wales, that recognises the fundamental, foundational requirement to understand a patient’s clinical encounters across disparate health and care services to create a “seamless” service via distributed modern technology.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Demographics and identity: A fundamental service in a health and care platform</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/platform/2019/10/18/demographics-patient-identity.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Demographics and identity: A fundamental service in a health and care platform" /><published>2019-10-18T11:10:10+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-18T11:10:10+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/platform/2019/10/18/demographics-patient-identity</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/platform/2019/10/18/demographics-patient-identity.html">&lt;p&gt;This blog post is a slightly expanded version of a recent &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mwardle/status/1184578331041247233?s=21&quot;&gt;Twitter thread&lt;/a&gt; that I live tweeted during the creation of a Wardley map looking at health and care architecture in relation to identity services and specifically, how we manage patient demographic information.  You can read more about Wardley mapping from &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/wardleymaps&quot;&gt;Simon Wardley’s own blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve been practicing my @swardley mapping to try to look at one facet of our health and care architecture and ecosystem: patient demographics. Wardley maps use a value chain to show user need and their dependencies running from top to bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding patient identity is pretty much essential to all that we do in health and care. One of major problems in health is that legacy applications have tended to be “full stack”, containing different components that are user-facing, do business logic and that do data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This approach is shown in this schematic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Value%20chain%200.png&quot; alt=&quot;Value Chain 0&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The application is dependent on components that support user-facing logic, components that handle business logic, and components that provide data storage. All are dependent on computing power and computing power is dependent on power (electricity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The historic approach to health and care software is the procurement of multiple ‘full-stack’ applications and consequently we, within health and care, have to consider how to integrate these applications in order to ensure information is available at the right time across different systems. In general, however, we have seen multiple applications in silos, resulting in patients being surprised that updating their address at their general practitioner might not be propagated to, for example, the radiology booking office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We realised that running multiple health and care applications each with their own idea of patient demographics was a &lt;em&gt;BAD IDEA&lt;/em&gt;. Many applications switched to using demographic information from the local (organisation-bound) “patient administrative system” (PAS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Value%20chain%201.png&quot; alt=&quot;Value Chain 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, the user facing application becomes dependent on local (organisation) patient administrative system. However, that might work in one organisation, with the PAS acting as an authoritative source of patient identity (demographic) information,  but we have multiple organisations! So what happened? We ended up with multiple applications and multiple organisations, all in silos:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Value%20chain%202.png&quot; alt=&quot;Value Chain 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now we have a problem. How do we share information about patients if we can’t match identities between organisations? How can we track the progress of a pathway of care across organisational boundaries without this? Patients don’t experience a “single seamless system” but the fractured, silo approach is evident for all to see - they update their telephone number with their general practitioner and are surprised when the hospital doesn’t know about the change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enter the EMPI, or “enterprise master patient index”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Value%20chain%203.png&quot; alt=&quot;Value Chain 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, you will also see that we need a new national identifier service, the WDS, that can reach out to NHS England who provides NHS number generation. This is getting complicated. How do we write applications that can deal with this? And what if the patient wants to get involved?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Value%20chain%204.png&quot; alt=&quot;Value Chain 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we now expecting applications to handle understanding demographics across multiple PAS, and to manage the ongoing updates and calls to the NHS Number Tracing Service?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely we want a “one system” approach in Wales, centred on the patient and not the organisation?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And hold on. We need to start running analytics across our whole enterprise, seeing how patients fare in the course of their care. How do we track them in our analytics software? We’re going to take A&amp;amp;E attendance data from a PAS and then, how do we match up information?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Value%20chain%205.png&quot; alt=&quot;Value Chain 5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Wales, there is an enterprise service bus (ESB) which securely carries HL7 V2 messages to request, update and merge demographic information. This approach means that your application will need to plug-in to what is essentially a firehose and deal with filtering and managing these messages to track changes over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;mapping&quot;&gt;Mapping&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mapping allows us to add another axis - the maturity of our components - from components that are brand new and being developed, to those that are custom-built, to those we can buy, to those that are a commodity (readily interchangeable alternatives exist). Let’s do that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Map%201.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a problem and the map demonstrates it for us. The map allows us to start to test our models &amp;amp; starts our discussions. Are we really expecting each of our user facing applications &amp;amp; analytics to try to deal with this mess? Instead, surely we need a single authoritative source of identity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Map%202.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that means we can break apart the tight (organisationally-centric) coupling between our applications &amp;amp; individual PAS Instead, we do the hard work to hide the complexity inherent in what is a complex adaptive enterprise containing multiple sources of demographic information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Map%203.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map 3&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see that our single authoritative source, abstracting (hiding) the complexity of our legacy problems with patient identity, will itself evolve towards being a commodity over time as we switch to using it. The red arrow shows the movement over time, as we first build and then deploy this service, and applications move from directly integrating with local administrative systems to a new shared national service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how to permit such an evolution? Such a switch will be best driven by adoption of robust open technical standards that make it easy for applications to consume and process patient identity information using this service. That means making it easier for applications to use our new service rather than directly integrating with proprietary lower level systems. To enable that transformation, we must recognise the value of open standards. So that means we must add standards and the supporting processes for their adoption to our map:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Map%204.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map 4&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final step is that this new service encapsulates and hides underlying platform implementation details. It is conceivable that, over time, that underlying implementation can be changed, simplified and &lt;em&gt;removed&lt;/em&gt; without changing client application code, because we’ve ensured loose coupling via the use of open standards and APIs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/demographics-mapping/Map%205.png&quot; alt=&quot;Map 5&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I think this demonstrates that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need a single authoritative source of patient identity information&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Applications should delegate identity services to that module rather than trying to manage demographics themselves …&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need to adopt robust open technical standards (e.g. HL7 FHIR Patient)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We need to support the ongoing processes to curate, manage and adopt technical standards to drive the commoditisation of a new “one system” approach to demographic, patient identity services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demographics is but one foundational service that are needed to build a modern open platform for health and care. I discuss the wider issues on the next steps in building an &lt;a href=&quot;/strategy/2019/09/22/health-technology.html&quot;&gt;open platform in different blog post&lt;/a&gt;, including the importance of demographics and appointments/scheduling as good examples of programmes of work, focused on implementing &lt;em&gt;products&lt;/em&gt; not projects, that will give us valuable learning for our next steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark Wardle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This blog post is a slightly expanded version of a recent Twitter thread that I live tweeted during the creation of a Wardley map looking at health and care architecture in relation to identity services and specifically, how we manage patient demographic information. You can read more about Wardley mapping from Simon Wardley’s own blog.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An open letter to the new chief digital officer for health and care in Wales</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/10/06/an-open-letter-to-the-cdo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An open letter to the new chief digital officer for health and care in Wales" /><published>2019-10-06T10:09:09+01:00</published><updated>2019-10-06T10:09:09+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/10/06/an-open-letter-to-the-cdo</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/10/06/an-open-letter-to-the-cdo.html">&lt;p&gt;This post is an open letter to whoever will become the new chief digital officer for health and care in Wales, prompted by this exciting announcement by the Health and Social Services Minister on 30th September 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;£50 million and new body to transform digital health and care services in Wales
The plans include creating the role of Chief Digital Officer for Health and Care and a new NHS Wales organisation to deliver national digital services, supported by £50 million new funding.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The Chief Digital Officer for Health and Care will define national standards for digital software and services, as part of moving to an open digital architecture, across all digital systems. The CDO will also advise Welsh Government on digital strategy, lead the digital profession, and be a champion for digital health and care in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Vaughan Gething, Health and Social Services Minister, 
&lt;a href=&quot;https://gov.wales/ps50-million-and-new-body-transform-digital-health-and-care-services-wales&quot;&gt;https://gov.wales/ps50-million-and-new-body-transform-digital-health-and-care-services-wales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dear Sir / Madam,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulations on being successfully appointed as the new Chief Digital Officer for Health and Care in Wales. This is an exciting time and I thought I’d take the opportunity to help you get started with your work; I want to highlight some opportunities, some challenges and suggest some priorities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-people&quot;&gt;1. People&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have some amazing people, projects and products in Wales. You will need to understand that somehow, at the moment, the total is currently less than the sum of the parts. However, there aren’t too many changes you’ll need to make to fix this paradox: I would say the two most important issues are &lt;em&gt;trust&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;collaboration&lt;/em&gt;. Ask: what can we do to help people achieve what they want to achieve, and what should be provided at a national scale to most support those efforts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;2-data&quot;&gt;2. Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have historically not prioritised &lt;em&gt;meaningful, interpretable data&lt;/em&gt; as the core foundation of our services - you need to understand that &lt;em&gt;data&lt;/em&gt; underpins what we want to achieve - whether for direct care, service management, quality improvement or clinical research. Please understand how &lt;em&gt;arbitrary&lt;/em&gt; boundaries between these different uses are a risk to building a truly learning health and care system. You must change this while taking into account the legal and regulatory constraints defined by the purpose for which those data are used. Carefully question proponents of an application-centred strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-transparency&quot;&gt;3. Transparency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a digital leader, you will already know that there is often no clear right choice or single solution, but instead decisions need a fine balance between the advantages and disadvantages of any specific solution, sprinkled with a healthy dose of pragmatism, and a need to consider the future roadmap. An easy way to address this challenge is to be open and transparent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;4-collaboration&quot;&gt;4. Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set broad principles and empower, don’t control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to be dogmatic in setting the broad principles and defining the ‘guard-rails’ that will define how we will use digital technology to support solving the problems in health and care that we need to solve. In keeping with our need for transparency, it should be straightforward to understand what approach should be used and what kind of work should be funded, because the rules we work by are explicit. But that doesn’t mean centralised command-and-control or mandating a specific application. What we do need is an approach predicated upon adoption of pragmatic open standards and the creation of a toolbox of software code and data services that can be used to solve our day-to-day problems in a &lt;em&gt;collaborative&lt;/em&gt; manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;5-agility&quot;&gt;5. Agility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agility means recognising the benefits of adaptability, flexibility and fast feedback. We must learn from other industries who are adopting these practices with pace, and improving the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/articles/path-devops&quot;&gt;safety and reliability of their software delivery pipeline&lt;/a&gt;. We must build systems that can adapt and evolve to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will already know about the benefits of modularisation of software and data services and particularly how the unbundling of services means that they can be developed independently, in parallel, with agreed technical standards defining their interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just because we have multiple modules all being built, deployed and continuously improved independently, it doesn’t mean that each doesn’t form a cog in the wider &lt;em&gt;single system&lt;/em&gt;. By single system, we should mean a credible, coherent, overall high-level strategic approach means that there are clear principles that guide all of our work, with definite and explicit direction-of-travel, but empowered teams delivering the incremental steps on that, truly collaborative, journey. That means a shared vision, but small steps, and that doesn’t mean only for our technology products but in our overall approach to management and leadership. Our work will never be complete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;6-technical-expertise&quot;&gt;6. Technical expertise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our work in health and care in Wales needs to be built on a solid foundation of technical skills. You will need to consider whether you need the support of a Chief Technical Officer, and emulate the highest performing technology companies of the world by fostering developer productivity and adopting a ‘products not projects’ approach. Our efforts to make the right information available at the right time, for both patients and professionals, will succeed or fail based on our ability to make use of the very best technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;7-standards-ecosystems-and-driving-the-commercial-market&quot;&gt;7. Standards, ecosystems and driving the commercial market&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will need to understand how we need to reboot our relationship with commercial and academic partners, and see how this can be fostered by building a truly open platform in which software and data services are made available for both internal and external users. You need to understand the meaning of “dogfooding”. You will need to see how programmes like the Digital Health Ecosystem cannot remain as a separate or external programme but in fact are &lt;em&gt;central&lt;/em&gt; in achieving what we want to deliver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;8-think-outside-of-health&quot;&gt;8. Think outside of health&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should seek to work across Welsh Government to share the same design patterns and user-centred approaches, understand how health and care can fit into the wider strategic government-as-a-platform approach, and shape the way we design services using data. You will need to look for common ground and shared learning across health and care as well as other departments, particularly in relation to user-centred design and the adoption of standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;9-be-humble&quot;&gt;9. Be humble&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognising that we don’t have &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;all of the answers&lt;/a&gt; is absolutely essential, but that doesn’t stop us taking responsibility for the broad over-arching principles and guard-rails that define our overall mission. I’m pretty sure that you will have to adapt and modify our plans as we go along, and be open and transparent about how we discover hitherto unconsidered challenges and how we will learn to overcome them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;10-have-fun&quot;&gt;10. Have fun&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wales could be the very best place in the world to deliver digital health and care; we are small, we pretty much all know one another and we have a health system that in theory lacks many of the arbitrary boundaries between organisations and services. There has been some very good work already that has delivered benefit for both patients and professionals. Your job will be to see the common thread that runs through our systems, our services and our nation and help us to use digital technology to create a truly learning, data-driven and person-centric health and care system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll quickly see that there are some  basics to get right - user login, single sign-on - but you will also need to have the clarity of vision to see how getting those fundamentals solved in the right way forms the foundation to deliver, iteratively and with pace, ever more sophisticated technology to support our health and care services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to do this together to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark Wardle&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;further-reading&quot;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-health-technology-and-digital-transformation&quot;&gt;On health technology and digital transformation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/strategy/2019/09/22/health-technology.html&quot;&gt;Digital transformation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/strategy/2018/11/12/manifesto-wales.html&quot;&gt;A manifesto for digital health in Wales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-once-for-wales&quot;&gt;On “Once for Wales”&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;Once for Wales : a debate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-trust-and-innovation&quot;&gt;On trust and innovation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/paradox-of-ambition.html&quot;&gt;The paradox of ambition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/05/enabling-innovation.html&quot;&gt;The paradox of control&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/12/06/5os-health.html&quot;&gt;The 5 Os of healthcare IT - objectives, ownership, openness, optimise, organic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-platforms&quot;&gt;On platforms:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/strategy/2018/10/02/open-platform-wales.html&quot;&gt;An open platform for Wales&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data-driven healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-1.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 1/3. Standards and interoperability&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-2.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 2/3. An API-first approach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/digital-platform/2018/03/03/platform-wales-3.html&quot;&gt;Platforms 3/3. What we need to do next&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-focus&quot;&gt;On focus:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-focus-focus.html&quot;&gt;Focus 1/3. The importance of strategy : focus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-challenges.html&quot;&gt;Focus 2/3. The challenges we face in delivering the vision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/01/19/focus-solutions.html&quot;&gt;Focus 3/3. Pragmatic solutions to those challenges&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-data&quot;&gt;On data:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/08/22/health-data.html&quot;&gt;Health data - start with a problem&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/10/19/data-driven.html&quot;&gt;Data-driven healthcare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;on-development-standards-and-ecosystems&quot;&gt;On development standards and ecosystems&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/cloud-ehr.html&quot;&gt;Creative 1/3: creative destruction in health IT&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/06/clinical-software-quality.html&quot;&gt;Creative 2/3: the value of software for healthcare: quality improvement and service transformation underpinned by software, and software underpinning by quality improvement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2018/05/08/ecosystems.html&quot;&gt;Creative 3/3: ecosystems and the platform&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This post is an open letter to whoever will become the new chief digital officer for health and care in Wales, prompted by this exciting announcement by the Health and Social Services Minister on 30th September 2019.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Healthcare and technology</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/09/22/health-technology.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Healthcare and technology" /><published>2019-09-22T17:16:16+01:00</published><updated>2019-09-22T17:16:16+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/09/22/health-technology</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/09/22/health-technology.html">&lt;p&gt;This blog post is about digital transformation in health and care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, I discuss our aspirations to create a seamless patient-centred service that blurs the boundaries between disciplines and organisations and how technology is an enabler of those ambitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, I discuss the paradox that while the best way to build that seamless service is with technology, that technology should itself be highly modular, fragmented, and developed and continuously improved using an agile, responsive, adaptive approach that uses real-life fast feedback and a continuous learning culture. Modularisation permits rapid deployment and iteration in parallel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, I discuss the importance of an overarching set of broad principles, adoption of open technical standards, openness and transparency to set strategic direction (“this is where we want to go”) while at the same time creating smaller, semi-independent teams trusted, and empowered, to take the incremental steps to get us closer to our intended destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, I reinforce the need to think carefully about how we structure our technical architecture and governance to start that journey - accepting that we will need to adapt and change our approach as we learn how to deliver health and care technology in a different way to that used previously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;transforming-health-and-care-creating-a-seamless-service&quot;&gt;Transforming health and care: creating a seamless service&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digital technology is going to transform healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We’re at the beginning of the digital revolution”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;by Bill Gates in his foreword to Satya Nadella’s book “Hit Refresh”, published not, as you might initially guess, twenty years ago, but in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health and care organisations, and those in charge of running health care systems, such as those within the National Health Services in the UK, need to understand that it is no longer appropriate to treat information technology as something separate from their core business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“The BMW Group’s CEO that said in the future the BMW Group expected more than half its R&amp;amp;D staff to be software developers.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Edward Taylor and Ilona Wissenbach, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/article/autoshow-geneva-software/exclusive-at-100-bmw-sees-radical-new-future-in-world-of-driverless-cars-idUSKCN0W60HP&quot;&gt;“Exclusive—At 100, BMW Sees Radical New Future in World of Driverless Cars,” Reuters, March 3, 2016&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see that in many industries - and that’s not only because of modern innovations such as mobile devices, machine learning and our ability to process enormous sets of data, but simply because information technology is the best way to deliver the results that we want: a seamless, responsive, patient-centred, evidence-based healthcare system that, at its heart, is driven by patients and professionals working together; collaboration, communication and a data-driven approach to building health and care services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, our goal must be to achieve a seamless, responsive, patient-centred “one system” healthcare service within NHS Wales, and technology is critical in enabling that. We need to break down silos between disciplines and organisations and draw together the common strands of work that underpin care for an individual patient while also caring for populations of patients and enabling better service design, supporting ongoing continuous improvement and transforming clinical research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It should be no surprise to see that a seamless “one system” outcome is explicit in the new NHS Wales health and care strategy: &lt;a href=&quot;https://gov.wales/sites/default/files/publications/2019-04/in-brief-a-healthier-wales-our-plan-for-health-and-social-care.pdf&quot;&gt;A Healthier Wales.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we have have to ask a question: what is the right approach to delivering technology for health and care to deliver that seamless service?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One option is to think that we can use top-down centrally-driven diktat to build a single solution for our “single” service and impose that solution on our services, but is that the right way to deliver software in health and care?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-software-value-chain-delivering-what-we-need&quot;&gt;The software value chain: delivering what we need&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health and care needs &lt;em&gt;software delivery at scale&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to become much much better at developing, deploying and constantly evaluating and improving software, because software is critical to what we need to do improve our health and care system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The problem is not with our organizations realizing that they need to transform; the problem is that organizations are using managerial frameworks and infrastructure models from past revolutions to manage their businesses in this one.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Kersten, Mik. Project to Product . IT Revolution Press. Kindle Edition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health and care needs to learn how to deliver software : reliably, safely, reproducibly, at scale and to ensure ongoing monitoring, evaluation and continuous improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is a paradox. We know that the &lt;em&gt;worst&lt;/em&gt; ways to create a seamless “one system” approach are thinking we can build a single monolithic application or expect the procurement of a “system” to solve, for example, closer working and communication between health and social care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to &lt;em&gt;slow down&lt;/em&gt; delivery is to have an approach to technical architecture and wider governance structures that slows down the &lt;em&gt;software value chain&lt;/em&gt;. The key to software delivery is delivery, and yet some organisations treat software as if they were managing capital projects such as building a new road or a bridge. In most cases, the technology is the easy bit; its the implementation on the ground across multiple complex adaptive systems that is most difficult. But we also need a design that makes it easy and safe to &lt;em&gt;change&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who think building technology is difficult and complex tend to want to centralise and control its development, because that feels less risky, but that approach is wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the advent of readily-available frameworks, rapid application development tools and drag-and-drop user interface design, building software is actually quite easy! What is hard is integration and deployment - the actual implementation of technology to support the transformation of health and care services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the best ways to speed up delivery of valuable technology are&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a) to become &lt;em&gt;agile&lt;/em&gt;,
b) break up our software architecture into smaller, easier-to-manage products and, 
c) create strong leadership to ensure a cohesive credible strategic approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agility means recognising the benefits of adaptability, flexibility and fast feedback. Health and care need to learn from other industries who are adopting these practices with pace, and improving the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thoughtworks.com/insights/articles/path-devops&quot;&gt;safety and reliability of their software delivery pipeline&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modularisation and unbundling of services means that they can be developed independently, in parallel, with agreed technical standards defining their interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But just because we have multiple modules all being built, deployed and continuously improved independently, it doesn’t mean that each doesn’t form a cog in the wider &lt;em&gt;single system&lt;/em&gt;. By single system, we should mean a credible, coherent, overall high-level strategic approach means that there are clear principles that guide all of our work, with definite and explicit direction-of-travel, but empowered teams delivering the incremental steps on that, truly collaborative, journey. That means a shared vision, but small steps, and that doesn’t mean only for our technology products but in our overall approach to management and leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To succeed, a team must be a real working group with proper time to devote to change, rather than a ‘steering committee’ who meet once a quarter for lunch. The team will achieve little if the ‘Agile’ element is merely added on top of their existing jobs. Proper time and space must be devoted to this, which means freeing individuals from existing commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.emergn.com/blog/7-steps-to-building-an-agile-organization/&quot;&gt;Seven steps to building an agile organisation &lt;/a&gt;, checked on 18/9/2019.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of our decisions are nuanced and a balance of positives and negatives, not unlike the practise of medicine itself, and such decisions must surely balance a range of factors including existing investments, cost, value, opportunity cost of not delivering valuable software. As such, we need to also focus on openness and transparency and that means clearly articulating the decisions that need to be made, how we are going to approach them, and finally the delicate balancing act that weighs up those factors. One important principle of agility is to make smaller, incremental decisions so that we lower risk and create greater opportunities to learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-does-this-mean-for-wales&quot;&gt;What does this mean for Wales?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Admitting that we don’t know, leads to a better outcome”
War and Peace and IT by Mark Schwartz&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Incremental releases for bigger changes”
from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kainos.com/making-safe-and-frequent-improvements-to-the-uk-passport-service&quot;&gt;Making Safe and Frequent Improvements to the UK Passport Service&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Our work can be used to engender culture change, and inculcate a respect for the appropriate use of technical standards across health and care in Wales. “
from my &lt;a href=&quot;https://standards.cymru/posts/2019-04-24-standards-culture/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt; for the Welsh Technical Standards Board (WTSB)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have so many amazing individuals and teams across health and care in Wales, and so much drive to continuously improve and transform services. Our work, across health and care in Wales, should be one to provide a toolbox of computing and data services that can be used to support the transformation of how we work, collaboratively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I don’t really care what patient administrative system an organisation uses; I’m far more interested in the articulation of the &lt;em&gt;outcomes we want&lt;/em&gt;, and a balanced decision as to the best way to achieve those outcomes with some broad principles to provide consistency on that weighing up procedure, together with what information goes in and what information comes out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, we have seen different PAS replaced with a “national PAS” in different organisations in Wales, but each has been configured differently and we still have no easy way of tracking pathways for patients across organisations, and any clear consistency on how specialities are coded. Likewise, I have used a “national application” to view a patient and found out that patient is alive when I’m sitting in one clinic, and dead in another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to see how we’d reach agreement on high-level outcomes - what I do care about for PAS is that we have a single patient record, that record is accurate and up-to-date, and that I can track pathways of care across organisational boundaries; once we agree the desired outcomes within a specific domain, we can apply our broad principles to start to tackle those needs by standardising our contracts between software components, without necessarily having to standardise the components themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;strategic-flexible-programmes-but-specific-products-and-small-long-lived-teams&quot;&gt;Strategic, flexible programmes but specific products and small, long-lived teams&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of our goals is to generate a credible and &lt;em&gt;cohesive&lt;/em&gt; strategy to deliver valuable software for our teams across health and care in Wales. I’m interested in finding the natural fault lines in our overall work to create strategic programmes that can work semi-independently from others, and so minimise the need for constant checks and approvals from advisory groups, boards and stakeholders. Such an approach minimises dependencies and the lessens the need for constant coordination. Good governance is essential, but good governance is also streamlined and efficient governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is seductive to think about programmes of work delineated by specialty, service or organisation. That approach leads to programmes such as a “National imaging programme board”, who has led on procurement of a new Picture Archive Communication System (PACS) for radiology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is probably better to think of programmes of work aligned to strategic themes instead - orientated to the outcomes we want, so that there is alignment and cohesiveness, when possible. For example, it is possible that an imaging programme board might recommend procurement of electronic test requesting functionality at the same time as laboratory colleagues procure the same functionality for laboratory tests. If these programmes are not aligned, and occur independently, test requesting will not feel cohesive for end-users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One option is to ensure that all stakeholders for all programmes all talk to one another, but that results in an exponential need for cross-talk and slow, difficult decision-making because all programmes of work are dependent on one another. Instead, programmes of work should be aligned strategically in core domains aligned to operational outcomes, planning to minimise cross-dependencies and coordination, and explicitly recognising common needs and adopting a &lt;em&gt;platform&lt;/em&gt; approach to common national services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, it might well be best to procure separate electronic test requesting functionality to get early benefits, so that professionals and patients get functionality delivered quickly, but strategically, ensure that both radiology and laboratory procurements provide standards-based APIs so that a concierge service can be built to streamline workflow for end-users. It is almost certainly wrong to jump to a decision on this today, as it may be that electronic test requesting is provided at no cost bundled with a laboratory management system, for example: our goal surely is to build capacity for empowered teams to make these kinds of decisions because they will be the experts?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognising that we don’t have &lt;a href=&quot;/clinical-informatics/2017/03/15/once-for-wales.html&quot;&gt;all of the answers&lt;/a&gt; is absolutely essential, but that doesn’t stop us taking responsibility for the broad over-arching principles and guard-rails that define our overall mission. I’m pretty sure that we will have to adapt and modify our plans as we go along, and be open and transparent about how we discover hitherto unconsidered challenges and how we will learn to overcome them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In keeping with an agile ethos, the best way to really understand how health and care in Wales can benefit from this approach is to try it with small experiments and get fast feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We don’t need to have a big-bang approach to transformation, or indeed, plan massive re-organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, what can we do now to prove the effectiveness of this approach?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;next-steps&quot;&gt;Next steps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d prioritise three programmes of work in order to a) create early benefit, and b) learn whether this approach can work in health and care, identifying unforeseen challenges and refining our approach:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Demographics programme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Appointments and scheduling programme&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;API management/authentication/authorisation logging.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demographics are an essential core requirement for a single patient record, and this programme might focus on coordinating the following products:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A HL7 FHIR based canonical demographic application programming interface (API)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A legacy HL7v2 pull/push demographic update messaging service (for legacy applications)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enterprise master patient index&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Patient administrative systems (PAS) - ie subsuming demographics user group and working with health boards to harmonise our understanding/processing of demographic data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, appointments and scheduling are a vital foundational service and the data and computing services underpin several important products such as professional-facing applications like a national portal as well as patient-facing portals and applications. In addition, our work on single cancer pathway and outcomes relies on an understanding of patient’s interactions across the health service, such as appointments in multiple hospitals and in different departments such as radiology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s already clear that appointments and scheduling have a dependency on demographics - we need to track a patient across organisations irrespective of their local identifiers. We can contractually define the dependency between these two programmes so that our appointments and scheduling programme can simply rely on an abstract computing service that manages the complexity and edge-cases inherent in demographic matching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The appointments and scheduling strategic programme might initially include the following products:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A HL7 FHIR based unified appointments and scheduling view across multiple organisations and departments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An analytics product that streams and stores (warehouse) appointment and scheduling information to permit analytics and real-time dashboards of service use&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A patient-facing portal to provide a simple view of upcoming appointments, with an initial concierge service to provide functionality to change appointments (this could be managed by humans initially and yet still provide valuable functionality for citizens).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Integration with commercial off-the-shelf patient portals, such as the “Patients Know Best” portal in pilot in Swansea Bay and Cardiff &amp;amp; Vale, so that appointments are visible to patients using these products.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It could include work to look at how we might manage to provide similar functionality for healthcare services for NHS Wales citizens whose care involves crossing over into NHS England, reinforcing the need to adopt open technical standards and work in partnership with external stakeholders. I’ve sketched out a more detailed “Appointments and scheduling” programme &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1aXDqANyTzPzwf9I2Rvq6yIEnaj-qYqi0a0VuMttDHWg/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One key aspect to this approach is a flexible, prioritised and adaptive approach to deciding on the structure of programmes, but software delivery made up of small, focused, and long-lived cross-functional developer teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve tried to show this in the following schematic, but this is simply a broad-brush, illustrative approach and not a fixed, regimented plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/governance.png&quot; alt=&quot;Governance&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here we see “guilds” or “tribes”, with specialist expertise in specific vertical domains such as security, engineering, and design, advising and being brought together into specific small teams to deliver specific products, such as an API for demographic data that are governed and coordinated, at least initially, by a strategic programme, because at the moment, we are starting from a fragmented and incoherent set of national and local systems, services and applications. Over time, our strategic programmes can and must evolve to meet the ever changing challenges we face, while our product teams continue to work to deliver valuable software components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, we might recognise three different categories of small, long-lived team that will be needed as we mature in our approach in health and care:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A value-stream aligned team type - focused on solving problems by understanding and then delivering software for end-users. This might be a team responsible for building a patient-facing application.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;An enabling team type - a “squad” - focused on supporting product teams in specific technical domains - in other words, a technical consulting team that works across product teams to empower and up-skill, in a collaborative way. For example, I understand that this is how Google’s Site Reliability Engineers (SRE) work. Such teams might extend their work across other public sector services.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A platform team type - focused on building core, common data and computing services that underpin delivering applications to end-users, often hiding underlying complexity or specialisms by providing an easy-to-use self-service API.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an approach similar to that outlined in &lt;a href=&quot;https://teamtopologies.com&quot;&gt;Team Topologies by Matthew Skelton&lt;/a&gt;, and indeed, we can see that it is likely that, over time, platform services will become increasingly more complex, and leverage other platform services as our demands and expectations rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of our work here is in building &lt;em&gt;capability&lt;/em&gt; - capability to adapt to change and deliver at pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;governance-that-follows-architecture&quot;&gt;Governance that follows architecture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implicit in this approach is recognition that our technical architecture and governance must go hand-in-hand. As we know:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Any organization that designs a system (defined broadly) will produce a design whose structure is a copy of the organization’s communication structure.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Dr Conway, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.melconway.com/Home/Conways_Law.html&quot;&gt;http://www.melconway.com/Home/Conways_Law.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means recognising that a modern, health and care enterprise architecture might look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/domains-functional-and-business.png&quot; alt=&quot;Domains Functional And Business&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In which there is loose-coupling between modular components providing software and data services, orientated and aligned with important strategic business (operational) domains. We will move towards lightweight applications that are focused on creating delightful user-centred workflows, that leverage platform services for business logic and data services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me know what you think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This blog post is about digital transformation in health and care.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reading list</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/05/16/reading-list.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reading list" /><published>2019-05-16T11:05:05+01:00</published><updated>2019-05-16T11:05:05+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/05/16/reading-list</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2019/05/16/reading-list.html">&lt;p&gt;These are books that I have enjoyed and found useful. I recommend them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=16&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiZqPf585_iAhXQSxUIHXWnDEQQFjAPegQIBRAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FDomain-Driven-Design-Tackling-Complexity-Software%2Fdp%2F0321125215&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0t-MzcuNObPOLp3MloCBt_&quot;&gt;Domain-Driven Design: Tackling Complexity in the Heart of Software&lt;/a&gt; by Eric Evans&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.com/War-Peace-Business-Leadership-Technology/dp/1942788711&quot;&gt;War and Peace and IT: Business Leadership, Technology, and Success in the Digital Age&lt;/a&gt; by Mark Schwartz&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Seat-Table-Leadership-Age-Agility/dp/1942788118&quot;&gt;A Seat at the Table: IT Leadership in the Age of Agility&lt;/a&gt; by Mark Schwartz&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Accelerate-Building-Performing-Technology-Organizations/dp/B07BLYJ4HR&quot;&gt;Accelerate: Building and Scaling High Performing Technology Organizations&lt;/a&gt; by Nicole Forsgren,  Jez Humble, Gene Kim&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjMmIPN7Z_iAhXiTxUIHfBRDjQQFjAAegQIBRAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FPhoenix-Project-Helping-Business-Anniversary%2Fdp%2FB00VBEBRK6&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2Vpyz5uZj3Dekuv3QbZSGa&quot;&gt;The Phoenix Project: A Novel about IT, DevOps, and Helping Your Business Win&lt;/a&gt; by Gene Kim, Kevin Behr, George Spafford&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwj935rb7Z_iAhU8SRUIHUf7AVoQFjAAegQIAxAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FThinking-Fast-Slow-Daniel-Kahneman%2Fdp%2F0141033576&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2DrhLGTE9IzK9ZIN1G4wVt&quot;&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow&lt;/a&gt; by Daniel Kahneman&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Hit-Refresh-Rediscover-Microsofts-Everyone-ebook/dp/B01HOT5SQA&quot;&gt;Hit Refresh&lt;/a&gt; by Satya Nadella&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=4&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjzlMv07Z_iAhWKRhUIHVoQANYQFjADegQIARAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FDevops-Handbook-World-Class-Reliability-Organizations%2Fdp%2F1942788002&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2KNX9830TcnjCmlLxp53PR&quot;&gt;The DevOps Handbook: How to Create World-Class Agility, Reliability, and Security in Technology Organizations&lt;/a&gt; by Gene Kim,Patrick Debois, John Willis, Jez Humble&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Startup-Way-Entrepreneurial-Management-Transforms/dp/0241197260&quot;&gt;The Startup Way: How Entrepreneurial Management Transforms Culture and Drives Growth&lt;/a&gt; by Eric Ries&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Lean-Startup-Innovation-Successful-Businesses/dp/0670921602/ref=pd_lpo_sbs_14_t_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&amp;amp;refRID=1K8FBPY06VDPM15DQNF7&quot;&gt;The Lean Startup: How Constant Innovation Creates Radically Successful Businesses&lt;/a&gt; by Eric Ries&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwj5uZeu95_iAhWlThUIHe-xDZkQFjAAegQIAxAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FBuilding-Evolutionary-Architectures-Neal-Ford%2Fdp%2F1491986360&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3bcrPv8RyP9zfZrTfsOXIu&quot;&gt;Building evolutionary architectures&lt;/a&gt; by Neal Ford&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiTqPq595_iAhWLQxUIHXKcAwEQFjAAegQIBBAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FPrinciples-Health-Interoperability-Information-Technology%2Fdp%2F3319303686&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3OjhLqYzPZ74izL0uL-aG8&quot;&gt;Principles of Health Interoperability HL7 and SNOMED&lt;/a&gt; by Tim Benson and Graham Grieve&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/How-Measure-Anything-Intangibles-Business/dp/1452654204&quot;&gt;How to Measure Anything: Finding the Value of ‘Intangibles’ in Business&lt;/a&gt; by Douglas W. Hubbard&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Black-Box-Thinking-Surprising-Success/dp/1473613779&quot;&gt;Black Box Thinking: The Surprising Truth About Success&lt;/a&gt; by Matthew Syed&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Work-Rules-Insights-Inside-Transform/dp/1444792369&quot;&gt;Work Rules!: Insights From Inside GoogleThat Will Transform How You Live and Lead&lt;/a&gt; by Laszlo Bock&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwil-vr375_iAhVQUhUIHTotCSUQFjAAegQIABAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FDigital-Doctor-Hope-Medicines-Computer%2Fdp%2F0071849467&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0ckCrG86Z0pK8FTaDNNDGI&quot;&gt;The Digital Doctor: Hope, Hype, and Harm at the Dawn of Medicine’s Computer Age&lt;/a&gt; by Robert Wachter&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Hard-Thing-About-Things-Building/dp/0062273205&quot;&gt;The Hard Thing About Hard Things: Building a Business When There Are No Easy Answers&lt;/a&gt; by Ben Horowitz&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwjcxL6N8J_iAhWCUBUIHYcABDQQFjAAegQIAhAB&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.co.uk%2FGood-Strategy-Bad-Difference-Matters%2Fdp%2F1846684811&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0hTYQmAhteo5bg90onBbVT&quot;&gt;Good Strategy/Bad Strategy: The Difference and Why It Matters&lt;/a&gt; by Richard P. Rumelt&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Tribes-We-need-you-lead/dp/0749939753&quot;&gt;Tribes: We Need You to Lead Us&lt;/a&gt; by Seth Godin&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/aclk?sa=L&amp;amp;ai=DChcSEwi0-NCg8J_iAhWuu-0KHbGxAFoYABABGgJkZw&amp;amp;sig=AOD64_1sx_nZ7mLepXsbjc8y41NJ5xO1OQ&amp;amp;ctype=5&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwiq68Wg8J_iAhXbSBUIHYdxBOwQ9aACCDY&amp;amp;adurl=&quot;&gt;The Lean Startup: How Today’s Entrepreneurs Use Continuous Innovation to Create Radically Successful Businesses&lt;/a&gt; by Eric Ries&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?sa=t&amp;amp;rct=j&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;esrc=s&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;cd=3&amp;amp;ved=2ahUKEwiig4it8J_iAhW3SBUIHe-nC6YQFjACegQIERAK&amp;amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.com%2FStart-Why-Leaders-Inspire-Everyone%2Fdp%2F1591846447&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2dceDsbE2RA1TaPcqip1mL&quot;&gt;Start with Why: How Great Leaders Inspire Everyone to Take Action&lt;/a&gt; by Simon Sinek&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Innovators-Dilemma-Technologies-Management-Innovation/dp/1633691780/ref=pd_lpo_sbs_14_t_2?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;psc=1&amp;amp;refRID=YBWTH3N4N7ZVTPQ2DWAJ&quot;&gt;The Innovator’s Dilemma: When New Technologies Cause Great Firms to Fail (Management of Innovation and Change)&lt;/a&gt; by Clayton M. Christensen.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;books-recommended-to-me-via-twitter&quot;&gt;Books recommended to me via Twitter&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Update: 18th May 2019&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since posting on Twitter, other people have recommended a range of books that I haven’t read, yet. Here’s the list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Innovators-Prescription-Disruptive-Solution-Health/dp/0071592083&quot;&gt;The Innovator’s Prescription&lt;/a&gt; by Clayton Christiansen, Jerome Grossman and Jason Hwang. Recommended by Chris Minmnagh.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Machine-That-Changed-World/dp/1847370551&quot;&gt;The Machine That Changed The World&lt;/a&gt; by James Womack, Daniel Jones and Daniel Roos. Recommended by Mike Broomhead.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cyber.harvard.edu/publications/2012/interop&quot;&gt;Interop: The Promise and Perils of Highly Interconnected Systems&lt;/a&gt; by John Palfrey and Urs Gasser. Recommended by Ian McNicoll.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Design-Essays-Computer-Scientist/dp/0201362988&quot;&gt;The Design of Design&lt;/a&gt; by Fred Brooks. Recommended by Thomas Beale.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Bad-Blood-Secrets-Silicon-Startup/dp/1509868062&quot;&gt;Bad blood&lt;/a&gt; by John Carreyrou. Recommended by Mike Broomhead.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Mythical-Man-Month-Software-Engineering-Anniversary/dp/0201835959/ref=sr_1_1?crid=3FKT2201SYVPZ&amp;amp;keywords=mythical+man+month&amp;amp;qid=1558215791&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;sprefix=mythical+man%2Cstripbooks%2C136&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;The Mythical Man Month&lt;/a&gt; by Fred Brooks. Recommended by Joe Hunter.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Before-Disrupting-Healthcare-What-Innovators/dp/1532923864/ref=sr_1_fkmrnull_1?keywords=before+disrupting+healthcare&amp;amp;qid=1558215900&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;sr=1-1-fkmrnull&quot;&gt;Before Disrupting Healthcare:  What Innovators Need to Know&lt;/a&gt; by Pallav Sharda. Recommended by Mian Sanon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Learn-Think-Systems-Archetypes-Understand-ebook/dp/B07MZWTJHC/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=learn+to+think+in+systems&amp;amp;qid=1558215930&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;sr=1-1&quot;&gt;Learn to Think in Systems&lt;/a&gt; by Albert Rutherford. Recommended by Mian Sanon.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Implementing-Domain-Driven-Design-Vaughn-Vernon/dp/0321834577&quot;&gt;Implementing Domain-driven design&lt;/a&gt; by Vaughn Vernon. Recommended by Seref Arikan.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amazon.co.uk/Getting-Yes-Negotiating-agreement-without/dp/1847940935&quot;&gt;Getting to Yes: Negotiating an agreement without giving in&lt;/a&gt; by Roger Fisher. Recommended by Steve Baguley&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;New blog post, 16th May 2019: my reading list on information technology and healthcare... &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/zcmuSeym2c&quot;&gt;https://t.co/zcmuSeym2c&lt;/a&gt; Any other books I&amp;#39;ve missed or that you&amp;#39;d recommend? &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/HO6AFcRs43&quot;&gt;pic.twitter.com/HO6AFcRs43&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mark Wardle (@mwardle) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/mwardle/status/1128981734262005761?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script async=&quot;&quot; src=&quot;https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js&quot; charset=&quot;utf-8&quot;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Have you read &amp;quot;the innovators prescription &amp;quot; by Clayton Christensen.&lt;br /&gt;Has a great breakdown of which bits of health can go off the mainframe first.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dr Chris Mimnagh (@ChrisMimnagh) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ChrisMimnagh/status/1129275722223300608?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 17, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Also: &amp;quot; The Machine That Changed The World&amp;quot; -- evidence-based explanation of &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ToyotaMotorCorp?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;@ToyotaMotorCorp&lt;/a&gt; Production System, essential learning about Lean. Am part-way through reading and already finding it to be a must-read for &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Lean?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#Lean&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/hashtag/Agile?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;#Agile&lt;/a&gt; (meaning not just software dev)&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mike Broomhead (@MikeBroomhead) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MikeBroomhead/status/1129854878996684801?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 18, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;und&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/ApbqA104jv&quot;&gt;https://t.co/ApbqA104jv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Ian McNicoll (@ianmcnicoll) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ianmcnicoll/status/1129088003178151936?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Fred Brooks The Design of Design &lt;a href=&quot;https://t.co/UnKkW64Vdg&quot;&gt;https://t.co/UnKkW64Vdg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Woland&amp;#39;s cat (@wolands_cat) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/wolands_cat/status/1129078609887584257?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Well &amp;quot;Bad Blood&amp;quot; - the Theranos story by John Carreyrou is utterly and horrifically fascinating !&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mike Broomhead (@MikeBroomhead) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MikeBroomhead/status/1129708924687589376?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 18, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Fred brooks mythical man month&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Joe Hunter (@joehunter) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/joehunter/status/1128988774900408323?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;Before Disrupting Healthcare - Pallav Sharda&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Learn to Think in Systems- Albert Rutherford &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Not that I agree 100% with either. But the broad perspectives are important.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mian Sanon (@MianSanon) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MianSanon/status/1128984704630308869?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I’d suggest Vaugh Vernon for Ddd Lots of lessons were learned whilst industry followed Evans, V.V gives you those, more solid examples and relevant practices too.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Seref Arikan (@SerefArikan) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/SerefArikan/status/1129075962329665536?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote class=&quot;twitter-tweet&quot; data-conversation=&quot;none&quot; data-lang=&quot;en&quot;&gt;&lt;p lang=&quot;en&quot; dir=&quot;ltr&quot;&gt;I found Getting to Yes pretty useful when it comes to implementation.&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Steve Baguley (@stevebaguley) &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/stevebaguley/status/1129053887850270720?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw&quot;&gt;May 16, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">These are books that I have enjoyed and found useful. I recommend them!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A manifesto for digital transformation in healthcare in Wales</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/11/12/manifesto-wales.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A manifesto for digital transformation in healthcare in Wales" /><published>2018-11-12T12:12:12+00:00</published><updated>2018-11-12T12:12:12+00:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/11/12/manifesto-wales</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/strategy/2018/11/12/manifesto-wales.html">&lt;p&gt;We have an extraordinary opportunity to transform the way we think about the use of digital technology in healthcare in Wales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My manifesto has five core principles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We don’t have all of the answers.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The only constant is change.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We should work in the open; we must be transparent and foster rigorous debate.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We set broad top-down principles and standards, but empower trusted teams who have freedom to deliver but also take responsibility for their work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We must deliver, deliver and then deliver again; we iterate, we improve and we continuously learn.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology is a tool; our work in developing and deploying technology is not an end in itself but instead, its use should help us to deliver our wider strategic aims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It therefore follows that our goals must be to deliver technology as quickly and as safely as possible. Some argue that those goals are contradictory, but evidence from the highest performing technology teams shows that adding more processes and procedures designed to add safety has the paradoxical effect of worsening safety. As such, we need to rethink our approach to project management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our culture must be open so that we are transparent about our success and our failures. We must foster constructive debate. Challenge me to defend this approach and let’s all learn from it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is seductive to think that, as a small nation, we should centralise. It is similarly seductive to think that we lower risk by centralisation. Neither are true. Getting more and more engagement to understand requirements up front &lt;em&gt;does not work&lt;/em&gt;. The best approach is to deliver functioning technology and then improve it based on rapid and continuous feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As none of us have all of the answers and we work in a complex and highly adaptive group of organisations, we must recognise that any credible plan must, itself, be adaptive and capable of evolutionary change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise, we must recognise that one size truly does not fit all. While Wales is of similar size to a strategic health authority in England, our structures and existing technological investments are much more complex. One of our goals must be to safely reduce needless variation, and yet at the same time foster innovation, permitting that new work to scale across all of our services when it is proven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not one approach solves everything we face; instead we should buy products that are an established solution to a problem and focus our in-house work on solving problems that only the public sector can do. That means blending different approaches and being transparent about the decisions we make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The steps we need to take are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;focus on our customers; that means professionals &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; patients. We align our information technology work with our wider service goals.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;modularisation, so we break apart our architecture into smaller, discrete components that can be developed independently of the whole.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;create small, cross-functional teams who are tasked with delivering those modules, iteratively, building in quality and safety from the onset.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;adopt open standards, so that we standardise the interactions between our modules speeding up delivery by permitting parallel developments and limiting the number of people from different teams who need to be involved in any decision.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;prioritise tools to acquire, store and make sense of meaningful clinical data.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;become open by default; for example, one of our first debates must be whether it makes any sense to run two data centres in Wales. Let’s debate!&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;focus on developer productivity, let’s copy the architectural and cultural practices from the most productive technology teams.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we should consider developers in three broad categories, and treat them equally with the same tools, frameworks and documentation available, those providing shared national services and components, those working in and across health boards developing solutions using the national toolbox of services and those outside of the NHS in a thriving commercial and academic ecosystem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I truly believe that Wales could have the best health information technology in the World. We are small, we have a unique and special health service that could be transformed by the safe and efficient deployment of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we need to do things differently to what has been tried in the past. Almost all of my blog posts explore these issues in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tell me what you think, let’s debate… and &lt;em&gt;learn&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">We have an extraordinary opportunity to transform the way we think about the use of digital technology in healthcare in Wales.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Semantic interoperability: SNOMED CT, post-coordination and the model</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/terminology/2018/10/27/snomed-postcoordination-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Semantic interoperability: SNOMED CT, post-coordination and the model" /><published>2018-10-27T20:10:19+01:00</published><updated>2018-10-27T20:10:19+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/terminology/2018/10/27/snomed-postcoordination-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/terminology/2018/10/27/snomed-postcoordination-1.html">&lt;p&gt;One of our goals in healthcare information technology is to enable the meaningful exchange of information between distributed systems in the support of three broad purposes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;direct care,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;management and quality improvement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;clinical research.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, it is insufficient to simply exchange information at a technical level, but we must aim for &lt;em&gt;semantic&lt;/em&gt; interoperability so that we exchange &lt;em&gt;meaningful data&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I say meaningful data, I mean data that has meaning and can be used for decisions, in order to reduce uncertainty about those decisions. Those decisions may be made by a professional, by a patient or carer, or much more likely, shared decisions among groups of those individuals. Those decisions may be clinical, such as should we start anticoagulation to prevent a stroke, or administrative, such as how many patients should we book into that clinic?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when I use the term meaningful data, I also  include the ability to use software to process that information; it is computable. It is important to understanding the benefits of computable information, because computer software is quite simply the best way to make sense of large amounts of information. Making data computable means our clinical work can become &lt;em&gt;data-driven&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making our data computable means that machines can help in processing and understanding, and with the advent of machine learning, even make or suggest decisions based on information. But this post isn’t about machine learning, although it is, I believe, a foundational step for the appropriate and meaningful development and application of machine learning in healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this blog post is about how we can record information in a way that is useful to both humans and machines. For humans it should mean data can be entered more quickly and for machines, it permits better processing so that they can support us humans!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-be-data-driven&quot;&gt;How to be data-driven&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SNOMED CT is a comprehensive terminology and ontology for use in healthcare and it forms an important component of the solution to semantic interoperability. I implemented SNOMED CT in a electronic patient record system and it has been live and running for clinical use in the UK since 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SNOMED CT model consists of three core entities:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;concepts, represents a unique concept&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;descriptions, represents synonyms for a concept&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;relationships, represents relationships between concepts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve written extensively about SNOMED-CT on this blog; the best way of understanding the ontology is to browse using an &lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk&quot;&gt;online browser&lt;/a&gt; but SNOMED International provide &lt;a href=&quot;https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCSTART/1.+Introduction&quot;&gt;a useful introductory guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;concepts&quot;&gt;Concepts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many concepts represent a single independent concept, but many are actually &lt;em&gt;compound&lt;/em&gt;, representing a number of concepts combined into a meaningful whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cholecystectomy&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=38102005&quot;&gt;38102005&lt;/a&gt;) is a single concept representing removal of the gallbladder. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Laparoscopic cholecystectomy&lt;/code&gt; is single concept representing removal of the gallbladder with a laparoscope (&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=45595009&quot;&gt;45595009&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A SNOMED CT &lt;em&gt;expression&lt;/em&gt; combines concepts without needing every possible combination of concepts to be created within the terminology. For example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;80146002|appendectomy|
   :260870009|priority|=25876001|emergency|,
   425391005|using access device|=86174004|laparoscope|
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;represents performing an appendicectomy as an emergency using an laparoscope. We could add this as a distinct single concept into SNOMED CT but that would result in a combinatorial explosion; that means we’d have to have single concepts representing all possible permutations which is simply not practical. However, mainly for historical reasons or to ease implementation, SNOMED CT does already contains many single concepts that combines multiple concepts into one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, SNOMED CT expressions are a powerful way of refining a concept with additional information, creating, in effect, a clinical phrase. This technique is called &lt;em&gt;post-coordination&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-not-use-post-coordination&quot;&gt;Why not use post-coordination?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have usually advocated keeping the implementation of SNOMED CT simple by using only pre-coordinated concepts. My concerns about using post-coordination have been that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it added complexity to end-users in terms of selection and display of terms,&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it made data storage more difficult, and would break referential integrity in my own system.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it would complicate using those terms at a computational level e.g. in automated decision support.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we gain significant value simply from recording pre-coordinated concepts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is (1) and (3) that concerned me most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in my own electronic health record software, users don’t know that they are selecting SNOMED terms; they start typing and it autocompletes or simply choose an option using a pop-up, choose a part of the anatomy from a picture or a term is imputed on the basis of other data entered. Adding complexity in adding refinements or qualifiers or embedding expressions worried me. I wanted to make SNOMED CT invisible to end-users and yet enable new decision support and analytics capabilities, hitherto not possible using unstructured free-text.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t conceived of a simple way to make using SNOMED invisible if I created functionality to build expressions; I now think differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;information-models&quot;&gt;Information models&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in the majority of cases, I think many uses of post-coordination such as qualification or refinement or additional information should instead be a function of the wider information model in which the SNOMED CT concept is recorded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, the FHIR definition of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/condition.html&quot;&gt;Condition&lt;/a&gt;, which includes metadata about the problem/diagnosis concept is shown here:
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/snomed-postcoord/fhir-condition.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Fhir Condition&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It includes information relating to status (active/inactive etc), verification (provisional, differential) and severity (severe, moderate, mild), as well as information about the condition’s onset and abatement (remission/resolution).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we use post-coordination without carefully considering the consequences and their mitigation, given that there is an overlap between information recorded within an expression and the wider information model, we risk duplication, complexity and inconsistency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;computing-attributes&quot;&gt;Computing attributes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there are clearly situations where refining a concept with additional information would be helpful. For example, we really wanted to be able to add a more specific anatomical location when we recorded that a patient had a brain abscess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SNOMED-CT ontology helps us, at the computational level, determine &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; “cerebral abscess” can be refined:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=60404007&quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cerebral abscess&lt;/code&gt; (60404007)&lt;/a&gt; is an abscess in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, we can determine a way to &lt;em&gt;refine&lt;/em&gt; this concept using post-coordination to specifically give the location. The ontology provides, as part of its model, attribute relationships for this concept, at a computational level:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt; Is a (attribute)                   -&amp;gt; Abscess of brain (disorder)	
 Associated morphology (attribute)  -&amp;gt; Abscess (morphologic abnormality)
 Finding site (attribute)           -&amp;gt; Cerebral structure (body structure)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we can see that we can refine the concept &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cerebral abscess&lt;/code&gt; with a finding site that is a child of the concept &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Cerebral structure (body structure)&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=83678007&quot;&gt;83678007&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, computationally, we can offer a choice to the end-user to refine this concept with any finding site, such as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Structure of parahippocampal gyrus&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=13989007&quot;&gt;13989007&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, we can add refinements as a result of our concept being in one of the nine main SNOMED CT hierarchies. The attributes appropriate for each hierarchy are listed &lt;a href=&quot;https://confluence.ihtsdotools.org/display/DOCSTART/6.+SNOMED+CT+Concept+Model&quot;&gt;on the SNOMED International concept model documentation&lt;/a&gt;. For example, a clinical finding can be qualified by adding concepts representing a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Finding Site&lt;/code&gt;, a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Causative Agent&lt;/code&gt;, or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Severity&lt;/code&gt; among others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, we can add refinements because of the existence of our concept within a certain reference set. For example, there is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://termbrowser.nhs.uk/?perspective=full&amp;amp;conceptId1=723264001&quot;&gt;laterality reference set&lt;/a&gt; that tells us which concepts can be lateralised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is therefore straightforward to imagine that, if a cerebral abscess is entered by a user as a diagnostic concept, we might configure our user interface or natural language parser to look for and refine that diagnostic concept with additional information relating to finding site, appropriately limited to the brain using subsumption, given that we have entered cerebral abscess, and offering a choice of laterality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we can see that location, laterality and causative agents &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be very appropriate options for refinement, but should we let users post-coordinate diagnostic concepts with a type of ```Severity’’’? This matters because we need to think about how we write software to process these terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;equivalence-and-the-importance-of-meaning&quot;&gt;Equivalence and the importance of meaning&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key issue with processing SNOMED CT, either as pre-coordinated terms or as expressions, is to ensure that we can process &lt;em&gt;meaning&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means that, in any implementation of SNOMED CT, whether using only pre-coordinated terms or post-coordination to create an expression, we need to handle equivalence at not just the level of SNOMED, but also take into account the wider information model, providing the context in which that concept or expression sits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, a HL7 FHIR representation of a condition looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;resourceType&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;Condition&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Resource&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;meta,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;implicitRules,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;language&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;DomainResource&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;contained,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;extension,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;modifierExtension&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;identifier&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Identifier&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}],&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;External&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Ids&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;condition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;clinicalStatus&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&amp;lt;code&amp;gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;C?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;active&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;recurrence&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;inactive&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;remission&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;resolved&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;verificationStatus&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&quot;&amp;lt;code&amp;gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;C?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;provisional&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;differential&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;confirmed&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;refuted&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;entered-in-error&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;unknown&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;category&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;CodeableConcept&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}],&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;problem-list-item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;encounter-diagnosis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;severity&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;CodeableConcept&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Subjective&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;severity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;condition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;code&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;CodeableConcept&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Identification&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;the&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;condition,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;problem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;or&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;diagnosis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;bodySite&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;[{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;CodeableConcept&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}],&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Anatomical&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;location,&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;relevant&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;subject&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Reference(Patient|Group)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;R!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Who&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;has&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;the&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;condition?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&quot;context&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Reference(Encounter|EpisodeOfCare)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;},&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;//&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;Encounter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;or&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;episode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;when&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;condition&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;first&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;err&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;w&quot;&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hl7.org/fhir/datatypes.html#codeableconcept&quot;&gt;CodeableConcept&lt;/a&gt; is a complex HL7 FHIR type that provides a reference to an arbitrary terminology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/snomed-postcoord/codeable-concept.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Codeable Concept&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens if we put a concept representing “SEVERE” as the severity in the FHIR model but record a post-coordinated SNOMED CT expression of “MILD” as a qualifier of our diagnostic concept?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;meaningful-data-in-context&quot;&gt;Meaningful data, in context&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means our analytics, for direct individual care, processing data as part of an electronic health record in real-time, or for quality improvement, service management or research use, must interpret the meaning of SNOMED CT concepts and expressions &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; the wider information model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what do we need from our software?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need to be able to process an arbitrary SNOMED concepts, provide the standard attribute relationships to client software so that those developers can easily understand how to refine, for example, a diagnostic term. This should include the value sets or necessary search constraints so that only appropriate values can be used for any specific attribute (e.g. if you are refining an anatomical location in the central nervous system, your values should only be anatomical locations within the central nervous system!)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need a set of tools that can parse SNOMED expressions into a useful internal representation and vice versa, so that expressions can be persisted and exchanged as well as permitting the information to be used effectively by humans and machines.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need to be able to process an arbitrary SNOMED concept or expression and normalise it into a canonical expression so that it can be used for analytics.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We need tools to be able to offer additional refinement of SNOMED concepts and expressions by virtue of the wider information model in which they sit. For example, normalisation of a concept within a FHIR condition model could be automatically refined by the appropriate attributes from the wider model, such as severity.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, I have been working on a set of open-source tools that not only support deriving understanding of meaning from pre-coordinated single terms in isolation, but from SNOMED expressions and those terms &lt;em&gt;in their wider context&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of this work, I have made use of the Google HL7 FHIR protobuf definitions, which can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/google/fhir&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and are now vendored in the go-terminology code repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My next blog post in this series will cover the details of a practical implementation. Like all standards, it is only with the development and availability of quality (open-source) implementations that a standard can truly become valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">One of our goals in healthcare information technology is to enable the meaningful exchange of information between distributed systems in the support of three broad purposes:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Digital transformation in healthcare</title><link href="https://www.wardle.org/digital/2018/10/23/on-digital.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Digital transformation in healthcare" /><published>2018-10-23T22:21:21+01:00</published><updated>2018-10-23T22:21:21+01:00</updated><id>https://www.wardle.org/digital/2018/10/23/on-digital</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.wardle.org/digital/2018/10/23/on-digital.html">&lt;p&gt;“We’re at the beginning of the digital revolution” wrote Bill Gates in his foreword to Satya Nadella’s book “Hit Refresh”, published not, as you might initially guess, twenty years ago, but in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This explicitly recognises that, while we have already seen remarkable changes to our lives, our societies and our cultures as a result of software, and the microprocessors on which they rely, we are actually only at the beginning of our journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://a16z.com/2016/08/20/why-software-is-eating-the-world/&quot;&gt;“Software is eating the World”&lt;/a&gt; said Marc Andreessen, referring to the fact that in every aspect of our lives, software has disrupted the status quo and has revolutionised industries, sometimes quietly, and sometimes by storm. Commercially, we have seen businesses that have put software at the heart of their business overtaking incumbents slower to adopt technology and slower to realise the role of technology as an intrinsic foundation of all they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I work as a full-time consultant neurologist caring for patients with a range of neurological illnesses. Like most senior clinical staff, have a range of academic and leadership roles in addition to my clinical practice; in all of these roles, I see, first-hand, how the right technology could help my work and, most importantly, help the patients I directly care as well as the populations I serve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what do we mean by nebulous terms such as ‘digital’ and ‘technology’ and are we right to think about a digital ‘revolution’, particularly in my own field, healthcare? After all, the technologies at our disposal continuously change improve and we have ever more computing power at our fingertips. The word ‘revolution’ suggests a fundamental and relatively sudden change and while it is true, the maturity of our digital tools sometimes advances quickly, such as near ubiquity of smart phones in the developed world, would we not be better to talk about the “digital era”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But whether we talk about a “digital revolution” or the start of a journey into a new “digital era”, what do we actually mean by “digital”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would argue that the starting point in trying to understand the implications of true digital thinking, in any industry,  is our ability to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;transfer and process information to make it accessible and useful&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;rapid-and-sophisticated-processing--faster-learning&quot;&gt;Rapid and sophisticated processing = faster learning&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But weren’t we were able to transfer and process information before we had digital tools?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, most of us in healthcare still rely on paper notes but that doesn’t stop our teams collecting piles of them to audit an important quality measure of our work.  So perhaps we need to refine our understanding of the “digital revolution”, to explicitly recognise the importance of &lt;em&gt;speed, accuracy and sophistication of our processing&lt;/em&gt; enabling us to make our information ever more useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transition from film to digital cameras is a useful example of how digital technology has impacted our lives. The digital camera speeds up processing; you no longer wait weeks to see the pictures you have taken but instead see your pictures immediately, but digital tools do more than simply improve the speed of feedback, I can now also crop my images and share with friends and family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when we talk about “accessible and useful”, aren’t we actually talking about &lt;em&gt;creating value&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;improving outcomes&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outcomes in photography that are important to me are recording a cherished memory and sharing with those closest to me, and digital tools support these outcomes in a way that was not as easy with traditional film.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the benefit of digital technologies over paper-based processes is that the feedback loops between our decision, in this case to take a photograph, and the outcome, can be made so much more quickly. With the right digital tools, my understanding of the best aperture and shutter speed to use in those conditions and in that situation improves; I learn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting the right information at the right time, synthesised appropriately to make it useful, informs our learning and therefore our ability to make decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And digital is, quite simply, the best way to enable a learning culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-continuous-learning-system&quot;&gt;A continuous learning system&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is why we are at the cusp of a true transformational change, because so many of our procedures and policies, our structures and services and even our budgets and planning, in so many industries, are rooted in the pre-digital era. That means our purchasing or budgeting decisions for solutions to problems are made on a cycle involving years. We plan projects because the pre-digital era required us to meticulous plan our work, deliver what was needed and then evaluate what we did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, digital is an important enabler of changing our mindset in all areas of our work, in healthcare and in other industries, mainly as a result of the speed and acuity of the feedback we can create by the right use of technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lean methodologies teach us to defer decisions to the last &lt;em&gt;responsible&lt;/em&gt; moment, understanding that there is always uncertainty and delaying decisions permits time to gain more information and reduce that uncertainty. Agile methodologies teach us that we should be iterative in our work, breaking it up into small chunks and gaining constant feedback to guide continuous improvement. We should be adopting these principles not only in our work to develop healthcare software, but to manage and improve our services. Digital is a vital ingredient to support those methodologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result, digital, and being data-driven, means our planning cycles should become shorter and shorter, because we’re using small focused interventions and data to constantly evaluate our hypotheses and build a continuously learning healthcare system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means changing the way we think about budgets and financing our work.  Similarly, our real-life prospectively recorded outcome data should be used to inform our clinical practice; we have small examples of how this can already be done but the potential of the digital era is to make such an approach ubiquitous by understanding the importance of routinely collected meaningful data and how it can be used to support decision making by patients and professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True digital transformation isn’t simply digitising our existing processes and replacing paper with a digital equivalent but instead, it is a complete change in mindset. We need to re-imagine our healthcare services with the benefit of the digital tools we have available to us and realise the value and improved outcomes that we can build on this data-driven foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;software-is-like-magic&quot;&gt;Software is like magic&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Software is like magic, automating and systematising even complex tasks. My mission is to make the most effective use of software in healthcare, and I think we’ve barely even started that journey yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a new and vast array of technologies available to us, from enormous quantities of data to real-time analytics, machine learning and applied artificial intelligence, with computing power and different sources of data all growing exponentially. None of us know what the future holds, and none of us have all of the answers, so whether we are talking about ambient sensors or interacting with software using our voice, the essence of our digital work is not just the technology, but instead our ability to make use of data to learn and to inform our decision making. And that means learning how to build software that supports that goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we bring digital technologies into play, we speed up feedback on our actions and can perform complex processing tasks to make sense of burgeoning quantities of information and so “digital”, to me, is inextricably linked to becoming data-driven, because digital tools are the best way to combine and process information. That means understanding the best, evidence-based ways of creating and delivering safe, secure and valuable software code to end-users. And the best ways to deliver software like that is to use those same data-driven methodologies and build our software incrementally in small chunks with constant feedback to guide continuous improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;so-what-next&quot;&gt;So what next?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my view, our biggest risk is to think that we have all of the answers. Instead, we can set the broad principles to which we must work but build trusted teams to deliver against the outcomes we set, whether that be our healthcare services or the software that supports and enables transformation of those services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The true digital revolution will come when we focus on generating meaningful data and use appropriate tools to make sense of that data, to drive our decision making, to use those data to reduce our uncertainty about our decisions, so that, we, in whatever role we have, are supported to make the right judgments at the right time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to &lt;em&gt;learn&lt;/em&gt;, and digital technology is an essential part of building a continuously learning culture, in whatever industry you work. And that is the essence of digital transformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mark&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">“We’re at the beginning of the digital revolution” wrote Bill Gates in his foreword to Satya Nadella’s book “Hit Refresh”, published not, as you might initially guess, twenty years ago, but in 2017.</summary></entry></feed>